<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc tocdepth='5'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>

<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<?rfc subcompact='no'?>

<rfc ipr="full3978" category="std">


    <front>
        <title abbrev="ICE Error Code">
A Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) Response Code for Interactive
Connectivity Establishment (ICE) Failures</title> 
    
        <author initials="J.R." surname="Rosenberg"
                fullname="Jonathan Rosenberg">
            <organization>Cisco</organization>
    
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <city>Edison</city> <region>NJ</region>
                    <country>US</country>
                </postal>
    
                <phone>+1 973 952-5000</phone>
                <email>jdrosen@cisco.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.jdrosen.net</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
    
        <date month="November" year="2007" />
    
        <area>RAI</area>
        <workgroup>SIP</workgroup>
        <keyword>SIP</keyword>
        <keyword>NAT</keyword>
        <keyword>ICE</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE) defines
            an extension to the offer/answer model used by the
            Session Initiation Protocol (SIP). This extension allows
            endpoints to traverse firewalls and NATs. However, in
            cases where highly restrictive firewalls exist, or where
            network failures have occurred, ICE may not be able to
            successfully find a media path. This document provides an
            error response code that can be used with SIP in these
            cases. </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

<middle>


<section title="Introduction">

<t>Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE)
<xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice"/> defines an extension to the
offer/answer model <xref target="RFC3264"/> used by the 
Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref target="RFC3261"/>. This
extension allows endpoints to traverse firewalls and NATs. ICE
functions by having each endpoint include a set of candidate IP
addresses and ports in their Session Description Protocol (SDP)
<xref target="RFC4566"/> messages. Once the candidates have been
exchanged in the offer/answer procedures, each endpoint begins a set
of connectivity checks. These connectivity checks are end-to-end
"pings" utilizing the Session Traversal Utilities for NAT (STUN)
Protocol <xref target="I-D.ietf-behave-rfc3489bis"/>. 
</t>

<t>
Once connectivity checks succeed, the associated candidates can be
used for the exchange of media. Very frequently, a particular
connectivity check will fail (usually through timeout). This happens
when the candidate is not reachable by the peer (as is the case with
private addresses), or a NAT or firewall prevents the peer from
reaching the candidate. In such cases, lower priority connectivity
checks, typically through a relay server, will succeed, allowing media
to flow.
</t>

<t>
However, in even more severe environments, none of the connectivity
checks will succeed. Some of the cases where this can happen include:
<list style="symbols">
<t>One of the users is behind a firewall that blocks all UDP traffic,
  and the users are not utilizing the ICE extensions for TCP
  <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice-tcp"/> which would allow the RTP
  traffic to flow over TCP.
</t>
<t>
  There is a firewall that is allowing UDP, but only to specific IP
  addresses or ports (such as DNS), and the media ports are not
  open. In addition, ICE-tcp is not being utilized.
</t>
<t>
  There has been a network failure, such that each party can reach the
  SIP server, but there is no IP path directly between the endpoints.
</t>
<t>
  There is severe network congestion, resulting in high packet loss
  through the duration of the connectivity checks. Consequently, all
  of the STUN requests or responses were dropped, and all checks timed
  out. 
</t>
</list>
In such cases, ICE recommends that the controlling agent terminates
the session. This can be done by sending a BYE, CANCELing the session,
or rejecting it with any error response code. 
</t>

<t>
However, it is extremely useful for diagnostic purposes to be able to
know that the reason for the termination of the session was that ICE
failed. SIP providers could use this information to track overall ICE
effectiveness, and to perform off-line diagnostics for those cases to
determine why ICE did not succeed. Endpoints could use this information
to inform the user that the call failed due to network error
conditions, which would allow the user to retry later, open a customer
support case, or other appropriate action.
</t>

<t>
To meet this need, this specification defines a new SIP error
response code, 562 (Connectivity Checks Failed). This can be used in
SIP responses or within the Reason header field
<xref target="RFC3326"/> of CANCEL or BYE
requests, depending on when in the dialog the ICE checks fail. 
</t>

</section>

<section title="Terminology">

<t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.  </t>

</section>


<section title="UAC Behavior">

<t>
If the User Agent Client (UAC) is acting as the controlling agent in
an ICE session, and according to the rules in Section 8.1.2 of
<xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice"/>, the state of all check lists is
Failed, the agent is supposed to terminate the session. If the state
of the SIP dialog is early, the agent SHOULD send a CANCEL request,
and it SHOULD include a Reason header field with the protocol of "SIP"
and a cause of 562. If the state of the SIP dialog is confirmed, the
UAC SHOULD send a BYE request, and it SHOULD include a Reason header
field with the protocol of "SIP" and a cause of 562.
</t>

<t>
If the UAC receives a response to its initial INVITE with a response
code of 562 (Connectivity Checks Failed), it MAY inform the user that
the session has failed due to IP network connectivity problems. Beyond
that, the 562 response code is treated like a 500 response. The UAC
can retry its request at a later time. 
</t>

</section>

<section title="UAS Behavior">

<t>
If the User Agent Server (UAS) is acting as the controlling agent in
an ICE session, and according to the rules in Section 8.1.2 of
<xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice"/>, the state of all check lists is
Failed, the agent is supposed to terminate the session. If the state
of the SIP dialog is early, the agent SHOULD send a 562 (Connectivity
Checks Failed) response to the outstanding INVITE request that
initiated the session. It SHOULD NOT include a Retry-After header
field in the response. There is not normally any way for a UAS to know
when a future attempt might succeed.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Proxy Behavior">

<t>
A proxy receiving a 562 (Connectivity Checks Failed) response code to
an initial INVITE request MAY retry the request on an alternate
destination. However, it is RECOMMENDED that it do this only if it has
knowledge or reason to believe that the alternate destination is more
likely to successfully complete a connectivity check with the
UAC. Deployers should also keep in mind that the 562 will only be sent
after all of the checks have failed, and thus will arrive some time
after the original INVITE. There will seldom be time to try several or
even one additional alternate destinations before the originating
caller gives up.
</t>

<t>
It is RECOMMENDED that proxies which support logging and diagnostic
facilities make note of the 562 code in responses and in the Reason
header field of CANCEL and BYE requests, and log them for purposes of
debugging and tracking the results of ICE deployments.
</t>

</section>

<section title="562 (Connectivity Checks Failed) Response Code">

<t>
This response indicates that the INVITE request could not be completed
because connectivity checks utilizing ICE failed for the session. Its
default reason phrase is (Connectivity Checks Failed).
</t>

</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">

<section title="Outside Attacks">

<t>
A Man-in-the-middle could send this
response code to prematurely terminate a session before checks
complete. However, a new response code is not required for that; an
attacker could use an existing response code. Since, functionally,
this response code results in the same behavior in a UAC, UAS and
proxy as any other 5xx response code, the 562 response code does not
introduce any new considerations for outsider attacks.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Insider Attacks">

<t>
A malicious user controlling a UA could send 562 error responses
prematurely, before ICE actually completes. This would cause the
session to fail, but that would affect only the attacker. However, if
the SIP provider is utilizing the 562 error code to track
deployments of ICE, an attacker could skew the results of the log
analysis. In a large scale deployment, the attacker would need to
compromise a large number of endpoints in order to be able to skew
statistics. However, if the provider initiates diagnostic procedures
(such as investigation by IT personnel) when logs show a 562, the
attacker would cause the provider to expend human resources tracking
down non-existent problems. This is similar to a human sending emails
to tech support reporting non-existing bugs.
</t>

<t>
These attacks cannot be prevented by any cryptographic means. Rather,
providers should track the relative frequency of 562 codes from
specific users of the system, and consider them as part of the fraud
systems typically in place within provider networks. Unusually high
occurrence of 562 codes, especially when investigations indicated no
reason for the ICE failures, should be considered suspect. However,
frequency of 562 responses alone is not sufficient cause for fraud; a
user may be behind a highly restrictive NAT and therefore all or most
of their calls may actually be failing.
</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t>
This section registers a new SIP response code according to the
procedures of RFC 3261.
</t>

<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="RFC Number:"> RFC XXXX [[NOTE TO IANA: Please replace
XXXX with the RFC number of this specification]]</t>

<t hangText="Response Code Number:">562</t>

<t hangText="Default Reason Phrase:">Connectivity Checks Failed</t>

</list>

</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3264"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4566"?>
<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-behave-rfc3489bis"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3326"?>
</references>

<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice-tcp"?>
</references>

</back>
</rfc>


