<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC3777  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3777.xml'>

]>
	<rfc category="bcp" updates="3777" ipr="trust200811" docName="draft-dawkins-nomcom-openlist-01"> 

  	<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  	<?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  	<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

 	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  	<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  	<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

	<?rfc compact="yes" ?>

	<?rfc comments="yes"?>

	<?rfc inline="yes"?>

<front>
  <title abbrev="NomCom Issues">Nominating Committee Process: Open Disclosure of Willing Candidates</title>

  <author initials="S." surname="Dawkins" fullname="Spencer Dawkins" role="editor">
    <organization abbrev="Huawei (USA)">Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
    <address>
      <phone>+1 214 755 3870</phone>
      <email>spencer@wonderhamster.org </email>
    </address>
  </author> 
  
  <date month="February" year="2009" />

  <area>RAI</area>
  <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

<abstract>
	<t>This document updates RFC 3777, Section 3, Bullet 6 to allow a Nominating and Recall
		Commitee to disclose the list of volunteers who are willing to serve in 
		positions the NomCom is responsible for filling.
	</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

	<t>The Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG), the Internet Architecture Board (IAB), 
		and at-large IETF representatives to the IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) are 
		selected by a "Nominating and Recall Committee" (universally abbreviated as "NomCom").
		<xref target='RFC3777' /> defines how the NomCom is selected, and the processes it follows as
		it selects candidates for these positions.
	</t>

	<t>The NomCom is responsible for filling positions across the breadth of the Internet Engineering
		Task Force (IETF). The NomCom needs relevant information about candidates being considered
		for these positions, but current <xref target='RFC3777' /> requirements for confidentiality
		limit the ability of the NomCom to solicit that information. The process change described in
		this document allows the 
		NomCom to openly solicit information about willing candidates.
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor="currentrules" title="Current Rules on Candidate Confidentiality" >

	<t><xref target='RFC3777' /> is the latest in a series of revisions to the NomCom process. 
	</t>

	<t><xref target='RFC3777' /> describes the confidental nature of NomCom deliberations in
		section 3, "General", bullet 6, which states:
	</t>

	<t><list><t>All deliberations and supporting information that relates to
      			specific nominees, candidates, and confirmed candidates are
      			confidential.
			<vspace blankLines='1' />
		</t>
		
		<t>The nominating committee and confirming body members will be
     			exposed to confidential information as a result of their
     			deliberations, their interactions with those they consult, and
      			from those who provide requested supporting information.  All
      			members and all other participants are expected to handle this
      			information in a manner consistent with its sensitivity.
			<vspace blankLines='1' />
		</t>
		
		<t>It is consistent with this rule for current nominating committee
      			members who have served on prior nominating committees to advise
      			the current committee on deliberations and results of the prior
      			committee, as necessary and appropriate.
		</t>
	</list></t>

</section>

<section anchor="problems" title="Problems with Existing Rules">

	<t>There are two problems with existing practice - candidate lists aren't as confidential as
		<xref target='RFC3777' /> would lead the reader to believe, but they aren't visible to
		the entire IETF community, either.
	</t>

	<t>Since at least 1996, most NomComs have sent out a "short list" of candidates under consideration
		to a variety of audiences. The target audiences differ from year to year, but have included
		members of specific leadership bodies, working group chairs in
		a specific area (for IESG positions), and all working group chairs 
		(for IAB and IAOC positions). "All working group chairs" includes multiple hundreds 
		of recipients.
	</t>
	
	<t>This practice is unavoidable, because most NomCom members will not have personal 
		experience with most candidates for most positions, but it is periodically 
		challenged because it's not explicitly allowed as an exception to the blanket 
		requirement for confidentiality.
	</t>

	<t>In an attempt to maintain the required level of confidentiality, past NomComs have also included
		"ringers" on the short list - candidates who have notified NomCom that they are NOT willing
		to serve. Since anyone who sees the short list does not know who the ringers are, 
		consciencious IETF participants also provide feedback on candidates who have already 
		declined. This is a waste of precious IETF-participant cycles, and Joel Halpern (2008-2009
		NomCom Chair) reports that "the ringer pool leaks like a sieve" - it's also ineffective.
	</t>

	<t>We also note that the practice of publishing a "short list" 
		penalizes IETF participants who aren't members of one of the
		audiences being surveyed - they have no way of knowing who is being considered, except
		for incumbent(s), 
		and have little incentive to provide feedback to NomCom on individuals who might not 
		even be candidates.
	</t> 

</section>

<section anchor="askingcommunity" title="Asking the Entire Community for Feedback" >

	<t>We take it as given that for today's NomComs, members will not likely have personal experience with
		all candidates for all positions under review. 
	</t>

	<t>We assume that asking the larger community for 
		feedback about these candidates is preferable to NomCom members without personal experience 
		simply deferring to the members of the NomCom
		who DO have personal experience with specific candidates. 
	</t>

	<t>We assume that asking for feedback from the entire community is preferable to asking for
		feedback from specific segments of the community.
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor="accuratelist" title="Publishing an Accurate Candidate List">

	<t>In proposing that an accurate candidate list be published as part of NomCom's request for
		feedback from the community, we considered three possibilities:
	</t>

	<t><list style='numbers'>
		<t>Asking for feedback on all candidates, whether they are willing to serve or not.</t>
		<t>Asking for feedback on all candidates who are willing to serve.</t>
		<t>Asking for feedback on the candidates that NomCom is seriously considering (the "short
			list").</t>
	</list></t>

	<t>Asking for feedback on candidates who are not willing to serve is a waste of 
		precious IETF-participant cycles, and may make it less likely that NomCom would receive 
		feedback on some candidates who ARE willing to serve.
	</t>

	<t>Asking for feedback on all candidates who are willing to serve allows the community to point 
		out specific strengths and weaknesses of all candidates, and this feedback should be useful 
		to NomCom in deciding which candidates to seriously consider. It also allows NomCom to
		receive
		feedback on candidates who might not appear on a "short list" initially, in the event
		that a strong candidate is suddenly unwilling or unable to serve.
	</t>

	<t>We also note that the list of willing candidates would include incumbents who are willing to 
		serve an additional term.
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor="concerns" title="Concerns About Open Candidate Lists">

	<t>This section acknowledges possible concerns about publishing open candidate
		lists in previous discussions.
	</t>

	<t>It is possible that candidates who are willing to be considered if the candidate list
		is not published, would not be willing to be considered if the candidate list is
		published. This reluctance might be the result of personal pride, or the result of
		the fear of retribution, for a candidate being considered as a replacement
		for the candidate's managing Area Director (this concern is usually raised in
		an IESG context).
	</t>

	<t>Spencer's personal opinion is that if retribution for willingness to be considered for 
		IETF leadership positions is a serious concern, we have bigger
		problems than candidate list confidentiality, and Spencer notes that it's called the
		"Nominating AND RECALL Committee" for a reason.
	</t>

	<t>We note that (for example) the Internet Architecture Board publishes the candidate list
		for their representative to the Internet Society Board of Trustees, without apparent
		ill effects.
	</t>

	<t>It is possible that publishing the candidate list publicly would lead to "lobbying",
		public statements supporting candidates on the IETF mailing list, etc. 
	</t>

	<t>Rather than trying to prohibit specific "undesirable" behaviors, we trust that NomCom would 
		focus on factual feedback, rather than on statements of support, in its deliberations.
	</t>

	<t>We note that candidates know they are under consideration and can "lobby" today, by telling
		people they are candidates and asking them to provide feedback to NomCom. Several
		candidates (both incumbents and non-incumbents) have posted statements of candidacy
		to the IETF Discussion mailing list, for example.
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor="updatedtext" title="Updated text from RFC 3777">
	<t>At the end of the three paragraphs in  <xref target='RFC3777' />, section 3, 
		"General", bullet 6, which are currently:
	</t>

	<t><list><t>All deliberations and supporting information that relates to
      			specific nominees, candidates, and confirmed candidates are
      			confidential.
			<vspace blankLines='1' />
		</t>
		
		<t>The nominating committee and confirming body members will be
     			exposed to confidential information as a result of their
     			deliberations, their interactions with those they consult, and
      			from those who provide requested supporting information.  All
      			members and all other participants are expected to handle this
      			information in a manner consistent with its sensitivity.
			<vspace blankLines='1' />
		</t>
		
		<t>It is consistent with this rule for current nominating committee
      			members who have served on prior nominating committees to advise
      			the current committee on deliberations and results of the prior
      			committee, as necessary and appropriate.
		</t>
	</list></t>

	<t>add the following paragraphs:
	</t>

	<t><list>
		<t>The list of candidates willing to serve in positions under review 
			in the current NomCom cycle is not confidential.
			The NomCom will publish the list of names of all
			willing candidates to the community,
			in order to obtain feedback from the community on these candidates.
			The list of candidates published should not contain candidates who
			have not indicated a willingness to serve in the position(s) under
			review.
			<vspace blankLines='1' />
		</t>

		<t>The published list is intended to be published as a complete list, but the
			NomCom may publish an updated list if the NomCom identifies errors/omissions
			in a previously-published version of the public list, or if the NomCom finds 
			it necessary to call for additional candidates, and these candidates indicate 
			a willingness to serve in time to be considered by the NomCom.
		</t>
	</list></t>

</section>

<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
	<t>This specification describes issues with the current IETF Nominating Committee process 
		(<xref target='RFC3777' />) and proposes an update to allow the NomCom to 
		solicit feedback on willing candidates from the entire community.
		No security considerations apply.
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
	<t>No IANA actions are requested in this specification.
	</t>
</section>  

<section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgements">
	<t>The editor thanks the following folks who have provided useful observations and 
		guidance on previous versions of this draft: Brian Carpenter, Leslie Daigle, 
		Joel Halpern, Danny McPherson.
	</t>
</section> 

</middle>

<back>

	<references title="Normative References">

		&RFC3777;

	</references>

</back>
</rfc>