<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<!-- 
 edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) 
  --> 
  <!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">  
 <rfc category="info" ipr="full3978" docName="draft-goldman-pcn-pstn-scope-01.txt" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?> 
  <?rfc autobreaks="yes" ?>
  <?rfc rfcprocack="yes" ?>
  <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?> 
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?> 
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?> 
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?> 
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?> 
 <front>
 <title> PSTN scope of PCN Charter</title>  
 <author initials="S" surname="Goldman" fullname="Stuart Goldman">
   <organization>Alcatel&ndash;Lucent</organization>
 <address>
 <postal>
  <street>5531 E. Kelton Ln.</street>
  <street>Scottsdale, AZ,85254-1111 USA</street> 
 </postal>
  <phone>- +1 623 582 7136</phone> 
  <email>sgoldman@alcatel-lucent.com</email> 
  </address>
  </author>
  <author initials="R" surname="Schafer" fullname="Robert Schafer">
   <organization>Verizon</organization>
 <address>
 <postal>
  <street>2400 N Glenville Dr.</street>
  <street>Richardson, TX 75082 USA</street> 
 </postal>
  <phone>- +1-972-729-6125 </phone> 
  <email>robert.schafer@verizon.com</email> 
  </address>
  </author>
<author initials="F" surname="Suraci" fullname="Frank Suraci">
   <organization>NATIONAL COMMUNICATIONS SYSTEM OFFICE OF THE MANAGER</organization>
 <address>
 <postal>
  <street>245 Murray Lane</street>
  <street>Washington, DC 20528-8500 USA</street> 
 </postal>
  <phone>- +1-703-607-4800</phone> 
  <email>sgoldman@alcatel-lucent.com</email> 
  </address>
  </author>
<author initials="B" surname="Schaefer" fullname="Bob Schaefer">
   <organization>Telcordia Technologies</organization>
 <address>
 <postal>
  <street>One Telcordia Drive, RRC-4B625</street>
  <street>Piscataway, NJ  08854 USA</street> 
 </postal>
  <phone>- +1 (908) 874-8513</phone> 
  <email>rschaefe@telcordia.com</email> 
  </address>
  </author>
<date /> 
 <abstract>
  <t>
  The IETF PCN Working Group has continued its work investigating pre-congestion and admission control mechanisms.
  This work has progressed under the current charter, but has not yet considered related legacy PSTN interactions
 or the need for ubiquitous connectivity between users on dissimilar networks. The PCN charter could be improved
 by a strong positive statement to the effect committing to future work addressing legacy networks. </t>
 <t>
In that light, please consider the questions below which include differential PCN treatment based on traffic types, security,
 and PSTN interoperability concerns. It seems helpful to have a touchstone of some concerns relative to the PSTN network
 and IP network Gateway in order to confirm that they will be addressed in future work. This attempt is motivated by a
 desire to avoid the accidental omission of a topic  that may be hard to "retrofit" in later.
</t>
 </abstract>
  </front>
 <middle>
 <section title="Requirements notation" toc="default">
 <t>
  The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in 
  <xref target="RFC2119" pageno="false" format="default" /> 
  . 
  </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
  <t>
  Experience in the legacy PSTN (Public Switched Telephone Network) and associated network management has taught that 
there are certain types of traffic that should be addressed 
differently than POTS (Plain Old Telephone Service). Examples are mass calling events and auto dialers.
</t>
<t>
 For the foreseeable future the legacy PSTN will co-exist with the newer IP 
based networks. Is there a need that Pre-congestion and congestion signaling be sent from the core to gateways into 
the PSTN? Similarly is there a need for PSTN gateways to inform the IP core of congestion within the 
PSTN? While these concerns may not be within scope of the initial PCN charter, it may be worthwhile to address if 
such needs do exist and if so, what would be the best course of action for the PCN working group.
  </t>
  <t>
  The charter discusses ingress and egress nodes but does not explicitly discuss the situation where these nodes may 
be gateways to the PSTN. Is there a belief that the interconnection to the legacy PSTN can be treated as an edge, or 
the same as the interconnection between two IP based networks, or is there sufficient reason to believe that this 
interface may have unique characteristics that need to be specifically addressed? Given that a significant portion of 
the 
legacy equipment in 
the PSTN is less likely to evolve to specially address unique aspects of interconnection with IP based networks,  it 
seems that one significant constraint on the industry would be that any adaptation needed to 
work with PCN would need to occur at the PSTN gateways and need to be encompassed in the characteristics of the PCN 
mechanisms. The trust 
model in the legacy PSTN model may differ fundamentally from that in the interconnection of IP based networks. We 
have not yet researched such characteristics, but feel the question should at least be raised here.
  </t>
<t>
We understand that these concerns may be out of 
scope of the initial work as it extends beyond a single domain, but may be addressed in future work as indicated by 
the text below from the charter.
</t>
<t>
"After completion of the initial phase, the PCN WG may re-charter to 
develop solutions for scenarios where some of these restrictions are 
not in place. It may also re-charter to consider applying the PCN 
mechanisms to additional deployment scenarios (operation over 
concatenated DiffServ domains, PCN-aware application mechanisms, 
etc.). The WG may also consider to investigate additional response 
mechanisms that act on (pre-)congestion information. One example 
could be flow-rate adaptation (rather than flow admission/
termination) during times of congestion. The details of these work 
items are outside the scope of the initial phase; but the WG may 
consider their requirements to design components that are 
sufficiently general to support such extensions in the future."
</t>
  </section>

  <section title="Differential PCN Treatment based on Types of Traffic" toc="default">
<t>
As we understand the PCN operation, it would be the responsibility of the ingress nodes to control the offered
 traffic and it would be outside the scope of the initial charter to address exactly how this control should be applied. 
Nevertheless it does seem to be helpful for understanding if the charter could at least provide recognition of mass
 calling events, auto dialers, and other non-"POTS" traffic types. The charter should provide guidance that the 
ingress node may address these traffic types separately.
</t>
</section>
  <section title="PSTN Interoperability Concerns" toc="default">
  <t>
  </t>
 
  <section title="Considerations Regarding Traffic Offered from the PSTN Gateway toward the Core" toc="default">
  <section title="Gateway reliance on PCN messages from the core" toc="default">
<t>
Is it reasonable for the PSTN gateway to rely on the IP network to send sufficient PCN messages to the gateway 
allowing the gateway to then limit the traffic its sends into the core? Conversely, can the core rely on the PSTN 
gateways to be responsive to PCN messages? Unless these concerns are eventually addressed, it would appear that 
PCN may not be as effective in this configuration as would be possible.
</t> 
</section>
<section title="Traditional Network Management" toc="default">
<t>
Should the PSTN and gateway also explore more traditional network management controls to prevent exceeding the 
allocated traffic offered to the core? Unless such exploration 
occurs PCN may not be as effective in this configuration as would be possible.</t>
<t>
Should the PSTN and gateway also provide exemptions to traditional network management controls for high priority calls?


 
 
  </t>
</section>
<section title="Mass Calling" toc="default">
<t>
Will there be any consideration of using PCN messages to control Mass Calling Events from the PSTN into the core?
Mass Calling Events are significantly different than general traffic so that special consideration should be given 
to controlling the traffic generated by them.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Hard to reach" toc="default">
<t>
Will there be any consideration of using PCN messages to control sending traffic to hard to reach destinations 
(hard to reach codes) into the core? Hard to reach destinations are significantly different than general traffic 
so that special consideration should be given 
to controlling the traffic generated by them.
  </t>
</section>

  </section>
  <section title="Considerations Regarding Traffic Offered to the PSTN Gateway from the Core" toc="default">
  <section title="Gateway sending PCN messages to the core" toc="default">
<t>
Should there be a consideration for the PTSN gateway to be able to send PCN messages toward the core when the PSTN 
is in precongestion or congestion?
</t>
</section>
<section title="Traditional Network Management" toc="default">
<t> 
Should the PSTN and gateway also explore more traditional network management controls to control the traffic being 
passed on to the PSTN from the gateway so as to not exceed the allocated traffic offered to the PSTN network?
  </t>
<t>
Should the PSTN and gateway also provide exemptions to traditional network management controls for high priority calls?
</t>
</section>
<section title="Mass Calling" toc="default">
<t>
Will there be any consideration of using PCN messages to control Mass Calling Events to the PSTN from the core? 
Mass Calling Events are significantly different than general traffic so that special consideration should be given 
to controlling the traffic generated by them.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Hard to reach" toc="default">
<t>
Will there be any consideration of using PCN messages to control sending traffic to hard to reach destinations (hard 
to reach codes) into the PSTN? Hard to reach destinations are significantly different than general traffic so that 
special consideration should be given 
to controlling the traffic generated by them.
  </t>

  </section>

  </section>

  </section>
  <section title="Proposal" toc="default">
  <t>
It does seem to be helpful for understanding if the charter could at least provide recognition of mass
 calling events, auto dialers, and other non-"POTS" traffic types. the charter should provide guidance that 
the ingress node may address these separately.
</t>
<t>
  Given the reality that the legacy PSTN will continue to exist for a considerable period of time, and the need for 
ubiquitous connectivity between users on the dissimilar networks, it seems to us that the charter could be improved 
by a strong positive statement to the effect committing to future work to address the unique aspects of PCN with 
regard to legacy networks as well as having this constraint in mind during the work under the initial charter.
  </t> 
  </section>
   <section title="Security Considerations" toc="default">
  <t>
  Traffic can be disrupted if malicious PCN messages are sent. The potential of a denial of service attack exists 
in that fraudulent PCN messages could result in a considerable percentage of legitimate subscriber traffic being 
blocked. At this point it appears that there is corresponding risk in both the IP networks and the legacy PSTN.
  </t> 
  </section>
  <section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
  <t>None.</t>
  </section>  
  <section title="Acknowledgement" toc="default">
  <t>
   We would like to thank Igor Faynberg and Gary Sacra for their comments. 
  </t>
  </section>
  </middle>
 <back>
 
 <references title="Normative References">
 <reference anchor="RFC2119">
 <front>
  <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title> 
 <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
  <organization>Harvard University</organization> 
 <address>
 <postal>  
  <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street> 
  <street>Cambridge</street> 
  <street>MA 02138</street> 
  </postal>
  <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone> 
  <email>sob@harvard.edu</email> 
  </address>
  </author>

  <date year="1997" month="March" /> 
  <area>General</area> 
  <keyword>keyword</keyword> 
 <abstract>
 <t>
  In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification. These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they MUST be interpreted in IETF documents. Authors who follow these guidelines MUST incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document: 
 <list>
  <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119.</t> 
  </list>
  </t>
  <t>Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement level of the document in which they are used.</t> 
  </abstract>
   </front>
  <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" /> 
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" /> 
  <format type="TXT" octets="4723" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt" /> 
  <format type="HTML" octets="16553" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html" /> 
  <format type="XML" octets="5703" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml" /> 
  </reference>
  </references>
  </back>
  </rfc>
