<?xml version='1.0'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="exp">
<front>
<title abbrev="HIT-TO-IP">Embedding Host Identity Tags Data in DNS</title>

<author initials='O.' surname='Ponomarev' fullname='Oleg Ponomarev'>
<organization>Helsinki Institute for Information Technology HIIT</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>PO Box 9800</street>
<city>TKK</city>
<code>FIN-02015</code>
<country>Finland</country>
</postal>
<email>oleg.ponomarev@hiit.fi</email>
</address>
</author>

<author initials='A.' surname='Gurtov' fullname='Andrei Gurtov'>
<organization>Helsinki Institute for Information Technology HIIT</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>PO Box 9800</street>
<city>TKK</city>
<code>FIN-02015</code>
<country>Finland</country>
</postal>
<email>gurtov@cs.helsinki.fi</email>
</address>
</author>

<date day='6' month='March' year='2009' />

<area>Host Identity Protocol</area>
<workgroup>Host Identity Protocol</workgroup>

<abstract><t>This document proposes conventions to access and manage 
Host Identity Tag (HIT) mappings using the Domain Name System (DNS) 
interface.</t></abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<section title='Introduction'>

<t>One of the approaches to use legacy applications<xref target="RFC5338" 
/> with Host Identity Protocol<xref target="RFC4423" /> is to use HIT as 
IPv6 address. The application may receive them from the nameserver, store 
internally and connect directly to a HIT. The HIP software would receive 
packet with HIT as a destination IPv6 address without any additional 
information about the current locator and therefore some HIT resolution 
service is needed in this case. This document suggests the DNS as a 
protocol to access such mapping databases in addition to a local list of 
Host Identities and Distributed Hash Tables (DHT) <xref 
target="I-D.ahrenholz-hiprg-dht" />.</t>

<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", 
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this 
document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119<xref 
target="RFC2119"/>.</t></section>

<section title='Domain names for HIT mappings'>

<t>Domain Name System is well-known to systems administrators and there 
is much experience with operations under high load. It also allows 
dynamic modifications and has low overhead when compared to many other 
protocols. It is used now, for example, to get IP address reputations 
from various blacklists.</t>

<section title='Preconfigured Domain'>
<t>The systems using this method MUST have the same domain 
pre-configured, for example hit-to-ip.example.net. If there are 
multiple parallel services with their own domains, the systems MUST have 
at least one of them in common to interoperate.</t>

<t>A HIT is represented as a sequence of nibbles separated by dots and 
followed by the suffix similarly to IPv6 addresses in ip6.arpa<xref 
target="RFC3596"/>. For example, the domain name corresponding to the 
HIT</t>

<figure><artwork>
2001:10:1234:5678:9abc:def0:1234:5678
</artwork></figure>

<t>would be</t>

<figure><artwork>
8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.
                                                hit-to-ip.example.net
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section title='Listing IP Addresses of the System'>

<t>The A/AAAA resource record types MAY be used to specify the IP/IPv6 
addresses of the system. There MAY be multiple locators listed for a 
HIT.</t>

<t>For example, the system with IP address 192.0.2.1 and IPv6 address 
2001:DB8::1 would have the following records</t>

<figure><artwork>
8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.
                                              hit-to-ip.example.net.
  1     IN      A       192.0.2.1
8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.
                                              hit-to-ip.example.net.
  1     IN      AAAA    2001:DB8::1
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section title='Listing host names'>

<t>The PTR resource record types MAY be used to specify name of the host 
using the Host Identity.</t>

<figure><artwork>
8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.
                                               hit-to-ip.example.net.
  86400 IN      PTR     alpha.example.com
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section title='Link to another domain'>

<t>The CNAME resource record types MAY be used to specify another domain 
to lookup the locators of the system.</t>

<figure><artwork>
8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.
                                               hit-to-ip.example.net.
  86400 IN      CNAME   8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.
                    4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.hit-to-ip.domain.example.
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section title='Managing the Records'>

<t>The system MAY send DNS UPDATE<xref target="RFC2136"/> to the server 
provided by SOA MNAME field of the domain. The system MAY add or delete 
A,AAAA,PTR,CNAME records for its own HIT representation. The update MUST 
then originate from the corresponding HIT. If there are multiple 
identities they should be modified separately.</t>

<t>The domain provided in SOA MNAME field of the preconfigured domain 
MUST have Host Identity of the server stored in DNS, the IP addresses 
MUST be listed in that domain using the suggested method and the server 
MUST accept DNS UPDATE messages, which add or delete A,AAAA,PTR,CNAME 
records for the HIT representation of the client after successful HIP 
base exchange. The server MUST refuse to perform the changes if the 
update is not originating from the host identity whose data is being 
updated.</t>

</section>
</section>

<section title='Usage scenarios'>

<t>The DNS selected as an interface should help in the deployment. There 
is vast amount of resursive DNS resolvers available to the clients, they 
can cache mapping information, for example. This section contains ideas 
about three different designs of the mapping service.</t>

<section title='Initial deployment'>

<t>Such mapping services can be started using the conventional DNS 
software with minor changes to authenticate DNS updates with HIP. There 
is hit-to-ip.net zone available for the experiments at the moment. 
According to the experiments<xref target="ISC-TN-2008-1"/> BIND 9 is 
able to send 60,361 replies/second under update at 256 updates/sec over 
IXFR. The performance of DDNS updates was only 93.46 updates/second as 
they are committed to nonvolatile storage before the response is 
returned. The version of BIND compiled without the file-system commits 
performed 471.70 updates/second. The performance of HIP implementations 
also limits the capacity, but about active 100,000 users may be served 
assuming 1 hour average update interval, if the peak performance is 100 
updates/second. Number of mappings that fits into the memory of a modern 
server has to be studied.</t>

<t>The TTL of the records is selected by the clients. If a Host 
Identity is used by a server with static IP addresses, its mappings may 
have long TTLs as any changes are scheduled in advance. This would allow 
the recursive resolvers to cache records of the frequently accessed 
static servers.</t>

<t>Delegation of 1.0.0.1.0.0.2.ip6.arpa would allow reverse resolution 
of HIT to a host name by any system without any changes. The host name 
does not change often and such mapping may be updated only when needed. 
</t>

<t>Although the service may be started with existing DNS software, it is 
not optimal for such a usage pattern and another database engine 
allowing higher update rate is needed.</t> </section>

<section title='Parallel services'>

<t>Although it is not desirable, there may be multiple independent 
mapping services. I.e. the host updates its IP addresses only in 
hit-to-ip.domain1.example, but has to look for IP addresses of an 
unknown host in hit-to-ip.domain1.example, hit-to-ip.domain2.example and 
hit-to-ip.domain3.example. This causes extra traffic due to multiple 
lookups.</t>

<t>Another possibility is that the host updates its IP addresses in 
hit-to-ip.domain1.example, hit-to-ip.domain2.example and 
hit-to-ip.domain3.example, but chose only hit-to-ip.domain1.example to 
lookup unknown hosts. This would cause growth of all three databases 
with every new user and extra traffic due to multiple updates, but 
provides redundancy</t>

<t>The delegation of domain for reverse mapping is unlikely in this case 
and would probably be blackholed similar to reverse subdomains for 
private-use netblocks <xref target='I-D.ietf-dnsop-as112-ops' /> 
</t>

</section>

<section title='Two-level mapping'>
<t>The flat identifiers do not have administrative division as in usual 
domain names and a single organization should serve all 
the identifiers. Therefore it is desirable to reduce its workload at the 
same time TTL of the records cannot be long to allow dynamic changes. 
Two-level design might help to solve this contradiction.</t>

<t>The first level would contain only links (CNAME) to different second 
level mapping providers. Such information does not change often and can 
have long TTL. Furthermore in this case, it would be enough to store in 
memory only HIT and an index of the second level provider both in binary 
format. The second level mapping would contain dynamic information about 
the current IP addresses. For example, there may be the following 
records in the DNS:</t>
<figure><artwork>
8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.
                                        hit-to-ip.arpa.
  86400 IN      CNAME   8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.
                  4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.hit-to-ip.domain.example.

8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.
                                        ip6.arpa.
  86400 IN      CNAME   8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.
                  4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.hit-to-host.domain.example.

8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.
                                        hit-to-ip.domain.example.
  1     IN      A       192.0.2.1

8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.
                                        hit-to-ip.domain.example.
  1     IN      AAAA    2001:DB8::1

8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.f.e.d.c.b.a.9.8.7.6.5.4.3.2.1.0.1.0.0.1.0.0.2.
                                        hit-to-host.domain.example.
  86400 IN      PTR     alpha.example.com
</artwork></figure>

<t>The information about frequently accessed static hosts may be 
available already at the first level.</t>

</section>
</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

<t>SHA1 is used now as a hash function to get HITs, but the complexity 
of an existing attack<xref target="SHA1-attack"/> is only 2**63. Since 
only HIT, but not complete HI is used for lookups, SHA1 should be phased 
out, for example, in favor of the SHA-2 variants. </t> 

<t>The actions, when multiple hosts share the same identity and start to 
constantly update their mappings, should be discussed.</t>

</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This draft would require that the IANA delegates
1.0.0.1.0.0.2.IP6.ARPA subdomain and HIT-TO-IP.ARPA for the Host 
Identity Protocol usage.</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">

<t>The authors would like to thank Tom Henderson and Miika Komu, who 
provided comments and helped to improve this document.</t>

</section>
</middle>
<back>

<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5338.xml"?>
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4423.xml"?>
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2136.xml"?>
</references>

<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ahrenholz-hiprg-dht-03.xml"?>
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3596.xml"?>

<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-dnsop-as112-ops'>
<front>
<title>AS112 Nameserver Operations</title>
<author initials='J' surname='Abley' fullname='Joe Abley'>
    <organization>Afilias Canada Corp.</organization>
</author>
<author initials='W' surname='Maton' fullname='William F. Maton Sotomayor'>
    <organization>National Research Council of Canada</organization>
</author>
<date month='November' day='16' year='2008' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-01' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-01.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='ISC-TN-2008-1' target='http://new.isc.org/proj/dnsperf/ISC-TN-2008-1.html'>
<front>
<title>BIND 9 performance while serving large zones under update</title>
<author initials='B' surname='Reid' fullname='Brian Reid'>
    <organization>ISC</organization>
</author>

<date month='February' day='29' year='2008' />
</front>
</reference>

<reference anchor='SHA1-attack' target='http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2005/08/new_cryptanalyt.html'>
<front>
<title>New Cryptanalytic Results Against SHA-1</title>
<author initials='B' surname='Schneier' fullname='Bruce Schneier'>
<organization />
</author>

<date month='August' day='17' year='2005' />
</front>
</reference>

</references>
</back>
</rfc>
