<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [

      <!ENTITY rfc5039 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5039.xml'>
      <!ENTITY I-D.tschofenig-sipping-framework-spit-reduction PUBLIC '' 
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.tschofenig-sipping-framework-spit-reduction.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.tschofenig-sipping-spit-policy PUBLIC '' 
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.tschofenig-sipping-spit-policy.xml'>
    ]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?> 
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?> 
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?> 
<?rfc compact="yes"?> 
<?rfc tocompact="no"?>

<rfc ipr="full3978" docName="draft-niccolini-sipping-spitstop-01" category="info">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SPITSTOP Reference Scenario">Signaling TO Prevent SPIT (SPITSTOP) Reference Scenario</title> 
      <author initials="S." surname="Niccolini" fullname="Saverio Niccolini">
        <organization abbrev="NEC">NEC Laboratories Europe, NEC Europe Ltd.</organization> 
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>Kurfuersten-Anlage 36</street> 
            <city>Heidelberg</city> 
            <code>69115</code> 
            <country>Germany</country> 
          </postal>
          <phone>+49 (0) 6221 4342 118</phone> 
          <email>niccolini@nw.neclab.eu</email> 
          <uri>http://www.nw.neclab.eu</uri> 
        </address>
      </author>
      
      <author initials="J." surname="Quittek" fullname="Juergen Quittek">
        <organization abbrev="NEC">NEC Laboratories Europe, NEC Europe Ltd.</organization> 
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>Kurfuersten-Anlage 36</street> 
            <city>Heidelberg</city> 
            <code>69115</code> 
            <country>Germany</country> 
          </postal>
          <phone>+49 (0) 6221 4342 115</phone> 
          <email>niccolini@nw.neclab.eu</email> 
          <uri>http://www.nw.neclab.eu</uri> 
        </address>
      </author>
      
      <author initials="J." surname="Seedorf" fullname="Jan Seedorf">
        <organization abbrev="NEC">NEC Laboratories Europe, NEC Europe Ltd.</organization> 
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>Kurfuersten-Anlage 36</street> 
            <city>Heidelberg</city> 
            <code>69115</code> 
            <country>Germany</country> 
          </postal>
          <phone>+49 (0) 6221 4342 221</phone> 
          <email>seedorf@nw.neclab.eu</email> 
          <uri>http://www.nw.neclab.eu</uri> 
        </address>
      </author>
      
      <date month="February" year="2008"/> 
      
      <area>Real-time Applications and Infrastructure</area> 
      
      <workgroup>SIPPING Working Group</workgroup> 
      
      <keyword>RFC</keyword>
      <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
      <keyword>I-D</keyword>
      <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
      <keyword>SPIT</keyword>
      <keyword>SPam over Internet Telephony</keyword>
      <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
      <keyword>Signaling</keyword> 
    <abstract>
      <t>This memo discusses the need for standards that support SPam over Internet Telephony (SPIT) prevention
      applications. After explaining the general need for SPIT prevention applications the memo provides a reference
      scenario for potential communication between entities that may be involved in SPIT prevention. Within this
      scenario the need for standardizing communication is analyzed for each pair of communicating entities.
      The analysis is intended to serve as a starting point for discussing the requirements for signaling standards
      as well as for architectural considerations, that support SPIT prevention applications.</t>
      <t>This memo is not intended to suggest any solution of SPIT signaling issues. Such work, if necessary at all,
      should be object of separate documents.</t>
    </abstract>
    
  </front>
  
  <middle>
    <section anchor="sec-intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Email is an essential mean for world-wide communication. The openness of the Internet make use of email easy
      but also makes it easy to mis-use it, particular to annoy users with spam email. Today, there is more spam email
      transmitted by the public Internet than regular email.</t>
      <t>Internet telephony is on its way to replace the traditional circuit-switched telephony. There is a strong
      concern that this migration to the open Internet will result in Spam over Internet Telephony (SPIT) that potentially
      will be annoy the users even more than spam email does today. If there are more SPIT calls than regular calls in
      the telephony world, then phones will ring all day making it hard to use this medium in a convenient and productive
      way.</t>
      <t>This memo discusses the need for producing standards that help preventing SPIT in the future. Although SPIT is
      not an actual problem today, it has a big potential to become one very soon. At this point in time it will be good
      to be prepared and have technology already available that protects users from SPIT.</t>
    
      <section anchor="sec-intro-threat" title="The SPIT Threat">
        <t>Most of the spam emails are generated by so-called bot nets. Bot nets are networks of hosts that have been
        invaded by a spammer in order to use them for sending spam email without the knowledge of or admission by the
        regular administrators of these hosts. Bot nets can easily be used for initiating spam voice calls instead of
        or in addition to sending spam email.</t>
        <t>Today, there is already voice spam in the switched telephony network. Many households in Europe receive between
        1 and 10 automated spam calls per month. During such a call, a prerecorded messages is played to the callee without
        supporting any interaction. However, these calls create significant cost for the caller, at least if they are made
        in numbers of thousands or hundred thousands.</t>
        <t>With the ongoing migration from traditional connection-switched telephony to packet-switched Internet telephony
        the cost of spam calls will drop drastically. The infrastructure for generating Spam over Internet Telephony (SPIT)
        is already there in form of the existing bot nets. A recent study <xref target="RFC5039" /> estimated that the cost
        per delivery of SPIT call will be up to four order of magnitude cheaper than the costs per delivery of spam over
        circuit-switched telephony. This is expected to cause a flood of SPIT calls as soon as Internet telephony becomes
        the dominating telephony technology.</t>
        <t> For dealing with this problem, particularly for preventing unwanted SPIT, not all methods that are used today
        for blocking spam email can be applied. Particularly, content checking, that is a basic method for detecting email
        spam, is not applicable, because content of a call is not available for checking before the phone rings. And stopping
        the phone from ringing for spam calls is one of the major goals of SPIT prevention. Therefore, further methods are needed.
        An overview of methods that are currently available for SPIT prevention is given in <xref target="RFC5039" />.</t>
        <t>The number of SPIT prevention methods listed there is quite large. Still, it is not considered to be a complete
        list or a list that is exhaustive enough for preventing SPIT sufficiently. On the contrary, this list shows that there
        are still a lot of opportunities left for SPIT generators to place SPIT calls successfully.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="sec-intro-need‚" title="Communication Need for SPIT Prevention">
        <t>An important aspect in this context has not been investigated in detail yet. It is sharing of information between
        entities that are involved in preventing SPIT. They may have a need to exchange information related to SPIT. The range
        of information to be exchanged includes information about</t>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>SPIT events that actually occurred,</t>
            <t>indicators concerning callers to be sources of SPIT,</t>
            <t>indicators concerning concrete calls to be SPIT,</t>
            <t>etc.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>This memo investigates the need of communication between entities involved in SPIT prevention and the need of
        standards for this communication. For this purpose, a reference scenario is defined in <xref target="sec-scenario"/>
        that serves for identifying which communications interfaces may be required for sharing SPIT-related information between
        involved entities. Based on this scenario, requirements for individual interfaces are discussed in
        <xref target="sec-interfaces"/>.</t>
        <t>Currently, the requirements are stated on a high level. Future revisions of this memo may elaborate the requirements
        in more detail. Which (kind of) communication protocol should be chosen for meeting the requirements is not subject of
        this memo.</t>
        <t>However, this memo is supposed to stimulate discussion on the need of standardization work in this area. The
        standardization work should both identify the reference architecture, the best suited protocols for such information
        sharing at each interface and if extensions to such protocols for the support of SPIT information sharing is needed.
        If no suitable protocols matching the requirements for a particular interface is found a suggestion for the design of
        a new protocol suited to such information sharing should be initiated.</t>
      </section>
    
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="sec-scenario" title="Reference Scenario">
      <t>For our reference scenario we consider four kinds of communicating entities:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>the caller User Agent (UA) that generates SPIT,</t>
          <t>Proxy Servers (PS) forwarding call signaling,</t>
          <t>specialized SPIT prevention entities,</t>
          <t>the callee User Agent (UA).</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>With the goal of avoiding that the callee's phone rings for SPIT calls, SPIT prevention devices
      should detect a SPIT message already based on the INVITE method that is sent in order to initiate the
      SPIT call. This goal can only be achieved along the path the INVITE message is forwarded from the caller
      towards the callee. This path starts at the caller UA, then potentially includes a set of forwarding PS,
      and terminates latest at the callee UA.</t>
      <t>Please note that the described reference scenario can be easily mapped to the framework overview 
      described in <xref target="I-D.tschofenig-sipping-framework-spit-reduction"/>, the major difference is
      that the framework discussed in such a draft takes into account only one domain boundary while the
      reference scenario here described is more general and assumes that interactions among multiple domains
      could be used in order to allow distributed decisions.</t>
      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig-scenario" title="SPIT prevention reference scenario with two proxy servers">
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[ 
                       +--------+
                       |        |
                       | caller | 
                       |   UA   |
                       |        |
                       +--------+                           |d   ^
                        #   | ^                             |o   |
                        #   | |                             |w   |u
                        #   | |                             |n   |p
                        #  -------(a)                       |s   |s
                        #   | |                             |t   |t
                        #   | |                             |r   |r
                 (d)    V   v |     (e)                     |e   |e
    +--------+    |    +--------+    |    +--------+        |a   |a
    |        |    |    |        |    |    | SPIT   |        |m   |m
    | Other  |<---|----| Proxy  |----|--->| Prev.  |        |    |
    | Proxy  |----|--->| Server |<---|----| Entity |        v    |
    |        |    |    |        |    |    |        |
    +--------+         +--------+         +--------+
                        #   | ^
                        #   | |
                        #   | |
                        #  -------(b)                         # S
                        #   | |                               # I
                        #   | |                               # P
                 (d)    V   v |     (e)                       #
    +--------+    |    +--------+    |    +--------+          # I
    |        |    |    |        |    |    | SPIT   |          # N
    | Other  |<---|----| Proxy  |----|--->| Prev.  |          # V
    | Proxy  |----|--->| Server |<---|----| Entity |          # I
    |        |    |    |        |    |    |        |          # T
    +--------+         +--------+         +--------+          # E
                        #   | ^                               #
                        #   | |                               # m
                        #   | |                               # e
                        #  -------(c)                         # t
                        #   | |                               # h
                        #   | |                               # o
                        V   v |     (f)                       # d
                       +--------+    |    +--------+          # 
                       |        |    |    | SPIT   |          V
                       | callee |----|--->| Prev.  |          
                       |   UA   |<---|----| Entity |
                       |        |    |    |        |
                       +--------+         +--------+
      

]]> 
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      
      <t>Entities on the path from caller to callee may share information related to SPIT prevention. Related
      communication may happen already before a certain INVITE methods is transmitted or it may be initiated by
      this message. If this communication includes transmitting information in the same direction as the INVITE
      message along the path, then we talk about downstream communication. Transmitting information in the opposite
      direction we call upstream communication.</t>
      
      <t>The SPIT prevention reference scenario shown in <xref target="fig-scenario"/> contains a caller UA,
      a callee UA and two PS on the path of the INVITE message from caller UA to callee UA. This number of PS
      was chosen because it contains exactly one instance of each pair of interacting kinds of entities along
      the path of the INVITE message:</t>
      
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>at interface (a) the caller UA is interacting with a PS,</t>
          <t>at interface (b) two consecutive PS are interacting with each other,</t>
          <t>at interface (c) a PS is interacting with the callee UA.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      
      <t>The number of two PS matched the common SIP signaling trapezoid. However, any number of proxy servers
      greater than zero can be applied to the scenario. If there is only one PS present, then the interface (b)
      is not instantiated.
      If there are two or more PS on the path, then interface (b) is used between each consecutive pair of them.
      In general, the INVITE message could be sent directly from caller UA to callee UA without involving any PS.
      A direct call would be possible if the caller UA sends the INVITE directly to the callee UA, anyway such IP
      address retrieval is prone to errors either because of possible change of IP address during time of callee UA
      or because of Network Address Translator along the path masking the real IP address. The direct call case
      becomes even less relevant if the callee UAs are configured to accept INVITEs only from their proxy servers.
      For these reasons we decided not to include an interface for direct communication between caller UA and callee
      UA in the reference scenario.</t>
      
      <t>Each proxy server on the signaling path of the INVITE message may communicate with off-path entities in
      order to help the task of SPIT identification and prevention.</t>
      
      <t>These entities include one or more specific SPIT prevention entities that are consulted by the proxy
      server using interface (e) in order to get an indication or estimation of a given INVITE message to belong
      to a SPIT call (e.g. using authorization policies
      <!--<xref target="I-D.draft-froment-sipping-spit-requirements"/>-->).</t> 
      
      <t>These entities also include one or more cooperating PS with which information about SPIT calls (or
      call attempts) is shared using interface (d) in order to improve the SPIT prevention accuracy. An example
      for such a cooperation would be a set of PS in a single administrative domain sharing information about known
      sources of SPIT (federation of black listing services across PS).</t>
      
      <t>The callee UA may also interact with a specific SPIT prevention entity similar to the PS (e.g. a local
      one located near the user agent in the access domain). Since in this case, the offered service might be
      more personalized than in the case of the PS, we use a different interface (f) for our reference model.
      This does not preclude that instantiations of (e) and (f) may have identical functions (e.g. using the
      same authorization policies language <xref target="I-D.tschofenig-sipping-spit-policy"/>).</t>
      
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="sec-interfaces" title="Signaling Interfaces Considerations">
      <t>This section discusses the interactions between entities of the reference scenario that is shown in
      <xref target="fig-scenario" />. The interfaces are grouped into three sections.</t>
      
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>The first one deals with interfaces (a), (b), and (c) which all serve for exchanging information
          between consecutive entities along the path of the INVITE message of a particular call (e.g.
          spam scores<!--<xref target="I-D.draft-wing-sipping-spam-score"/>--> or spam feedbacks
          <!--<xref target="I-D.draft-niccolini-sipping-spam-feedback"/>--> with well defined semantics
          <!--<xref target="I-D.draft-niccolini-sipping-spam-semantics"/>-->).</t>
          <t>Interface (d) has a similar function but is off-path and not necessarily related to individual
          (SPIT) calls (e.g. black listing services across PS).</t>
          <t>Interfaces (e) and (f) are used by PS or the callee UA when they need to decide whether or not to
          consider a particular call request as SPIT (e.g. authorization policies).</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      
      <section anchor="sec-if-on-path" title="Interfaces on the Signaling Path">
        <t>At all three interfaces (a), (b), and (c) information may be exchanged in upstream direction as well
        as in downstream direction.</t>
        
        <section anchor="sec-if-on-path-down" title="Downstream">
          <t>There are several considerations of downstream communication that apply to all three interfaces.
          We first describe them before pointing out differences between the three interfaces.</t>
          
          <t>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="All Interfaces (a), (b), and (c)"/>
              <t hangText="" />
              <t>Downstream information is sent along with an INVITE in order to provide information about the
              INVITE to belong to a SPIT call (e.g. indicate that a caller is exceeding a sending treshold, that
              the caller did not pass a specific test like a CAPTCA test
              <!--<xref target="I-D.draft-tschofenig-sipping-captcha"/>-->, etc.).
              A sender or forwarder of an INVITE may, for example, want to signal such information to the downstream
              entity (be it PS or UA) but still not have sufficient certainty or not have legal rights for blocking
              a SPIT call.</t>
              <t />
              <t>In any case, interface (a), (b), or (c) would allow to pass such information further along
              the path of the INVITE. Even if such information does not always lead to achieving a clear idea
              on the nature of the requested call (e.g. the final decision is taken only by downstream entities,
              like the UA), the transmitted information can be recorded by the receivers of this information and
              used for improving future judgments of call requests for SPIT prevention.</t>
              <t />
              <t>In addition such interfaces would allow to pass statistics about the recent behavior of the sender.
              An example of these statistics would consist in the rate of (SPIT) calls initiated by the sender
              during the last time slot, the ratio between regular calls and SPIT calls initiated by the sender
              during the last time slot, etc. The above mentioned statistics can also be bundled together and passed
              only after the expiration of a timeout in order to increase scalability.</t>
              <t />
              <t>Besides the estimation and the statistics itself, also the source of the estimation may be transmitted.
              This way, an entity can indicate, whether it has been involved in producing the estimate, or just
              forwarded the received estimation along the path of the INVITE.</t>
              <t />
              <t hangText="Interface (a)"/>
              <t />
              <t>This interface is instantiated between the caller UA and the first PS along the INVITE path. The
              relevance of interface (a) seems to be rather limited. It does not seem a good idea to have the caller
              UA neither estimating itself the likelihood of the INVITE to belong to a SPIT call not transmitting
              statistics about the its recent behavior. Moreover the instantiation of such an interface could be
              maliciously used by entities initiating SPIT without the PS having the proper means to judge if the
              information passed is trustable or not.</t>
              <t />
              <t hangText="Interface (b)"/>
              <t />
              <t>This interface is instantiated if there are two or more PS on the path. In this case interface
              (b) is used between each consecutive pair of them. It is used to send downstream information about
              the infomration associated with an INVITE (e.g. the caller has a bad reputation according ot the
              originating domain) and about most relevant statistics of the INVITE initiator recent behavior. If
              also the source of the estimation and statistics is transmitted, a receiving PS may be able to judge
              how much trust to associate with the indications based on local policies. Still depending on local
              policies and legal rights the PS can decide to carry out additional tests on the INVITE, initiate
              communication to other entities (see <xref target="sec-if-off-path"/> or <xref target="sec-if-special"/>
              ), or block the call.</t>
              <t />
              <t hangText="Interface (c)" />
              <t />
              <t>This interface is instantiated between the last PS and the callee UA. It is used to send
              downstream information about the information associated with an INVITE (e.g. the caller did not pass a
              CAPTCHA <!--<xref target="I-D.draft-tschofenig-sipping-captcha"/>-->) and about most relevant statistics
              of the INVITE initiator recent behavior. If also the source of the estimation and statistics is
              transmitted, the callee UA can judge how much trust to associate to the indications based on local
              policies. Still depending on local policies and legal rights the callee UA can decide to carry out
              additional tests on the INVITE, initiate communication to other entities (see <xref target="sec-if-special"/>),
              or block the call without having the phone ringing.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="sec-if-on-path-up" title="Upstream">
          <t>As for downstream communication above, we first describe considerations that are common for
          all three interfaces before them before pointing out differences between them.</t>
          <t>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="All Interfaces (a), (b), and (c)" />
              <t />
              <t>Upstream information is sent by entities after receiving an INVITE as feedback to
              the entity from which they received it. It may contain a feedback on the INVITE received.
              This feedback may be sent before the call is established (if at all), after it was blocked,
              while the call is established, and after the call has been terminated. This information can
              help the sender in better judging following calls that are forwarded and the users sending
              the call initiation request or to block subsequent calls of the same caller for the callee
              (feedback to insert users in black lists hosted at the PS). An example for the delivery of
              feedback information is reported in separate documents
              <!--<xref target="I-D.draft-niccolini-sipping-spam-feedback"/>-->.</t>
              <t />
              <t>In addition to the feedback associated to a particular INVITE, such interfaces, similar
              to downstream communication of statistics, would allow to feed back statistics about the
              recent behavior of the sender. An example of these statistics would consist in the rate of
              SPIT calls (estimated using the feedback mechanism) initiated by the sender during the last
              time slot, the ratio between regular calls and SPIT calls initiated by the sender during the
              last time slot, etc. The above mentioned statistics can also be bundled together and passed
              only after the expiration of a timeout in order to increase scalability.</t>
              <t />
              <t>Similar to downstream communication of information and statistics, the source of the feedback
              information may be contained. This is particularly interesting if the feedback was generated
              by the callee who received the call.</t>
              <t />
              <t hangText="Interface (a)" />
              <t />
              <t>This interface is instantiated between the first PS along the INVITE path and the caller UA.
              The relevance of interface (a) seems to be rather limited. It does not seem to be a good idea
              to give feedback to an initiator of SPIT on if and why requested calls have been blocked. 
              This would allow the SPIT initiator to use this feedback for improving methods that bypass SPIT
              prevention systems in the network.</t>
              <t />
              <t>A potential argument for sending a notification about detected SPIT to the SPIT generator
              would be that many legal operators of SPIT generating hosts might not be aware of this. Today,
              this is the case for email spam. Most of them are generated by bot nets where the legal operators
              of the contained hosts are not aware of their hosts being used for this purpose. However, in case
              of SPIT generation, it must be assumed that the generating software is either a software not in
              control of the legal operator or it is controlling the caller UA and capable of suppressing any
              feedback that should not be seen by the legal operator. Therefore, this means would probably not
              show the desired results.</t>
              <t />
              <t hangText="Interface (b)" />
              <t />
              <t>This interface is instantiated if there are two or more PS on the path. In this case interface
              (b) is used between each consecutive pair of them. It is used to feed back information about a
              certain INVITE (e.g. callee indicated the call as SPIT) and about most relevant statistics of the
              INVITE initiator recent behavior. If also the source of the information and statistics is transmitted,
              the PS can judge how much trust to associate to the indications based on local policies and act
              consequently. Still depending on local policies and legal rights the PS can decide to carry out
              additional tests on selected subsequent INVITEs, initiate communication to other entities (see
              <xref target="sec-if-off-path" /> or <xref target="sec-if-special"/>), or block selected subsequent
              calls.</t>
              <t />
              <t hangText="Interface (c)" />
              <t />
              <t>This interface is instantiated between the callee UA and the last PS along the INVITE path.
              It is used to feed back information about an INVITE (e.g. it belonged to a SPIT call) and about
              most relevant statistics of the INVITE initiator recent behavior (even if in this case the statistics
              can be rather limited since are generated by the callee UA directly which has a narrow view on all
              the traffic). This feedback is supposed to be a very important one since it is the one directly
              generated by the callee UA (be it the software or the human itself). The PS will therefore associate
              high trust to such a feedback and act consequently. Still depending on local policies and legal
              rights the PS can decide to carry out additional tests on selected subsequent INVITEs, initiate
              communication to other entities (see <xref target="sec-if-off-path" /> or <xref target="sec-if-special"/>
              ), or block selected subsequent calls.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="sec-if-off-path" title="Off-Path Interfaces between Proxy Servers">
        <t>The basic idea of interface (d) is similar to the interface (b) where different PS exchange
        SPIT-related information. The difference to (b) is that for (d) this exchange is not bound to the
        path of an INVITE message. At interface (d) information will be shared among PS that collaborate
        on SPIT prevention (e.g. federations). While the (b) interface can potentially be an inter-domain
        interface, (d) is rather seen as an intra-domain interface where collaborating proxies of a domain
        enforce a domain-wide SPIT prevention policy. For such a purpose, information needs to be exchanged
        rather on collected information than on single events of an observed INVITE message, although this
        case should not be excluded.</t>
        <t>Interface (d) has two major purposes. the first is the exchange of information regarding certain
        caller UAs or certain administrative domains estimated to produce SPIT. This does not necessarily
        require exchanging observations per INVITE message, but rather on a regular basis or incident-driven,
        for example whenever a PS detects a correlation between several calls that have been classified as
        SPIT.</t>
        <t>The exchange of such information may, for example, lead to a classification of a source address 
        or a source network as source of SPIT which requires and update of blacklists and SPIT detection
        mechanisms.</t>
        <t>Consequently, the second major purpose of interface (d) is exchanging information that updates
        or synchronizes the prevention mechanisms that are acting at different PS. This includes particularly
        blacklist and whitelist entries, but also other SPIT prevention mechanisms may make use of exchanged
        information.</t>
        <t>Still, interface (d) may also serve for exchanging estimated results associated to single calls,
        for example for collecting this information at a central repository that serves for updating
        domain-wide SPIT prevention policies.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="sec-if-special" title="Interfaces to Special SPIT Prevention Entities">
        <t>Communication to special SPIT prevention entities can be performed either by a proxy server
        via interface (e) or by the callee UA via interface (f). We first discuss considerations that
        apply to both interfaces before pointing out differences between the two.</t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Both Interfaces (e) and (f)"/>
            <t hangText=""/>
            <t>The service offered by special SPIT prevention entities is related to the estimation
            of an INVITE to belong to a SPIT call. This communication is supposed to be instantiated
            in order to off-load computational intensive tasks to an external entity.</t>
            <t />
            <t>The communication with this SPIT prevention entity follows the client-server scheme.
            The PS or UA acting as client requests an estimation for a given INVITE message to belong
            to a SPIT call. The estimation is performed by the SPIT prevention entity acting as server.
            A request may include call parameters to be used by the server when performing the
            estimations.</t>
            <t />
            <t hangText="Interface (e)" />
            <t />
            <t>This interface is instantiated between a proxy server and a special SPIT prevention
            entity in order to request for SPIT estimations. In addition to the above considerations
            it is necessary to note that such service could be less personalized with respect to the
            service offered over the interface (f) since the estimations have to be general in order
            to deal with all the users served by the proxy server using such an interface. Otherwise
            the instantiated functions seems to be identical.</t>
            <t />
            <t hangText="Interface (f)" />
            <t />
            <t>This interface is instantiated between a UA and a special SPIT prevention entity in
            order to request for SPIT estimations. In addition to the above considerations it is
            necessary to note that such service should be more personalized with respect to the
            service offered over the interface (e) since the estimations have to be specific to
            the callee requesting them over the interface. Otherwise the instantiated functions
            seems to be identical.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="sec-need" title="Need for Standardization">
      <t>The considerations above indicate that there is an actual need for standardization of
      communication information.</t>
      <t>The strongest need seems to be for interfaces (b) and (c) in upstream direction for
      providing feedback on calls or call attempts. But also in downstream direction, there seems
      to be an obvious need to support this communication by providing a standard for it. This
      concerns both in intra- and inter-domain communication.</t>
      <t>The situation is very different for Interface (a). The considerations in <xref target="sec-if-on-path"/>
      indicate that it might even be a bad idea to provide any feedback via (a) at all. Therefore,
      we do not see a need to work on standards for interface (a).</t>
      <t>Interface (d) seems to be useful but with a more limited scope of application within
      a (federated) administrative domain (intra-domain). Still for interoperability between
      different devices it appears to be beneficial to have a standard way of sharing SPIT-related
      information.</t>
      <t>For the remaining interfaces (e) and (f) we do not yet see a clear need for interoperability.
      SPIT prevention engines to which functions are outsourced by a PS or callee UA may typically
      be part of a solution that is offered together with the PS or with a set of SIP UAs.
      For these cases proprietary communication protocols appear to be sufficient. Still need for
      standardization may arise at later stages when SPIT prevention entities become more common.</t>
      
      <section anchor="sec-protocols" title="Preliminary Protocol Considerations">
        <t>The fact that the communication over interfaces (b) and (c) follows the same path as the
        SIP signaling itself may influence the choice of the signaling protocols used for exchanging
        information at the interfaces. An obvious choice to be discussed would be embedding the SPIT
        information directly in the SIP messages flowing among the entities anyway.</t>
        <t>For the other interfaces (d), (e) and (f) other signaling protocols may be preferable since
        the communication will happen anyway not synchronously with the SIP messages used to initiate
        the session. An example could be the exchange of XML files among different entities.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="sec-conclusions" title="Conclusions">
      <t>This memo addresses the necessity of providing standards for communication between entities
      involved in SPIT prevention. For this purpose a reference scenario is defined with involved
      entities and interfaces between them. For each interface the need for it and the need for standards
      for is discussed.</t>
      <t>This memo is intended to stimulate a discussion on SPIT prevention and to reach consensus
      on the identification of standardization goals and reference architectures in this area. Some
      of the considerations in <xref target="sec-interfaces" /> seem to indicate that there is an
      actual need to standardize communication for some of the discussed interfaces. This memo does 
      ot try to standardize any solution to the problems identified. The necessary work outcoming
      from the discussion stimulated will have to be carried out in separate documents.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="sec-security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This memo discusses the exchange of information related to SPIT prevention. This includes
      information on particular calls or call attempts as well as information on call initiators
      potentially being a source of SPIT.</t>
      <t>Exchanging per-call information may violate the privacy of a caller. Therefore, instantiations
      of the discussed exchange of information need to be carefully checked for compliance with legal
      regulations of information privacy. Also, since this information may be sensitive, appropriate
      steps should be undertaken to provide confidentiality when it is transmitted over the Internet.</t>
      <t>Both, per-call information and information of a caller being a source of SPIT may be a target
      of denial-of-service attacks. If such messages are faked, a regular caller may be blocked
      network-wide and not able anymore to perform calls. Therefore, integrity and authenticity need
      to be provided when this kind of information is transmitted over the Internet.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="sec-iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
    </section>
    
  </middle>
  
  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">    
    &rfc5039;
    &I-D.tschofenig-sipping-framework-spit-reduction;
    &I-D.tschofenig-sipping-spit-policy;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>