<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5039 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5039.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3761 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3761.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4474 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4474.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.tschofenig-sipping-framework-spit-reduction SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-tschofenig-sipping-framework-spit-reduction-02.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc colonspace='yes' ?>
<?rfc tocindent='yes' ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-schwartz-rucus-problem-statement-01" ipr="full3978">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RUCUS Problem statement">RUCUS Problem Statement</title>

	<author initials="D.S" surname="Schwartz" fullname="David Schwartz">
			<organization>XConnect Global Networks</organization>
				<address>
					<postal>
						<street>Malcha Technology Park</street>
						<street>Building # 1</street>
						<city>Jerusalem</city><code>90961</code>
						<country>Israel</country>
					</postal>
					<phone>+972 52 347 4656</phone>
					<email>dschwartz@xconnect.net</email>
					<uri>www.kayote.com</uri>
			   </address>
		</author>

    <date year="2008" />

    <abstract>
      <t>SIP is being used more an more today 
      for everyday communication purposes. With this widespread adoption comes 
      the inevitability of abuse. This document describes the problems that fit 
      into the category of "unwanted Communication".</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">
      </xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>As worldwide communication infrastructure is shifting to IP the 
      potential for disruption or abuse is increasing as well (see cost
      analysis brought down in <xref target="RFC5039"></xref>). As such it 
      is important to be able to assess the potential threat so that possible
      remedies can be sought. It is important to stress, however, that 
      this document and by extension this WG is not focusing ONLY on fraud
      or misrepresentation attacks such as those mentioned in <xref 
      target="RFC5039"></xref>) but on all types of "unwanted" communications.</t>

      <t>Fortunately (or unfortunately) we have a large body of work 
      already completed in other similar areas such as email and as such 
      the guiding principles of this WG MUST be:</t>

      <t>What has been done right</t>

      <t>What has been done wrong</t>

      <t>What should have been done earlier</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Unwanted Communication">
      <t>So what constitutes Unwanted Communication? Until now, most of the 
      work that has been done in this area in the various IETF WGs has 
      focused on the "misrepresentation" issue (<xref target="RFC5039"></xref>)
      suggesting strong Identity (e.g. <xref target="RFC4474"></xref>) as the 
      cornerstone of any solution. Lately, there has been a lot of discussion
      on the various lists trying to extend the identity protection (or better
      yet - give it some meaning) to e.164 numbers as well as sip URIs.</t>

     <t>Still, this is only one aspect of "Unwanted Communications" and 
     focusing or solving only this issue (if at all possible) will clearly 
     not eliminate SPAM. As an example, one attack that is cropping up
     of late is a hybrid email VoIP attack which upgrades the age old phishing
     attack by replacing a compromised web server with a compromised PBX (or 
     one set up just for this purpose) and includes an e.164 number in the email 
     message that supposedly is sent by your bank instead of the traditional
     fake URL.  Since there is no "whois" equivalent for e.164 numbers there
     is no way today to combat this attack.  While not much can be done if 
     the unsuspecting caller initiates the call from the PSTN, if the call is
     initiated using SIP, there may be some help we can provide. But this 
     help is contingent on us realizing that the problem scope is wider than
     we previously imagined.</t>
	 
	 <t>Following is an initial list of possible unwanted communication 
	 categories:</t>
	 
	 <figure anchor="unwanted categories" title="Unwanted Communications Categories">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
    Data Mining -       This category includes messaging whose sole
                        purpose is to mine for information.
                        Included in this category are things like Number 
                        Harvesting via SIP or ENUM		
	
    B-side attacks -    This category is rooted in the lack of a 
                        "whois" equivalent for e.164 numbers and
                        includs attacks where the originating 
                        party has no information attesting to the 
                        credibility or authenticity of the signaled 
                        party

    Lack of policy -    This category deals with the non-malicious
                        middle-of-the-night or foreign-language 
                        communication.  Strong identity will not 
                        prevent this sort of communication.
		
    Misrepresentation - The one we all like to hate. In this 
                        category are included:
		    			
                        * Telemarketing
                        * Fraudulent access (e.g. voice mail)
                        
                        Any application where access is based
                        on the signaling party's phone number
                        falls into this category
					
    "underprivileged" - Malicious applications just trying to 
                        gain a foothold on a remote computer fall 
                        into this category. This class addresses
                        attacks that use IP communications as
                        a means rather than an end.
        ]]></artwork>
     </figure>
	 
	 <t>You will note in the list above I have included things like number
	 mining even though the is not part of a "communication" process. I did
	 this since this is a prepatory attack for unwanted communcations I felt
	 it should be dealt with in this context as well.</t>
   </section>

    <section title="Data Mining">
      <t>As opposed to the URI namespace which is infinite, the e.164 namespace 
	  which is in use for the majority of SIP voice calls today is not large
	  in computing terms.  As a result, it is quite trivial to gather or mine 
	  this information for use (individually or for resale) in misrepresentation 
	  attacks.  Low volume SIP INVITE messages recording failures (e.g. 404 Not found) 
	  and successes (e.g. 183 Session Progress) are highly effective and relatively 
	  hard to defend against.  These kind of attacks have been seen in the field using 
	  both SIP <xref target="RFC3261"></xref> and ENUM <xref target="RFC3761">
	  </xref></t>
    </section>

    <section title="B-Side Attacks">
      <t>It is important to understand that SPAM is not static but rather is all
	  about economics and adapts accoridignly. While the return on investment for 
	  the misrepresentation attacks does not yet justify widespread use, the ROI 
	  for B-side attacks is clearer and is being seen in the field today.  Basically, 
	  the spammers go with what works - and phishing works better than telemarketing. 
	  When you do the math you see that a very small hit percentage is needed for a 
	  highly successful phishing campaign to materialize.  Continual improvement in
	  protection against this sort of attack is forcing the phishers to adapt as
	  well (e.g. inline GIFs instead of embedded URLs that can be verified).</t>
	  
	  <t>Against this backdrop it is to be expected that the next step in
	  the evolution of phishing is to include an instruction to dial a DID or 
	  virtual phone number that the caller has no way to verify - where this will 
	  lead to nefarius activities.  In a sense it is the "B-side" that is 
	  threatening the "A-side" and hence the name of this category.  It is 
	  important to realize that this attack is not unique to IP communications.
	  The compromised "B-side" could belong a PSTN compromised switch.  The 
	  thing is that (a) its harder to comparmise a PSTN switch (b) who ever
	  said that we have to limit ourselves to the protection available
	  on the PSTN?</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Lack Of Policy">
      <t>Unwanted communication is subjective - not objective. As such it is entirely 
	  possible for a legitimate call to be unwanted (even at the level of not having
	  the phone ring and force me to answer) at its intended destination and 
	  it is completely reasonable to arm the receiving party with the ability to 
	  prevent this sort of occurance a-priori.  In order to combat this form of 
	  unwanted communication there is a need for policy exchange mechanisms as
	  discussed in <xref target="I-D.tschofenig-sipping-framework-spit-reduction">
	  </xref></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Misrepresentation">
      <t>This category deals with propagation of trusted identity across trust
	  boundaries and is covered in <xref target="RFC5039"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Regulatory">
      <t>It wouldn't be right to finish a document describing the RUCUS problem
	  statement without raising the specter of regulatory involvement.  An incident 
	  which occurred in 1997 in which House Speaker Newt Gingrich's cellular telephone 
	  conversation was illegally intercepted, taped and published by the media 
	  prompted calls in Congress for stronger anti-eavesdropping legislation.  One can 
	  only imagine what unwanted communications to one of these legislatures will
	  cause to IP communications.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security_considerations" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>[[This section will be completed in a later version of this
   document.]]</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Adam O'Donell for alerting me to the VoIP aspects
	  of email phishing.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>None. This document is informational</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;

      &rfc3261;
	  	  
    </references>

    <references title="Informational References">
	  &rfc5039;
	  
	  &rfc4474;

	  &rfc3761;

	  &I-D.tschofenig-sipping-framework-spit-reduction;

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
