<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<!--<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>-->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-ietf-tsvwg-iana-ports-00" ipr="full3978"
    updates="2780, 4340">
 <front>
   <title abbrev="IANA Port Number Space Procedures">IANA Procedures for the
   Transport Protocol Port Number Space</title>

   <!-- AUTHORS ALPHABETICAL -->

   <author fullname="Michelle Cotton" initials="M." surname="Cotton">
     <organization abbrev="ICANN">Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and
     Numbers</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>4676 Admiralty Way, Suite 330</street>

         <code>90292</code>

         <city>Marina del Rey</city>

         <region>CA</region>

         <country>USA</country>
       </postal>

       <phone>+1 310 823 9358</phone>

       <email>michelle.cotton@icann.org</email>

       <uri>http://www.iana.org/</uri>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Lars Eggert" initials="L." surname="Eggert">
     <organization abbrev="Nokia">Nokia Research Center</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>P.O. Box 407</street>

         <code>00045</code>

         <city>Nokia Group</city>

         <country>Finland</country>
       </postal>

       <phone>+358 50 48 24461</phone>

       <email>lars.eggert@nokia.com</email>

       <uri>http://research.nokia.com/people/lars_eggert/</uri>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Allison Mankin" initials="A." surname="Mankin">
     <organization abbrev="NSF">National Science Foundation</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>4102 Wilson Boulevard</street>

         <city>Arlington</city>

         <region>VA</region>

         <code>22230</code>

         <country>USA</country>
       </postal>

       <phone>+1 301 728 7199</phone>

       <email>mankin@psg.com</email>

       <uri>http://www.psg.com/~mankin/</uri>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Magnus Westerlund" initials="M. " surname="Westerlund">
     <organization>Ericsson</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>Torshamsgatan 23</street>

         <city>Stockholm</city>

         <code>164 80</code>

         <country>Sweden</country>
       </postal>

       <phone>+46 8 719 0000</phone>

       <email>magnus.westerlund@ericsson.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Joe Touch" initials="J." surname="Touch">
     <organization>USC/ISI</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>

         <code>90292</code>

         <city>Marina del Rey</city>

         <region>CA</region>

         <country>USA</country>
       </postal>

       <phone>+1 310 448 9151</phone>

       <email>touch@isi.edu</email>

       <uri>http://www.isi.edu/touch</uri>
     </address>
   </author>

   <date year="2008" />

   <area>Transport Area</area>

   <workgroup>Transport Area Working Group</workgroup>

   <keyword>IANA</keyword>

   <keyword>transport</keyword>

   <keyword>ports</keyword>

   <keyword>port numbers</keyword>

   <keyword>allocation</keyword>

   <keyword>procedures</keyword>

   <abstract>
     <t>This document defines the IANA procedures for registering port number
     values for use with the various IETF transport protocols, including TCP,
     UDP, DCCP, and SCTP. It provides clear procedures for the management of
     the port number registry, which is important for its long-term
     management. It updates RFC2780 by obsoleting Sections 8 and 9.1 of that
     RFC, and it updates the IANA allocation procedures for DCCP as defined
     in RFC4340.</t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
     <t>The Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) <xref
     target="RFC0793"></xref> and the User Datagram Protocol (UDP) <xref
     target="RFC0768"></xref> have enjoyed a remarkable success over the
     decades as the two most widely used transport protocols on the Internet.
     They have introduced the concept of "ports" as logical entities for
     Internet communication. Ports serve two purposes: first, they provide a
     demultiplexing identifier to differentiate transport sessions between
     the same pair of endpoints, and second, they also identify the
     application protocol and associated service to which processes bind
     <xref target="I-D.touch-tsvwg-port-guidelines"></xref>. Newer transport
     protocols, such as the Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP) <xref
     target="RFC4960"></xref> and the Datagram Congestion Control Protocol
     (DCCP) <xref target="RFC4342"></xref> have adopted the concept of ports
     for their communication sessions and use port numbers in the same way as
     TCP and UDP.</t>

     <t>Port numbers are the original and most widely used means for
     application and service identification on the Internet. Ports are 16-bit
     numbers, and the combination of source and destination port numbers
     together with the IP addresses of the communicating end systems uniquely
     identifies a session of a given transport protocol. Port numbers are
     also known by their corresponding service names, such as "telnet" for
     port number 23 and "http" for port number 80.</t>

     <t>Hosts running services, hosts accessing services on other hosts, and
     intermediate devices (such as firewalls and NATs) that restrict services
     need to agree on which service corresponds to a particular destination
     port. Although this can be a local decision between the endpoints of a
     connection, most Internet components use a single, shared view of this
     association, provided by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA)
     through the port number registry <xref target="REGISTRY"></xref>.</t>

     <t>Designers of applications and application-level protocols may apply
     to IANA for a registered port number for a specific application, and may
     - after successful registration - assume that no other application will
     use that port number for its communication sessions. It is important to
     note that ownership of registered port numbers remains with IANA. For
     many years, the allocation and registration of new port number values
     for use with TCP and UDP have had less than clear guidelines.
     Information about the registration procedures for the port namespace
     existed in three locations: the forms for requesting port number
     registrations on the IANA web site <xref target="SYSFORM"></xref><xref
     target="USRFORM"></xref>, an introductory text section in the file
     listing the port number registrations themselves <xref
     target="REGISTRY"></xref>, and two brief sections of <xref
     target="RFC2780"></xref>.</t>

     <t>This document aggregates this scattered information into a single
     reference and at the same time clarifies the guidelines for the
     management of the port number space. It gives more detailed guidance to
     prospective requesters of ports than the existing documentation, and it
     streamlines the IANA procedures for the management of the port number
     space, so that management requests can complete in a timely manner. A
     key factor of this streamlining is to establish identical registration
     procedures for transport protocol ports, independent of a specific
     transport protocol. This document brings the IANA procedures for TCP and
     UDP in line with those already in effect for SCTP and DCCP, resulting in
     a single process that requesters and IANA follow for all port number
     requests for all transport protocols, including those not yet
     defined.</t>

     <t>A second purpose of this document is to describe the principles that
     guide the IETF and IANA in their role as the long-term joint stewards of
     the port number space. TCP and UDP have been a remarkable success over
     the last decades. Thousands of applications and application-level
     protocols have registered ports for their use, and there is every reason
     to believe that this trend will continue into the future. It is hence
     extremely important that management of the port number space follow
     principles that ensure its long-term usefulness as a shared resource.
     <xref target="principles"></xref> discusses these principles in detail.
     Guidelines for users seeking port numbers, as well as a detailed history
     of the port number registry and alternate means for coordinating host
     agreement on service-to-port-number mappings, is provided in a <xref
     target="I-D.touch-tsvwg-port-guidelines">companion document</xref>.</t>

     <t>In addition to detailing the IANA procedures for the initial
     assignment of port numbers, this document also specifies post-assignment
     procedures that until now have been handled in an ad hoc manner. These
     include procedures to de-register a port number that is no longer in
     use, to re-use a port number allocated for one application that is no
     longer in use for another application, and procedure by which IANA can
     unilaterally revoke a prior port number registration. <xref
     target="iana-procedures"></xref> discusses the specifics of these
     procedures.</t>

     <t><!--Unsure how to handle the following paragraph...O-->This document
     also addresses two technical issues related to the ports registry that
     are tangential to long-term stewardship. First, it clarifies that a
     method for the early allocation of port numbers is available for IETF
     working groups, in line with <xref target="RFC4020"></xref>. Second, it
     discusses how the use of symbolic names for assigned ports (the
     "keyword" field in <xref target="REGISTRY"></xref>) for Service Resource
     Records (SRV RRs) in the Domain Name System (DNS) <xref
     target="RFC2782"></xref> relates to the use of SRV RRs for applications
     without an assigned port.</t>

     <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC2780"></xref> by obsoleting
     Sections 8 and 9.1 of that RFC. Note that <xref target="RFC5237"></xref>
     updates a different subset of the IANA allocation guidelines originally
     given in <xref target="RFC2780"></xref> (specifically, the policies on
     the namespace of the IP protocol number and IPv6 next header).</t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="term" title="Terminology">
     <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
     "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
     document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14, RFC 2119 <xref
     target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="types" title="Port Number Types">
     <t>TCP, UDP, SCTP and DCCP use 16-bit namespaces for their port number
     registries. The port registries for all these transport protocols are
     subdivided into three ranges of numbers, and <xref
     target="requests"></xref> describes the IANA procedures for each range
     in detail: <list style="symbols">
         <t>the Well Known Ports, i.e., the System Ports, from 0-1023
         (assigned by IANA)</t>

         <t>the Registered Ports, i.e., the User Ports, from 1024-49151
         (assigned by IANA)</t>

         <t>the Dynamic Ports, i.e., the Private Ports, from 49152-65535
         (never assigned)</t>
       </list></t>

     <t>Of the assignable port ranges (Well Known and Registered, i.e., port
     numbers 0-49151), individual port numbers are in one of three states at
     any given time:</t>

     <t><list style="numbers">
         <t>Assigned: Assigned port numbers are currently allocated to the
         service indicated in the registry.</t>

         <t>Unassigned: Unassigned port numbers are currently available for
         assignment upon request, as per the procedures outlined in this
         document.</t>

         <t>Reserved: Reserved port numbers are not available for regular
         assignment; they are "assigned to IANA" for special purposes.
         Reserved port numbers include values at the edges of each range,
         e.g., 0, 1023, 1024, etc., which may be used to extend these ranges
         or the overall port number space in the future.</t>
       </list></t>

     <t>When this document was written, approximately 76% of the TCP and UDP
     Well Known Ports were assigned, as were a significant fraction of the
     Registered Ports. (As noted, Dynamic Ports are never assigned.)</t>

     <section anchor="exp" title="Assigned Port Numbers for Experimentation">
       <t>Of the Registered Ports, two TCP and UDP port numbers (1021 and
       1022) have been assigned for experimentation with new applications and
       application-layer protocols that require a port number in the
       Registered Ports range <xref target="RFC4727"></xref>. <cref
       anchor="sctp-dccp-exp" source="Lars">This document should register
       ports 1021 and 1022 for DCCP and SCTP.</cref></t>

       <t>The experimental ports 1021 and 1022 SHOULD be used for local
       experiments only in controlled environments, and they SHOULD NOT be
       used on the global Internet. Many new applications and
       application-layer protocols can be experimented with without requiring
       a port in the Registered Ports range, and port numbers in the Dynamic
       Ports range can be also used.</t>

       <t>Unfortunately, it can be difficult to limit access to these ports.
       Users SHOULD take measures to ensure that experimental ports are
       connecting to the intended process. For example, users of these
       experimental ports might include a 64-bit nonce, once on each segment
       of a message-oriented channel (e.g., UDP), or once at the beginning of
       a byte-stream (e.g., TCP), which is used to confirm that the port is
       being used as intended. Such confirmation of intended use is
       especially important when these ports are associated with privileged
       (e.g., system or administrator) processes.</t>
     </section>
   </section>

   <section anchor="principles"
            title="Principles for Port Number Space Management">
     <t>Management procedures for the port number space include allocation of
     port numbers upon request, as well as coordination of information about
     existing allocations. The latter includes maintaining contact and
     description information about assigned ports, revoking abandoned ports,
     and redefining port allocations when needed. Of these procedures, port
     number allocation is most critical, because of the limited number of
     remaining port numbers.</t>

     <t>Before the publication of this document, the principles of port
     number space allocation followed some simple, undocumented
     guidelines:</t>

     <t><list style="symbols">
         <t>TCP and UDP ports were simultaneously allocated when either was
         requested</t>

         <t>Port numbers were the primary allocation; service names were
         informative only, and did not need to be unique</t>

         <t>Port numbers were conserved informally, and sometimes
         inconsistently (e.g., some services were allocated ranges of many
         port numbers even where not strictly necessary)</t>

         <t>SCTP and DCCP port number and service name spaces were managed
         separately from the TCP/UDP spaces</t>
       </list>This document attempts to update these guidelines to more
     conservatively manage the limited remaining TCP and UDP port number
     spaces, recognizes the potential use of service names in the absence of
     corresponding port number allocations, such as in SCTP and DCCP.</t>

     <!--Verify that both SCTP and DCCP use service names without assigned port numbers.-->

     <t>The basic principle of port number registry management is to conserve
     the space where possible. Extensions to support larger port number
     spaces would require changing many core protocols of the current
     Internet in a way that would not be backward compatible and interfere
     with both current and legacy applications.</t>

     <t>Port numbers are intended to indicate a service and enable process
     demultiplexing at an endpoint; uses beyond those basic requirements
     should be avoided <xref
     target="I-D.touch-tsvwg-port-guidelines"></xref>. This document also
     focuses on service names as a unique identifier, to increase the space
     available (from 4 bytes to 14), and to enable their use in the absence
     of corresponding port number assignments.</t>

     <section title="Basic Principles of Port Conservation">
       <t>This section summarizes the basic principles by which IANA attempts
       to conserve the port number space. This description is intended to
       inform applicants requesting port numbers. IANA decisions are not
       required to be bound to these principles, however; other factors may
       come into play, and exceptions may occur where deemed in the best
       interest of the Internet.</t>

       <t>Conservation of the port number space recognizes that because this
       space is a limited resource, applications are expected to participate
       in the demultiplexing process where feasible. The port numbers are
       expected to encode as little information as possible that will enable
       an application to perform further demultiplexing by itself. In
       particular, there should be:</t>

       <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>only one port per service</t>

           <t>one port for all versions of a service</t>

           <t>the same port for different types of devices using the same
           service</t>
         </list>A given service is expected to further demultiplex messages
       where possible. For example, applications and protocols are expected
       to include in-band version information, so that future versions of the
       application or protocol can share the same allocated port.
       Applications and protocols are also expected to be able to efficiently
       use a single allocated port, either by demultiplexing multiple streams
       within one port, or using the allocated port to coordinate using
       dynamic ports for subsequent exchanges (e.g., in the spirit of FTP
       <xref target="RFC0959"></xref>).</t>

       <t>These principles of port conservation are explained in <xref
       target="I-D.touch-tsvwg-port-guidelines"></xref>. That document
       explains in further detail how ports are used in various ways,
       notably:</t>

       <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>Endpoint process identifier</t>

           <t>Application protocol identifier</t>

           <t>Firewall filtering</t>
         </list>The process and protocol identifier use suggests that
       anything a single process can demultiplex, or that can be encoded into
       a single protocol, should be. The firewall filtering use suggests that
       some uses that could be de-multiplexed or encoded must be separated to
       allow for firewall management. Note that this latter use is much less
       sound, because port numbers have meaning only for the two endpoints of
       a connection (again, as discussed in detail in <xref
       target="I-D.touch-tsvwg-port-guidelines"></xref>).</t>
     </section>

     <section title="Principles Specific to Individual Port Number Ranges">
       <t>It is important to note that different IANA procedures apply to
       different ranges of the port number registry. <xref
       target="requests"></xref> discusses the details of these procedures;
       this section outlines the rationale for these differences:<list
           style="symbols">
           <t>Ports in the Dynamic Ports range (49152-65535) have been
           specifically set aside for local and dynamic use and cannot be
           registered through IANA. Applications may simply use them for
           communication without any sort of registration. On the other hand,
           applications MUST NOT assume that a specific port number in the
           Dynamic Ports range will always be available for communication at
           all times, and a port number in that range hence MUST NOT be used
           as a service identifier.</t>

           <t>Ports in the Registered Ports range (1024-49151) are available
           for registration through IANA, and MAY be used as service
           identifiers upon successful registration. Because registering a
           port number for a specific application consumes a fraction of the
           shared resource that is the port number registry, IANA will
           require the requester to document the intended use of the port
           number, and have a technical expert review this documentation to
           determine whether to grant the registration request. This
           documentation MUST explain why a port number in the Dynamic Ports
           range is unsuitable for the given application.</t>

           <t>Ports in the Well Known Ports range (0-1023) are also available
           for registration through IANA. Because the Well Known Ports range
           is both the smallest and the most densely allocated one, the bar
           for new allocations is higher than that for the Registered Ports
           range (1024-49551). A request for a Well Known port number MUST
           document why a port number in the Registered Ports or Dynamic
           Ports ranges is unsuitable.</t>
         </list></t>
     </section>

     <section title="New Principles">
       <t>Several new practices stem from the conservation principle that
       guides management of the port numbers registry, and will take effect
       with the approval of this document:</t>

       <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>IANA will allocate port numbers only to the transport protocols
           requested</t>

           <t>IANA will recover unused port numbers, via the new procedures
           of de-registration, revocation, and transfer</t>
         </list></t>

       <t>IANA will begin assigning protocol numbers only for those transport
       protocols explicitly included in a registration request. This ends the
       long-standing practice of automatically assigning a port number to an
       application for both TCP and a UDP, even if the request is only for
       one of these transport protocols. The new allocation procedure
       conserves resources by only allocating a port number to an application
       for those transport protocols (TCP, UDP, SCTP and/or DCCP) it actually
       uses. The port number will be marked as reserved - instead of assigned
       - in the port number registries of the other transport protocols. When
       applications start supporting the use of some of those additional
       transport protocols, they must request IANA to convert the reservation
       into an assignment. An application MUST NOT assume that it can use a
       port number assigned to it for use with one transport protocol with
       another transport protocol without another registration with IANA. The
       reason for this procedure is to allow allocation of reserved port
       numbers on the day the range has no more unassigend values. <cref
       source="Magnus" anchor="port-reserv">The usage of for the above reason reserved port
       numbers should probably not have the same rules as the other reserved
       ports. Needs discussion if we should separate this properly. I think
       the IETF consultation part will make it difficult the day one registry
       runs out of unassigned ones.</cref> </t>

       <t>Conservation for the port numbers registry is improved by
       procedures that allow previously allocated port numbers to become
       unassigned, either through de-registration or through revocation, and
       by a procedure that lets application designers transfer an allocated
       but unused port number to a new application. <xref
       target="iana-procedures"></xref> describes these procedures, which so
       far were undocumented.</t>
     </section>
   </section>

   <section anchor="iana-procedures"
            title="IANA Procedures for Managing the Port Number Space">
     <t>IANA supports various procedures to manage the port number space that
     enable ports to be registered, de-registered, reused, and revoked. This
     section explains these procedures, as well as other related issues.</t>

     <section anchor="registration" title="Port Number Registration">
       <t>Registration refers to the allocation of port numbers to
       applicants. All such registrations are made from port numbers that are
       Unassigned or Reserved at the tine of the allocation. Unassigned
       numbers are allocated as needed, and without further explanation.
       Reserved numbers are assigned only after review by IANA and the IETF,
       and are accompanied by a statement explaining the reason a reserved
       number is appropriate for this action.</t>

       <t>When a registration for one or more (but not all) transport
       protocols is approved, the port number for the non-requested transport
       protocol(s) will remain unassigned but is marked as reserved. However,
       IANA SHOULD NOT assign that port number to any other application or
       service until no port numbers remain unassigned in the request range.
       The current registration owner of a port number MAY register the same
       port number for other transport protocols when needed.</t>

       <t>A port number registration consists of the following tuple:</t>

       <t><list style="hanging">
           <t hangText="Registration Contact:">Name and email address of the
           contact person for the registration. This is REQUIRED. Additional
           address information MAY be provided. For registrations done
           through IETF-published RFCs, one or more technical contact persons
           SHALL be provided. In addition, in this case the registration
           ownership will belong to the IETF and not the technical contact
           persons.</t>

           <t hangText="Transport Protocol:">The transport protocol(s) for
           which the port allocation is requested, currently limited to one
           or more of TCP, UDP, SCTP, and DCCP</t>

           <t hangText="Port Number:">The currently unassigned port number(s)
           the requester suggests for allocation. If specified and when
           possible, IANA is encouraged to allocate the suggested number. If
           not specified, IANA will choose a suitable number from the
           Registered Ports range.</t>

           <t hangText="Broadcast, Multicast or Anycast:">Indicates whether
           the protocol supports either broadcast, multicast or anycast
           network layer addresses.</t>

           <t hangText="Port Name:">The long name (description) of the port.
           It should avoid all but the most well known acronyms.</t>

           <t hangText="Service Name:">This short name for the port number,
           used in various service selection and discovery mechanisms,
           currently including TCPMUX <xref target="RFC1078"></xref> and DNS
           SRV resource records <xref target="RFC2782"></xref>. This name is
           limited to 14 bytes, case-insensitive US-ASCII letters, digits,
           and dashes. It MUST NOT conflict with already allocated names in
           the service name registry <cref anchor="serv-nam-reg"
           source="Lars">Add citation to the service name registry draft,
           when it exists</cref>.</t>

           <t hangText="Reference:">A reference document describing the
           protocol or application using this port. For registration requests
           for Registered Ports, this documentation MUST explain why a port
           number in the Dynamic Ports range is unsuitable for the given
           application. For registration requests for Well Known Ports, this
           documentation MUST explain why a port number in the Registered
           Ports or Dynamic Ports ranges is unsuitable.</t>
         </list>The following rules apply to the port number registry
       database maintained by IANA: <cref anchor="database-rules"
       source="Lars">Some of these rules below allow entries that aren't in
       full alignment with the procedures in this document. I assume that is,
       because the rules attempt to describe the state of the IANA database
       including all existing entries? If so, we should make that
       clearer.</cref></t>

       <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>Service Names MUST be unique</t>

           <t>Service Name MUST exist for all transport protocols</t>

           <t>Port Number MUST exist for TCP and UDP; it MAY exist for SCTP
           and DCCP</t>

           <t>Transport Protocol MUST exist for all entries</t>

           <t>Service Code MUST NOT occur for TCP, UDP or SCTP, and MUST
           occur for DCCP</t>

           <t>Port Name MUST exist for all entries</t>

           <t>Currently valid Registration Contact SHOULD exist for all
           entries; it MUST exist for all new entries</t>

           <t>Reference SHOULD exist for all entries</t>
         </list></t>
     </section>

     <section anchor="deregistration" title="Port Number De-Registration">
       <t>The original requesters of a granted port number assignment can
       return the port number to IANA at any time if they no longer have a
       need for it. The port number will be de-registered and will be marked
       as reserved <cref anchor="res-vs-unass" source="Lars">This used to say
       "unassigned" instead of "reserved". I suggest "reserved", so that IANA
       has an indication in their list that they need to be careful when
       re-assigning a previously de-registered port.</cref> IANA should not
       re-assign port numbers that have been de-registered until all other
       available port numbers in the specific range have been assigned.</t>

       <t>Before proceeding with a de-registration, IANA needs to confirm
       that the port number is actually no longer in use.</t>
     </section>

     <section anchor="reuse" title="Port Number Re-Use">
       <t>If the original requesters of a granted port number assignment no
       longer have a need for the registered number, but would like to re-use
       it for a different application, they can submit a request to IANA to
       do so.</t>

       <t>Logically, port number re-use is to be thought of as a
       de-registration followed by an immediate re-registration of the same
       port number for a new application. Consequently, the information that
       needs to be provided about the proposed new use of the port number is
       identical to what would need to be provided for a new port number
       allocation for the specific ports range.</t>

       <t>IANA needs to carefully review such requests before approving them.
       In some instances, the Expert Reviewer will determine that the
       application that the port number was assigned to has found usage
       beyond the original requester, or that there is a concern that it may
       have such users. This determination MUST be made quickly. A community
       call concerning revocation of a port number (see below) MAY be
       considered, if a broader use of the port number is suspected.</t>
     </section>

     <section anchor="revocation" title="Port Number Revocation">
       <t>Sometimes, it will be clear that a specific port number is no
       longer in use and that IANA can de-register it and mark it as reserved
       <cref anchor="res-vs-unass2" source="Lars">See [res-vs-unass].</cref>
       But at other times, it may be unclear whether a given assigned port
       number is still in use somewhere in the Internet. In those cases,
       despite the requester's wish to de-register, IANA must consider the
       consequences that de-registering the port number.</t>

       <t>With the help of their IESG-appointed Expert Reviewer, IANA SHALL
       formulate a request to the IESG to issue a four-week community call
       concerning the pending port number revocation. The IESG and IANA, with
       the Expert Reviewer's support, SHALL determine promptly after the end
       of the community call whether revocation should proceed and then
       communicate their decision to the community. This procedure typically
       involves similar steps to de-registration except that it is initiated
       by IANA.</t>
     </section>

     <section anchor="transfer" title="Port Number Transfer">
       <t>The value of port numbers is defined by their careful management as
       a shared Internet resource, whereas enabling transfer allows the
       potential for associated monetary exchanges to motivate this
       management. As a result, current IANA procedures do not permit port
       number assignments to be transferred between parties, even when they
       are mutually consenting. The appropriate alternate procedure is for
       the new party to request its own port number registration and for the
       previous party to release its registration via the de-registration
       procedure outlined above.</t>
     </section>

     <section title="Maintenance Issues">
       <t>The previous procedures help IANA manage defining properties of the
       port name space. There are additional procedures which are
       administrative, and help IANA maintain non-defining information in a
       registration. This includes changes to the Port Name (i.e.,
       description), and changes to contact information. These changes are
       coordinated by IANA in an informal manner, and may be initiated by
       either the registrant or by IANA, e.g., the latter when requesting an
       update to current contact information.</t>
     </section>
   </section>

   <section anchor="requests" title="Port Number Space Requests">
     <t>This section describes the process for requests associated with
     IANA's management of the the port number space. Such requests include
     initial registration, de-registration, re-use, changes to the service
     name, as well as updates to the contact information or port name
     (description). Revocation is initiated by IANA.</t>

     <!--Does this include changes to the service name? that seems semantic, and should require the form, IMO (as noted above).-->

     <section title="Request Procedure">
       <t>All registration requests for a TCP, SCTP, DCCP and/or UDP ports
       must contain the following pieces of information:</t>

       <t><list style="hanging">
           <t hangText="Port number tuple:">A port number tuple, as described
           in <xref target="registration"></xref>. The port number would
           typically be omitted; when provided, it indicates a preference for
           requesting a currently unassigned value.</t>

           <t hangText="Port Range:">Indicates the port range desired (i.e.,
           Well Known Ports or Registered Ports).</t>

           <t hangText="Requested Action:">One of REGISTER, DEREGISTER,
           REUSE, SVC_NAME_CHANGE, or UPDATE_INFO (port name, registration
           contact).</t>

           <!--What characters are allowed in service names?-->
         </list><!--Are service names supposed to be unique? does this document define that requirement?--></t>

       <t>The Well Known Ports are assigned by IANA and cover the range
       0-1023. On many systems, they can only be used by system (or root)
       processes or by programs executed by privileged users. Registration
       requests for a Well Known port number MUST follow the "IETF Review"
       policy of <xref target="RFC5226"></xref>. Registrations for a port
       number in this range MUST document why a port number in the Registered
       Ports range will not fulfill the application needs.</t>

       <t><!--[JT - IMO, this is an outdated artifact; since some systems allow all users to attach listening processes to these ports, clients cannot assume that such ports are run by privileged process. The only difference remaining is IETF review vs. expert review. Why do we care?]-->The
       Registered Ports are assigned by IANA and on most systems can be used
       by ordinary user processes or programs executed by ordinary users. The
       Registered Ports are in the range 1024-49151. Registration requests
       for a Registered Port number MUST follow the "Expert Review" policy of
       <xref target="RFC5226"></xref>.</t>
     </section>
   </section>

   <section anchor="seccons" title="Security Considerations">
     <t>The IANA guidelines described in this document do not change the
     security properties of either TCP, SCTP, DCCP or UDP.</t>

     <t><!-- disclaimer from http://www.iana.org/assignments/port-numbers -->Assignment
     of a port number does not in any way imply an endorsement of an
     application or product, and the fact that network traffic is flowing to
     or from a registered port number does not mean that it is "good"
     traffic, or even that the it is used by the assigned service. Firewall
     and system administrators should choose how to configure their systems
     based on their knowledge of the traffic in question, not whether there
     is a port number registered or not.</t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="ianacons" title="IANA Considerations">
     <!-- put all changes from 2780 into this section
-->

     <t>This document obsoletes Sections 8 and 9.1 of <xref
     target="RFC2780"></xref>. Upon approval of this document, IANA is
     requested to adopt the procedures described herein.</t>

     <t>IANA should take immediate actions to resolve inconsistencies raised
     by requirements of this document.<!--, notably [UNIQUE KEYS].--></t>

     <t><!--[IS well-known deprecated?]--></t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgments">
     <t>The text in <xref target="dccp"></xref> is based on a suggestion by
     Tom Phelan.</t>

     <t>Lars Eggert is partly funded by <xref target="TRILOGY"></xref>, a
     research project supported by the European Commission under its Seventh
     Framework Program.</t>
   </section>
 </middle>

 <!-- REFERENCE TEMPLATE
     <reference anchor="reference.XXX">
             <front>
                     <title>XXX</title>
                     <author initials="X." surname="XXX" fullname="XXX">
                             <organization abbrev="XXX">XXX</organization>
                             <address>
                                     <postal>
                                             <street>XXX</street>
                                             <city>XXX</city>
                                             <region>XXX</region>
                                             <code>XXX</code>
                                             <country>XXX</country>
                                     </postal>
                                     <phone>XXX</phone>
                                     <facsimile>XXX</facsimile>
                                     <email>XXX</email>
                                     <uri>XXX</uri>
                             </address>

                     </author>
                     <date month="XXX" year="XXX"/>
             </front>
             <seriesInfo name="XXX" value="XXX"/>
             <format type="XXX" target="XXX"/>                       
     </reference>
     -->

 <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0768" ?>

     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0793" ?>

     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>

     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2780" ?>

     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4020" ?>

     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4340" ?>

     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4727" ?>

     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226" ?>
   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0959" ?>

     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1078" ?>

     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2782" ?>

     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4342" ?>

     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4960" ?>

     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5237" ?>

     <reference anchor="I-D.touch-tsvwg-port-guidelines">
       <front>
         <title>Guidelines for Transport Port Use</title>

         <author fullname="Joe Touch" initials="J" surname="Touch">
           <organization></organization>
         </author>

         <date month="July" year="2008" />
       </front>

       <seriesInfo name="" value="Work in Progress" />
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="SYSFORM">
       <front>
         <title>Application for System (Well Known) Port Number</title>

         <author surname="Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA)">
           <organization />
         </author>
       </front>

       <seriesInfo name=""
                   value="http://www.iana.org/cgi-bin/sys-port-number.pl" />
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="USRFORM">
       <front>
         <title>Application for User (Registered) Port Number</title>

         <author surname="Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA)">
           <organization />
         </author>
       </front>

       <seriesInfo name=""
                   value="http://www.iana.org/cgi-bin/usr-port-number.pl" />
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="REGISTRY">
       <front>
         <title>Port Numbers</title>

         <author surname="Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA)">
           <organization />
         </author>
       </front>

       <seriesInfo name=""
                   value="http://www.iana.org/assignments/port-numbers" />
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="TRILOGY">
       <front>
         <title>Trilogy Project</title>

         <author>
           <organization />
         </author>
       </front>

       <seriesInfo name="" value="http://www.trilogy-project.org/" />
     </reference>
   </references>

   <section anchor="dccp" title="Updates to DCCP Registries">
     <t>This document updates the IANA allocation procedures for the DCCP
     Port Number and DCCP Service Codes Registries as defined in <xref
     target="RFC4340"></xref>.</t>

     <section title="DCCP Service Code Registry">
       <t>Service Codes are allocated first-come-first-served according to
       Section 19.8 of <xref target="RFC4340"></xref>. This document updates
       Section 19.8 of <xref target="RFC4340"></xref> by extending the
       guidelines given there in the following ways:</t>

       <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>IANA MAY assign new Service Codes without seeking Expert Review
           using their discretion, but SHOULD seek expert review when a
           request seeks an appreciable number of Service Codes (e.g., more
           than five).</t>

           <t>IANA should feel free to contact the DCCP Expert Reviewer with
           questions on any registry, regardless of the registry policy, for
           clarification or if there is a problem with a request <xref
           target="RFC4340"></xref>.</t>
         </list></t>
     </section>

     <section title="DCCP Port Numbers Registry">
       <t>The DCCP ports registry is defined by <xref
       target="RFC4340"></xref> in Section 19.9. Allocations in this registry
       require prior allocation of a Service Code. Not all Service Codes
       require IANA-registered ports. This document updates Section 19.9 of
       <xref target="RFC4340"></xref> by extending the guidelines given there
       in the following way:</t>

       <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>IANA should normally assign a value in the range 1024-49151 to
           a DCCP server port. IANA allocation requests to allocate port
           numbers in the Well Known Ports range (0 through 1023), require
           IETF Action prior to allocation by IANA <xref
           target="RFC4340"></xref>.</t>
         </list></t>

       <t>Section 19.9 of <xref target="RFC4340"></xref> requires each DCCP
       server port assignment to be associated with at least one Service Code
       value. This document updates <xref target="RFC4340"></xref> in the
       following way:</t>

       <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>IANA MUST NOT allocate a single Service Code value to more than
           one DCCP server port.</t>

           <t>The set of Service Code values associated with a DCCP server
           port should be recorded in the ports registry.</t>

           <t>A request for additional Service Codes to be associated with an
           already allocated Port Number requires Expert Review. These
           requests will normally be accepted when they originate from the
           contact associated with the port registration. In other cases,
           these applications will be expected to use an unallocated port,
           when this is available.</t>
         </list></t>

       <t><xref target="RFC4340"></xref> notes that a short port name MUST be
       associated with each DCCP server port that has been registered. This
       document requires that this name MUST be unique.</t>
     </section>
   </section>
 </back>
</rfc>