<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc3550 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4585 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4585.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3095 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3095.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4588 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4588.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5104 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5104.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-avt-rtcp-non-compound-04"
     ipr="full3978">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Non-compound RTCP in RTP profile">Support for non-compound
    RTCP, opportunities and consequences</title>

    <author fullname="Ingemar Johansson" initials="I." surname="Johansson">
      <organization>Ericsson AB</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Laboratoriegrand 11</street>

          <city>SE-971 28 Lulea</city>

          <country>SWEDEN</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+46 73 0783289</phone>

        <email>ingemar.s.johansson@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Magnus Westerlund" initials="M." surname="Westerlund">
      <organization>Ericsson AB</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Torshamnsgatan 21-23</street>

          <city>SE-164 83 Stockholm</city>

          <country>SWEDEN</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+46 8 7190000</phone>

        <email>magnus.westerlund (AT) ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="24" month="Apr" year="2008" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo discusses benefits and issues that arise when allowing RTCP
      packets to be transmitted as non-compound packets, i.e not follow the
      rules of RFC 3550. Based on that analysis this memo proposes changes to
      the rules to allow feedback messages to be sent as non-compound RTCP
      packets when using the RTP AVPF profile (RFC 4585) under certain
      conditions.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In <xref target="RFC3550">RTP</xref> it is currently mandatory to
      always use RTCP compound packets containing at least Sender Reports or
      Receiver reports, and a SDES packet containing at least the CNAME item.
      There are good reasons for this as discussed below (see <xref
      target="sec-compound-packets"></xref>). However this do result in that
      the minimal RTCP packets are quite large. The <xref target="RFC4585">RTP
      profile AVPF</xref> specifies new RTCP packet types for feedback
      messages. Some of these feedback messages would benefit from being
      transmitted with minimal delay and AVPF do provide some mechanism to
      enable this. However for environments with low-bitrate links this still
      consumes quite large amount of resources and introduce extra delay in
      the time it takes to completely send the compound packet in the network.
      There are also other benefits as discussed in <xref
      target="sec-benefitts"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The use of non-compound packets is not without issues. This is
      discussed in <xref target="sec-issues"></xref>. These issues needs to be
      considered and are part of the motivation for this document.</t>

      <t>In addition this document proposes how AVPF could be updated to allow
      the transmission of non-compound packets in a way that would not
      substantially affect the mechanisms that compound packets provide. The
      connection to AVPF is motivated by the fact that non-compound RTCP is
      mainly intended for event driven feedback purposes and that the AVPF
      early and immediate modes make this possible.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-compound-packets" title="RTCP Compound Packets">
      <t>Section 6.1 in <xref target="RFC3550"></xref> specifies that an RTCP
      packet must be sent in a compound packet consisting of at least two
      individual packets, first an Sender Report (SR) or Receiver Report (RR),
      followed by additional packets including a mandatory SDES packet
      containing a CNAME Item for the transmitting source identifier (SSRC).
      Lets examine what these RTCP packet types are used for.</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>The sender and receiver reports (see Section 6.4 of <xref
          target="RFC3550"></xref>) provides the RTP session participant with
          the Sender Source Identifier (SSRC) of all RTCP senders. Having all
          participants send these packets periodically allows everyone to
          determine the current number of participants. This information is
          used in the transmission scheduling algorithm. Thus this is
          particularly important for new participants so that they quickly can
          establish a good estimate of the group size. Failure to do this
          would result in RTCP senders consuming to much bandwidth.</t>

          <t>The sender and receiver reports contain some basic statistics
          usable for monitoring of the transport and thus enable adaptation.
          These reports become more useful if sent regularly as the receiver
          of a report can perform analysis to find trends between the
          individual reports. When used for media transmission adaptation the
          information become more useful the more frequently it is received,
          at least until one report per round-trip time (RTT) is achieved.
          Therefore there are most cases no reason to not include the sender
          or receiver report in all RTCP packets.</t>

          <t>The CNAME SDES item (See Section 6.5.1 of <xref
          target="RFC3550"></xref>) exists to allow receivers to determine
          which media flows that should be synchronized with each other
          between different RTP sessions carrying different media types. Thus
          it is important to quickly receive this for each media sender in the
          session when joining an RTP session.</t>

          <t>Sender Reports (SR) is used in combination with the above SDES
          CNAME mechanism to synchronize multiple RTP streams, such as audio
          and video. After having determined which media streams should be
          synchronized using the CNAME field, the receiver uses the Sender
          Report's NTP and RTP timestamp fields to establish
          synchronization.</t>
        </list>Reviewing the above it is obvious that both SR/RR and the CNAME
      are very important for new session participants to be able to utilize
      any received media and to avoid flooding the network with RTCP reports.
      In addition, if not sent regularly the dynamic nature of the information
      provided would make it less and less useful.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-benefitts" title="Benefits with non-compound packets">
      <t>As mentioned in the introduction, most advantages of using
      non-compound packets exists in cases when the available RTCP bitrate is
      limited. This because non-compound packets will be substantially smaller
      than compound packets. A compound packet is forced to contain both an RR
      or an SR and the CNAME SDES item. The RR containing a report block for a
      single source is 32 bytes, an SR is 52 bytes. Both may be larger if they
      contain report blocks for multiple sources. The SDES packet containing a
      CNAME item will be 10 bytes plus the CNAME string length. Here it is
      reasonable that the CNAME string is at least 10 bytes to get a decent
      collision resistance. And if the recommended form of user@host is used,
      then most strings will be longer than 20 characters. Thus a non-compound
      packet can become at least 70-80 bytes smaller than the compound
      packet.</t>

      <t>The following benefits exist for the non-compound packets,</t>

      <section anchor="sec-low-bitrate-links" title="Low birate links">
        <t>For low birate links the benefits are as follows.<list
            style="symbols">
            <t>For links where the packet loss rate grows with the packet
            size, smaller packets are be less likely to be dropped. An example
            of such links are radio links. In the cellular world there exist
            links that are optimized to handle RTP packets sized for carrying
            compressed speec. This increases the capacity and coverage for
            voice services in a given wireless network. Minimum sized compound
            RTCP packets are commonly 2-3 times the size of a RTP packet
            carrying compressed speech. If the speech packet over such a
            bearer has a packet loss probability of p, then the RTCP packet
            will experience a loss probability of 1-(1-p)^x where x is the
            number of fragments the compound packet will be split on the link
            layer, i.e. commonly into 2 or 3 fragments.</t>

            <t>Shorter serialization time, i.e the time it takes the link to
            transmit the packet. For slower links this time can be
            substantial. For example transmitting 120 bytes over an link
            interface capable of 30 kbps takes 32 milliseconds (ms) assuming
            uniform transmission rate.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In cases when non-compound packets carry important and time
        sensitive feedback, both shorter serialization time and the lower loss
        probability are important to enable the best possible functionality.
        Having a packet loss rate that is much higher for the feedback packets
        compared to media packets hurts when trying to perform media
        adaptation, to for example handle the changed performance present at
        the cell border in cellular system.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Higher bitrates">
        <t>For high bitrate applications there is usually no problem of
        supplying RTCP with sufficient bitrates. When using AVPF one can use
        the "trr-int" parameter to restrict the regular reporting interval to
        approximately once per RTT or less often. As in most cases there is
        little reason to provide with regular reports of higher density than
        this. Any additional bandwidth can then be used for feedback messages.
        The benefit of non-compound packets in this case is limited, but
        exists. One typical example is video using generic NACK in cases where
        the RTT is low. Using non-compound packets would reduce the total
        amount of bits used for RTCP. This is primarily applicable if the
        number of non-compound packets is large. This would also result in
        lower processing delay and less complexity for the feedback packets as
        they do not need to query the RTCP database to construct the right
        messages.</t>

        <t>As message size generally is a smaller issue for higher birates, it
        is also possible to transmit multiple RTCP in each lower layer
        datagram in these cases. The motivation behind non-compound RTCP is in
        this case is not size, rather it is to avoid the extra overhead caused
        by inclusion of the SR/RR and SDES CNAME items in each transmitted
        RTCP.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Both high and low bitrate links">
        <t>Independently of the link type there are additional benefits with
        sending feedback in small non-compound RTCP. <list style="symbols">
            <t>Applications that use RTCP AVPF in early or immediate mode to
            send frequent event driven feedback. Under these circumstances
            non-compound RTCP reduces the risk that the RTCP bandwidth becomes
            too high during periods of heavy adaptation feedback
            signaling.</t>

            <t>In cases when regular feedback is needed, such as the profile
            under development for TCP friendly rate control (TFRC) for RTP
            <xref target="I-D.ietf-avt-tfrc-profile"></xref>, the size of
            compound RTCP can result in very high bandwidth requirements if
            the round trip time is short. For this particular application
            non-compound RTCP gives a very substantial improvement.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-use-cases" title="Use cases for non-compound RTCP">
      <t>Below are listed a few use cases for non-compound RTCP. The current
      use of non-compound RTCP is very application specific. A general
      definition of the use of non-compound RTCP for e.g control plane or
      codec control signaling would probably need to be specified within the
      IETF.</t>

      <section title="Control plane signaling">
        <t>Open Mobile Alliance (OMA) Push-to-talk over Cellular (PoC) <xref
        target="OMA-PoC"> </xref> makes use of non-compound packets when
        transmitting certain events. The OMA POC service is primarily used
        over cellular links capable of IP transport, such as the GSM GPRS.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Codec control signaling">
        <t>Examples of codec control usage for non-compound RTCP are found in
        <xref target="3GPP-MTSI"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Another example that can be used with non-compound RTCP is e.g
        TMMBR messages as specified in <xref target="RFC5104"></xref> which
        signal a request for a change in codec bitrate. The benefit of
        non-compound RTCP for these messages is that in bad channel
        conditions, a non-compound RTCP can be considerably more likely to be
        received than larger compound RTCP messages. This is critical as these
        messages are likely to occur when channel conditions are poor.</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Feedback">
        <t>An example of a feedback scenario that would benefit from
        non-compound RTCP is Video streams with generic NACK. In cases where
        the RTT is shorter than the receiver buffer depth, generic NACK can be
        used to request retransmission of missing packets, thus improving
        playout quality considerably. If the generic NACK packets are
        transmitted as non-compound packets, the bandwidth requirement for
        RTCP will be minimal, enabling more frequent feedback. Like in the
        Codec control case it is important that these packets can be
        transmitted with as little delay as possible.</t>

        <t>Another interesting use for non-compound RTCP is in cases when
        regular feedback is needed, such as the profile under development for
        TCP friendly rate control (TFRC) for RTP <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-avt-tfrc-profile"></xref>. The size of compound RTCP
        can result in very high bandwidth requirements for the feedback when
        the round trip time is short. For this particular application
        non-compound RTCP may give a very substantial improvement.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-status-reports" title="Status reports">
        <t>One proposed idea is to transmit small measurement or status
        reports in non-compound RTCP, and to be able to split the sub-packets
        of a minimum compound RTCP and transmit them separately. The status
        reports can be used either by the endpoints or by other network
        monitoring boxes in the network.</t>

        <t>The benefit is that with some radio access technologies small
        packets are more robust to poor radio conditions than large packets.
        Additionally, with small (report) packets there is a smaller risk that
        the report packets will affect the channel that they report upon.</t>

        <t>Another benefit is that it is, with non-compound RTCP, possible to
        allow e.g anonymous status reportorting to be transmitted unencrypted.
        Something that may be beneficial for e.g network monitoring
        purposes.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-issues" title="Issues with non-compound RTCP packets">
      <t>This section describes the known issues with non-compound RTCP
      packets and also a brief analysis.</t>

      <section anchor="sec-middleboxes" title="Middle boxes">
        <t>Middle boxes in the network may discard RTCP packets that do not
        follow the rules outlined in section 6.1 of RFC3550. Newer report
        types may be interptered as unknown by the middle box. For instance if
        the payload type number is 207 instead of 200 or 201 it may be treated
        as unknown. The effect of this might for instance be that compound
        RTCP packets would get through while the non-compound feedback packets
        would be lost.</t>

        <t>Verification of the delivery of non-compound RTCP is discussed in
        <xref target="sec-verification"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-packet-validation" title="Packet Validation">
        <t>A non-compound packet will be discarded by the packet validation
        code in Appendix A of <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>. This has several
        impacts as described in the following sub sections.</t>

        <section title="Old RTCP Receivers">
          <t>Any RTCP receiver without updated packet validation code will
          discard the non-compound packets. Thus these receivers will not see
          the feedback contained in the these non-compound packets. The effect
          of this depends on the type of feedback message and the role of the
          receiver. For example this may cause complete function loss in the
          case of attempting to use a non-compound NACK message (see Section
          6.2.1 of <xref target="RFC4585"></xref>) to non updated media sender
          in a session using the retransmission scheme defined by <xref
          target="RFC4588"></xref>.</t>

          <t>This type of discarding would also effect the feedback
          suppression defined in AVPF. The result would be a partitioning of
          the receivers within the session between old ones only seeing the
          compound RTCP feedback messages and the newer ones seeing both.
          Where the old ones may send feedback messages for events already
          reported on in non-compound packets.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Weakened Packet Validation">
          <t>The packet validation code needs to be rewritten to accept
          non-compound packets. This in particular affects section 9.1 in
          <xref target="RFC3550"></xref> in the sense that the header
          verification must take into account that the payload type numbers
          for the (first) RTCP packet may differ from 200 or 201 (SR or
          RR).</t>

          <t>One potential effect of this change is much weaker validation
          that received packets actually are RTCP packets, and not packets of
          some other type being wrongly delivered. Thus some consideration
          should be done to ensure the best possible validation is available.
          For example restricting non-compound packets to contain only some
          specific RTCP packet types, that is preferably signalled on a
          session basis.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Bandwidth considerations">
          <t>The discarding of non-compound RTCP packets would effect the RTCP
          transmission calculation in the following way: the avg_rtcp_size
          value would become larger than for RTP receivers that exclude the
          non-compound in this calculation (assuming that non-compound packets
          are smaller than compound ones). Therefore these senders would
          under-utilize the available bitrate and send with a longer interval
          than updated receivers. For most sessions this should not be an
          issue. However for sessions with a large portion of non-compound
          packets may result in that the updated receivers time out
          non-updated senders prematurely. A solution to this is presented in
          <xref target="sec-algorithm"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Computation of avg_rtcp_size">
          <t>Long intervals between compound RTCP packets and many
          non-compound RTCP packets in between may lead to a computation of a
          value for avg_rtcp_size that varies greatly over time. This is
          discussed more in <xref target="sec-algorithm"></xref>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Encryption/authentication">
        <t>SRTP presents a problem for non-compound RTCP. Section 3.4 in <xref
        target="RFC3711"></xref> states "SRTCP MUST be given packets according
        to that requirement in the sense that the first part MUST be a sender
        report or a receiver report".</t>

        <t>However the same text also states that the encryption prefix that
        is present in the receiver and sender reports should not be used by
        SRTP. The conclusion is therefore that it is possible to use
        non-compound RTCP with SRTP.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-issue-mux"
               title="RTP and RTCP multiplex on the same port">
        <t>In applications which multiplex RTP and RTCP on the same port, as
        defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-avt-rtp-and-rtcp-mux"></xref>, care
        must be taken to ensure that the de-multiplexing is done properly even
        though RTCP packets are non-compound.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Header compression">
        <t>Two issues are related to header compression:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Payload type number identification: The RoHC header compression
            algorithm algorithm <xref target="RFC3095"></xref> needs to create
            different compression contexts for RTP and RTCP for optimum
            performance. If RTP and RTCP are multiplexed on the same port the
            classification is based on payload type numbers. The
            classification algorithm must here acklowledge the fact that the
            payload type number for (the first) RTCP may differ from 200 or
            201.</t>

            <t>Compression of RTCP packets: No IETF defined header compression
            method compress RTCP packets, however if such methods are
            developed in the future, these methods must take non-compound RTCP
            in account.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-rules"
             title="Rules and guidelines for non-compound packets in AVPF">
      <t>Based on the above analysis it seems feasible to allow transmission
      of non-compound RTCP under some restrictions.</t>

      <t>First of all it is important that compound packets are transmitted at
      regular intervals to ensure that the feedback reporting works. The
      tracking of session size and number of participants is also important as
      this ensures that the RTCP bandwidth remain bounded independent of the
      number of session participants.</t>

      <t>As the compound packets are also used to establish the
      synchronization, any newly joining participant in a session would need
      to receive a compound packet from the media sender.</t>

      <t>In summary the regular usage of compound packets must be maintained
      throughout the complete session. Thus non-compound packets should be
      restricted to be used as extra RTCP (e.g feedback) sent in cases when a
      regular compound packet would not have been sent.</t>

      <t>The usage of non-compound RTCP packet SHALL only be done in RTP
      sessions operating in <xref target="RFC4585">AVPF</xref> Early RTCP or
      Immediate feedback mode. Non-compound packets SHALL NOT be sent until at
      least one compound packet has been sent. In Immediate feedback mode all
      feedback messages MAY be sent as non-compound packets. In early RTCP
      mode a feedback message scheduled for transmission as an Early RTCP
      packet, i.e not a Regular RTCP packet, MAY be sent as a non-compound
      packet. All packets that are scheduled for transmission as Regular RTCP
      packets SHALL be sent as (full) compound RTCP packets as indicated by
      <xref target="RFC4585">AVPF</xref>.</t>

      <section anchor="sec-definition" title="Definition of non-compound RTCP">
        <t>A non-compound RTCP is a packet that deviates from the rules
        regarding (minimal) compound RTCP given in RFC3550/4585 in the aspect
        that they don't contain both the mandatory elements SR/RR and
        SDES-CNAME. The definition does not make any distinction based on
        size. This means that it is possible to transmit multiple RTCP in one
        lower layer datagram.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-algorithm" title="Algorithm considerations">
        <section anchor="sec-verification" title="Verification of delivery">
          <t>If an application is to use non-compound packets it is important
          to verify that they actually reach the session participants. As
          outlined above in <xref target="sec-middleboxes"></xref> and <xref
          target="sec-packet-validation"></xref> packets may be discarded
          along the path or in the end-point.</t>

          <t>The end-points can be resolved by introducing signaling that
          informs if all session participants are capable of non-compound
          packets or not.</t>

          <t>The middle box issue is more difficult and here one will be
          required to use heuristics to determine if the non-compound packets
          are delivered or not. However in many cases the feedback messages
          sent using non-compound packets will result in either explicit or
          implicit indications that they have been received. Example of such
          are the <xref target="RFC4588">RTP retransmission</xref> that result
          from a <xref target="RFC4585">NACK message</xref>, the <xref
          target="RFC5104">Temporary Maximum Media Bitrate Notification
          message resulting from a Temporary Maximum Media Bitrate
          Request</xref>, or the presence of a <xref target="RFC5104">Decoder
          Refresh Point</xref> in the video media stream resulting from the
          Full Intra Request sent.</t>

          <t>An algorithm to detect consistent failure of delivery of
          non-compound packets must be used by any application using
          non-compound. The details of this algorithm is application dependent
          and therefore outside the scope of this document.</t>

          <t>A method to detect if non-compound RTCP are discarded is to send
          a non-compound SR packet, then check that the timestamp is echoed
          back in the corresponding RR packet. This verification method is not
          compelety safe however as it SR is still one of the expected packet
          types.</t>

          <t>If the verification fails it is strongly RECOMMENDED that only
          compound RTCP according to the rules outlined in RFC3550 is
          transmitted.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Single vs multiple RTCP in a non-compound RTCP">
          <t>The result of the definition in <xref
          target="sec-definition"></xref> may be that the resulting size of
          non-compound RTCP can become larger than a normal compound RTCP. For
          applications that use access types that are sensitive to packet size
          (see <xref target="sec-low-bitrate-links"></xref>) it is strongly
          RECOMMENDED that the use of non-compound RTCP is limited to the
          transmission of single RTCP packets in each lower layer
          datagram.</t>

          <t>The methods to detemine the need for this is outside the scope of
          this draft.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Enforcing compound RTCP">
          <t>As discussed earlier it is important that the transmission of
          compound RTCP packets occurs at regular intervals. However, this
          will occur as long as the RTCP senders follow the AVPF scheduling
          algorithm defined in Section 3.5 in <xref target="RFC4585"></xref>.
          This as all regular RTCP packets must be full compound RTCP packets.
          Note that also in immediate mode is there a requirement on sending
          regular RTCP packets.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Immediate mode">
          <t>Section 3.3 in RFC4585 gives the option to use AVPF Immediate
          mode as long as the groupsize is below a certain limit. As feedback
          using non-compound RTCP may become smaller it opens up for a more
          liberal use of immediate mode.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-sdp-attribute" title="SDP Signalling Attribute">
        <t>We request to define the a "a=rtcp-nc" <xref
        target="RFC4566"></xref> attribute to indicate if the session
        participant is capable of supporting non-compound packets. It is a
        required that a participant that proposes the use of non-compound RTCP
        itself supports the reception of non-compound RTCP.</t>

        <t>An offering client that wish to use non-compound RTCP MUST include
        the attribute "a=rtcp-nc" in the SDP offer. If "a=rtcp-nc" is present
        in the offer SDP, the answerer that supports non-compound RTCP and
        wishes to use it SHALL include the "a=rtcp-nc" attribute in the
        answer.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>Following the guidelines in <xref target="RFC4566"></xref>, the IANA
      is requested to register one new SDP attribute:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Contact name, email address and telephone number: Authors of
          RFCXXXX</t>

          <t>Attribute-name: rtcp-nc</t>

          <t>Long-form attribute name: Non-compound RTCP</t>

          <t>Type of attribute: media-level</t>

          <t>Subject to charset: no</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This attribute defines the support for non-compound RTCP, i.e the
      possibility to transmit RTCP that does not comform to the rules for
      compund RTCP defined in RFC3550. It is a property attribute, which does
      not take a value.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: please replace "RFC XXXX" above with the RFC
      number of this memo, and remove this note.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations of <xref target="RFC3550">RTP</xref> and
      <xref target="RFC4585">AVPF</xref> will apply also to non-compound
      packets. The reduction in validation strength for received packets on
      the RTCP port may result in a higher degree of acceptance of spurious
      data as real RTCP packets. This vulnerability can mostly be addressed by
      usage of any security mechanism that provide authentication, one example
      such mechanism is SRTP <xref target="RFC3711"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank all the people who gave feedback on
      this document.</t>

      <t>This document also contain some text copied from <xref
      target="RFC3550"></xref><xref target="RFC4585">,</xref><xref
      target="RFC3711"> and</xref>. We take the opportunity to thank the
      authors of said documents.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc3550;

      &rfc4585;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc3095;

      &rfc4588;

      &rfc5104;

      <reference anchor="OMA-PoC">
        <front>
          <title>Specification : Push to talk Over Cellular User Plane,
          http://www.openmobilealliance.org/release_program/docs/PoC/V1_0_1-20061128-A/OMA-TS-PoC-UserPlane-V1_0_1-20061128-A.pdf</title>

          <author fullname="">
            <organization>Open Mobile Alliance</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="28" month="November" year="2006" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="3GPP-MTSI">
        <front>
          <title>Specification : 3GPP TS 26.114 (v7.4.0),
          http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/archive/26_series/26.114/26114-740.zip</title>

          <author fullname="3gpp.org">
            <organization>3GPP</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="29" month="March" year="2007" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-avt-tfrc-profile'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4566'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3711'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-avt-rtp-and-rtcp-mux'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>