<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-p2psip-concepts-01" ipr="full3978">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="P2PSIP Concepts and Terminology">Concepts and Terminology
    for Peer to Peer SIP</title>

    <author fullname="David A. Bryan" initials="D.A." surname="Bryan">
      <organization>College of William and Mary and SIPeerior
      Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3000 Easter Circle</street>

          <city>Williamsburg</city>

          <code>23188</code>

          <region>Virginia</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 757 565 0101</phone>

        <email>bryan@sipeerior.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Philip Matthews" initials="P." surname="Matthews">
      <organization>Avaya</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1135 Innovation Drive</street>

          <city>Ottawa</city>

          <code>K2K 3G7</code>

          <region>Ontario</region>

          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 613 592 4343 x224</phone>

        <email>philip_matthews@magma.ca</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Eunsoo Shim" initials="E." surname="Shim">
      <organization>Locus Telecommunications</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>111 Sylvan Avenue</street>

          <city>Englewood Cliffs</city>

          <code>07632</code>

          <region>New Jersey</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>unlisted</phone>

        <email>eunsooshim@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dean Willis" initials="D." surname="Willis">
      <organization>Unaffiliated</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3100 Independence Pkwy #311-164</street>

          <city>Plano</city>

          <code>75075</code>

          <region>Texas</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>unlisted</phone>

        <email>dean.willis@softarmor.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="November" year="2007" />

    <area>Real-Time Applications Infrastructure Area</area>

    <workgroup>P2PSIP Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines concepts and terminology for use of the Session
      Initiation Protocol in a peer-to-peer environment where the traditional
      proxy-registrar and message routing functions are replaced by a
      distributed mechanism that might be implemented using a distributed hash
      table or other distributed data mechanism with similar external
      properties. This document includes a high-level view of the functional
      relationships between the network elements defined herein, a conceptual
      model of operations, and an outline of the related open problems being
      addressed by the P2PSIP working group. As this document matures, it is
      expected to define the general framework for P2PSIP.</t>
    </abstract>

    <!-- I (Philip)  don't think we need this, because this is just going to be an Informational RFC. 
    
    <note title="Requirements Language">
    <t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
    &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;,
    &quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;,
    &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and
    &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be interpreted as described in
    <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </note>
    
    -->
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Background">
      <t>One of the fundamental problems in multimedia communication between
      Internet nodes is that of discovering the host at which a given user can
      be reached. In the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref
      target="RFC3261"></xref> this problem is expressed as the problem of
      mapping an Address of Record (AoR) for a user into one or more Contact
      URIs <xref target="RFC3986"></xref>. The AoR is a name for the user that
      is independent of the host or hosts where the user can be contacted,
      while a Contact URI indicates the host where the user can be
      contacted.</t>

      <t>In the common SIP-using architectures that we refer to as
      "Conventional SIP" or "Client/Server SIP", there is a relatively fixed
      hierarchy of SIP routing proxies and SIP user agents. To deliver a SIP
      INVITE to the host or hosts at which the user can be contacted, a SIP UA
      follows the procedures specified in <xref target="RFC3263"></xref> to
      determine the IP address of a SIP proxy, and then sends the INVITE to
      that proxy. The proxy will then, in turn, deliver the SIP INVITE to the
      hosts where the user can be contacted.</t>

      <t>This document gives a high-level description of an alternative
      solution to this problem. In this alternative solution, the relatively
      fixed hierarchy of Client/Server SIP is replaced by a peer-to-peer
      overlay network. In this peer-to-peer overlay network, the various AoR
      to Contact URI mappings are not centralized at proxy/registrar nodes but
      are instead distributed amongst the peers in the overlay.</t>

      <t>The details of this alternative solution are currently being worked
      out in the P2PSIP working group. This document describes the basic
      concepts of such a peer-to-peer overlay, and lists the open questions
      that still need to be resolved. As the work proceeds, it is expected
      that this document will develop into a high-level architecture document
      for the solution.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="High Level Description">
      <t>A P2PSIP Overlay is a collection of nodes organized in a peer-to-peer
      fashion for the purpose of enabling real-time communication using the
      Session Initiation Protocol (SIP). Collectively, the nodes in the
      overlay provide a distributed mechanism for mapping names to overlay
      locations. This provides for the mapping of Addresses of Record (AoRs)
      to Contact URIs, thereby providing the "location server" function of
      <xref target="RFC3261"></xref>. A P2PSIP Overlay also provides a
      transport function by which SIP messages can be transported between any
      two nodes in the overlay.</t>

      <t>A P2PSIP Overlay consists of one or more nodes called P2PSIP Peers.
      The peers in the overlay collectively run a distributed database
      algorithm. This distributed database algorithm allows data to be stored
      on peers and retrieved in an efficient manner. It may also ensure that a
      copy of a data item is stored on more than one peer, so that the loss of
      a peer does not result in the loss of the data item to the overlay.</t>

      <t>One use of this distributed database is to store the information
      required to provide the mapping between AoRs and Contact URIs for the
      distributed location function. This provides a location function within
      each overlay that is an alternative to the location functions described
      in <xref target="RFC3263"></xref>. However, the model of <xref
      target="RFC3263"></xref> is used between overlays.</t>

      <section title="Services">
        <t>The nature of peer-to-peer computing is that each peer offers
        services to other peers to allow the overlay to collectively provide
        larger functions. In P2PSIP, peers offer storage and transport
        services to allow the distributed database function and distributed
        transport function to be implemented. It is expected that individual
        peers may also offer other services. Some of these additional services
        (for example, a STUN server service <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-behave-rfc3489bis"></xref>) may be required to allow
        the overlay to form and operate, while others (for example, a
        voicemail service) may be enhancements to the basic P2PSIP
        functionality.</t>

        <t>To allow peers to offer these additional services, the distributed
        database may need to store information about services. For example, it
        may need to store information about which peers offer which services,
        and perhaps what sort of capacity each peer has for delivering each
        listed service.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Clients">
        <t>An overlay may or may not also include one or more nodes called
        P2PSIP Clients. The role of a client in the P2PSIP model is still
        under discussion, with a number of suggestions for roles being put
        forth, and some arguing that clients are not needed at all. However,
        if they exist, then people agree that they will also be able to store
        and retrieve information from the overlay. <xref
        target="Clients"></xref> discusses the possible roles of a client in
        more detail.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Protocol">
        <t>Peers in an overlay need to speak some protocol between themselves
        to maintain the overlay and to store and retrieve data. Until a better
        name is found, this protocol has been dubbed the P2PSIP Peer Protocol.
        The details of this protocol are still very much under debate: some
        have suggested that the protocol should be SIP with some extensions,
        while others have suggested that it should be an entirely new
        protocol.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Relationship of Peer and Client Protocols">
        <t>If the P2PSIP model also contains clients, then a protocol is
        needed for client - peer communication. Until a better name is found,
        this protocol has been dubbed the P2PSIP Client Protocol. The details
        of this protocol are also very much under debate. However, if the
        client protocol exists, then it is agreed that it should be a logical
        subset of the peer protocol. In other words, the syntax of the peer
        and client protocols may be completely different, but any operation
        supported by client protocol is also supported by the peer protocol.
        This implies that clients cannot do anything that peers cannot also
        do.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Relationship Between P2PSIP and SIP">
        <t>Since P2PSIP is about peer-to-peer networks for real-time
        communication, it is expected that most (if not all) peers and clients
        will be coupled with SIP entities. For example, one peer might be
        coupled with a SIP UA, another might be coupled with a SIP proxy,
        while a third might be coupled with a SIP-to-PSTN gateway. For such
        nodes, we think of the peer or client portion of the node as being
        distinct from the SIP entity portion. However, there is no hard
        requirement that every P2PSIP node (peer or client) be coupled to a
        SIP entity, and some proposed architectures include peer nodes that
        have no SIP function whatsoever.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Relationship Between P2PSIP and Other AoR Dereferencing Approaches">
        <t>As noted above, the fundamental task of P2PSIP is turning an AoR
        into a Contact. This task might be approached using zeroconf
        techniques such as multicast DNS and DNS Service Discovery (as in
        Apple's Bonjour protocol), link-local multicast name resolution <xref
        target="RFC4795"></xref>, and dynamic DNS <xref
        target="RFC2136"></xref>.</t>

        <t>These alternatives were discussed in the P2PSIP Working Group, and
        not pursued as a general solution for a number of reasons related to
        scalability, the ability to work in a disconnected state, partition
        recovery, and so on. However, there does seem to be some continuing
        interest in the possibility of using DNS-SD and mDNS for bootstrapping
        of P2PSIP overlays.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="NAT Issues">
        <t>Network Address Translators (NATs) are impediments to establishing
        and maintaining peer-to-peer networks, since NATs hinder direct
        communication between peers. Some peer-to-peer network architectures
        avoid this problem by insisting that all peers exist in the same
        address space. However, in the P2PSIP model, it has been agreed that
        peers can live in multiple address spaces interconnected by NATs. This
        implies that Peer Protocol connections must be able to traverse NATs.
        It also means that the peers must collectively provide a distributed
        transport function that allows a peer to send a SIP message to any
        other peer in the overlay - without this function two peers in
        different IP address spaces might not be able to exchange SIP
        messages.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Reference Model">
      <t>The following diagram shows a P2PSIP Overlay consisting of a number
      of P2PSIP Peers, one P2PSIP Client, and an ordinary SIP UA. It
      illustrates a typical P2PSIP overlay but does not limit other
      compositions or variations; for example, Proxy Peer P might also talk to
      a ordinary SIP proxy as well. The figure is not intended to cover all
      possible architecture variations in this document.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
          

                                               --->PSTN
  +------+    N     +------+     +---------+  /
  |      |    A     |      |     | Gateway |-/
  |  UA  |####T#####|  UA  |#####|   Peer  |########
  | Peer |    N     | Peer |     |    G    |       #   P2PSIP
  |  E   |    A     |  F   |     +---------+       #   Client
  |      |    T     |      |                       #   Protocol
  +------+    N     +------+                       #    |
     #        A                                    #    |
   NATNATNATNAT                                    #    |
     #                                             #    |   \__/
   NATNATNATNAT                              +-------+  v   /  \
     #        N                              |       |=====/ UA \
  +------+    A       P2PSIP Overlay         | Peer  |    /Client\
  |      |    T                              |   Q   |    |___C__|
  |  UA  |    N                              |       |
  | Peer |    A                              +-------+
  |  D   |    T                                    #
  |      |    N                                    #
  +------+    A                                    # P2PSIP
     #        T                                    # Peer
     #        N    +-------+        +-------+      # Protocol
     #        A    |       |        |       |      #
     #########T####| Proxy |########| Redir |#######
              N    | Peer  |        | Peer  |
              A    |   P   |        |   R   |
              T    +-------+        +-------+
                     |                 /
                     | SIP            /
               \__/  /               /
                /\  / ______________/ SIP
               /  \/ /
              / UA \/
             /______\
             SIP UA A
	       
        ]]></artwork>

        <postamble>Figure: P2PSIP Overlay Reference Model</postamble>
      </figure>

      <t>Here, the large perimeter depicted by "#" represents a stylized view
      of the P2PSIP Overlay (the actual connections could be a mesh, a ring,
      or some other structure). Around the periphery of the P2PSIP Overlay
      rectangle, we have a number of P2PSIP Peers. Each peer is labeled with
      its coupled SIP entity -- for example, "Proxy Peer P" means that peer P
      which is coupled with a SIP proxy. In some cases, a peer or client might
      be coupled with two or more SIP entities. In this diagram we have a PSTN
      gateway coupled with peer "G", three peers ("D", "E" and "F") which are
      each coupled with a UA, a peer "P" which is coupled with a SIP proxy, an
      ordinary peer "Q", and one peer "R" which is coupled with a SIP
      Redirector. Note that because these are all P2PSIP Peers, each is
      responsible for storing P2PSIP Resource Records and transporting
      messages around the P2PSIP Overlay.</t>

      <t>To the left, two of the peers ("D" and "E") are behind network
      address translators (NATs). These peers are included in the P2PSIP
      overlay and thus participate in storing resource records and routing
      messages, despite being behind the NATs.</t>

      <t>Below the P2PSIP Overlay, we have a conventional SIP UA "A" which is
      not part of the P2PSIP Overlay, either directly as a peer or indirectly
      as a client. It speaks neither the P2PSIP Peer nor P2PSIP Client
      protocols. Instead, it uses SIP to interact with the P2PSIP Overlay.</t>

      <t>On the right side, we have a P2PSIP client "C", which uses the P2PSIP
      Client Protocol depicted by "=" to communicate with Proxy Peer "Q". The
      P2PSIP client &ldquo;C&rdquo; could communicate with a different peer,
      for example peer "F", if it establishes a connection to "F" instead of
      or in addition to "Q". The exact role that this client plays in the
      network is still under discussion (see <xref
      target="Clients"></xref>).</t>

      <t>Both the SIP proxy coupled with peer "P" and the SIP redirector
      coupled with peer "R" can serve as adapters between ordinary SIP devices
      and the P2PSIP Overlay. Each accepts standard SIP requests and resolves
      the next-hop by using the P2PSIP overlay Peer Protocol to interact with
      the routing knowledge of the P2PSIP Overlay, then processes the SIP
      requests as appropriate (proxying or redirecting towards the next-hop).
      Note that proxy operation is bidirectional - the proxy may be forwarding
      a request from an ordinary SIP device to the P2PSIP overlay, or from the
      P2PSIP overlay to an ordinary SIP device.</t>

      <t>The PSTN Gateway at peer "G" provides a similar sort of adaptation to
      and from the public switched telephone network (PSTN).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Definitions">
      <t>This section defines a number of concepts that are key to
      understanding the P2PSIP work.</t>

      <list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Overlay Network:">An overlay network is a computer
        network which is built on top of another network. Nodes in the overlay
        can be thought of as being connected by virtual or logical links, each
        of which corresponds to a path, perhaps through many physical links,
        in the underlying network. For example, many peer-to-peer networks are
        overlay networks because they run on top of the Internet. Dial-up
        Internet is an overlay upon the telephone network. <eref
        target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P2P_overlay" /></t>

        <t hangText="P2P Network:">A peer-to-peer (or P2P) computer network is
        a network that relies primarily on the computing power and bandwidth
        of the participants in the network rather than concentrating it in a
        relatively low number of servers. P2P networks are typically used for
        connecting nodes via largely ad hoc connections. Such networks are
        useful for many purposes. Sharing content files (see <eref
        target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File_sharing" />) containing
        audio, video, data or anything in digital format is very common, and
        realtime data, such as telephony traffic, is also exchanged using P2P
        technology. <eref
        target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer-to-peer" />. A P2P Network
        may also be called a "P2P Overlay" or "P2P Overlay Network" or "P2P
        Network Overlay", since its organization is not at the physical layer,
        but is instead "on top of" an existing Internet Protocol network.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP:">A suite of communications protocols related to
        the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref target="RFC3261" /> that
        enable SIP to use peer-to-peer techniques for resolving the targets of
        SIP requests, providing SIP message transport, and providing other
        SIP-related functions. The exact contents of this protocol suite are
        still under discussion, but is likely to include the P2PSIP Peer
        Protocol and may include a P2PSIP Client Protocol (see definitions
        below).</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Overlay:">A P2PSIP Overlay is an association,
        collection, or federation of nodes that provides SIP registration, SIP
        message transport, and similar functions using a P2P organization, as
        defined by "P2P Network" above.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Overlay Name:">A human-friendly name that
        identifies a specific P2PSIP Overlay. This is in the format of (a
        portion of) a URI, but may or may not have a related record in the
        DNS.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Peer:">A node participating in a P2PSIP Overlay
        that provides storage and transport services to other nodes in that
        P2PSIP Overlay. Each P2PSIP Peer has a unique identifier, known as a
        Peer-ID, within the P2PSIP Overlay. Each P2PSIP Peer may be coupled to
        one or more SIP entities. Within the P2PSIP Overlay, the peer is
        capable of performing several different operations, including: joining
        and leaving the overlay, transporting SIP messages within the overlay,
        storing information on behalf of the overlay, putting information into
        the overlay, and getting information from the overlay.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Peer-ID:">Information that uniquely identifies
        each P2PSIP Peer within a given P2PSIP Overlay. This value is not
        human-friendly -- in a DHT approach, this is a numeric value in the
        hash space. These Peer-IDs are completely independent of the
        identifier of any user of a user agent associated with a peer. (Note:
        This is often called a "Node-ID" in the P2P literature).</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Client:">A node participating in a P2PSIP Overlay
        that is less capable than a P2PSIP Peer in some way. The role of a
        P2PSIP Client is still under debate, with a number of competing
        proposals, and some have suggested removing the concept entirely (see
        the discussion on this later in the document). If clients exist, then
        it has been agreed that they do have the ability to add, modify,
        inspect, and delete information in the overlay. Note that the term
        client does not imply that this node is a SIP UAC. Some have suggested
        that the word 'client' be changed to something else to avoid both this
        confusion and the implication of a client-server relationship.</t>

        <t hangText="User:">A human that interacts with the overlay through
        SIP UAs located on peers and clients (and perhaps other ways).</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP User Name:">A human-friendly name for a user. This
        name must be unique within the overlay, but may be unique in a wider
        scope. User Names are formatted so that they can be used within a URI
        (likely a SIP URI), perhaps in combination with the Overlay Name.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Service:">A capability contributed by a peer to an
        overlay or to the members of an overlay. It is expected that not all
        peers and clients will offer the same set of services, so a means of
        finding peers (and perhaps clients) that offer a particular service is
        required. Services might include routing of requests, storing of
        routing data, storing of other data, STUN discovery, STUN relay, and
        many other things. This model posits a requirement for a service
        locator function, possibly including supporting information such as
        the capacity of a peer to provide a specific service or descriptions
        of the policies under which a peer will provide that service. We
        currently expect that we will need to be able to search for available
        service providers within each overlay. We think we might need to be
        able to make searches based on network locality or path
        minimalization.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Service Name:">A unique, human-friendly, name for
        a service.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Resource:">Anything about which information can be
        stored in the overlay. Both Users and Services are examples of
        Resources.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Resource-ID:">A non-human-friendly value that
        uniquely identifies a resource and which is used as a key for storing
        and retrieving data about the resource. One way to generate a
        Resource-ID is by applying a mapping function to some other unique
        name (e.g., User Name or Service Name) for the resource. The
        Resource-ID is used by the distributed database algorithm to determine
        the peer or peers that are responsible for storing the data for the
        overlay.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Resource Record:">A block of data, stored using
        distributed database mechanism of the P2PSIP Overlay, that includes
        information relevant to a specific resource. We presume that there may
        be multiple types of resource records. Some may hold data about Users,
        and others may hold data about Services, and the working group may
        define other types. The types, usages, and formats of the records are
        a question for future study.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Responsible Peer">The Peer that is responsible for
        storing the Resource Record for a Resource. In the literature, the
        term "Root Peer" is also used for this concept.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Peer Protocol:">The protocol spoken between P2PSIP
        Overlay peers to share information and organize the P2PSIP Overlay
        Network.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Client Protocol:">The protocol spoken between
        P2PSIP Clients and P2PSIP Peers. It is used to store and retrieve
        information from the P2P Overlay. The nature of this protocol, and
        even its existence, is under discussion. However, if it exists, it has
        been agreed that the Client Protocol is a functional subset of the P2P
        Peer Protocol, but may differ in syntax and protocol implementation
        (i.e., may not be syntactically related).</t>

        <t
        hangText="P2PSIP Peer Protocol Connection / P2PSIP Client Protocol Connection:">The
        TCP, UDP or other transport layer protocol connection over which the
        P2PSIP Peer Protocol (or respectively the Client protocol) is
        transported.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Neighbors:">The set of P2PSIP Peers that either a
        P2PSIP Peer or P2PSIP Client know of directly and can reach without
        further lookups.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Joining Peer:">A node that is attempting to become
        a P2PSIP Peer in a particular P2PSIP Overlay.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Bootstrap Peer:">A P2PSIP Peer in the P2PSIP
        Overlay that is the first point of contact for a P2PSIP Joining Peer.
        It selects the peer that will serve as the P2PSIP Admitting Peer and
        helps the joining peer contact the admitting peer.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Admitting Peer:">A P2PSIP Peer in the P2PSIP
        Overlay which helps the P2PSIP Joining Peer join the Overlay. The
        choice of the admitting peer may depend on the joining peer (e.g.,
        depend the joining peer's P2PSIP Peer-ID). For example, the admitting
        peer might be chosen as the peer which is "closest" in the logical
        structure of the overlay to the future position of the joining peer.
        The selection of the admitting peer is typically done by the bootstrap
        peer. It is allowable for the bootstrap peer to select itself as the
        admitting peer.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Bootstrap Server:">A network node used by P2PSIP
        Joining Peers to locate a P2PSIP Bootstrap Peer. Typically, a P2PSIP
        Bootstrap Server acts as a proxy for messages between the P2PSIP
        Joining Peer and the P2PSIP Bootstrap Peer. The P2PSIP Bootstrap
        Server itself is typically a stable host with a DNS name that is
        somehow communicated (for example, through configuration) to peers
        that want to join the overlay. A P2PSIP Bootstrap Server is NOT
        required to be a peer or client, though it may be if desired.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Peer Admission:">The act of admitting a node (the
        "P2PSIP Joining Peer") into a P2PSIP Overlay as a P2PSIP Peer. After
        the admission process is over, the joining peer is a fully-functional
        peer of the overlay. During the admission process, the joining peer
        may need to present credentials to prove that it has sufficient
        authority to join the overlay.</t>

        <t hangText="P2PSIP Resource Record Insertion:">The act of inserting a
        P2PSIP Resource Record into the distributed database. Following
        insertion, the data will be stored at one or more peers. The data can
        be retrieved or updated using the P2PSIP Resource-ID as a key.</t>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Discussion">
      <section title="The Distributed Database Function">
        <t>A P2PSIP Overlay functions as a distributed database. The database
        serves as a way to store information about things called Resources. A
        piece of information, called a Resource Record, can be stored by and
        retrieved from the database using a key associated with the Resource
        Record called its Resource-ID. Each Resource must have a unique
        Resource-ID. In addition to uniquely identifying the Resource, the
        Resource-ID is also used by the distributed database algorithm to
        determine the peer or peers that store the Resource Record in the
        overlay.</t>

        <t>It is expected that the P2PSIP working group will standardize the
        way(s) certain types of resources are represented in the distributed
        database.</t>

        <t>One type of resource representation that the working group is
        expected to standardize is information about users. Users are humans
        that can use the overlay to do things like making and receiving calls.
        Information stored in the resource record associated with a user might
        include things like the full name of the user and the location of the
        UAs that the user is using.</t>

        <t>Before information about a user can be stored in the overlay, a
        user needs a User Name. The User Name is a human-friendly identifier
        that uniquely identifies the user within the overlay. The User Name is
        not a Resource-ID, rather the Resource-ID is derived from the User
        Name using some mapping function (often a cryptographic hash function)
        defined by the distributed database algorithm used by the overlay.</t>

        <t>The overlay may also require that the user have a set of
        credentials. Credentials may be required to authenticate the user
        and/or to show that the user is authorized to use the overlay.</t>

        <t>Another type of resource representation that the working group is
        expected to standardize is information about services. Services
        represent actions that a peer (and perhaps a client) can do to benefit
        other peers and clients in the overlay. Information that might be
        stored in the resource record associated with a service might include
        the peers (and perhaps clients) offering the service.</t>

        <t>Each service has a human-friendly Service Name that uniquely
        identifies the service. Like User Names, the Service Name is not a
        resource-id, rather the resource-id is derived from the service name
        using some function defined by the distributed database algorithm used
        by the overlay.</t>

        <t>It is expected that the working group will standardize at least one
        service. For each standardized service, the working group will likely
        specify the service name, the nature and format of the information
        stored in the resource record associated with the service, and the
        protocol used to access the service.</t>

        <t>The overlay may require that the peer (or client) have a set of
        credentials for a service. For example, credentials might be required
        to show that the peer (or client) is authorized to offer the service,
        or to show that the peer (or client) is a providing a trustworthy
        implementation of the service.</t>

        <t>It is expected that the P2PSIP WG will not standardize how a User
        Name is obtained, nor how the credentials associated with a User Name
        or a Service Name are obtained, but merely standardize at least one
        acceptable format for each. To ensure interoperability, it is expected
        that at least one of these formats will be specified as
        "mandatory-to-implement".</t>

        <t>A class of algorithms known as Distributed Hash Tables <eref
        target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P2P_overlay"></eref> are one way
        to implement the Distributed Database. In particular, both the Chord
        and Bamboo algorithms have been suggested as good choices for the
        distributed database algorithm. However, no decision has been taken so
        far.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Using the Distributed Database Function">
        <t>There are a number of ways the distributed database described in
        the previous section might be used to establish multimedia sessions
        using SIP. In this section, we give four possibilities as examples. It
        seems likely that the working group will standardize at least one way
        (not necessarily one of the four listed here), but no decisions have
        been taken yet.</t>

        <t>The first option is to store the contact information for a user in
        the resource record for the user. A peer Y that is a contact point for
        this user adds contact information to this resource record. The
        resource record itself is stored with peer Z in the network, where
        peer Z is chosen by the distributed database algorithm.</t>

        <t>When the SIP entity coupled with peer X has an INVITE message
        addressed to this user, it retrieves the resource record from peer Z.
        It then extracts the contact information for the various peers that
        are a contact point for the user, including peer Y, and forwards the
        INVITE onward.</t>

        <t>This exchange is illustrated in the following figure. The notation
        "Put(U@Y)" is used to show the distributed database operation of
        updating the resource record for user U with the contract Y, and
        "Get(U)" illustrates the distributed database operation of retrieving
        the resource record for user U. Note that the messages between the
        peers X, Y and Z may actually travel via intermediate peers (not
        shown) as part of the distributed lookup process or so as to traverse
        intervening NATs.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
            
Peer X           Peer Z           Peer Y
 |                 |                |
 |                 |       Put(U@Y) |
 |                 |<---------------|
 |                 | Put-Resp(OK)   |
 |                 |--------------->|
 |                 |                |
 | Get(U)          |                |
 |---------------->|                |
 |    Get-Resp(U@Y)|                |
 |<----------------|                |
 | INVITE(To:U)    |                |
 |--------------------------------->|
 |                 |                |
	       
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The second option also involves storing the contact information for
        a user in the resource record of the user. However, SIP entity at peer
        X, rather than retrieving the resource record from peer Z, instead
        forwards the INVITE message to the proxy at peer Z. The proxy at peer
        Z then uses the information in the resource record and forwards the
        INVITE onwards to the SIP entity at peer Y and the other contacts.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
            
Peer X           Peer Z           Peer Y
 |                 |                |
 |                 |       Put(U@Y) |
 |                 |<---------------|
 |                 | Put-Resp(OK)   |
 |                 |--------------->|
 |                 |                |
 | INVITE(To:U)    |                |
 |-----------------| INVITE(To:U)   |
 |                 |--------------->|
 |                 |                |
	       
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The third option is for a single peer W to place its contact
        information into the resource record for the user (stored with peer
        Z). A peer Y that is a contact point for the user retrieves the
        resource record from peer Z, extracts the contact information for peer
        W, and then uses the standard SIP registration mechanism <xref
        target="RFC3261"></xref> to register with peer W. When the SIP entity
        at peer X has to forward an INVITE request, it retrieves the resource
        record and extracts the contact information for W. It then forwards
        the INVITE to the proxy at peer W, which proxies it onward to peer Y
        and the other contacts.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
            
Peer X           Peer Z           Peer Y           Peer W
 |                 |                |                 |
 |                 |       Put(U@W) |                 |
 |                 |<---------------------------------|
 |                 | Put-Resp(OK)   |                 |
 |                 |--------------------------------->|
 |                 |                |                 |
 |                 |                |                 |
 |                 |                | REGISTER(To:U)  |
 |                 |                |---------------->|
 |                 |                |             200 |
 |                 |                |<----------------|
 |                 |                |                 |
 |                 |                |                 |
 | Get(U)          |                |                 |
 |---------------->|                |                 |
 |    Get-Resp(U@W)|                |                 |
 |<----------------|                |                 |
 | INVITE(To:U)    |                |                 |
 |--------------------------------------------------->|
 |                 |                |    INVITE(To:U) |
 |                 |                |<----------------|
 |                 |                |                 |
	       
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The fourth option works as in option 3, with the exception that,
        rather than X retrieving the resource record from Z, peer X forwards
        the INVITE to a SIP proxy at Z, which proxies it onward to W and hence
        to Y.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
            
Peer X           Peer Z           Peer Y           Peer W
 |                 |                |                 |
 |                 |       Put(U@W) |                 |
 |                 |<---------------------------------|
 |                 | Put-Resp(OK)   |                 |
 |                 |--------------------------------->|
 |                 |                |                 |
 |                 |                |                 |
 |                 |                | REGISTER(To:U)  |
 |                 |                |---------------->|
 |                 |                |             200 |
 |                 |                |<----------------|
 |                 |                |                 |
 |                 |                |                 |
 | INVITE(To:U)    |                |                 |
 |---------------->| INVITE(To:U)   |                 |
 |                 |--------------------------------->|
 |                 |                |    INVITE(To:U) |
 |                 |                |<----------------|
 |                 |                |                 |
	       
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The pros and cons of option 1 and 3 are briefly discussed in <xref
        target="Using-an-External-DHT"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="NAT Traversal">
        <t>Two approaches to NAT Traversal for P2PSIP Peer Protocol have been
        suggested. The working group has not made any decision yet on the
        approach that will be selected.</t>

        <t>The first, the traditional approach adopted by most peer-to-peer
        networks today, divides up the peers in the network into two groups:
        those with public IP addresses and those without. The networks then
        select a subset of the former group and elevate them to "super peer"
        status, leaving the remaining peers as "ordinary peers". Since super
        peers all have public IP addresses, there are no NAT problems when
        communicating between them. The network then associates each ordinary
        peer with (usually just one) super peer in a client-server
        relationship. Once this is done, an ordinary peer X can communicate
        with another ordinary peer Y by sending the message to X's super peer,
        which forwards it to Y's super peer, which forwards it to Y. The
        connection between an ordinary peer and its super peer is initiated by
        the ordinary peer, which makes it easy to traverse any intervening
        NATs. In this approach, the number of hops between two peers is at
        most 3.</t>

        <t>The second approach treats all peers as equal and establishes a
        partial mesh of connections between them. Messages from one peer to
        another are then routed along the edges in the mesh of connections
        until they reach their destination. To make the routing efficient and
        to avoid the use of standard Internet routing protocols, the partial
        mesh is organized in a structured manner. If the structure is based on
        any one of a number of common DHT algorithms, then the maximum number
        of hops between any two peers is log N, where N is the number of peers
        in the overlay.</t>

        <t>The first approach is significantly more efficient than the second
        in overlays with large numbers of peers. However, the first approach
        assumes there are a sufficient number of peers with public IP
        addresses to serve as super peers. In some usage scenarios envisioned
        for P2PSIP, this assumption does not hold. For example, this approach
        fails completely in the case where every peer is behind a distinct
        NAT.</t>

        <t>The second approach, while less efficient in overlays with larger
        numbers of peers, is efficient in smaller overlays and can be made to
        work in many use cases where the first approach fails.</t>

        <t>Both of these approaches assume a method of setting up Peer
        Protocol connections between peers. Many such methods exist; the now
        expired <xref target="I-D.iab-nat-traversal-considerations"></xref> is
        an attempt to give a fairly comprehensive list along with a discussion
        of their pros and cons. After a consideration of the various
        techniques, the P2PSIP working group has decided to select the
        Unilateral Self-Address Fixing method <xref target="RFC3424"></xref>
        of NAT Traversal, and in particular the ICE <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice"></xref> implementation of this
        approach.</t>

        <t>The above discussion covers NAT traversal for Peer Protocol
        connections. For Client Protocol connections, the approach depends on
        the role adopted for clients and we defer the discussion on that point
        until the role becomes clearer.</t>

        <t>In addition to Peer Protocol and Client Protocol messages, a P2PSIP
        Overlay must also provide a solution to the NAT Traversal problem for
        SIP messages. If it does not, there is no reliable way for a peer
        behind one NAT to send a SIP INVITE to a peer behind another NAT. One
        way to solve this problem is to transport SIP messages along Peer and
        Client Protocol connections: this could be done either by
        encapsulating the SIP messages inside Peer and Client Protocol
        messages or by multiplexing SIP with the Peer (resp.Client) Protocol
        on a Peer (resp. Client) Protocol connection.</t>

        <t>Finally, it should be noted that the NAT traversal problem for
        media connections signaled using SIP is outside the scope of the
        P2PSIP working group. As discussed in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-sipping-nat-scenarios"></xref>, the current
        recommendation is to use ICE.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Locating and Joining an Overlay">
        <t>Before a peer can attempt to join a P2PSIP overlay, it must first
        obtain a Peer-ID and optionally a set of credentials. The Peer-ID is
        an identifier that will uniquely identify the peer within the overlay,
        while the credentials show that the peer is allowed to join the
        overlay.</t>

        <t>The P2PSIP WG will not standardize how the peer-ID and the
        credentials are obtained, but merely standardize at least one
        acceptable format for each. To ensure interoperability, it is expected
        that at least one of these formats will be specified as
        "mandatory-to-implement".</t>

        <t>Once a peer (the "joining peer") has a peer-ID and optionally a set
        of credentials, it can attempt to join the overlay. To do this, it
        needs to locate a bootstrap peer for the Overlay.</t>

        <t>A bootstrap peer is a peer that serves as the first point of
        contact for the joining peer. The joining peer uses a bootstrap
        mechanism to locate a bootstrap peer. Locating a bootstrap peer might
        be done in any one of a number of different ways: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>By remembering peers that were part of the overlay the last
            time the peer was part of the overlay;</t>

            <t>Through a multicast discovery mechanism;</t>

            <t>Through manual configuration; or</t>

            <t>By contacting a P2PSIP Bootstrap Server, and using its help to
            locate a bootstrap peer.</t>
          </list> The joining peer might reasonably try each of the methods
        (and perhaps others) in some order or in parallel until it succeeds in
        finding a bootstrap peer.</t>

        <t>The job of the bootstrap peer is simple: refer the joining peer to
        a peer (called the "admitting peer") that will help the joining peer
        join the network. The choice of admitting peer will often depend on
        the joining node - for example, the admitting peer may be a peer that
        will become a neighbor of the joining peer in the overlay. It is
        possible that the bootstrap peer might also serve as the admitting
        peer.</t>

        <t>The admitting peer will help the joining peer learn about other
        peers in the overlay and establish connections to them as appropriate.
        The admitting peer and/or the other peers in the overlay will also do
        whatever else is required to help the joining peer become a
        fully-functional peer. The details of how this is done will depend on
        the distributed database algorithm used in the overlay.</t>

        <t>At various stages in this process, the joining peer may be asked to
        present its credentials to show that it is authorized to join the
        overlay. Similarly, the various peers contacted may be asked to
        present their credentials so the joining peer can verify that it is
        really joining the overlay it wants to.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Clients" title="Possible Client Behavior">
        <t>As mentioned above, a number of people have proposed a second type
        of P2PSIP entity, known as a "P2PSIP client". The question of whether
        the concept of a "client" is needed and, if it is needed, its exact
        nature, is still very much under debate. This section presents some of
        the alternatives that have been suggested for the possible role of a
        client.</t>

        <t>In one approach, a client interacts with the P2PSIP overlay through
        an associated peer (or perhaps several such peers) using the Client
        Protocol. The client does not run the distributed database algorithm,
        does not store resource records, and is not involved in routing
        messages to other peers or clients. Through interactions with its
        associated peer, a client can insert, modify, examine, and remove
        resource records. A client can also send SIP messages to its
        associated peer for routing through the overlay. In this approach, a
        client is a node that wants to take advantage of the overlay, but is
        unable or unwilling to contribute resources back to the overlay.</t>

        <t>One way to realize this alternative is for a peer to behave as a
        <xref target="RFC3261"></xref> proxy/registrar. Clients then use
        standard SIP mechanisms to add, update, and remove registrations and
        to send SIP messages to peers and other clients. If this is done,
        there is no need for a separate Client Protocol and no need for P2PSIP
        to define a distinct "P2PSIP Client" concept.</t>

        <t>In a second alternative, a client behaves in a way similar to the
        way described in first alternative, except that it does store resource
        records. In essence, the client contributes its storage capacity to
        its associated peer. A peer which needs to store a resource record may
        elect to store this on one or more of its associated clients instead,
        thus boosting its effective storage capacity.</t>

        <t>In a third alternative, a client acts almost the same as a peer,
        except that it does not store any resource records. In this
        alternative, a client has a "peer-ID" and joins the overlay in the
        same way as a peer, perhaps establishing the same network of
        connections that a peer would. Clients participate in the distributed
        database algorithm, and can help in transporting messages to other
        peers and clients. However, the distributed database algorithm does
        not assign resource records to clients. The role of a client in this
        model has been described as "a peer with bad memory".</t>

        <t>Another way to look at this distinction is that a client is simply
        a peer that is not currently offering some or all services to the
        overlay, possibly due to a run-time decision about available resources
        such as bandwidth or storage capacity. With this approach, the
        distinction between client and peer becomes much less distinct, and
        probably eliminates the requirement to have two distinct terms for the
        roles. Rather, we might speak in terms such as "high-function" vs
        "low-function" peers. This approach would also seem to eliminate the
        requirement for a distinct P2PSIP Client Protocol.</t>

        <t>It has also been proposed that the client role could be fulfilled
        by conventional SIP UAs served by a peer that is also acting as a
        proxy/registrar. While this might fulfill the requirement, the authors
        contend that such as device is a "SIP UA", not a "P2PSIP Client" as
        defined in this document, and that exclusively using SIP UAs in this
        role eliminates the need for P2PSIP Clients and P2PSIP Client Protocol
        from the architecture.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Interacting with non-P2PSIP entities">
        <t>It is possible for network nodes that are not peers or clients to
        interact with a P2PSIP overlay. Such nodes would do this through
        mechanisms not defined by the P2PSIP working group provided they can
        find a peer or client that supports that mechanism and which will do
        any related P2PSIP operations necessary. In this section, we briefly
        describe two ways this might be done. (Note that these are just
        examples and the descriptions here are not recommendations).</t>

        <t>One example is a peer that also acts as a standard SIP proxy and
        registrar. SIP UAs can interact with it using mechanisms defined in
        <xref target="RFC3261"></xref>. The peer inserts registrations for
        users learned from these UAs into the distributed database, and
        retrieves contact information when proxying INVITE messages.</t>

        <t>Another example is a peer that has a fully-qualified domain name
        (FQDN) that matches the name of the overlay and acts as a SIP proxy
        for calls coming into the overlay. A SIP INVITE addressed to
        "user@overlay-name" arrives at the peer (using the mechanisms in <xref
        target="RFC3263"></xref>) and this peer then looks up the user in the
        distributed database and proxies the call onto it.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Architecture">
        <t>There has been much debate in the group over what an appropriate
        architecture for P2PSIP should be. Currently, the group is
        investigating architectures that involve a P2P layer that is distinct
        from the applications that run on the overlay.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[      __________________________
     |                          |
     |    SIP, other apps...    |
     |       ___________________|
     |      |   P2P Layer       |
     |______|___________________|
     |     Transport Layer      |
     |__________________________|
]]></artwork>

          <postamble></postamble>
        </figure>

        <t>The P2P layer implements the Peer Protocol (and the Client
        Protocol, if such a protocol exists). Applications access this P2P
        layer for various overlay-related services. Applications are also free
        to bypass this layer and access the existing transport layer protocols
        (e.g., TCP, UDP, etc.) directly.</t>

        <t>A notable feature of this architecture is that it envisions the use
        of protocols other than SIP in the overlay. Though the working group
        is primarily focused on the use of SIP in peer-to-peer overlays, this
        architecture envisions a future in which other protocols can play a
        role.</t>

        <t>The group initially considered another architecture. In this
        alternative architecture, the Peer Protocol was defined as an
        extension to SIP. That is, that the necessary operations for forming
        and maintaining the overlay and for storing and retrieving resource
        records in the distributed database were defined as extensions to SIP.
        Each peer in the overlay was viewed as a SIP proxy that would forward
        the overlay maintenance and distributed database query messages
        (expressed in SIP) on behalf of other peers. <xref
        target="I-D.bryan-p2psip-dsip"></xref> presents a detailed design, and
        <xref target="I-D.zangrilli-p2psip-whysip"></xref> argues for this
        general approach.</t>

        <t>This architecture was eventually rejected by the working group for
        the following reasons: <list style="symbols">
            <t>The architecture was totally focused on SIP, and made it
            difficult to use other protocols in the overlay.</t>

            <t>In SIP, proxies are assumed to be trusted parties. Relying on
            the peers to route the message as proxies exposes the SIP messages
            to attacks from untrusted proxies that SIP's design does not
            anticipate. A design that does not allow the peers to modify the
            SIP message and ideally prevents them from reading it is
            preferable.</t>

            <t>SIP was seen as a "heavy-weight" protocol for this task. SIP
            uses a text-based encoding which is very flexible, but leads to
            both large messages and slow processing times at proxies. This was
            seen to be a poor match for P2PSIP, where a distributed database
            lookup operation requires O(log N) peers to receive, process and
            forward the message.</t>
          </list>More discussion on this alternate approach and why it was
        rejected can be found on the P2PSIP mailing list in a thread that
        started on 20 March 2007.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- section 3 -->

    <section title="Additional Questions">
      <t>This section lists some additional questions that the proposed P2PSIP
      Working Group may need to consider in the process of defining the Peer
      and Client protocols.</t>

      <section title="Selecting between Multiple Peers offering the Same Service">
        <t>If a P2PSIP network contains two or more peers that offer the same
        service, then how does a peer or client that wishes to use that
        service select the peer to use? This question comes up in a number of
        contexts: <list style="symbols">
            <t>When two or more peers are willing to serve as a STUN Relay,
            how do we select a peer that is close in the netpath sense and is
            otherwise appropriate for the call?</t>

            <t>When two or more peers are willing to serve as PSTN gateways,
            how do we select an appropriate gateway for a call that is both
            netpath efficient and provides good quality or inexpensive PSTN
            routing?</t>
          </list> It has been suggested that, at least initially, the working
        group should restrict itself to defining a mechanism that can return a
        list of peers offering a service and not define the mechanism for
        selecting a peer from that list.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Visibility of Messages to Intermediate Peers">
        <t>When transporting SIP messages through the overlay, are the headers
        and/or bodies of the SIP messages visible to the peers that the
        messages happen to pass through? If they are, what types of security
        risks does this pose in the presence of peers that have been
        compromised in some way?</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Using C/S SIP and P2PSIP Simultaneously in a Single UA">
        <t>If a given UA is capable of operating in both P2PSIP and
        conventional SIP modalities (especially simultaneously), is it
        possible for it to use and respond to the same AOR using both
        conventional and P2PSIP? An example of such a topology might be a UA
        that registers an AOR (say, "sip:alice@example.com") conventionally
        with a registrar and then inserts a resource record for that resource
        into a P2PSIP topology, such that both conventional SIP users and
        P2PSIP users (within the overlay or a federation thereof) would be
        able to contact the user without necessarily traversing some sort of
        gateway. Is this something that we want to make work?</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Clients, Peers, and Services">
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Do all peers providing routing, storage, and all other services,
          or do only some peers provide certain services?</t>

          <t>What services, if any, must all peers provide?</t>

          <t>Do we need clients as a discrete class, or do SIP UAs and/or
          low-function peers completely satisfy the requirements?</t>

          <t>How we can we describe the capacity of a peer for delivering a
          given service?</t>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section title="Relationships of Domains to Overlays">
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Can there be names from more than one domain in a single
          overlay?</t>

          <t>Can there be names from one domain in more than a single overlay?
          If so, how do we route Client/Server SIP requests to the right
          overlay?</t>

          <t>Can the domain of an AoR be in more than one overlay?</t>

          <t>Should we have a "default overlay" to search for peers in many
          domains?</t>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Building a P2PSIP system has many security considerations, many of
      which we have only begun to consider. We anticipate that the protocol
      documents describing the actual protocols will deal more thoroughly with
      security topics.</t>

      <t>One critical security issue that will need to be addressed is
      providing for the privacy and integrity of SIP messages being routed by
      peer nodes, when those peer nodes might well be hostile. This is a
      departure from Client/Server SIP, where the proxies are generally
      operated by enterprises or service providers with whom the users of SIP
      UAs have a trust relationship.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document presently raises no IANA considerations.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Changes in This Version">
      <list style="numbers">
        <t>Revised "Open Questions" to reflect current discussion.</t>

        <t>Resolved conflict between "services provided by overlay" and "named
        services provided by peers" by calling all overlay-level operations
        "functions". Thus, we would now speak of an overlay providing a
        "distributed transport function".</t>

        <t>Resolved open issue "Does P2PSIP provide a distributed location
        function or an alternative mechanism to RFC 3263? The answer seems to
        be both, but what is the relationship between these?" by documenting
        that each overlay provides an alternative to <xref target="RFC3263" />
        within that overlay, but that <xref target="RFC3263" /> is used in the
        conventional manner between overlays.</t>

        <t>Revised abstract to include SIP message routing within the
        scope.</t>

        <t>Added brief mention of peer's capacity for services offered in
        overview section on distributed database.</t>

        <t>Revised definition of P2PSIP Service.</t>

        <t>Revised abstract and high level discussion.</t>

        <t>Added discussion of proposed peer models and relationship to SIP
        UAs.</t>

        <t>Revised reference model diagram to clarify client behavior.</t>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document draws heavily from the contributions of many
      participants in the P2PSIP Mailing List but the authors are especially
      grateful for the support of Spencer Dawkins, Cullen Jennings, and
      Henning Schulzrinne, all of whom spent time on phone calls about this
      document or provided text. In addition, Spencer contributed the
      Reference Model figure.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>   not currently referenced -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3986"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3263"?>

      <!--      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3327"?>    not currently referenced -->
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4485"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.bryan-p2psip-dsip"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.zangrilli-p2psip-whysip"?>

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.johnston-sipping-p2p-ipcom"?> -->

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.matthews-p2psip-hip-hop"?>

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.bryan-sipping-p2p-usecases"?> -->

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.irtf-p2prg-survey-search"?> -->

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-behave-rfc3489bis"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4795"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2136"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.marocco-p2psip-xpp-pcan"?>

      <!--      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-behave-turn"?>    not currently referenced -->

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice"?>

      <!--      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-sip-outbound"?>   not currently referenced -->

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.iab-nat-traversal-considerations"?>

      <!-- 	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.matthews-p2psip-nats-and-overlays"?>  not currently referenced -->

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-sipping-nat-scenarios"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3424"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.bryan-p2psip-reload"?>

      <reference anchor="Using-an-External-DHT">
        <front>
          <title>Using an External DHT as a SIP Location Service</title>

          <author initials="K." surname="Singh" />

          <author initials="H." surname="Schulzrinne" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name=""
                    value="Columbia University Computer Science Dept. Tech Report 388)" />

        <annotation>Copy available at
        http://mice.cs.columbia.edu/getTechreport.php?techreportID=388/</annotation>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>