<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="std" ipr="full3978" docName="draft-ietf-avt-rtcp-xr-concsec-00.txt">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

    <front>
        <title abbrev='RTCP XR Concealed Seconds'>RTCP XR Report Block for Concealed Seconds metric Reporting</title>
        <author initials='G.' surname='Hunt' fullname='Geoff Hunt'>
            <organization abbrev='BT'>BT</organization>
		<address>
	    <postal>
        	<street>Orion 1 PP9</street>
        	<street>Adastral Park</street>
        	<street>Martlesham Heath</street>
        	<city>Ipswich</city> <region>Suffolk</region>
        	<code>IP4 2TH</code>
        	<country>United Kingdom</country>
    	    </postal>
	    <phone>+44 1473 608325</phone>
	    <email>geoff.hunt@bt.com</email>
	    </address>
        </author>
        <author initials='A.' surname='Clark' fullname='Alan Clark'>
            <organization abbrev='Telchemy'>Telchemy Incorporated</organization>
		<address>
	    <postal>
        	<street>2905 Premiere Parkway, Suite 280</street>
        	<city>Duluth</city> <region>GA</region>
        	<code>30097</code>
        	<country>USA</country>
    	    </postal>
	    <email>alan.d.clark@telchemy.com</email>
	    </address>
        </author>
        <date month='October' year='2008' />
       <area>Real-time Applications and Infrastructure Area</area>
        <workgroup>Audio/Video Transport Working Group</workgroup>
        <keyword>RFC</keyword>
        <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
        <keyword>I-D</keyword>
        <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
        <keyword>Real Time Control Protocol</keyword>
        <abstract>
        <t>
   This document defines an RTCP XR Report Block that allows the
   reporting of Concealed Seconds metrics primarily for audio applications of RTP.
        </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>

<section anchor='intro' title="Introduction">
<section anchor='intro1' title="Concealed Seconds Block">
<t>
   This draft defines a new block type to augment those defined
   in <xref target='RFC3611'/>, for use primarily in audio applications of RTP.
</t><t>
   At any instant, the audio output at a receiver may be classified as
   either 'normal' or 'concealed'.  'Normal' refers to playout of audio
   payload received from the remote end, and also includes locally
   generated signals such as announcements, tones and comfort noise.
   Concealment refers to playout of locally-generated signals used to
   mask the impact of network impairments or to reduce the audibility of
   jitter buffer adaptations.
</t><t>
   The new block type provides metrics for concealment. Specifically, the first metric 
(Unimpaired Seconds) reports the number of whole seconds
occupied only with normal playout of data which the receiver obtained from the sender's stream. The 
second metric 
(Concealed Seconds) reports the number of whole seconds during which the receiver played 
out any locally-generated media data. A third 
metric (Severely Concealed Seconds) reports the number of whole seconds during which 
the receiver played out locally-generated data for more than SCS Threshold (ms).
</t>
<t>
The metric belongs to the class of transport-related terminal metrics defined in [MONARCH] (work in progress).
</t><t>
Instances of this Metrics Block refer by tag to the separate auxiliary Measurement Identity block 
<xref target='MEASIDENT'/> which contains information 
such as the SSRC of the measured stream, and RTP sequence numbers and time intervals indicating the span of the report.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor='intro2' title="RTCP and RTCP XR Reports">
<t>
   The use of RTCP for reporting is defined in <xref target='RFC3550'/>. 
   <xref target='RFC3611'/> defined an extensible structure for reporting using
   an RTCP Extended Report (XR).  This draft defines
   a new Extended Report block that MUST be used as defined in
   <xref target='RFC3550'/> and <xref target='RFC3611'/>.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor='intro3' title="Performance Metrics Framework">
<t>
   The Performance Metrics Framework <xref target='PMOLFRAME'/> provides guidance on the
   definition and specification of performance metrics.  Metrics
   described in this draft either reference external definitions
   or define metrics generally in accordance with the guidelines
   in <xref target='PMOLFRAME'/>.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor='intro4' title="Applicability">
<t>
This metric is primarily applicable to audio applications of RTP. 
EDITOR'S NOTE: are there metrics for concealment of transport errors for video?
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor='blockdef' title="Concealed Seconds Metrics Block">
<t>
   This sub-block provides a description of potentially audible
   impairments due to lost and discarded packets at the endpoint,
   expressed on a time basis analogous to a traditional PSTN T1/E1
   errored seconds metric.
</t><t>
   The following metrics are based on successive one second intervals as
   declared by a local clock.  This local clock does NOT need to be
   synchronized to any external time reference.  The starting time of
   this clock is unspecified.  Note that this implies that the same loss
   pattern could result in slightly different count values, depending on
   where the losses occur relative to the particular one-second
   demarcation points.  For example, two loss events occurring 50ms
   apart could result in either one concealed second or two, depending
   on the particular 1000 ms boundaries used.
</t><t>
   The seconds in this sub-block are not necessarily calendar seconds.
   At the tail end of a call, periods of time of less than 1000ms shall
   be incorporated into these counts if they exceed 500ms and shall be
   disregarded if they are less than 500ms.
</t>
<section anchor='blockdef1' title="Report Block Structure">
    <figure anchor='blockdata' title="Report Block Structure">
        <artwork>
   Concealed seconds metrics block
    0               1               2               3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     BT=NCS    |I| tag |plc|rsv|       block length = 3        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                      Unimpaired Seconds                       |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                       Concealed Seconds                       |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Severely Concealed Seconds    | RESERVED      | SCS Threshold |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	</artwork>
    </figure>
</section>
<section anchor='blockdef2' title="Definition of Fields in Concealed Seconds Metrics Block">
<t>
   block type (BT): 8 bits
</t>
<t>
<list style='empty'>
<t>
         A Concealed Seconds Metrics Report Block is identified by the constant 
         NCS. 
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
[Note to RFC Editor: please replace NCS with the
         IANA provided RTCP XR block type for this block.]
</t>
<t>
   Interval Metric flag (I): 1 bit
</t>
<t>
<list style='empty'>
<t>
This field is used to indicate whether the Concealed Seconds metric block is an Interval or a Cumulative report, 
that is, whether the reported values apply to the most 
recent measurement interval duration between successive metrics reports (I=1) (the Interval Duration) or to the accumulation period 
characteristic of cumulative 
measurements (I=0) (the Cumulative Duration). Numerical values for both these intervals are provided in the Measurement Identifier block 
referenced by the tag field below.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
   Measurement Identifier association (tag): 3 bits
</t>
<t>
<list style='empty'>
<t>
This field is used to identify the Measurement Identifier block <xref target='MEASIDENT'/> which describes this measurement. The relevant 
Measurement Identifier block has the same tag value as the Concealed Seconds Metrics block. Note that there may be 
more than one Measurement Identifier block per RTCP packet.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
   Packet Loss Concealment Method (plc): 2 bits
</t>
<t>
<list style='empty'>
<t>
This field is used to identify the packet loss concealment method in use at the receiver, according to the 
following code:
</t>
</list>
</t>
<figure>
<artwork>
        bits 0-3
              0 = silence insertion
              1 = simple replay, no attenuation
              2 = simple replay, with attenuation
              3 = enhanced
              Other values reserved
</artwork>
</figure>
<t>
   Reserved (rsv): 2 bits
</t>
<t>
<list style='empty'>
<t>
These bits are reserved. They SHOULD be set to zero by senders and MUST be ignored by receivers.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
   block length: 16 bits
</t>
<t>
<list style='empty'>
<t>
The length of this report block in 32-bit words, minus one. For the Concealed Seconds block, the block length 
is equal to 3.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Unimpaired Seconds: 32 bits
</t>
<t>
<list style='empty'>
<t>
   A count of the number of unimpaired Seconds that have occurred.
</t><t>
   An unimpaired Second is defined as a continuous period of 1000ms
   during which no frame loss or discard due to late arrival has
   occurred.  Every second in a call must be classified as either OK or
   Concealed.
</t><t>
   Normal playout of comfort noise or other silence concealment signal
   during periods of talker silence, if VAD is used, shall be counted as
   unimpaired seconds.
</t><t>
   If the measured value exceeds 0xFFFFFFFD, the value 0xFFFFFFFE SHOULD
   be reported to indicate an over-range measurement.  If the
   measurement is unavailable, the value 0xFFFFFFFF SHOULD be reported.
</t><t>
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Concealed Seconds: 32 bits
</t>
<t>
<list style='empty'>
<t>
   A count of the number of Concealed Seconds that have occurred.
</t><t>
   A Concealed Second is defined as a continuous period of 1000ms during
   which any frame loss or discard due to late arrival has occurred.
</t><t>
   Equivalently, a concealed second is one in which some Loss-type
   concealment (defined in Section 3.6) has occurred.  Buffer
   adjustment-type concealment SHALL not cause Concealed Seconds to be
   incremented, with the following exception.  An implementation MAY
   cause Concealed Seconds to be incremented for 'emergency' buffer
   adjustments made during talkspurts.
</t><t>
   For clarification, the count of Concealed Seconds MUST include the
   count of Severely Concealed Seconds.
</t><t>
   If the measured value exceeds 0xFFFFFFFD, the value 0xFFFFFFFE SHOULD
   be reported to indicate an over-range measurement.  If the
   measurement is unavailable, the value 0xFFFFFFFF SHOULD be reported.
   The duration, in milliseconds, of audio playout corresponding to
   Loss-type concealment.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Severely Concealed Seconds: 16 bits
</t>
<t>
<list style='empty'>
<t>
   A count of the number of Severely Concealed Seconds.
</t><t>
   A Severely Concealed Second is defined as a non-overlapping period of
   1000 ms during which the cumulative amount of time that has been
   subject to frame loss or discard due to late arrival, exceeds the SCS
   Threshold.
</t><t>
   If the measured value exceeds 0xFFFD, the value 0xFFFE SHOULD be
   reported to indicate an over-range measurement.  If the measurement
   is unavailable, the value 0xFFFF SHOULD be reported.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
RESERVED: 8 bits
</t>
<t>
<list style='empty'>
<t>
These bits are reserved. They SHOULD be set to zero by senders and MUST be ignored by receivers.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
SCS Threshold: 8 bits
</t>
<t>
<list style='empty'>
<t>
   The SCS Threshold defines the amount of time corresponding to lost or
   discarded frames that must occur within a one second period in order
   for the second to be classified as a Severely Concealed Second.  This
   is expressed in milliseconds and hence can represent a range of 0.1
   to 25.5 percent loss or discard.
</t>
<t>
   A default threshold of 50ms (5% effective frame loss per second) is
   suggested.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor='sdp' title="SDP Signaling">
<t>
   <xref target='RFC3611'/> defines the use of SDP (Session Description Protocol) 
   <xref target='RFC4566'/> for signaling the use of XR blocks.  XR blocks MAY be used without
   prior signaling.
</t>
<t>
   This section augments the SDP <xref target='RFC4566'/> attribute "rtcp-xr" defined in 
   <xref target='RFC3611'/> by providing an additional value of "xr-format" to signal the use of the report
   block defined in this document. 
</t><t>
The SDP attribute for the block has an additional optional paremeter, "thresh", used to supply a value for 
the SCS Threshold parameter. If this parameter is present, the RTP system receiving the SDP SHOULD use this value
for the current session. If the parameter is not present, the RTP system SHOULD use a locally configured value.
</t><t>
     rtcp-xr-attrib = "a=" "rtcp-xr" ":" [xr-format *(SP xr-format)] CRLF
</t><t>
     (defined in <xref target='RFC3611'/>)
</t><t>
     xr-format = xr-format / 
                xr-conc-sec-block
</t><t>
     xr-conc-sec-block   = "xr-concsec" ["=" thresh]
</t>
<figure>
<artwork>
     thresh      = 1*DIGIT          ; threshold for SCS (ms) 
     DIGIT          = %x30-39 
</artwork>
</figure>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>   
   This document creates a new block type within the IANA "RTCP XR Block
   Type Registry" called the Concealed Seconds Metrics Block, and a new
   parameter xr-concsec within the "RTCP XR SDP Parameters Registry".
</t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>
   It is believed that this proposed RTCP XR report block introduces no
   new security considerations beyond those described in <xref target='RFC3611'/>.  This block does not provide 
   per-packet statistics so the risk
   to confidentiality documented in Section 7, paragraph 3 of <xref target='RFC3611'/> does
   not apply.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Contributors">
<t>
   The authors gratefully acknowledge the comments and contributions
   made by Bruce Adams, Philip Arden, Amit Arora, Bob Biskner, Kevin Connor, Claus Dahm, Randy Ethier, 
   Roni Even, Jim Frauenthal, Albert Higashi, Tom Hock, 
   Shane Holthaus, Paul Jones, Rajesh Kumar, Keith Lantz, Mohamed Mostafa, Amy Pendleton, 
   Colin Perkins, Mike Ramalho, 
   Ravi Raviraj,
   Albrecht Schwarz, Tom Taylor, and Hideaki Yamada.
</t>
</section>
</middle>

    <back>
<references title='Normative References'>
                <reference anchor='MEASIDENT'>
			<front> 
				<title>RTCP XR Measurement Identifier Block</title> 
				<author initials='G.' surname='Hunt' fullname='Geoff Hunt'> 
					<organization>BT</organization> 
				</author> 
				<date month='August' year='2008' /> 
			</front> 
			<seriesInfo name='ID' value='draft-ietf-avt-rtcp-xr-measid-00' /> 	
			<format type='TXT' /> 
		</reference>
                <reference anchor='RFC3550'>
			<front> 
				<title>RTP: A Transport Protocol for Real-Time Applications</title> 
				<author initials='H.' surname='Schulzrinne' fullname='Henning Schulzrinne'> 
					<organization>Columbia University</organization> 
				</author> 
				<date month='July' year='2003' /> 
			</front> 
			<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3550' /> 	
			<format type='TXT' /> 
		</reference>
                <reference anchor='RFC3611'>
			<front> 
				<title>RTP Control Protocol Extended Reports (RTCP XR)</title> 
				<author initials='T. (Ed)' surname='Friedman' fullname='Timur Friedman'> 
					<organization> Paris 6 </organization> 
				</author> 
				<date month='November' year='2003' /> 
			</front> 
			<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3611' /> 	
			<format type='TXT' /> 
		</reference>
                <reference anchor='RFC2119'>
			<front> 
				<title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title> 
				<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'> 
					<organization>Harvard University</organization> 
				</author> 
				<date month='March' year='1997' /> 
			</front> 
			<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' /> 	
			<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' /> 	
			<format type='TXT' /> 
		</reference>
                <reference anchor='RFC4566'>
			<front> 
				<title>SDP: Session Description Protocol</title> 
				<author initials='M.' surname='Handley' fullname='Mark Handley'> 
					<organization>UCL</organization> 
				</author> 
				<date month='July' year='2006' /> 
			</front> 
			<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4566'/>
			<format type='TXT' /> 
		</reference>
</references>
        <references title='Informative References'>
		<reference anchor='PMOLFRAME'>
			<front>
                                <title>Framework for Performance Metric Development</title> 
                                <author initials='A.' surname='Clark' fullname='Alan Clark'> 
                                        <organization>Telchemy Incorporated</organization> 
				</author> 
                                <date month='July' year='2008' /> 
			</front> 
                        <seriesInfo name='ID' value='draft-ietf-pmol-metrics-framework-00' />  
			<format type='TXT' /> 
            </reference>
                <reference anchor='MONARCH'>
			<front> 
				<title>Monitoring Architectures for RTP</title> 
				<author initials='G.' surname='Hunt' fullname='Geoff Hunt'> 
					<organization>BT</organization> 
				</author> 
				<date month='August' year='2008' /> 
			</front> 
			<seriesInfo name='ID' value='draft-hunt-avt-monarch-01' /> 	
			<format type='TXT' /> 
		</reference>
	</references>
    </back>

</rfc>
