<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'><!ENTITY rfc2368 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2368.xml'><!ENTITY rfc2616 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml'><!ENTITY rfc2782 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2782.xml'><!ENTITY rfc2818 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2818.xml'><!ENTITY rfc3986 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'><!ENTITY rfc4791 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4791.xml'><!ENTITY rfc5397 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.5397.xml'><!ENTITY id2445bis PUBLIC '' 'bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-calsify-rfc2445bis.xml'>]> <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?><?rfc toc="yes"?><?rfc tocdepth="4"?><!-- default = 3 --><?rfc symrefs="yes"?><?rfc sortrefs="yes"?><?rfc compact="yes"?><?rfc subcompact="no"?><!-- <?rfc strict="yes"?> --><!-- <?rfc comments="yes"?> --><!-- <?rfc inline="yes"?> --><rfc ipr='trust200902' docName='draft-daboo-srv-caldav-00'>  <front>    <title abbrev="SRV for CalDAV">Use of SRV records for locating CalDAV calendar services</title>    <author initials="C." surname="Daboo" fullname="Cyrus Daboo">      <organization abbrev="Apple Inc.">        Apple Inc.       </organization>      <address>        <postal>          <street>            1 Infinite Loop           </street>          <city>            Cupertino           </city>          <region>            CA           </region>          <code> 95014 </code>           <country>            USA           </country>        </postal>        <email>          cyrus@daboo.name         </email>        <uri>          http://www.apple.com/         </uri>      </address>    </author>    <date />    <area>      Applications     </area>    <abstract>      <t>        This specification describes how SRV records can be used to locate a CalDAV based calendar service.      </t>    </abstract>  </front>  <middle>    <section title='Introduction'>      <t>        <xref target="RFC2782"/> defines a DNS-based service discovery protocol that has been widely adopted as a means of locating particular services within a local area network and beyond, using SRV RR records.      </t>      <t>        <xref target="RFC4791"/> defines the CalDAV Calendar Access protocol, based on HTTP <xref target="RFC2616"/>, for accessing calendar data stored on a server. CalDAV clients need to be able to discover appropriate CalDAV servers within their local area network and at other domains.      </t>      <t>        This specification defines new SRV service types for the CalDAV protocol, and gives an example of how clients can use this together with other protocol features to enable simple client configuration.       </t>    </section>    <section title='Conventions Used in This Document'>      <t>        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119' />.       </t>    </section>    <section title='CalDAV SRV service types'>		<t>			This specification adds two service types for use with SRV records:			<list style="hanging">				<t hangText="caldav:">					Identifies a CalDAV server that uses HTTP without transport layer security (<xref target="RFC2818"/>).				</t>				<t hangText="caldavs:">					Identifies a CalDAV server that uses HTTP with transport layer security (<xref target="RFC2818"/>).				</t>			</list>		</t>		<t>			Clients SHOULD honor "TTL", "Priority" and "Weight" values in the SRV records, as described by <xref target="RFC2782"/>.		</t>		<figure>			<preamble>				Example: service record for server without transport layer security			</preamble>			<artwork>    _caldav._tcp     SRV 0 1 80 calendar.example.com.			</artwork>		</figure>		<figure>			<preamble>				Example: service record for server with transport layer security			</preamble>			<artwork>    _caldavs._tcp    SRV 0 1 443 calendar.example.com.			</artwork>		</figure>    </section>	<section title='CalDAV Client "Bootstrapping"'>		<t>			This section describes a procedure that CalDAV clients MAY use to do their initial configuration based on minimal user input.		</t>		<t>			Minimal input from a user would consist of a calendar user address. A calendar user address is defined by <xref target="I-D.ietf-calsify-rfc2445bis">iCalendar</xref> to be a <xref target="RFC3986">URI</xref>. Provided a user identifier and a domain name can be extracted from the URI, this simple "bootstrap" configuration can be done.		</t>		<t>			If the calendar user address is a <xref target="RFC2368">"mailto:"</xref> URI, the "mailbox" portion of the URI is examined and the "local-part" and "domain" portions extracted. The "local-part" is used for the user identifier and the "domain" is used as the service domain.		</t>		<t>			If the calendar user address is an <xref target="RFC2616">"http:"</xref> or <xref target="RFC2818">"https:"</xref> URI, the "userinfo" and "host" portion of the URI is extracted. The "userinfo" is used for the user identifier and the "host" is used as the service domain.		</t>		<t>			Once the user identifier and service domain have been extracted, the following is done:			<list style='numbers'>				<t>An SRV lookup for _caldavs._tcp is done against the extracted service domain.</t>				<t>If no result is found for _caldavs._tcp, the client can try _caldav._tcp provided non-SSL connections are appropriate.</t>				<t>If an SRV record is returned the client extracts the server host name and port number</t>				<t>The client does an authenticated <xref target="RFC4791">"PROPFIND"</xref> request using the user identifier, host name and port number and a request URI of "/". The body of the request should include the <xref target='RFC5397'>DAV:current-user-principal</xref> property as one of the properties to return. Note that clients MUST properly handle HTTP redirect response statuses for the request.</t>				<t>If the DAV:current-user-principal property is returned, the client uses the value for the principal-URI of the calendar user. Given that quantity, it can do a "PROPFIND" on the principal-URI and discover additional properties for configuration.</t>				<t>If the DAV:current-user-principal property is not returned, then the client will need to request the principal-URI path from the user in order to continue with configuration.</t>			</list>		</t>	</section>    <section title='Security Considerations'>      <t>      	Clients that support transport layer security as defined by <xref target="RFC2818"/> SHOULD try the "caldavs" service first before trying the "caldav" service. If a user has explicitly requested a connection with transport layer security, the client MUST NOT use any service information returned for the "caldav" service.      </t>      <t>        A malicious attacker with access to the DNS server data can potentially cause clients to connect to any server chosen by the attacker. In the absence of a secure DNS option, clients SHOULD check that the host name returned in the SRV record matches the original service domain that was queried. If the host is not in the queried domain, clients SHOULD verify with the user that the SRV host name is suitable for use before executing any CalDAV requests against the host.      </t>    </section>    <section title='IANA Considerations'>      <t>        This document does not require any actions on the part of IANA.       </t>    </section>    <section title='Acknowledgments'>      <t>        This specification was suggested by discussion that took place within the Calendaring and Scheduling Consortium's CalDAV Technical Committee. The authors thank the participants of that group for their input. The "bootstrapping" process is based on diagrams developed by Wilfredo Sanchez.      </t>    </section>  </middle>  <back>    <references title='Normative References'>      &rfc2119;       &rfc2368;      &rfc2616;      &rfc2782;      &rfc2818;      &rfc3986;      &rfc4791;    </references>    <references title='Informative References'>      &rfc5397;      &id2445bis;    </references><!--<section title='Change History (to be removed prior to publication as an RFC)'><t>Changes from -00:</t><list style='numbers'><t></t></list></section>-->  </back></rfc>