<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc1034 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2181 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2181.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2606 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2606.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2782 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2782.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2821 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2821.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2822 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2822.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4033 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4034 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4686 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4686.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4871 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4871.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5016 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5016.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5234 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml'>
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-otis-dkim-adsp-03" ipr="full3978">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ADSP">DKIM Author Domain Signing Practices (ADSP)</title>
    <author fullname="Douglas Otis" initials="D." surname="Otis">
      <organization>Trend Micro, NSSG</organization>
      <address>
         <postal>
           <street>10101 N. De Anza Blvd</street>
           <city>Cupertino</city>
           <region>CA</region>
           <code>95014</code>
           <country>USA</country>
         </postal>
         <phone>+1.408.257-1500</phone>
         <email>doug_otis@trendmicro.com</email>
       </address>
    </author>

    <date day="23" month="June" year="2008"/>
    <area>Internet Area</area>
    <workgroup>DKIM Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>email, e-mail, rfc2822, rfc 2822, rfc822, rfc 822, rfc2821, rfc 2821, rfc821, rfc 821,
      rfc4871, rfc 4871, DKIM, domain keys, domainkeys, ADSP, ADSP, SSP, architecture, mta, user,
      delivery, smtp, submission, email, e-mail, smtp, Internet, mailfrom, mail from, author, return
      address, sender signing, signing practices, key domain, author key domain, author address,
      author domain</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM) as described in <xref target="RFC4871"/>, defines a
        domain-level authentication framework for email to permit verification of the source and
        contents of messages. This document specifies an adjunct mechanism to aid in assessing
        messages lacking valid DKIM signatures for domains used in the author's address. It defines
        a record that can advertise the extent that a domain signs outgoing mail publicly exchanged
        on SMTP port 25, as described in <xref target="RFC2821"/>, and how other hosts can access
        those records.</t>

      <t>Advertisements defined by this document may also increase DKIM signature expectations for
        messages received by Mail User Agents (MUAs) or for messages which might have been exchanged
        over protocols other than SMTP. In some circumstances, author domains may wish to have
        accommodations for protocol failures or for mixed public protocol messaging not made.</t>

      <t>In addition, DKIM's identity parameters related to the author address are decisive only
        when a corresponding DKIM key local-part template precludes an author address. DKIM in
        conjunction with ADSP is to provide methods for detecting the spoofing of known domains, but
        not for making assertions about the identity of the message author.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM) defines a mechanism by which email messages can be
        cryptographically signed, permitting a Key Domain to claim responsibility for the
        introduction of a message. Receiving hosts can verify the signature by querying the Key
        Domain to retrieve the appropriate public key, and thereby confirm a message has been
        attested to by a party in possession of the private key and in control of a portion of the
        Key Domain.</t>

      <t>However, the legacy of the Internet is such that not all messages will be signed or retain
        a valid signature, and that absence of a valid signature on a message is not an a priori
        indication of forgery. In fact, during early phases of deployment it is likely that most
        messages will remain unsigned. However, some domains might decide to sign all of their
        outgoing mail, for example, to better protect their brand name. It is desirable such domains
        be able to advertise that fact to other hosts. This is the premise of Author Domain Signing
        Practices (ADSP).</t>

      <t>Receiving hosts implementing this specification ensure greater safety by first inquiring
        into the validity of the SMTP domain before attempting a series of DKIM related validation
        transactions. The transactions pertaining to this document determine Author Domain Signing
        Practices advertised by the Author Domains. This determination is called ADSP Discovery.</t>

      <t>The detailed requirements for Author Domain Signing Practices are given in <xref
          target="RFC5016"/>. This document refers extensively to <xref target="RFC4871"/> and
        assumes the reader is familiar with it.</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Requirements Notation:"> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED",
            "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
            this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Language and Terminology">
      <section title="Terms Imported from DKIM Signatures Specification">
        <t>Some terminology used herein is derived directly from <xref target="RFC4871"/>.In several
          cases, references in that document to Sender have been changed to Author here, to
          emphasize the relationship to the Author address(es) in the From: header field described
          in <xref target="RFC2822"/>. Briefly, <list style="symbols">

            <t>A "Local-part" is the part of an address preceding the @ sign, as defined in <xref
                target="RFC2822"/> and used in <xref target="RFC4871"/>.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Valid Signature">
        <t>A <spanx style="verb">Valid Signature</spanx> is any message signature which correctly
          verifies using procedures described in section 6.1 of <xref target="RFC4871"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Valid Author Signature">
        <t>A <spanx style="verb">Valid Author Signature</spanx> is any message signature which
          correctly verifies using procedures described in section 6.1 of <xref target="RFC4871"/>,
          and where the local-part template, the "g" parameter in the key and the Key Domain,
          matches against the author address.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Key Domain">
        <t>The <spanx style="verb">Key Domain</spanx> is the domain listed in the <spanx
            style="verb">d=</spanx> tag of a Valid Signature.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Author Key Domain">
        <t>The <spanx style="verb">Author Key Domain</spanx> is the domain listed in the <spanx
            style="verb">d=</spanx> tag of a Valid Author Signature that is at or above the Author
          Domain. The Author Key Domain must match all of its domain components with that of the
          Author Domain. When a referenced Key contains a <spanx style="verb">t=s</spanx> tag and
          value, the Author Key Domain will contain the entire Author Domain for the signature to be
          valid.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Author Address">
        <t>An "Author Address" is an email address in the From header field of a message <xref
            target="RFC2822"/>. If the From header field contains multiple addresses, the message
          has multiple Author Addresses.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Author Domain">
        <t>An "Author Domain" is determined by the entire right-hand-side of the Author Address (the
          portion that is to the right of the "@", excluding the "@" itself).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Author Domain Signing Practices">
        <t>"Author Domain Signing Practices" (or just "practices") consist of a machine-readable
          record published at the <spanx style="verb">_adsp.</spanx> subdomain of the Author Domain.
          The ADSP record includes statements about outgoing mail practices for messages containing
          the Author Domain.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Operation Overview">
      <t>Domain owners can publish Author Domain Signing Practices via a distribution service, such
        as the Domain Name System; specific details related to the use of DNS are given in <xref
          target="dnsrep"/>.</t>

      <t>Hosts can obtain Author Domain Signing Practices of the domain(s) specified by the Author
        Domain as described in <xref target="checkproc"/>. If a message has multiple Author
        Addresses, ADSP Discovery SHOULD be performed independently. This standard will not cover
        the consolidation of combined ADSP Discovery results.</t>

      <section title="ADSP Discovery Results Usage">
        <t>A receiving host might obtain varying amounts of useful information through ADSP
          Discovery. Such as:<list style="symbols">

            <t>When a message has a Valid Author Signature, the ADSP Discovery result is of no
              benefit since the message is compliant with any possible ADSP assertion.</t>

            <t>When a message has a Valid Signature that is not also a Valid Author Signature, the
              ADSP Discovery result, in conjunction with the Key Domain of the Valid Signature, is
              directly relevant to message assessment.</t>

            <t>When a message is without a Valid Author Signature, the ADSP Discovery result at the
              Author Domain is directly relevant to message assessment.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="ADSP Discovery Results">
        <t>Author Domain Signing Practices Discovery at an Author Domain provide three possible
            results:<list style="symbols">

            <t>Messages containing the Author Domain advertise practices indicating they do not
              ensure messages are initially signed by an Author Key Domain.</t>

            <t>Messages containing the Author Domain advertise practices indicating they ensure
              messages are initially signed by an Author Key Domain.</t>

            <t>Messages containing the Author Domain advertise practices indicating they ensure
              messages are initially signed, and they recommend dismissing messages not signed by an
              Author Key Domain.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Detailed Description">
      <section title="DNS Representation" anchor="dnsrep">
        <t>Author Signing Practices records are published using the DNS TXT resource record type.</t>

        <t>NON-NORMATIVE DISCUSSION [to be removed before publication]: There has been considerable
          discussion on the DKIM WG mailing list regarding the relative advantages of TXT and a new
          resource record (RR) type. Read the archive for details.</t>

        <t>The RDATA for ADSP resource records is textual in format, with specific syntax and
          semantics relating to their role in describing Author Domain Signing Practices. The
          "Tag=Value List" syntax described in section 3.2 of <xref target="RFC4871"/> is used.
          Records not in compliance with that syntax or the syntax of individual tags described in
          Section 4.3 MUST be ignored, although they MAY cause the logging of warning messages via
          an appropriate system logging mechanism. If the RDATA contains multiple character strings,
          the strings are to be logically concatenated with no delimiters placed between the
          strings.</t>

        <t>The ADSP record for an Author Domain is published at a <spanx style="verb">_adsp.</spanx>
          subdomain directly below the Author Domain; e.g., the ADSP record for <spanx style="verb"
            >example.com</spanx> would be a TXT record that is published at <spanx style="verb"
            >_adsp.example.com</spanx>. A domain MUST NOT publish more than one ADSP record; the
          semantics of an ADSP transaction returning multiple ADSP records for a single domain are
          undefined. (Note that <spanx style="verb">example.com</spanx> and <spanx style="verb"
            >mail.example.com</spanx> are different domains.)</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Publication of ADSP Records">
        <t>Author Domain Signing Practices are intended to apply to all mail containing the Author
          Domain. As a defensive strategy against subdomain spoofing, ADSP records can be placed at
          domains that might appear to support SMTP.</t>

        <t>Wildcards within a domain publishing ADSP records will not pose a problem. This is
          discussed in more detail in <xref target="wildcards"/>.</t>

        <section title="Record Syntax" anchor="syntax">
          <t>ADSP records use the "tag=value" syntax described in section 3.2 of <xref
              target="RFC4871"/>. Terms used to describe signing practices employ a metaphor of a
            door to avoid connotations that might differ from definitions given this document.</t>

          <t>Tags used in ADSP records are described below. Unrecognized tags MUST be ignored. In
            the ABNF below, the WSP token is imported from <xref target="RFC2822"/>. The ALPHA and
            DIGIT tokens are imported from <xref target="RFC5234"/>. <vspace blankLines="100"/>
            <list style="hanging">

              <t hangText="dkim="> practices (plain-text; REQUIRED). Possible values are as follows:
                  <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="OPEN"> (Default) The Author Domain practice permits unsigned outbound
                    mail.</t>

                  <t hangText="CLOSED"> The Author Domain practice always initially signs messages
                    containing the Author Domain by an Author Key Domain.</t>

                  <t hangText="LOCKED"> The Author Domain practice always initially signs messages
                    containing the Author Domain by an Author Key Domain. Furthermore, when a
                    message is received without a valid Author Key Domain signature, receiving hosts
                    are requested to dismiss these messages.</t>
                </list>
                <figure>
                  <preamble>ABNF:</preamble>
                  <artwork name="" type="ABNF" height="" width="" align="center" xml:space="preserve">
      adsp-dkim-tag = %x64.6b.69.6d *WSP "=" 
          *WSP ("OPEN" / "CLOSED" / "LOCKED")
                  </artwork>
                </figure>
              </t>
              <t>Unrecognized flags MUST be ignored.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="checkproc" title="Author Signing Practices Discovery Procedure">
          <t>Hosts performing ADSP Discovery should exclude those being made for SMTP clients that
            have demonstrated a history of abuse. The transactions needed for ADSP Discovery or DKIM
            signature validation should follow confirmations the Author Domain might support SMTP.
            In addition, hosts may consider some domains exempt, such as Top Level Domains (TLDs)
            listed in <xref target="RFC2606"/>. TLDs listed in <xref target="RFC2606"/> do not
            represent a comprehensive list of TLDs that might be excluded from an SMTP domain
            validation process. Appending to a list of exempted domains may be required.</t>

          <t>For the purposes of this section, a "valid ADSP record" is one that is both
            syntactically and semantically correct; in particular, it matches the ABNF for a <spanx
              style="verb">tag-list</spanx> and includes a defined <spanx style="verb">dkim=</spanx>
              tag.<list style="symbols">
              <t><spanx>ADSP Discovery.</spanx> The host SHOULD query DNS for a TXT record
                corresponding to the Author Domain prefixed by <spanx style="verb">_adsp.</spanx>
                (note the trailing dot). The results returned by this operation would be the value
                of the "dkim" tag or a value of "MISSING" when none exist.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

              <t>NON-NORMATIVE DISCUSSION: Rather than placing ADSP records below the "_domainkey."
                prefix used by DKIM, "_adsp." prefixed to the Author Domain reduces the number of
                DNS entities needed when ADSP records are desired at every address record.
                Delegation of a domain at or below "_domainkey." and at "_adsp." may be required
                when consolidating control of DNS entries related to DKIM.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>When any of the DNS transactions involved in ADSP Discovery result in a temporary error
            condition, the algorithm terminates without returning a result; possible actions include
            queuing the message or returning an SMTP error indicating a temporary failure.</t>
          <t>
            <list style="empty">
              <t>NOTE: Within a DNS transaction, as defined by <xref target="RFC1034"/> section
                5.2.2 and <xref target="RFC4034"/> section 3, when a CNAME is returned, the alias
                name is to be processed as if it were the initial name. <xref target="RFC2181"/>
                section 10.3 makes an exception for Exchange host names returned by MX records. An
                Exchange host name must not return a CNAME.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>ADSP introduces the "_adsp" name into currently unregistered name space. Although domain
        names beginning with an underscore will not collide with host names, service names for <xref
          target="RFC2782"/> SRV records, and labels for TXT records defined by other protocols
        reference underscore prefixed names to designate specific use.</t>
      <t>INFORMATIVE NOTE [to be removed before publication]: If at the time of publication no
        registry has been established or planned for underscore prefixed names, this section may be
        removed.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations in the Author Domain Signing Practices mostly relate to attempts on
        the part of malicious senders to represent themselves as sending messages from the Author
        Domain for whom they are not authorized to use in their message, often in an attempt to
        defraud recipients of the message.</t>

      <t>Messages signed by keys having a local-part template in the <spanx style="verb">g=</spanx>
        tag restricting the range of valid local-parts are likely employed by systems that are
        beyond the direct control of the Author Key Domain. As a result, additional care should be
        taken when the local-part template does not match against the Author Address. Signatures
        where the <spanx style="verb">g=</spanx> local-part template does not match against the
        Author Addresses should not be considered as offering a valid signature.</t>

      <t>Additional security considerations regarding Author Domain Signing Practices are found in
          <xref target="RFC4686">the DKIM threat analysis</xref>.</t>

      <section title="ADSP Threat Model">
        <t>Email recipients often have a core set of content Author Domains they trust. Common
          examples include those of financial institutions with which they have an existing
          relationship and Internet web transaction sites with which they conduct business. DKIM
          validation and ADSP Discovery results will not provide any benefit unless receiving hosts
          act by either treating the message differently during delivery, or by providing some
          indicator to the end recipient. Such an email annotation system is out of scope for this
          specification.</t>

        <t>Bad actors often seek to exploit the name-recognition of a trusted Author Domain. This
          might be done with just spoofed display-names or with user local-parts placed above
          subdomains or cousin domains in the From: header field. This problem is made worse by
          popular MUAs that do not display actual email addresses. As a result, there is no
          empirical evidence as to what extent unauthorized use of a domain name contributes to
          recipient deception, or that its elimination will provide a significant effect. Being able
          to automate the accrual of behavioural feedback that ignores invalid identifiers better
          ensures systematic confidence is retained for trusted Author Key Domains.</t>

        <t>Nevertheless, training recipients to use automated folder placement could help reduce
          deceptions that utilize domain look-alike and subdomain based tactics. In addition,
          automated recognition facilitates optimized processing by receive-side message filtering
          engines that attempt to curb unauthorized uses of domain names, organizations' names and
          their logos elsewhere within the message. These attacks and their mitigation are outside
          the scope of this specification.</t>

        <t>The ADSP Discovery algorithm performs one DNS transactions per Author Domain. Since this
          transaction, as well as those needed to validate the DKIM signature, are driven by domain
          names in email message headers of possibly fraudulent email, receiving hosts attempting
          ADSP Discovery and DKIM validation can become participants in traffic multiplication
          attacks.</t>

        <t>These attacks often target servers consolidating and distributing behavioral information
          aimed at curbing bad-actor activities. An attack may not lead to a denial of service, but
          may dramatically impact the cost of offering the service. A reduction in those offering
          consolidated behavioral information places remaining providers in greater jeopardy of
          receiving a larger portion of the abuse being generated.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="DNS Attacks">
        <t>An attack might be waged against DNS infrastructure in an attempt to disable services
          dependent upon DNS. Such attacks could be made worse by receiving hosts employing ADSP
          Discovery and DKIM validations. For this reason, SMTP should eventually consider making MX
          records mandatory for public exchanges. The ADSP Discovery process is not expected to
          impact the likelihood of an attacker being successful at poisoning local DNS resolvers. In
          addition, such DNS security issues are addressed by <xref target="RFC4033">DNSSEC</xref>.</t>

        <t>A steady attack may not cause a denial of service, but can consume significant resources
          related to "in the cloud" consolidation and distribution of behavioral information. A
          typical strategy used by bad actors employing bot-nets is to rapidly transition from an
          active to dormant state. The duration of activity experienced by an SMTP server is often
          brief, and is then followed by a fairly long dormant period. This tactic proves
          challenging for defensive strategies instantiated by individual hosts. There may be tens
          of millions of bot-nets in the active state, while hundreds of millions appear dormant to
          SMTP servers.</t>

        <t>Consolidating and distributing behavioral information offers a defensive tactic that can
          minimize the effectiveness of a blitzkrieg or fast-flux tactic. Unfortunately, often part
          of a bad-actor's tactic is to inundate behavioral repositories with virtual identifiers.
          For DKIM, the signature's identity ("i=") parameter can be synthesized since it permits
          use of wildcarded domains, unlike the Key Domain ("d=") parameter or that of the ADSP
          record.</t>

        <t>Because ADSP operates within the framework of the legacy e-mail system, the default
          result in the absence of an ADSP record is for the Author Domain to be considered <spanx
            style="verb">OPEN</spanx> where not all messages are expected to be signed by a Author
          Key Domain. It is therefore important that the ADSP clients distinguish a DNS failure such
          as <spanx style="verb">SERVFAIL</spanx> from other DNS errors so that appropriate actions
          can be taken.</t>

        <t>It is likely DKIM and ADSP combined roles will be in preventing deception in conjunction
          with automated folder placements for those domains considered trustworthy. To ensure
          message reception remains viable for crucial systems when DNS fails, IP addresses of
          crucial SMTP clients should be white listed to allow ADSP and DKIM to be selectively
          bypassed during such events.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="DNS Wildcards" anchor="wildcards">
        <t>Wildcards within a domain, excluding wildcard MX records, that also publish ADSP records,
          do not pose a significant problem. While referencing SMTP related records will not provide
            <spanx style="verb">NXDOMAIN</spanx> results, SMTP discovery records such as MX or A
          records offer evidence of SMTP support. Whether AAAA records absent MX or A records are to
          be considered evidence of SMTP support has not withstood widespread use of AAAA only
          servers. <vspace blankLines="1"/>NON-NORMATIVE NOTE: Complete ADSP coverage for all
          subdomains of a domain remains possible. However, ADSP records would need to be published
          at every subdomain containing A records, in addition to subdomains containing MX records.
          When SMTP adopts an MX record mandate for public exchanges, ADSP records would then be
          required only at subdomains containing MX records. This strategy shelters domains not
          publishing MX records from the transactions associated with any number of Author Addresses
          and DKIM signatures per message.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="References - Normative"> &rfc1034; &rfc2119; &rfc2181;
      &rfc2606; &rfc2821; &rfc2822; &rfc4033; &rfc4034; &rfc4686;
      &rfc4871; &rfc5234; </references>
    <references title="References - Informative"> &rfc2782; &rfc5016; </references>

    <section title="Usage Examples">
      <t>These examples are intended to illustrate typical uses of ADSP. They are not intended to be
        exhaustive, nor to apply to every domain's or mail system's individual situation.</t>

      <t>Administrators are advised to consider the ways that mail processing can modify messages in
        a manner that will invalidate existing DKIM signatures, such as mailing lists, courtesy
        forwarders, and other paths that could add or modify headers, or modify the message body. In
        that case, if these modifications invalidate DKIM signatures, receiving hosts will consider
        the mail not to have an Author Key Domain signature, even though a Valid Author Signature
        was present when the mail was originally sent.</t>

      <section title="Single Location Domains">
        <t>A common mail system configuration handles all of a domain's users' incoming and outgoing
          mail through a single MTA or group of MTAs. In that case, the MTA(s) can be configured to
          sign outgoing mail with an Author Key Domain signature.</t>

        <t>In this situation it might be appropriate to publish a <spanx style="verb">CLOSED</spanx>
          ADSP record for the Author Domain, depending on whether users also send mail through other
          paths that do not apply an Author Key Domain signature. Such paths could include MTAs at
          hotels or hotspot networks used by travelling users, or web sites that provide "mail an
          article" features.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Bulk Mailing Domains">
        <t>Another common configuration uses a domain solely for bulk or broadcast mail, with no
          individual human users, again typically sending all the mail through a single MTA or group
          of MTAs that can apply an Author Key Domain signature. In this case, before publishing a
            <spanx style="verb">CLOSED</spanx> ADSP record, the domain's management should be
          confident that all of its outgoing mail will be sent through signing MTAs. Lacking
          individual users, the domain is unlikely to participate in mailing lists, but could still
          send mail through other paths that might invalidate signatures.</t>

        <t>Domain owners also often use specialist mailing providers to send their bulk mail. In
          that case, the mailing provider needs access to a suitable signing key in order to apply
          an Author Key Domain signature. One possible method would be for the Author Key Domain
          owner exchange keys with the mailing provider. Another would be for the Author Key Domain
          to delegate a subdomain below the <spanx style="verb">_domainkey.</spanx> label to the
          mailing provider. For example, <spanx style="verb">bigbank.example</spanx> might delegate
            <spanx style="verb">esp-00._domainkey.bigbank.example.com</spanx> to such a provider. In
          that case, the provider could generate keys and DKIM DNS records itself and provide Author
          Key Domain signatures.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Commonly Forged Transactional Messages">
        <t>In some cases, a domain might sign all its outgoing mail with an Author Key Domain
          signature, but prefers that receiving host systems dismiss mail without a valid Author Key
          Domain signature to avoid confusion with mail sent from fraudulent sources unable to apply
          an Author Key Domain signature. (This latter kind of mail is sometimes loosely called
          "forgeries".) In that case, it might be appropriate to publish a "LOCKED" ADSP record.
          Note that a domain SHOULD NOT publish a <spanx style="verb">LOCKED</spanx> ADSP record
          when it wishes to maximize the likelihood that its mail is delivered, since it could cause
          some fraction of the mail to become rejected or discarded.</t>
        <t>As a special case, if a domain sends no mail at all, it can safely publish a <spanx
            style="verb">LOCKED</spanx> ADSP record, since any mail with this Author Domain would be
          a forgery.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Third Party Senders">
        <t>Another common use case is for a third party to enter into an agreement whereby that
          third party will send bulk or other mail on behalf of a designated Author Domain, using
          that domain in the RFC2822 From: or other headers. Due to the many and varied complexities
          of such agreements, third party signing is not addressed in this specification.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document was based upon the draft-ietf-dkim-ssp-003. Dave Crocker, Frank Ellermann,
        and Charles Lindsey inputs were valuable, however inclusion of their names should not be
        misconstrued as an endorsement of this draft. This draft is an individual submission intended
        to illustrate a comprehensive solution that might help foreclose protracted debate when there
        is otherwise general agreement.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Changes in draft-otis-dkim-adsp-00">
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Conditioned Author Signing Practices Discovery Procedure SMTP verification step to be
            made only when an MX record had not been found.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Changes in draft-otis-dkim-adsp-01">
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Modified the Author Signing Practices Discovery Procedure to better conform with terms
            in RFC2821. In addition, a note now covers the issue of CNAMEs.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Changes in draft-otis-dkim-adsp-02">
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Modified the abstract to include the language recommended by Dave Crocker, clarified
            the relationship this document has with DKIM, SMTP and other protocols, and clarified
            the extent of DKIM identity parameter. The general language describing the intent was
            taken from the WG charter.</t>
          <t>Included non retention of a valid signature and offered an admonishment to first
            validate from domain in the introduction.</t>
          <t>Added a separate definition for Valid Author Signatures by including the requirement
            the local-part template much match against the author addresses.</t>
          <t>Made a few minor changes to the Author Key Domain definition.</t>
          <t>Included the phrase "related to the use of DNS" to the operation Overview as well as
            expanding upon the term ADSP Discovery in several places.</t>
          <t>Modified ADSP Usage to Discovery Results Usage. The information provided was
            reorganized from least to most useful.</t>
          <t>Modified the terms in ADSP Discovery Results to be consistent with advertised practices
            to align more closely with Dave Crocker's Abstract.</t>
          <t>The Record syntax now mentions the terms used are a metaphor for a door, and the terms
            modified to be in closer alignment with the abstract.</t>
          <t>The ADSP Discovery procedure now warns about unlimited application of this process, and
            suggests some domains may require exemption, and introduces the term MISSING when no
            ADSP record is discovered.</t>
          <t>The IANA considerations where shortened based upon the assumption a registry may not
            be established for underscore prefixed TXT records.</t>
          <t>Change the beginning of the security section to clarify the domain and not the author
            identity is assured by DKIM and ADSP.</t>
          <t>Changed the wording related to the key "g=" parameter to be more consistent throughout
            the document.</t>
          <t>Mention in the threat model annotation is required by out of scope.</t>
          <t>Modified the paragraph that describes exploitation of trust to be about the domain and
            not the author identity.</t>
          <t>Mention that the target of an attack is often directed to behavioral information
            services.</t>
          <t>Add paragraph describing the typical nature of bot-net behaviour, and how the DKIM "i="
            represents a significant venerability for the accrual of behavioral information.</t>
          <t>Add a sentence to highlight benefits using automatic folder placement.</t>
          <t>Expanded the DNS wildcard section to generally describe what might be involved when
            validating the domains support of SMTP.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
