<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY rfc0822 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0822.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc2195 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2195.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc2617 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2617.xml'> <!--HTTP Digest-->
	<!ENTITY rfc2831 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2831.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc4013 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4013.xml'> <!--SASLPrep-->
	<!ENTITY rfc4234 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4234.xml'> <!--ABNF-->
	<!ENTITY rfc4422 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4422.xml'>
]>
<!-- ?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ? -->

<rfc category="std"
     ipr="full3978"
     docName="draft-melnikov-digest-to-historic-00">
	<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

	<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
	<?rfc tocompact="no" ?>
	<?rfc tocindent="no" ?>
	<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
	<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
	<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
	<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
	<?rfc compact="yes"?>
	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
  <front>
    <title>Moving DIGEST-MD5 to Historic</title>
    
    <author initials='A.' surname="Melnikov" fullname='Alexey Melnikov'>
        <organization>Isode Limited</organization>
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>5 Castle Business Village</street>
            <street>36 Station Road</street>
            <city>Hampton</city>
            <region>Middlesex</region>
            <code>TW12 2BX</code>
            <country>UK</country>
          </postal>
          <email>Alexey.Melnikov@isode.com</email>
          <uri>http://www.melnikov.ca/</uri>
        </address>
    </author>
      
    <date year="2007"/>
    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>SASL Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>SASL</keyword>
    <keyword>DIGEST-MD5</keyword>
    <keyword>Digest</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
	  This memo documents problems with the DIGEST-MD5 Simple Authentication
      and Security Layer (SASL) mechanism, as specified in RFC 2831.  This
      document recommends DIGEST-MD5 to be marked as OBSOLETE in the
      IANA Registry of SASL mechanims and RFC 2831 to be moved to Historic
      status.
	  </t>
    </abstract>
    <note title="Note">
      <t>
        A revised version of this draft document will be submitted to the RFC
        editor as a Proposed Standard for the Internet Community.
        Discussion and suggestions for improvement are requested, and should
        be sent to ietf-sasl@imc.org.
      </t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Overview">

	<t><xref target="RFC2831"/> defined how HTTP Digest Authentication <xref target="RFC2617"/>
   	can be used as a Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) <xref target="RFC4422"/>
	mechanism for any protocol that has a SASL profile. It was intended both as an improvement
    over CRAM-MD5 <xref target="RFC2195"/> and as a convenient way to support a single
	authentication mechanism for web, mail, LDAP, and other protocols.
	While it can be argued that it was an improvement over CRAM-MD5, many implementors commented
	that the additional complexity of DIGEST-MD5 made it difficult to implement fully and securely.
	</t>

      <t>Below is an incomplete list of problems with DIGEST-MD5 mechanism as specified in RFC 2831:
        <list style="numbers">
		<t>The mechanism had too many options and modes. Some of them were not well described
		   and were not implemented. For example, DIGEST-MD5 allowed the "qop" directive
		   to contain multiple values. But it also allowed for multiple qop directives to be specified.
		   Handling of multiple options was not specified, which resulted in minor interoperability problems.
		   Some implementations amalgamated multiple qop values into one, while others treated multiple
		   qops as an error. Another example is use of empty authorization identity. In SASL an empty
		   authorization identity means that the client is willing to authorize as the authentication
		   identity. The document was not clear on whether the authzid must be omitted or
		   can be specified with the empty value to convey this.
		
		   The requirement for backward compatibility with HTTP Digest meant that
		   the situation was even worse. For example DIGEST-MD5 required all usernames/passwords which
		   can be entirely represented in ISO-8859-1 charset to be down converted from UTF-8 to
		   ISO-8859-1. Another example is use of quoted strings. Handling of characters that needed
		   escaping was not properly described and the DIGEST-MD5 document had no examples to
		   demonstrate correct behavior.</t>

		<t>The document used ABNF from RFC 822 <xref target="RFC0822"/>, which allowes for an extra construct
		   and allows for "implied folding whitespace" to be inserted in many places. Difference
		   from ABNF <xref target="RFC4234"/> was confusing for some implementors. As a result, many
		   implementations didn't allow for folding whitespaces in many places where they were allowed.</t>

		<t>The DIGEST-MD5 document uses a concept of "realm" to define a collection of accounts.
		   A DIGEST-MD5 server can support one or more realms.
		   The DIGEST-MD5 document didn't provide any guidance on how realms should be named, and,
		   more importantly, how they can be entered in User Interfaces (UIs).
		   As the result many DIGEST-MD5 clients had confusing UI, didn't allow users to enter a realm
		   and/or didn't allow users to pick one of the server supported realms.</t>
			
		<t>Use of username in the inner hash. The inner hash of DIGEST-MD5 is an MD5 hash of colon
		   separated username, realm and password. Implementations may chose to store inner hashes
		   instead of clear text passwords. While this has some useful properties, such as
		   compromise of an authentication database on one server does not automatically compromise
		   an authentication database with the same username and password on other servers,
		   in practice this was rarely done. Firstly, the inner hash is not compatible with
		   commonly deployed Unix password databases. Secondly, change of a username invalidates
		   the corresponding inner hash.</t>
			
		<t>Description of DES/3DES and RC4 security layers are inadequate to produce
		   independently-developed interoperable implementations. In the DES/3DES case
		   this was partly a problem with existing DES APIs.</t>

		<t>DIGEST-MD5 outer hash (the value of the "response" directive) didn't protect the whole
		   authentication exchange, which made the mechanism vulnerable to "man in the middle"
		   MITM attacks, such as modification of the list of supported qops or ciphers.</t>
			
		<t>The following features are missing from DIGEST-MD5, which make it insecure or insuitable
		   for use in protocols:
			<list style="letters">
				<t>Lack of channel bindings.</t>
				
				<t>Lack of hash agility. MD5 hash is suffuciently weak to make a brute force attack
				on DIGEST-MD5 easy with common hardware.</t>
				
				<t>Lack of SASLPrep <xref target="RFC4013"/> support. The original DIGEST-MD5 document predates SASLPrep
				and doesn't recommend any Unicode character normalization.</t>
			</list>
		</t>

        </list>
	</t>

	<t>Note that most of the problems listed above are already present in HTTP Digest
	authentication mechanism.</t>
		
	<t>Bacause DIGEST-MD5 mechanism was defined as an extensible mechanism, it would be possible
	to fix most of the problems listed above. However this would increase implementation complexity
	of an already complex mechanism even further, so the effort would not be worth the cost.
	In addition, an implementation of a "fixed" DIGEST-MD5 specification would likely either
	not interoperate with any existing implementation of RFC 2831, or would be vulnerable
	to various downgrade attacks.</t>

    <t>Note that despite DIGEST-MD5 seeing some deployment on the Internet, this specification
	   recommends obsoleting DIGEST-MD5 because DIGEST-MD5, as implemented, is not a
	   reasonable candidate for further standardization and should be deprecated in favor of
	   one or more new password-based mechanisms currently being designed.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security issues are discussed through out this document.</t>
      
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
		<t>IANA is requested to change the "Intended usage" of the DIGEST-MD5 mechanism
		   registration in the SASL mechanism registry to OBSOLETE. The SASL mechanism
		   registry is specified in <xref target="RFC4422"/> and is currently available at:
		</t>

		<figure>
			<artwork>
				<![CDATA[
   http://www.iana.org/assignments/sasl-mechanisms
    ]]>
			</artwork>
		</figure>
	</section>
    
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
		<t>The author gratefully acknowledges the feedback provided by Chris Newman, Simon Josefsson and Kurt Zeilenga.
		<cref>Various text was copied from other RFCs.</cref></t>
    </section>    
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
		&rfc2617;
		&rfc2831;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
		&rfc4422;
		&rfc2195;
		&rfc4234;
		&rfc4013;
		&rfc0822;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
