<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<!-- $Id$ -->
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-baset-tsvwg-tcp-over-udp-00" ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Abbreviated Title">TCP-over-UDP</title>

    <author fullname="Salman A. Baset" initials="S.A." surname="Baset">
      <organization>Columbia University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1214 Amsterdam Avenue</street>

          <city>New York</city>

          <region>NY</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>salman@cs.columbia.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Henning Schulzrinne" initials="H.G."
            surname="Schulzrinne">
      <organization>Columbia University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1214 Amsterdam Avenue</street>

          <city>New York</city>

          <region>NY</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>hgs@cs.columbia.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date month="May" year="2009" />

    <area>Transport Area</area>
    
    <workgroup>Transport Area Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>TCP UDP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>We present TCP-over-UDP (ToU), an instance of TCP on top of UDP. It provides
      exactly the same congestion control, flow control, reliability, and extension
      mechanisms as offered by TCP. It is intended for use in scenarios where applications
      running on two hosts may not be able to establish a direct TCP connection but are 
      able to exchange UDP packets.      
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>
        The applications running on hosts behind restrictive network address
        translators (NATs) may not be able to establish a direct TCP connection 
        with each other. Instead, these applications must establish a TCP 
        connection with a reachable host, which relays the traffic of the 
        application on the first host to the application on the second host 
        and vice versa. While this works, this is undesirable as it creates a 
        dependency on a reachable host. With certain NAT types, even though the 
        applications cannot 
        establish a direct TCP connection, they may be able to exchange UDP 
        traffic by using techniques such as 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice">ICE-UDP</xref>. Thus, using UDP is
        attractive for such applications as it removes the dependency on a
        reachable host. However, these applications have a requirement
        that the underlying transport be reliable. Further, these applications
        may run on machines with heterogeneous network connectivity, thereby
        requiring flow control. UDP does not provide reliability, congestion
        control, or flow control semantics. Therefore, these applications may
        either use TCP with a reachable host, or invent their own reliable,
        congestion control, and flow control transport protocol to establish
        a direct connection.
      </t>

      <t>
        We present TCP-over-UDP (ToU), a reliable, congestion control, and flow control 
        transport protocol on top of UDP. The idea is that TCP is a well-designed
        transport protocol that provides reliable, congestion control, and flow control
        mechanisms and these mechanisms must be reused as much as possible. Further, 
        a transport protocol that provides reliability and flow control mechanisms 
        must not be tied to a specific application and must be designed to provide modular
        functionality. To accomplish this, ToU almost uses the same header as TCP
        which allows to easily incorporate TCP's reliable and congestion 
        control algorithms as defined in 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-tcpm-rfc2581bis">TCP congestion control</xref> 
        document. In essence, ToU is not a new protocol 
        but merely an instance (or profile) of TCP over UDP minus the TCP checksum, 
        urgent data, and PSH flag.
      </t>

      <t>
        We think that our approach is attractive for several reasons. First,
        we are not proposing a new congestion control algorithm. Designing
        new congestion control algorithms is complex, and requires
        a large validation effort. Second, our approach takes advantage
        of existing user-level-TCP (such as <xref target="Daytona">Daytona</xref>
        and <xref target="MINET">MINET</xref>)
        or TCP-over-UDP implementations (such as <xref target="atou">atou</xref>). Finally,
        since we are replicating TCP semantics over UDP including
        TCP header, any TCP options such as 
        <xref target="RFC2018">selective acknowledgement option (SACK)</xref>
        or proposed TCP options such as <xref target="I-D.ietf-tcpm-tcp-auth-opt">TCP-Auth</xref> can be 
        easily incorporated in ToU without a new standardization effort.
      </t>

      <section title="Conventions">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>
          We use the terms such as congestion window (cwnd), initial window (IW),
          restart window (RW), receiver window (rwnd), and sender maximum segment 
          size (SMSS) as defined 
          in <xref target="I-D.ietf-tcpm-rfc2581bis">TCP congestion control</xref>
          document.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>


    <section title="Model of Operation">

      <!--
      <t>
        <xref target="tou_model">Figure 2</xref> describes how an application may use
        TCP-over-UDP. The ToU exists as a user-level library that provides a socket-like
        interface to the application. We refer to this interface as tou_socket_interface.
        This interface creates 'logical sockets' and the library maintains a mapping to the
        underlying OS-level sockets. Like OS-level sockets, the interface returns
        and operates on integer socket handles, which we refer to as tou_socket_handle.
        These handles are not related to the OS-level socket handles and cannot be
        used by the OS-level socket operations.
      </t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="tou_model">
        <artwork align="left">
          <![CDATA[
       +-----------------+
       |   Application   |
       +---|--------|----+
           |        | tou_socket_interface
        +--------------+  
        | TCP-over-UDP |
        |   library    |
        +--|--------|--+
           |        | OS sockets
        +--------------+
        |  Operating   |
        |    system    |
        +--|--------|--+
           |        |
             Network
          ]]>
        </artwork>

        <postamble>Using TCP-over-UDP</postamble>
      </figure>

      <t>
        This interface provides methods for opening and closing a ToU socket, listen
        for incoming connections and accept new connections, connect to a server,
        and send and receive data. An application that desires to send data reliably over 
        UDP uses the socket calls provided by this library to open a socket, 
        and connects to the server that listens for incoming connections on a specific port,
        and send the data.
      </t>
    -->
      <t>Below, we describe the key ToU operations.</t>
      
      <section title="Setup and tear down">
        <t>
          Like TCP, ToU uses a three-way handshake to establish a connection. Similarly, it
          follows TCP's semantics in tearing down the connection.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Connection tracking">
        <t>
          A key difference between TCP and UDP is that the former is connection-oriented whereas
          the later is not. This means that a ToU server must provide a way to keep track of existing
          connections. It does so through the source port and IP address of the UDP packet.
        </t>
      </section>
      
    </section>    
    

    <section title="Congestion Control, Flow Control, and Reliability">
      <t>ToU follows the TCP congestion control algorithms described in 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-tcpm-rfc2581bis">TCP congestion control</xref> document. 
        Thus, a ToU sender goes through the slow-start and congestion-avoidance phases. 
        A ToU sender
        starts with an initial window (IW) following the guidelines in 
        <xref target="RFC3390">RFC 3390</xref>. During slow start, a ToU sender 
        increments congestion window (cwnd) by at most SMSS bytes for each ACK 
        received that cumulatively acknowledges new data. It switches to congestion 
        avoidance when the congestion window (cwnd) exceeds slow start threshold 
        (ssthresh). A ToU receiver generates an acknowledgement following the
        guidelines in 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-tcpm-rfc2581bis">Section 4.2 of TCP congestion control</xref>
        document. It immediately generates an ACK when an out-of-order
        segment arrives. The ToU sender uses the fast retransmit algorithm
        to detect and repair losses, and fast recovery algorithm to govern the 
        transmission of new data until a non-duplicate ACK arrives. When ToU sender 
        has not received a segment for more than one retransmission timeout (RTO), cwnd 
        is reduced to the value of the restart window (RW) before transmission begins.
        The ToU sender may also use 
        <xref target="RFC2018">selective acknowledgement option (SACK)</xref> to improve
        loss recovery when multiple packets are lost from one window of data. Like
        TCP, it uses receiver window (rwnd) to achieve flow control.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Header Format">
      <t>
        ToU header is like a <xref target="RFC0793">TCP header</xref>
        except that it does not include source port, destination port,
        and checksum, as they are already included in the UDP header.        
        ToU header also does not include the 1-bit PSH flag and 1-bit 
        Urgent flag and bits corresponding to these flags are reserved
        in ToU header. Further, it also does not include the 16-bit Urgent Pointer.
        Between sequence number and acknowledgement number, we have 
        inserted a 32-bit magic cookie that allows to demultiplex ToU 
        with other UDP-based protocols such as <xref target="RFC5389">STUN</xref>.
        The rest of the fields in a ToU header have exactly the same meaning
        as those in a TCP header. The size of the fixed ToU header is 
        16 bytes, whereas the size of fixed TCP header is 20 bytes. The fixed 
        ToU header and UDP header have a cumulative size of 24 bytes, four 
        more than a fixed TCP header.
      </t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="tou_header">
        <artwork align="left">
          <![CDATA[   
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1

   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                        Sequence Number                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                         Magic Cookie                          |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                    Acknowledgment Number                      |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  Data |             |A| |R|S|F|                               |
   | Offset|  Reserved   |C|R|S|Y|I|            Window             |
   |       |             |K| |T|N|N|                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                    Options                    |    Padding    |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                             data                              |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            ]]>
        </artwork>

        <postamble>Header for TCP-over-UDP (ToU)</postamble>
      </figure>

      <t>
        Since ToU header fields are exactly the same as TCP, we have borrowed
        their descriptions from the <xref target="RFC0793">TCP RFC</xref>.
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Sequence Number (32-bits):"> Same as a TCP sequence number.</t>

          <t hangText="Magic Cookie (32-bits):">
            A fixed value of 0x7194B32E in network byte order to demultiplex ToU from 
            other application layer protocols.
          </t>

          <t hangText="Acknowledgement Number (32-bits):"> Same as a TCP acknowledgement number.</t>

          <t hangText="Data offset (4-bits):">
            The number of 32-bit words in ToU header. Like a TCP header,
            ToU header is an integral number of 32-bits long.
          </t>

          <t hangText="Reserved (7-bits):"> Reserved for future use. Must be zero.</t>

          <t hangText="Control Bits (4-bits):">5-bits from left to right. Unlike TCP, the 
           Urgent and PSH bits are excluded.</t>
          <t> ACK:  Acknowledgment field significant</t>
          <t> R:    Reserved in ToU. In the TCP header, it is used for the PSH function.</t>
          <t> RST:  Reset the connection</t>
          <t> SYN:  Synchronize sequence numbers</t>
          <t> FIN:  No more data from sender</t>

          <t hangText="Window (16-bits):">
            Same as the window in TCP header. The number of data octets beginning with 
            the one indicated in the acknowledgment field which the sender of this segment is 
            willing to accept.
          </t>

          <t hangText="Options:">Same as TCP options.</t>

          <t hangText="Padding:">
            Like TCP, the ToU header padding is used to ensure that the ToU header ends
            and data begins on a 32 bit boundary.  The padding is composed of zeros.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="ToU, TLS, and DTLS">
      <t>
        <xref target="RFC5246">Transport layer security (TLS)</xref> and
        <xref target="RFC4347">Datagram transport layer security (DTLS)</xref> 
        protocols provide
        privacy and data integrity between two communicating applications. TLS is
        layered on top of some reliable transport protocol such as TCP, whereas DTLS
        only assumes a datagram service. A question is what is the layering 
        relationship between ToU protocol, TLS, and DTLS. 
        <xref target="tou_tls">Figure 2</xref> shows four possible options. We
        think that Option-2 and Option-4 are not feasible since ToU layer must be
        made aware of the size of header which DTLS and TLS protocols may add.
        Since ToU provides the same reliable and inorder delivery semantics as 
        TCP, we prefer Option-1 over Option-3 in which TLS is layered on top of ToU.
      </t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="tou_tls">
        <artwork align="left">
          <![CDATA[   
   +-+-+-+-+   +-+-+-+-+   +-+-+-+-+   +-+-+-+-+
   |  TLS  |   |  ToU  |   |  DTLS |   |  ToU  |
   +-+-+-+-+   +-+-+-+-+   +-+-+-+-+   +-+-+-+-+
   |  ToU  |   |  TLS  |   |  ToU  |   |  DTLS |
   +-+-+-+-+   +-+-+-+-+   +-+-+-+-+   +-+-+-+-+
   |  UDP  |   |  UDP  |   |  UDP  |   |  UDP  |
   +-+-+-+-+   +-+-+-+-+   +-+-+-+-+   +-+-+-+-+
   Option-1    Option-2    Option-3    Option-4
            ]]>
        </artwork>

        <postamble>Layering options for ToU, TLS, DTLS</postamble>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Implementation Guidelines">
      <t>
        From the implementers perspective, the use of ToU should be as modular
        as possible. Once way to achieve this modularity is to implement ToU
        as a user-level library that provides socket-like function calls to
        the applications. The library may have its own thread of execution and
        can be instantiated at the start of the program. The library implements the
        reliable, inorder, congestion control, and flow control semantics of TCP.
        Applications can interact with the ToU library through socket-like function calls.
      </t>
      
    </section>
    
    <section title="Design Alternatives">
      <t>
        ToU is strictly meant for scenarios where end-points desire to establish a TCP
        connection but are unable to do so due to the presence of NATs and firewalls.
        Below, we briefly discuss the design alternatives.
      </t>
      
      
      <section title="Simplified TCP">
        <t>It may be argued that TCP semantics are too complicated and it might be easier
        to define a protocol that adds retransmission of individual UDP packets, and
        ACK mechanisms, and sequencing layer. However, unless one is content with 
        stop-and-wait congestion control (and roughly modem data rates), it is necessary 
        for a transport protocol to have AIMD or rate-based congestion control (TFRC). 
        As discussed in <xref target="tfrc"></xref>, rate-based congestion control 
        is not suitable for mid-sized transfers and is not any simpler than AIMD.        
        Further, since hosts may have heterogeneous network connectivity, a transport protocol
        needs to provide flow control. Moreover, it may not be easy to validate a new
        transport protocol that only provides selective TCP semantics. </t>
        <!--Conversely, it 
        is relatively easy to validate ToU behavior by running TCP and ToU together on the same 
        simulator and lots of implementers already understand TCP.-->
      </section>

      <section title="TCP-like mechanism within an application layer protocol">
        <t>
          In this approach, key TCP mechanims such as reliability, congestion control, 
          and flow control are designed as part of the application layer protocol. This approach 
          has several disadvantages. First, every application layer protocol that is unable 
          to establish TCP connections in the presence of NAT and firewalls but may 
          use UDP will need to invent its own reliable, congestion control and flow 
          control transport protocol. Second, it is non-trivial to get the first implementations 
          of a conceptually new protocol right. Third, any new transport protocol, even if 
          it is specified within an application layer protocol must undergo a large 
          validation effort. Finally, most long-term successful protocols are those 
          that provide modular functionality, and not extremely narrowly-tailored protocols.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Tunneling">
        <t>Another design option is to provide a VPN-like tunneling option for sending 
        and receiving TCP packets over UDP. This is conceivable as follows. An application 
        uses the regular TCP socket calls which make use of the TCP stack. Just before the 
        transmission of the packet, a module or a virtual ethernet driver intercepts
        the packet, and sends the TCP packet along with its payload over UDP. Similarly,
        when a packet is received over UDP, the virtual ethernet driver checks if it is an
        encapsulated TCP packet, and if yes, passes it to the appropriate kernel level TCP handler.        
        </t>

        <t>This approach is not desirable for several reasons. First, it creates a 
        dependency on a kernel-level module or a virtual ethernet driver that must 
        capture TCP packets before transmission and immediately upon reception. Kernel-level 
        modules or virtual ethernet drivers require root access to a machine. Peer-to-peer 
        applications are user space applications are expected to be the main users of ToU. 
        It is unrealistic to create a dependency 
        between these user space applications and a kernel level module. Second, sending
        a full-sized TCP segment over UDP may cause fragmentation. Lastly, other 
        UDP based protocols such as STUN may need to be 
        run on the same port as the tunneling port which can complicate the 
        disambiguation of these protocols from the tunneled TCP.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="TFRC" anchor="tfrc">
        <t>
          <xref target="RFC5348">TFRC</xref> is a congestion control mechanism (not
          a protocol) that is designed for long-lived media streams. Its main benefit
          is of smoothing rates to these media streams. It does not
          provide any packet formats, reliability, or flow control. It's congestion
          control mechanism is not suited for exchanging data objects that range from a 
          few dozen to a few hundred packets. The reason is that TFRC is based on 
          estimating loss rates within 8 loss intervals. With a loss rate of 
          1%, this translates, very roughly, into 800 packets or roughly 800 kB, 
          before a reliable estimate of a better (higher) rate is computed. Further, 
          its main  benefit, smoothing rates, is of no importance to applications desiring
          to replicate TCP functionality over UDP.          
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="SCTP">
        <t>
          <xref target="RFC4960">SCTP</xref> is significantly more complicated than 
          TCP in its implementation and
          its performance is generally the same, except in circumstances involving
          head-of-line blocking. Further, SCTP will have trouble getting traction in 
          the consumer and enterprise Internet space unless it (also) runs over UDP, 
          as there seem to be few NATs that know how to handle SCTP and thus it is 
          effectively unusable by a fair fraction of the Internet user population.
        </t>        
      </section>
      
    </section>
    
<!--    
    <section title="ToU Socket API">
      <t>We define a socket API for TCP-over-UDP whose semantics exactly mimic 
      the TCP socket API.</t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="int tou_socket()" />
          <t>Parameters: int domain, int type, int protocol</t>
          <t>
            Creates a ToU socket, allocates the send and receive buffers,
            and returns an integer handle (tou_socket_handle) to the created ToU socket.
            The method internally creates a UDP socket and stores a mapping between
            the tou_socket_handle and UDP socket. The type parameter is SOCK_STREAM.
          </t>

          <t hangText="int tou_bind()" />
          <t>Parameters: int socketfd, const struct sockaddr *address, socklen_t address_len</t>
          <t>Assigns a local socket address to a ToU socket identified by the socket descriptor. </t>

          <t hangText="int tou_listen()" />
            <t>Parameters: int socketfd, int backlog</t>
            <t>
              Marks a ToU socket specified by the socketfd argument, as ready to accept new connections.
              The backlog parameter provides a hint to the ToU library to limit the number
              of outstanding connections in the ToU socket's queue.
            </t>

          <t hangText="int tou_accept()" />
            <t>Parameters: int socketfd, struct sockaddr *restrict address, socklen_t *restrict address_len</t>
            <t>
              Extracts the first connection on the queue for ToU socket connections, creates a ToU socket,
              and returns the handle to the newly created ToU socket to the application. At the 
              system level, no new sockets are created.
            </t>

          <t hangText="int tou_accept()" />
            <t>Parameters: int socketfd, const struct sockaddr *address, socklen_t address_len</t>
            <t>Attempts to make a connection on a ToU socket.</t>

          <t hangText="int tou_select()" />
            <t>
              Parameters: int nfds, fd_set *restrict readfds, fd_set *restrict writefds, 
              fd_set *restrict errorfds, struct timeval *restrict timeout
            </t>
            <t>Examines the file descriptors given by readfds, writefds, and errorfds parameters
            to determine whether they are ready for reading, writing, or have an error condition.</t>

          <t hangText="int tou_close()" />
            <t>Parameters: int socketfd</t>
            <t>Closes the socket indicated by socketfd descriptor. Any system level
            UDP sockets associated with this logical socket descriptor are also closed.</t>

          <t hangText="int tou_get_sys_sock()" />
            <t>Parameters: int socketfd</t>
            <t>Returns the system level socket descriptor associated with the socketfd.</t>

          <t hangText="int tou_setsockopt()" />
            <t>Parameters: int socketfd, int level, int optname, const void *optval, socklen_t optlen</t>
            <t>Set options associated with the socket.</t>


          <t hangText="int tou_getsockopt()" />
            <t>Parameters: int socketfd, int level, int optname, void *optval, socklen_t *optlen</t>
            <t>Retrieve options associated with the socket.</t>
          
        </list>
      </t>
      
    </section>
-->
    
    <!-- This PI places the pagebreak correctly (before the section title) in the text output. -->

    <?rfc needLines="8" ?>

<!--
    <section title="Implementation Considerations">
      <t></t>
    </section>
-->

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The draft incorporates comments from the discussion on P2PSIP mailing list.</t>
    </section>


    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>TBD.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>ToU is subject to the same security considerations as TCP.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
   
    <references title="Normative References">

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0793"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1122"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2018"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3390"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4347"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4960"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5348"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"?>      
      
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tcpm-rfc2581bis"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tcpm-tcp-auth-opt"?>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice"?>
      
      <reference anchor="Daytona"
                 target="http://nms.lcs.mit.edu/~kandula/data/daytona.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Daytona : A User-Level TCP Stack</title>

          <author initials="P." surname="Pradhan">  
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Kandula">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="W." surname="Xu">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="A." surname="Sheikh">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="E." surname="Nahum">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2004" />
        </front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="MINET"
                 target="http://cs.northwestern.edu/~pdinda/minet/NWU-CS-02-08.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>The Minet TCP/IP Stack</title>

          <author initials="P." surname="Dinda">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2002" />
        </front>
      </reference>
      

      <reference anchor="atou"
                       target="http://www.csm.ornl.gov/~dunigan/atou.ps">
        <front>
          <title>A TCP-over-UDP Test Harness</title>

          <author initials="T." surname="Dunigan">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="F." surname="Fowler">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2002" />
        </front>
      </reference>
      
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
