<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<!ENTITY RFC3484  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3484.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5220  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5220.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5221  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5221.xml'>
<!ENTITY SOLUTIONS PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6man-addr-select-sol.xml'>
<!ENTITY REVISE PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.arifumi-6man-rfc3484-revise.xml'>
<!ENTITY DHCOPT PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.fujisaki-dhc-addr-select-opt.xml'>



<rfc ipr="full3978" category="info" docName="draft-chown-addr-select-considerations-00">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="Address Selection Considerations">Considerations for IPv6 Address Selection Policy Changes </title>
		<author fullname="Tim Chown" initials="T.J." role="editor" surname="Chown">
			<organization> University of Southampton </organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street/>
					<city> Southampton </city>
					<code> SO17 1BJ </code>
					<region> Hampshire </region>
					<country> United Kingdom </country>
				</postal>
				<email> tjc@ecs.soton.ac.uk </email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date month="October" year="2008"/>
		<area>Operations</area>
		<workgroup>IPv6 Operations</workgroup>

		<abstract>
<t>
Through operational experience of IPv6 Default Address Selection (RFC3484)
<xref target="RFC3484" />
implementations, it appears that a requirement has arisen for hosts and 
networks to be able to have their policies for address selection updated.
This text discusses considerations for such policy changes, e.g. 
examples of cases where a change of policy is required, and the
likely frequency of such policy changes.   This text also includes some
discussion on the need to also update RFC3484, where default policies
are currently defined.
</t>
		</abstract>
<!--
		<note title="Requirements Language">
			<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
&quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;,
&quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be
interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
</t>
		</note>
-->
	</front>

	<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

	<t>
There have been various operational issues observed (RFC5220)
<xref target="RFC5220" />
with Default Address
Selection for IPv6 (RFC3484)
<xref target="RFC3484" />.   As as a result, there has been some demand
for the capability for systems and networks to be able to have their
policy tables, and potentially the rules described in RFC3484, 
modified.
	</t>

</section>

<section title="Issues to Consider">
	<t>
There are a number of aspects to consider in the context of such address
selection policy updates.   
	</t>
	<t>
First is the frequency for which such updates
are likely to be required; this will be determined largely from identifying
the scenarios in which policy changes will be required.  This may include
overriding default system policies on startup, as well as changes while
a system is running.
	</t>
	<t>
Second, by understanding how dynamic the policy update mechanism needs to be
we should be better placed to determine what types of update approaches best
meet those needs.   There may be other considerations of course, e.g. 
whether the systems are in managed or unmanaged environments, and whether
the solution should be proactive or automated, as discussed in
<xref target="I-D.ietf-6man-addr-select-sol" />.
	</t>
	<t>
Third, if we assume some policy update mechanism is defined we should 
consider how hosts and systems may become aware that a policy change has 
happened, and how policy can be disseminated in a timely fashion.
Thus we need to understand what kind of technical/concrete event(s) can be 
used for triggering the policy table update mechanism, e.g. address 
re-obtainment, address lifetime expiration, or perhaps policy lifetime 
expiration.
	</t>
	<t>
Finally, we should assess whether these
update solutions require or need 3484 to be updated.  In some
instances, we might envision solutions that simply use RFC3484 as 
guidelines and provide sufficient controls to address the current limitations 
in the RFC.   However, as noted in RFC5220
<xref target="RFC5220" />, not all the operational issues observed to
date can be remedied by updating RFC3484 alone.
Thus there may be further work required elsewhere, which may of course
still include an 
RFC3484 update, to address all the issues detailed in RFC5220, as 
described in
<xref target="I-D.arifumi-6man-rfc3484-revise" />).
	</t>
</section>

<section title="Other Related Work">
	<t>
We note that there is some existing work in defining Requirements for
Address Selection Machanisms
<xref target="RFC5221" />,
and some initial work has been done in the solution space (for DHCP)
<xref target="I-D.fujisaki-dhc-addr-select-opt" />, but these are not
discussed here.   While RFC5221 does assume that a dynamic policy update
mechanism of some form is available, this draft is currently aimed at
understanding the scenarios and triggers for policy changes, to better
inform future solution discussions.
	</t>

</section>

<section title="Drivers for Policy Changes">

	<t>
If we wish to determine how frequent address selection policy changes are likely
to be, we need to understand why such policies might need to be
changed, for particular sites or networks.
	</t>
	<t>
One obvious source of drivers for policy change
is RFC5220, in which operational issues with the existing policies described
in RFC3484 are listed.   Each subsection of this document gives a reason
why the existing rules or policy tables in RFC3484 may not be sufficient
in certain cases.
There have been some significant changes to IPv6 since RFC3484 was drafted
which have impacted the RFC, e.g.
the introduction of Unique Local Addresses (ULAs), and concerns about
longest prefix matching affecting (DNS) round robin load balancing.
	</t>
	<t>
In summary, the issues raised in RFC5220 were:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Multiple Routers on a Single Interface</t>
<t>Ingress Filtering</t>
<t>Problem Half-Closed Network Problem (*)</t>
<t>Combined Use of Global and ULA (*)</t>
<t>Site Renumbering (*)</t>
<t>Multicast Source Address Selection (*)</t>
<t>Temporary Address Selection</t>
<t>IPv4 or IPv6 Prioritization (*)</t>
<t>ULA and IPv4 Dual-Stack Environment (*)</t>
<t>ULA or Global Prioritization (*)</t>
</list>
	</t>
	<t>
The authors of RFC5220 noted which of these issues can be solved by changes to
the RFC3484 policy table, marked (*) above, and which cannot.  It is interesting
to note that issues largely related to internal networking and 
(administrative) policy decisions can be handled this way.
	</t>

	<section title="Internal vs External Tiggers">
	<t>
When considering drivers or triggers that may lead to a requirement for
the policy to change, we can consider those external to a site or network
and those internal.     In the case of the first two examples above, 
a dynamic policy table update may be required by externally driven
routing changes, assuming the site uses a dynamic routing protocol
intra-site and the routing protocol is configured to reflect changes
of extra-site routing topology.
In such a case, the policy table of hosts may needs to be updated
according to the routing policy.   
	</t>
	<t>
It should be noted that we have other mechanims for dynamic routing
topology change, for example deprecating one of the advertised prefixes,
perhaps when one of the upstream links has a problems.
	</t>
	<t>
Other examples of external factors include a new transition mechanism
being defined (e.g. as with the emergence of Teredo using 2001::/32
as assigned by IANA) and its inclusion being required in the policy table, 
or a site renumbering event that could be triggered by an upstream 
provider's actions.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Administratively Triggered Changes">
	<t>
The other examples above are, in the general case, where the
site administrator chooses to change a local policy and in doing so 
triggers the need for policy table updates.   Some of these
changes one might assume to be set once, and to change rarely, e.g.:
	</t>
	<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t> Setting priority use of IPv6 over IPv4 (or vice versa).</t>
<t> Setting priority use of ULAs over globals (or vice versa).</t>
<t> Setting priority use of privacy addresses over globals (or vice versa).</t>
<t> An internal network renumbering occurs, perhaps due to a site expanding.</t>
<t> Disabling longest-prefix match functions to facilitate round-robin load
balancing.</t>
</list>
	</t>
	<t>
However it may be the case that different parts of a site have different
policies, or policies are changed in a rolling fashion across a site over
time as IPv6 or ULAs are introduced (for example).
	</t>
	<t>
Other administrative changes may occur more frequently, e.g.:
	</t>
	<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t> Routing tables and forwarding tables change dynamically.</t>
<t> A different provider (link) is preferred for a given destination.</t>
</list>
	</t>
	<t>
It's possible that provider links may vary on a daily basis, or by time
of day.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Start-up vs Running Changes">
	<t>
When a host starts up it may be configured with the default RFC3484 policies.
At this stage a number of addresses may be configured on a number of interfaces
on the host.   At this time it may be desirable for the host to be able
to receive the site-specific policy updates as a start-up override from
the RFC3484 defaults.
	</t>
	<t>
Other policy changes may later be required while the host is running.   Ideally
the same protocol should be used for the start-up and running state updates.
	</t>
	</section>

</section>

<section title="On Address Changes and Obtaining Policy">
	<t>
When a policy table change is made, the change of policy needs to
be propogated to the hosts in a network.
From the host perspective, one could assume that when a host changes
an address, it should re-obtain the selection policy.
If the policy is distributed via the same mechanism that informs a
host of a change of address(es), the application of the policy should
be synchronised sufficiently with the address change.   However, 
not all hosts may receive the update information at the same time, e.g.
dependent on DHCP lease timers.
	</t>
	<t>
Where hosts use DHCPv6 for address information, in the absence of some
form of Reconfigure message, a host may see a delay in policy changes
being notified.   It should also be noted of course that 
not all policy changes are tied to a host changing
one or more addresses.   One possible tool to help here is the DHCPv6
Lifetime Option (RFC4242), which was originally introduced to assist
with network renumbering events.
	</t>
	<t>
Thus there is a general issue of timely and synchronised dissemination
of new policy.
	</t>
</section>

<section title="How Dynamic?">
	<t>
The discussion above suggests that many of the potential triggers for
policy table changes are 'one-off' in nature, i.e. a site makes a one-time
policy change.
	</t>
	<t>
However, there are also some cases where updates may be required to be more frequent, e.g. the gradual introduction of new policy across a large
site, and cases where preferred links for certain destinations change frequently
over time (possibly daily).   It is not clear how common these cases are,
and thus further input is welcomed here.
	</t>
</section>

<section title="On RFC3484 Default Policies">

	<t>
RFC3484 includes text about mechanisms for changing policy, having 'policy
hooks' and having a configurable policy table.   The implication is
that defaults can be changed, and the text gives examples of this in 
Section 10.   That said, it remains the case that
some operational issues with RFC3484 are not just related to the table,
but on rules themselves, e.g. longest prefix match (affecting DNS round
robin as described in <xref target="RFC5220" />).  
	</t>
	<t>
We should note though that
the word 'default' has to be defined here, i.e. what
is the scope of this 'default'. It seems it is 'system wide'
but first it just moves the issue to the 'system' definition
and second larger or smaller granularities make sense (for
instance 'link wide' and 'user wide').   Whether and how this can
be considered in an open question.
	</t>
	<t>
It certainly seems the case that the issues raised in RFC5220, and
discussed in <xref target="I-D.arifumi-6man-rfc3484-revise" /> mean
that an update of RFC3484 is required, if only because some of the issues 
(as highlighted earlier) cannot be addressed by updating the policy
table alone.
	</t>
</section>

<section title="Considerations for Solutions">

	<t>
In this first draft we avoid any discussion of impact on or implications
for solutions.   Except that it would be highly preferable if the start-up
and running state solutions used the same protocol.
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
	<t>
There are no extra Security consideration for this document.
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
	<t>
There are no extra IANA consideration for this document.
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
	<t>
The design team working on this draft is: 
Marcelo Bagnulo Braun,
Marc Blanchet,
Tim Chown,
Francis Dupont,
Tim Enos,
TJ Evans,
Brian Haberman,
Tony Hain,
Ruri Hiromi,
Suresh Krishnan,
Arifumi Matsumoto,
Janos Mohacsi,
Sebastien Roy,
Teemu Savolainen,
Fujisaki Tomohiro,
and
John Zhao.
	</t>
</section>


</middle>
<back>

<references title="Informative References">

	&RFC3484;
	&RFC5220;
	&RFC5221;
	&SOLUTIONS;
	&DHCOPT;
	&REVISE;

</references>

</back>
</rfc>
