<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="full3978" docName="draft-mase-autoconf-prefix-framework-00">
 
<front>
    <title abbrev="Prefix Distribution Framework">
      Prefix Distribution Framework for Connected MANETs 
    </title>
 
    <author initials="K.M." surname="Mase" fullname="Kenichi Mase">
      <organization>
	Graduate School of Science and Technology, Niigata University
      </organization>
      <address>
	<street>8050 Ikarashi2</street>
	<city>Niigata-shi, Niigata</city>
	<code>950-2181</code>
	<country>Japan</country>
	<phone>+81 25 262 7446</phone>
	<email>mase@ie.niigata-u.ac.jp</email>
	<uri>http://www.net.ie.niigata-u.ac.jp/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="K.A." surname="Akima" fullname="Kazuki Akima">
      <organization>
	Graduate School of Science and Technology, Niigata University
      </organization>
      <address>
	<street>8050 Ikarashi2</street>
	<city>Niigata-shi, Niigata</city>
	<code>950-2181</code>
	<country>Japan</country>
	<email>kakima@net.ie.niigata-u.ac.jp</email>
	<uri>http://www.net.ie.niigata-u.ac.jp/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
   
    <date day='9' month='November' year='2007'/>
    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>MANET Autoconfiguration (AUTOCONF)</workgroup>
    <keyword>I-D</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet Draft</keyword>
    <abstract></abstract>
</front>

<middle>
 
<section anchor='introduction' title='Introduction'>
<t>
Connected MANETs have connectivity to one or more external networks, 
typically the Internet, through one or more MNBR (MANET Border Router, 
see [2]). MANET routers may generate traffic destined to remote hosts 
across these external networks. This document gives a framework of 
autoconfiguration solutions for connected MANETs.	
</t>
<t>
 The keywords "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
 "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
 document are to be interpreted as described in [1].
</t>
</section>




   
<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
<t>
This document uses the MANET architecture and autoconfiguration problem state terminology defined in [2] 
and [3], as well as the following terms:
</t>

<t>
Edge router (ER): The router residing in the external network that maintains links with 
MANET nodes serving as the gateway between the MANET and external network.
</t>

<t>
Mobility Anchor Point (MAP): A physical or virtual entity to generate topologically correct prefix 
for Connected MANETs. 
</t>
</section>





<section anchor="Problem Statement" title="Problem Statement">
<t>
Problem statement for Connected MANETs is given in [3].
 We describe more specific problems to consider in this document as follows:
</t>

<t>
Suppose a MANET has one or more MNBRs and a MANET router needs to communicate with a remote 
host in the Internet via one of MNBRs (Fig. 1). To do this, the MANET router selects one of 
the MNBRs and configures a global address for each of its MANET interface using a prefix, 
that is advertised through the selected MNBR. The MANET router then starts to communicate 
with the remote host using the configured global address. When the selected MNBR leaves the 
MANET or it is no longer appropriate as the MNBR for the communication, the MANET router 
needs to discover a new MNBR to continue communication. If this new MNBR advertises a different 
prefix, the MANET router configures a new global address using the new prefix, resulting in 
address change. The address change also occurs, when a MANET has multiple MNBRs and a MANET 
router re-selects a better MNBR in terms of communication efficiency and a different prefix 
is advertised thorough this new MNBR.
</t>

<artwork>
        INTERNET                      MANET                                 
    +---------------+        +----------------------+
    |               |   a    |          a           |
    |          +--+ | -----&gt; |  +---+ -----&gt;  +---+ |     
    |   +-----&gt;|  |------------&gt;|   | -------&gt;|   | | axxx  
    |   |      +--+ |        |  +---+ ---+    +---+ |
    |   |      ER1  |        |  MNBR1    | a   MNR  |  
    |   |           |        |           +---&gt;      |  
    |   |           |        |                      |
    | +---+         |        |             b        |
    | |CN |         |        |           +---&gt;      |
    | +---+         |        |           |          |
    |          +--+ |        |  +---+ ---+          |
    |          |  | |        |  |   |               |
    |          +--+ | -----&gt; |  +---+ ---+          |
    |          ER2  |   b    |  MNBR2    |          |
    |               |        |           +---&gt;      |
    +---------------+        +----------------------+
      MNR  : MANET Router
      MNBR : MANET Border Router
      ER   : ISP Edge Router
        
       Fig. 1: The example of communication with a remote host
       in the Internet via one of MNBRs.
</artwork>

<t>
Such address change is harmful in two aspects. Firstly, any application sessions established 
between the MANET router in question and the corresponding remote hosts in the Internet are 
obliged to be terminated, when address change occurs, and new application sessions need to be 
re-established between them to continue communications. Secondly, route entries based on old 
addresses in MANET routers become obsolete and route entry re-establishment based on new 
addresses is required. During route re-establishment, data packets forwarding may fail.
</t>
</section>





<section anchor="Prefix distribution" title="Prefix distribution">
<t>
There are two schemes for advertising and distributing topologically correct global prefixes 
into a connected MANET, that is, Individual Prefix Distribution (IPD) [4]-[7] and Common Prefix 
Distribution (CPD) [8]-[9]. IPD and CPD are explained in Fig. 2 and Fig. 3, respectively.
</t>

<t>
In IPD, a topologically correct global prefixes are maintained and advertised by Edge Routers 
(ERs) and distributed via MNBRs, each of which is connected to the corresponding ER, into the 
MANET. Different ERs may advertise different global prefixes depending on their topological 
locations in the Internet.
</t>

<t>
In Case I of Fig. 2, an MNR obtains the prefix a though MNBR1 and
configures the address axxx to communicate with a CN. Later, MNBR1
leaves the MANET and MNR re-select a new MNBR2 and obtains the new
prefix b to configure the address bxxx, thus address change occurs.
In case of Fig.2, MNR itself roams in the MANET and select MNBR2 based
on some metric such as the number of hops between MNR and MNBR. Again
the address change from axxx to bxxx occurs.
</t>

<t>
In CPD, a global prefix is maintained and advertised by a Mobility Anchor Point (MAP) and 
distributed via ERs and the corresponding MNBRs into the MANET. The same global prefix is 
therefore distributed regardless of different MNBRs into the MANET.
</t>

<t>
In Fig. 3, the same prefix a is supplied to both ER1 and ER2 based on
an appropriate mechanism such as use of the Moblity Anchor Point
(MAP). an MNR obtains the prefix a through MNBR1 and configures the
address axxx to communicate with a CN. Later, MNR roams and select
MNBR2 for communication efficiency. MNR obtains the same prefix a
through MNBR2 and thus can keep the same address axxx. No address
change is required.
</t>

<artwork>















       INTERNET                     MANET
  +---------------+        +---------------------+
  |               |   a    |                     |
  |          +--+ | -----&gt; |  +---+   a          |
  |   +-----&gt;|  |------------&gt;|   | ------&gt;      |
  |   |      +--+ |        |  +---+ ---+         |
  | +---+    ER1  |        |  MNBR1    |   +--+  |
  | |CN |         |        |    |      +--&gt;|  |  | axxx
  | +---+         |        |  a |          +--+  |   |
  |               |        |    v          MNR   |   | Re-select
  +---------------+        +---------------------+   | a new MNBR
                      |                              | 
                      v             ^                |
  +---------------+        +------- | -----------+   |
  |          +--+ |        |  +--+  |            |   | 
  |   +-----&gt;|  |------------&gt;|  |--+            |   |
  |   |      +--+ |        |  +--+               |   |
  | +---+    ER1  |        |  MNBR1     b  +--+  |   v
  | |CN |         |        |          +---&gt;|  |  | bxxx
  | +---+         |        |          |    +--+  |
  |   |      +--+ |        |  +--+ ---+    MNR   |
  |   +-----&gt;|  |------------&gt;|  | -------&gt;      |
  |          +--+ | -----&gt; |  +--+ ---+          |
  |          ER2  |   b    |  MNBR2   |          |
  |               |        |          +---&gt;      |
  +---------------+        +---------------------+
              (Case I : The selected MNBR leaves)                

       INTERNET                      MANET                                 
  +---------------+        +----------------------+
  |               |   a    |          a           |
  |          +--+ | -----&gt; |  +---+ -----&gt;  +---+ |     
  |   +-----&gt;|  |------------&gt;|   | -------&gt;|   | | axxx  
  |   |      +--+ |        |  +---+ ---+    +---+ |  |
  |   |      ER1  |        |  MNBR1    | a   MNR  |  |
  |   |           |        |           +---&gt;  |   |  |
  |   |           |        |                  |   |  | Select a
  | +---+         |        |             b    |   |  | better MNBR
  | |CN |         |        |           +---&gt;  |   |  |
  | +---+         |        |           |      v   |  |
  |   |      +--+ |        |  +---+ ---+ b  +---+ |  v
  |   +-----&gt;|  |------------&gt;|   | -------&gt;|   | | bxxx
  |          +--+ | -----&gt; |  +---+ ---+    +---+ |
  |          ER2  |   b    |  MNBR2    |     MNR  |
  |               |        |           +---&gt;      |
  +---------------+        +----------------------+
              (Case II : A MANET router roams)

      MNR  : MANET Router
      MNBR : MANET Border Router
      ER   : ISP Edge Router

              Fig. 2: Individual Prefix Distribution Scheme           
</artwork>
<artwork>
          INTERNET                         MANET                                 
  +---------------------+        +----------------------+
  |                     |   a    |          a           |
  |        +---&gt;  +--+  | -----&gt; |  +---+ -----&gt;  +---+ |     
  |        | +---&gt;|  |-------------&gt;|   | -------&gt;|   | | axxx  
  |      a | |    +--+  |        |  +---+ ---+    +---+ |  |
  |        | |    ER1   |        |  MNBR1    | a    |   |  |
  |          |          |        |           +---&gt;  |   |  |
  |          |          |        |                  |   |  | Select a
  | +--+   +---+        |        |             a    |   |  | better MNBR
  | |  |--&gt;|   | MAR    |        |           +---&gt;  |   |  |
  | +--+   +---+        |        |           |      v   |  |
  |  CN      |    +--+  |        |  +---+ ---+ a  +---+ |  v
  |        | +---&gt;|  |-------------&gt;|   | -------&gt;|   | | axxx
  |        +---&gt;  +--+  | -----&gt; |  +---+ ---+    +---+ |
  |          a    ER2   |   a    |  MNBR2    |          |
  |                     |        |           +---&gt;      |
  +---------------------+        +----------------------+
               
              Fig. 3: Common Prefix Distribution Scheme
</artwork>
</section>





<section anchor="Evaluation" title="Evaluation">
<t>
In IPD, a MANET router my change its global address when it re-selects a new MNBR, resulting in 
having route entries based on the old address obsolele. Route entries thus needs to be 
re-established in the MANET. To suppress route re-establishment, multiple address advertisement [6] 
or MANET-local address-based routing [7] may be used with additional overhead. Specifically, In the 
former, each node configures multiple care-of-addresses based on the received prefixes and 
advertises all of them throughout the MANET so that the routing protocol maintains all routes to 
the multiple addresses [6].  When a node changes its address to one of the advertised addresses, 
all other nodes already have maintained the route to this address. In the second approach, data 
packets are tunneled between the MANET routers and the selected MNBRs in both directions. 
MANET-local address is used for forwarding packets within the MANET [7].  As the result, no route 
re-establishment needs to be performed. However, these methods can't avoid address change. 
When address change occurs, application sessions are terminated and need to be re-established.
</t>   

<t>
In CPD, address change does not occur, since the same global prefix is distributed into the 
MANET, regardless of the difference of MNBR. Application sessions continue to work, when a MANET 
router re-selects MNBR.
</t>

<t>
The evaluation is summarized in Table I.
</t>

<artwork>
          Table I. The evaluation of prefix distribution schemes
          for connected MANETs.   
  +--------------+---------+----------------+--------------------------+
  |              | Address | Route          | Remarks                  |
  |              | Change  | Reconstruction |                          |
  |              |         | In MANET       |                          |
  +--------------+---------+----------------+--------------------------+
  | Individual   | Yes     | Yes            | Route reconstruction can |
  | Prefix       |         |                | be suppressed using,     |
  | Distribution |         |                | -  Multiple address      |
  |              |         |                |    advertisement         |
  |              |         |                | -  MANET-local address   |
  |              |         |                |    based routing         |
  +--------------+---------+----------------+--------------------------+
  | Common       | No      | No             | Mobility Anchor Point,   |
  | Prefix       |         |                | fixedly or dynamically   |
  | Distribution |         |                | configured, may be       |
  |              |         |                | necessary.               |
  +--------------+---------+----------------+--------------------------+
</artwork>
</section>

</middle>

<section anchor="References" title="References">
<list>
<t>
[1] Bradner, S., "Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels", 
BCP 14, RFC 2119, March 1997.
</t>

<t>
[2] I. Chakeres, J. Macker, T. Clausen, "Mobile Ad hoc Network Architecture", 
draft-ietf-autoconf-manetarch-07 (work in progress), November 2007.
</t>

<t>
[3] E. Baccelli, K. Mase, S. Ruffino, S. Shingh, "Address Autoconfiguration for MANET: Terminology and 
Problem statement", draft-ietf-autoconf-statement-01 (work in progress), August 2007.
</t>

<t>
[4] Wakikawa, R., J. T. Malinen, C. E. Perkins, A. Nilsson, and A. J. Tuominen, "Global Connectivity for 
Mobile Ad Hoc Networks", draft-wakikawa-manet-globalv6-04 (work in progress), July 2005.
</t>

<t>
[5] Jelger, C., T. Noel, and A. Fre, "Gateway and Address Autoconfiguration for IPv6 Ad Hoc Networks", 
draft-jelger-manet-gateway-autoconf-v6-02 (work in progress), April 2004.
</t>

<t>
[6] Ruffino, S. and P. Stupar, "Automatic Configuration of IPv6  Addresses for noes in a MANET with Mutiple 
Gateways", draft-ruffino-manet-autoconf-multigw-01 (work in progress), December 2005.
</t>

<t>
[7] Hofmann, P., "Multihop Radio Access Network (MRAN) Protocol Specification", 
draft-hofmann-autoconf-mran-00 (work in progress), March 2006.
</t>

<t>
[8] F. Templin, S. Russert, I. Chakeres, S. Yi, "MANET Autoconfiguration",
 draft-templin-autoconf-dhcp-09 (work in progress), September 2007.
</t>

<t>
[9] K.Mase, Y.Owada, "Gateway Aggregation Protocol (GAP) for Mobile Ad hoc Networks",
 draft-mase-autoconf-gap-01 (work in progress), July 2007.
</t>

</list>
</section>

<back></back>

</rfc>
