<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?><?rfc compact="yes"?><?rfc strict="yes"?><?rfc symrefs="yes"?><?rfc sortrefs="yes"?><rfc ipr="full3978" docName="draft-newman-email-subaddr-01" category="info">

<front>
  <title abbrev="Internet Email Subaddressing">Internet Email Subaddressing</title>
  <author initials="D.A." surname="Cridland" fullname="Dave Cridland">
<organization>Isode Limited</organization>
<address>
	<postal>
		<street>5 Castle Business Village</street>
		<street>36, Station Road</street>
		<city>Hampton</city>
		<region>Middlesex</region>
		<code>TW12 2BX</code>
		<country>GB</country>
	</postal>
	<email>dave.cridland@isode.com</email>
</address>
</author>
  <date day="16" month="November" year="2007"/>
  <area>Applications</area>
  <abstract>
    <t>It is often useful for a single user to have multiple email
     addresses which can be used to assist categorizing incoming email.
     One way of doing this is to divide the local-part of an email
     address into user and detail parts.  The user part is used
     to route the message within the specified domain
     and the detail part is used to route the message according to a
     particular user's wishes.</t>
     <t>This specification formalizes the de-facto standard for
     subaddressing in use today and includes advice and requirements for
     final delivery agents, MUAs and mail list servers which wish to
     support subaddressing.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
  <section title="Introduction">
  <t>Subaddressing is a common technique for providing users with multiple addresses which can be used for filtering incoming email. A key feature is that no administrative action is required to provision or enable a particular detail part; instead, as long as the domain's mail system is subaddress-aware, the user may use arbitrary detail parts.</t>
  <t>Although commonly deployed, subaddressing has had minimal formal documentation; this document attempts to define subaddressing, and also define what it means to be subaddress-aware.</t>
  <t>In general, deployed forms of subaddressing divide the local-part of an email address into two strings, seperated by a delimiter character. This is most commonly a plus sign, "+".</t>
  <t>This document does not document all forms of subaddressing, merely the most common form, also known as "plus-addressing". Other forms are also deployed, sometimes using a minus sign, and in some rare cases using encoding rules rather than simple catenation.</t>
  <section title="Conventions used in this document">
    <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
   document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="KEYWORDS"/>.</t>
    <t>The formal grammar in this document uses Augmented BNF <xref target="ABNF"/>.</t>
  </section>
  </section>
  
  <section title="Definitions">
  <t><list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Final Delivery Agent"><vspace/>
    The final delivery agent is the agent started by the Final MTA
    which interprets the local-part of the email address.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    <t hangText="Final MTA"><vspace/>
    The final MTA is the MTA designated by the domain to the left
    of the "@" in an email address.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    <t hangText="Local-Part"><vspace/>
          The local-part of an email address is everything to the left
          of the "@" in the address used for delivery and is formally
          defined in [IMAIL].  It is also know as the "left hand side"
          of an address.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

     <t hangText="Mail List Server"><vspace/>
          A Mail List Server takes messages directed to it, rewrites the
          envelope addresses and redistributes the message to one or
          more subscribers.

    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
     <t hangText="MTA"><vspace/>  A Mail Transport Agent (MTA) receives email from other MTAs or
          MUAs and routes it towards the final MTA.

    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
     <t hangText="MUA"><vspace/>  A Mail User Agent (MUA) is used by a user to send and read
          email.

    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
     <t hangText="Detail Part"><vspace/>
          A detail part is information in addition to the address of a
          primary mailbox which may be used for categorization by the
          recipient. It is also known as a subaddress.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
     <t hangText="User Part"><vspace/>
          A user part is that portion of the local part which indicates the
	  primary mailbox. In a mail system which is not subaddress-aware, the
	  user part is equal to the local part.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Detailed Address"><vspace/>
    An email address which has a detail part.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Primary Address"><vspace/>
    An email address which has no detail part, or the corresponding address to a detailed address with the detail part removed.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    </list></t>
  </section>
  <section title="Subaddressing Syntax">
  <t>A subaddress-aware final delivery agent divides the local-part into two pieces
     separated by a "+".  The user part is to the left of the "+"
     and the detail part is to the right of the "+".  A message with a
     valid user part is delivered to the primary address by
     default, regardless of the contents of the detail part.  The
     detail part MAY be used by final delivery filtering (e.g. to deliver
     messages with a particular detail part into a special mailbox) or by
     an MUA.</t>
     <t>For example, the detailed address &lt;delenn+grey-council@babylon5.example.org&gt; might be
     used to send email to &lt;delenn@babylon5.example.org&gt; relating to grey-council
     business.  Delenn can then direct her final delivery agent
     to file messages with a "grey-council" subaddress into her "grey-council" mailbox, perhaps with the <xref target="SIEVE-SUBADDRESS"/> extension.</t>
     <t>When generating a detailed address, the local part of the address MUST be
     canonically quoted.  A local part is canonically quoted if it is
     legal according to both the formal grammer in <xref target="IMAIL"/> and the
     formal grammar in <xref target="SMTP"/>.  The following formal grammar restricts
     &lt;local-part&gt; in this fashion and distinguishes the user part
     from the detail part.  Subaddress-aware MUAs MUST NOT generate
     addresses which violate this syntax and subaddress-aware final
     delivery agents MAY refuse to apply subaddress interpretation to
     addresses which violate this syntax.</t>
     <figure><artwork type="abnf">
local-part     = local-quoted / local-unquoted

local-quoted   = DQUOTE user-part-q ["+" detail-q] DQUOTE

local-unquoted = [user-part-c] ["+" [detail-c]]

user-part      = *(SAFEQ-CHAR / QUOTE-CHAR)
                 ;; This is the syntax for an unquoted user-part
                 ;; address. If it fits canonical form (user-part-c)
                 ;; it is used directly in a local-part.  Otherwise
                 ;; QUOTE-CHARs are escaped to fit quoted form.

user-part-c    = userc-word *("." userc-word)

user-part-q    = *(SAFEQ-CHAR / quoted)

userc-word     = 1*SAFE-CHAR

quoted         = "\" QUOTE-CHAR

detail-part    = *(SAFEQ-CHAR / QUOTE-CHAR / "+")
                 ;; This is the syntax for an unquoted subaddress.
                 ;; If it fits canonical form (subaddress-c) it is
                 ;; used directly in a local-part.  Otherwise
                 ;; QUOTE-CHARs are escaped to fit quoted form.

detail-c       = detailc-word *("." detailc-word)

detail-q       = *(SAFEQ-CHAR / "+" / quoted)

detailc-word   = 1*(SAFE-CHAR / "+")

QUOTE-CHAR     = DQUOTE / "\"

SAFE-CHAR      = %x21 / %x23-27 / %x2A / %x2D / %x2F-39 / %x3D /
                 %x3F / %x41-5A / %x5E-7E
                 ;; All printable US-ASCII characters except
                 ;; space, plus "+" and &lt;specials&gt; as defined
                 ;; in [IMAIL]

SAFEQ-CHAR     = %x20-21 / %x23-2A / %x2C-5B / %x5D-7E
                 ;; All printable US-ASCII characters except
                 ;; plus, quote and backslash.

</artwork></figure>
  </section>
  <section title="Subaddress Support Requirements">
    <t>This section defines the requirements for subaddress aware final
     delivery agents, gateway/firewalls, MUAs and mail list servers.</t>
     <section title="Final Delivery Agent Requirements">
     <t>By default, delivery to a detailed address MUST be identical to delivery to the primary address. Configuration MAY be used to override behaviour for specific detailed addresses.</t>
     <t>If <xref target="SIEVE"/> is supported by the delivery agent, then <xref target="SIEVE-SUBADDRESS"/> MUST be supported.</t>
     </section>
     <section title="Gateway/Firewall Requirements">
     <t>A subaddress-aware gateway or firewall SHOULD preserve the
     detail part when rewriting an address.  A subaddress aware gateway
     MAY rewrite an address into canonical quoted form.</t>
     </section>
     <section title="MUA Requirements">
     <t>A subaddress-aware MUA MUST allow the user to include a detail part
     in the From header when sending a message.  A subaddress-aware MUA
     MUST generate addresses in canonically quoted form following the
     syntax for local-part in this specification.  A subaddress-aware
     MUA SHOULD allow the user to user a detailed address as the envelope
     sender address (as used in the SMTP MAIL FROM command).  A
     subaddress-aware MUA which validates local addresses MUST ignore
     detail parts for the purposes of such validation.</t>
     </section>
     <section title="Mailing List Server Requirements" anchor="mlm">
     <t>A subaddress-aware mailing list server MUST allow users to subscribe
     using a detailed address.  If such a server restricts postings by their
     envelope sender, Sender or From address, it MUST be able to be configured,
     by the subscriber, to ignore
     detail parts for the purposes of such restrictions.</t>
     <t>Mailing list servers SHOULD provide a per-user configuration setting to allow for
     alternate delimiters, such as "-".</t>
     </section>
  </section>
  <section title="Security Considerations">
  <t>If a final delivery agent executes a command line containing the
     delivery address and the detail part contains meta-characters with
     special meaning to the command line interpretor this could result
     in a serious security violation.  In order to avoid this problem,
     the final delivery agent MUST verify the detail part contains no
     characters with special meaning to the command line interpretor,
     not use a command line interpretor, or strip the detail part from
     the address prior to generating the command line when it contains
     characters with special meaning.</t>
     <t>If a final delivery agent were to automatically create a mailbox
     based on the detail part, this could result in a denial of service
     problem as well as placing control of a user's mailbox namespace in
     the hands of outsiders.  In order to avoid this problem, final
     delivery agents MUST NOT automatically create new mailboxes based on
     the detail part without explicit permission from the owner of the
     primary address.  Final delivery agents SHOULD NOT automatically
     file a message into a mailbox based on the subaddress without
     explicit configuration from the owner of the primary address.</t>
     <t>Detailed addresses themselves may be used as a weak form of authorization
     token, for example in the scenario given in <xref target="bank"/>. In such
     cases, acquisition of the token by a third party may aid in fraud.
     Therefore such subaddresses MUST be random, and MUST NOT be disclosed.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Acknowledgements">
  <t>This draft is a direct ancestor of a 1997 draft by Chris Newman. Some usages documented herein may reflect this long heritage, however it has been updated with current usages, including the use of subaddressing as an anti-phishing technique described by John Klensin on the IETF mailing list. No existing usages had fallen out of fashion in the intervening decade.</t>
  <t>Discussions within the SIEVE working group also influenced the changes to the draft - in particular, the terminology has been changed to match that of <xref target="SIEVE-SUBADDRESS"/>.</t>
  </section>
</middle>
<back>
  <references title="Normative References">
    <reference anchor="KEYWORDS">

<front>
<title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street></postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year="1997" month="March"/>
<area>General</area>
<keyword>keyword</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t></list></t>
<t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="4723" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt"/>
<format type="HTML" octets="17491" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"/>
<format type="XML" octets="5777" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"/>
</reference>
    <reference anchor="IMAIL">

<front>
<title>Internet Message Format</title>
<author initials="P." surname="Resnick" fullname="P. Resnick">
<organization/></author>
<date year="2001" month="April"/>
<abstract>
<t>This document specifies a syntax for text messages that are sent between computer users, within the framework of "electronic mail" messages. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2822"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="110695" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2822.txt"/>
</reference>
    <reference anchor="SMTP">

<front>
<title>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="J. Klensin">
<organization/></author>
<date year="2001" month="April"/>
<abstract>
<t>This document is a self-contained specification of the basic protocol for the Internet electronic mail transport. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2821"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="192504" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2821.txt"/>
</reference>
    <reference anchor="ABNF">

<front>
<title abbrev="ABNF">Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
<author fullname="Dave Crocker" initials="D." role="editor" surname="Crocker">
<organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>675 Spruce Dr.</street>
<city>Sunnyvale</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94086</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1.408.246.8253</phone>
<email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email></address></author>
<author fullname="Paul Overell" initials="P." surname="Overell">
<organization>THUS plc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1/2 Berkeley Square, </street>
<street>99 Berkeley Street</street>
<city>Glasgow</city>
<code>G3 7HR</code>
<country>UK</country></postal>
<email>paul.overell@thus.net</email></address></author>
<date year="2005" month="October"/>
<keyword>ABNF</keyword>
<keyword>Augmented</keyword>
<keyword>Backus-Naur</keyword>
<keyword>Form</keyword>
<keyword>electronic</keyword>
<keyword>mail</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>Internet technical specifications often need to define a formal	
			syntax.  Over the years, a modified version of Backus-Naur Form	
			(BNF), called Augmented BNF (ABNF), has been popular among many	
			Internet specifications.  The current specification documents ABNF.	
			It balances compactness and simplicity, with reasonable	
			representational power.  The differences between standard BNF and	
			ABNF involve naming rules, repetition, alternatives, order-	
			independence, and value ranges.  This specification also supplies	
			additional rule definitions and encoding for a core lexical analyzer	
			of the type common to several Internet specifications.
      </t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4234"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="26351" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4234.txt"/>
<format type="HTML" octets="52334" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc4234.html"/>
<format type="XML" octets="37285" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc4234.xml"/>
</reference>
    <reference anchor="SIEVE-SUBADDRESS">
<front>
<title>Sieve Email Filtering -- Subaddress Extension</title>

<author initials="K" surname="Murchison" fullname="Ken Murchison">
    <organization/>
</author>

<date month="June" day="16" year="2006"/>

<abstract><t>On email systems that allow for 'subaddressing' or 'detailed addressing' (e.g., "ken+sieve@example.org"), it is sometimes desirable to make comparisons against these sub-parts of addresses. This document defines an extension to the Sieve mail filtering language that allows users to compare against the user and detail sub-parts of an address.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-sieve-rfc3598bis-05"/>
<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-sieve-rfc3598bis-05.txt"/>
</reference>
    <reference anchor="SIEVE">
<front>
<title>Sieve: An Email Filtering Language</title>

<author initials="T" surname="Showalter" fullname="Tim Showalter">
    <organization/>
</author>

<author initials="P" surname="Guenther" fullname="Philip Guenther">
    <organization/>
</author>

<date month="October" day="8" year="2007"/>

<abstract><t>This document describes a language for filtering email messages at time of final delivery. It is designed to be implementable on either a mail client or mail server. It is meant to be extensible, simple, and independent of access protocol, mail architecture, and operating system. It is suitable for running on a mail server where users may not be allowed to execute arbitrary programs, such as on black box Internet Message Access Protocol (IMAP) servers, as the base language has no variables, loops, or ability to shell out to external programs.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-sieve-3028bis-13"/>
<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-sieve-3028bis-13.txt"/>
</reference>
  </references>
  <references title="Informative References">
    <reference anchor="MBOX-NAMES">

<front>
<title abbrev="Mailbox Names">MAILBOX NAMES FOR COMMON SERVICES, ROLES AND FUNCTIONS</title>
<author initials="D." surname="Crocker" fullname="Dave Crocker">
<organization>Internet Mail Consortium</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>127 Segre Ave.</street>
<street>Santa Cruz</street>
<country>CA</country></postal>
<phone>+1 408 246 8253</phone>
<email>dcrocker@imc.org</email></address></author>
<date year="1997" month="May"/>
<area>Applications</area>
<keyword>mail</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   This specification enumerates and describes Internet mail addresses
   (mailbox name @ host reference) to be used when contacting personnel
   at an organization.  Mailbox names are provided for both operations
   and business functions.  Additional mailbox names and aliases are not
   prohibited, but organizations which support email exchanges with the
   Internet are encouraged to support AT LEAST each mailbox name for
   which the associated function exists within the organization.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2142"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="12195" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2142.txt"/>
<format type="HTML" octets="29012" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2142.html"/>
<format type="XML" octets="16576" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2142.xml"/>
</reference>
    <reference anchor="MIXER">

<front>
<title abbrev="MIXER">MIXER (Mime Internet X.400 Enhanced Relay): Mapping between X.400 and RFC 822/MIME</title>
<author initials="S." surname="Kille" fullname="Steve Kille">
<organization>Isode Ltd</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>The Dome, The Square</street>
<city>Richmond</city>
<region>England</region>
<code>TW9 1DT</code>
<country>UK</country></postal>
<phone>+44 181 3329091</phone>
<email>S.Kille@ISODE.COM</email></address></author>
<date year="1998" month="January"/></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2156"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="280385" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2156.txt"/>
</reference>
    <reference anchor="MAIL-ARCH">
<front>
<title>Internet Mail Architecture</title>

<author initials="D" surname="Crocker" fullname="David Crocker">
    <organization/>
</author>

<date month="May" day="29" year="2007"/>

<abstract><t>Over its thirty-five year history Internet Mail has undergone significant changes in scale and complexity, as it has become a global infrastructure service. The first standardized architecture for networked email specified little more than a simple split between the user world and the transmission world. Core aspects of the service, such as the styles of mailbox address and basic message format, have remained remarkably constant. However today's Internet Mail is marked by many independent operators, many different components for providing service to users and many others for performing message transfer. Public discussion of the service often lacks common terminology and a common frame of reference for these components and their activities. Having a common reference model and terminology makes a basic difference when talking about problems with the service, changes in policy, or enhancement to the service's functionality. This document offers an enhanced Internet Mail architecture that targets description of the existing service, in order to facilitate clearer and more efficient technical, operations and policy discussions about email.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-crocker-email-arch-09"/>
<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-crocker-email-arch-09.txt"/>
<format type="PDF" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-crocker-email-arch-09.pdf"/>
</reference>
  </references>
  <section title="Subaddressing Scenarios">
  <t>This appendix includes examples of how subaddressing used on the
     Internet today.</t>
  <section title="Subscribe to Mailing List by Detailed Address">
  <t>Many users subscribe
     to mailing lists using a detailed address and use the final delivery
     agent to file all messages from that mailing list into a different
     incoming mailbox based on the detail part.  This sorts mailing list
     traffic into appropriate mailboxes with 100% accuracy and without
     scanning the contents of the message headers.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="User Controlled Distribution Lists">
  <t>Some final delivery agents allow a user to set up a distribution
     list and associate it with a particular detailed address.  This permits
     users to manage their own distribution lists without administrative
     intervention.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Mailto URL Indicator">
  <t>By including a different detail part for each mailto URL on a web
     page, a user can determine which mailto URL was selected for a
     particular message.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Support for Special Addresses">
  <t>A user may forward mail from special purpose addresses, such as
     those described in <xref target="MBOX-NAMES"/> to a subaddress of their primary
     account.  This avoids the need to login as multiple users while
     still keeping the mail separated.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Priority Categorization">
  <t>A user may advertise different detailed addresses to different audiences
     and prioritize reading them appropriately.  For example, one of the
     current esteemed area directors uses an "ietf" detail part to
     prioritize IETF traffic separately from regular email.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Anti-Phishing" anchor="bank">
  <t>If a user provides their bank with a unique detailed address, then any messages
  arriving either to the primary address or to a different detailed address are more easily detirmined to be fraudulent, and can be easily filtered out.</t>
  <t>This effectively uses the detailed address as a weak authorization token, so it is advisable to choose a random or unusual detail part.</t>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section title="Open Issues and Discussion">
  <t>This section will hopefully be empty prior to publication as an RFC.</t>
  <t>The author is aware of two main areas of contention which stalled the original document. Firstly, the choice of subaddress delimiter character is not universal, nor even the choice of having one at all. Unfortunately, a choice must be made for interoperability, therefore the plus character remains specified by this document, being the most common case.</t>
  <t>Secondly, the recommendation in <xref target="mlm"/> effectively means that mailing list management software is encouraged into interpreting the local-part of addresses in foreign domains. This recommendation has been reduced in this version - to requiring that the ability be present, and possible to configure by the subscriber. It is the author's assertion that modern mailing list management software is typically able to be configured by the subscriber in many ways already, so this ought to settle contention.</t>
  <section title="To-do">
  <t>This is likely to break <xref target="MIXER"/> - either a solution or advice will be needed here.</t>
  <t>Need to switch to and use terminology within <xref target="MAIL-ARCH"/>, rather than defining potentially clashing terminology.</t>
  </section>
 </section>
</back>
</rfc>
