<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2560 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2560.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-hallambaker-ipr-patent-harmonization-00" ipr="full3978">

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="IETF Patent Policy">IETF Patent Policy: A Quantum Approach</title>
    <author fullname="Phillip Hallam-Baker" initials="P. M."
            surname="Hallam-Baker">
      <organization>VeriSign Inc</organization>
      <address>
        <email>pbaker@verisign.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Daniel Weitzner" initials="D. J."
            surname="Hallam-Baker">
      <organization>World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
      <address>
        <email>djweitzner@w3.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="4" month="November" year="2007" />

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>Patents</keyword>
    <keyword>IPR</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        Considerations for IETF patent policy are considered and proposals made for
        reform. The particular objective of these proposals is to reduce the amount
        of time spent in unproductive discussion of IPR issues and to allow Working
        Groups to provide Patent Rights Holders with clearly defined criteria
        that must be met in order for their technology to be accepted.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
          document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Definitions">

        <t>
          The following defined terms are used:
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Open Source">
              a set of principles and practices intended to promote access to the design and
              production of goods and knowledge through full disclosure of all relevant design materials.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Open Source Implementation">
              a software or hardware implementation that is licensed on terms
              compatible with Open Source principles.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Zero Cost Open Source Implementation">
              An Open Source implementation that is provided at no
              charge to any party and which may be extended or adapted without restriction.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Patent">
              a set of exclusive rights granted by a state to a patentee for a fixed period of
              time in exchange for a disclosure of an invention.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Patent Access">
              terms that allows a party to practice the invention covered by a patent
              without risk of a lawsuit.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Patent License"> a contract granting a Patent Access.</t>

            <t hangText="RAND">Reasonable and Non Discriminatory terms</t>
            <t hangText="RANDZ">Reasonable, Non Discriminatory and Zero cost terms</t>
            <t hangText="Royalty RAND">
              Reasonable and Non Discriminatory terms in which a royalty fee
              is required for some or all uses..
            </t>
            <t hangText="Reciprocal Rights">
              rights granted by one party to another on the condition that the
              recipient grant terms that are equally favorable to the granting party.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          Certain definitions are adapted from text found in Wikipedia.
        </t>

      </section>
    </section>


    <section title="Stakeholder Concerns">
      <section title="Patent Rights Holders">
        <section title="License Revenue">
          <t>
            A Patent Rights Holder may seek revenue in the form of license fees. The terms
            offered for these rights may or may not be RAND.
          </t>
          <t>
            In many instances a Patent Rights Holder seeking to obtain license revenue
            will offer RANDZ terms for certain types of use (e.g. non-commercial,
            educational) or certain uses of the patent (e.g. allow free use of rights
            to decode content but charge fees for encoders). Such terms are properly
            regarded as a business model rather than Zero Cost terms.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Monopoly Rights">
          <t>
            A Patent Rights Holder may seek to use patent rights to establish or extend a
            dominant or otherwised advantageous market position. As with a revenue
            exploitation model the Patent Rights Holder may offer liberal terms in
            some areas while protecting others.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Defensive Use">
          <t>
            As issue of Patent grants has increased Implementors and Users, particularly
            those with deep pockets have become increasingly concerned about their
            exposure to litigation and damages risks.
          </t>
          <t>
            Defensive patent applications provide a degree of mitigation for this risk.
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Establish Prior Art">
                A defensive patent application establishes prior art for the invention(s)
                claimed. This MAY pre-empt subsequent grant of a patent for the same claims
                by another party or allow for a successful defense should a subequent patent
                be issued. This is not certain however.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Obtain Reciprocal Access">
                A defensive patent applicatiopn MAY be used to obtain reciprocal rights
                from other patent rights holders.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Protecting Rights">
          <t>
            A Patent Rights Holder may be subeject to limitations of their rights
            or lose them entirely for certain specific types of inequiable conduct.
            This has occurred in the US courts for failure to disclose the existence of
            rights to an invention when the Patent Rights Holder was under a
            specific obligation to do so.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Attribution">
          <t>
            A Patent Rights Holder that has invested substantial resources in
            developing an invention may desire credit for doing so.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Adoption">
          <t>
            The value of a communication protocol is dependent on adoption. As
            Nicholas Negroponte observed, the utility of the first fax machine
            was nil until the second one was produce and has climbed steadily as the
            number of faxes has increased.
          </t>
          <t>
            The need for widespread adoption is the reason that standards play an
            unusually critical role in the development of communication technologies.
            Without standardization of features such as thread pitch, nuts and bolts
            would be considerably more expensive. Without standardization a
            communications protocol is no use whatsoever.
          </t>
          <t>
            Without adoption, the value of a typical communications invention is
            zero. It is thus in the interests of Patent Rights Holders to seek
            adoption of the inventions they have rights to by promoting them in
            standards process.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Implementors">
        <section title="Litigation Risk">
          <t>
            The cost of defending a patent infringement lawsuit can be enormous.
          </t>
          <t>
            Litigation risk is a particular concern in the US where costs cannot be
            recovered from a losing plaintif and cases routinely cost defendants with
            'deep pockets' $2 million or more.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Damages Risk">
          <t>
            Damages in patent lawsuits can be very high. Several recent awards have
            exceeded a hundred million dollars.
          </t>
          <t>
            US law allows for damages to be trebled in cases of willful infringement.
            As a result some companies have policies which prohibit engineers fro
            engaging in any patent searches or other activities that might bring
            patents to their notice and thus provide grounds for a treble
            damages claim.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="License Cost">
          <t>
            The cost of patent licenses is usually paid by implementors. Although these
            costs will subsequently be passed onto users certain types of implementors
            may be unable to meet these costs. In addition to providers of Zero Cost
            Implementations, smaller implementors may be unable to afford minimum
            license fees or meet other licensing requirements.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Encumberance">
          <t>
            Once a patent license is accepted, the licensee is bound by the terms of
            the license. These terms may continue even after the original patent term
            expires or the patent is found to be invalid.
          </t>
          <t>
            A royalty-free license may still be regarded as an encumberance by an
            implementor. For example a royalty-free license may require the licensee
            to use a particular technology (e.g. programming language) or support
            particular features (e.g. direct access to a particular online store) that
            the implementor would not otherwise accept.
          </t>
          <t>
            In particular 'royalty-free' license terms that require the implementor
            to surrender patent rights to unrelated technologies or to provide the
            implementation at zero cost are generally considered an encumberance
            by the affected parties.
          </t>
          <t>
            Sublicensing terms have proved problematic in this respect. Commercial
            providers of middleware products have objected to license terms which
            would require their customers to obtain a royalty-free license from
            a Patent Rights Holder as requiring them to reveal their customer list
            to a competitor. Sublicensing is also a concern with certain open source
            licenses as a patent license obtained by the developer may not transfer to
            another developer that modifies the code.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Adoption">
          <t>
            Adoption is also a concern for Implementors. Implementors will not
            adopt a technology unless they beleive that they can access all
            necessary and enforceable patents on acceptable terms.
          </t>

        </section>
        <section title="Patent Rights Holders">
          <t>
            Some Implementors are also Patent Rights Holders. Their interests in
            one role may conflict with those in the other. In some cases this
            conflict may lead to proloinged indecision and thus inaction which
            in itself impedes the standards process.
          </t>
          <t>
            A particular concern raised by some Implementors/Patent Rights Holders is
            that the reciprocal rights clause of a Patent License may not be
            enforceable against a party that obtains a patent grant indirectly through
            a sublicense. While it has been argued that such reciprocal rights are
            likely to be found enforceable by a court, in the absence of binding precedent
            this argument does little to convince a party concerned about litigation risk.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Users">
        <t>
          A lawsuit for patent infringement may in certain circumstances be brought
          against the user of an infringing article. Users with deep pockets may
          thus be exposed to the same litigation and damages risks as developers and
          all users can expect that licensing costs paid by implementors will be passed
          onto them.
        </t>
        <t>
          In some recent cases a plaintif who has been successful in a patent infringement
          lawsuit against an implementor has subsequently brought suit against users,
          effectivly claiming double damages for the same infringement.
        </t>
        <section title="Indeminity">
          <t>
            Users may seek an indemnity against these risks from a third party, typically,
            but not necessarily, the implementor.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Patents in the Standards Process">

      <section title="Issues Arising from Current IETF Practice">
        <section title="Royalty Terms">
          <t>
            Current IETF practice is that access to all essential claims necessary to
            implement a specification MUST be available to all parties on RAND
            terms. The IETF does not require Zero Cost access to be available.
          </t>
          <t>
            While it is clear that there is no IETF consensus to change this policy,
            there is an even stronger preference for choosing technology available on
            RANDZ terms unless an encumbered technology overs exceptionally strong
            advantages.
          </t>
        </section>


        <section title="Time Taken for Discussion">
          <t>
            The most frequent complaint made of the IETF patent policy is the amount
            of time spent dicussing it.
            Extended discussion of patent access issues is particularly problematic
            when it occurs during Working Group or IETF last call at a point where the
            Working Group has invested considerable time and effort in developing the
            specification.
          </t>
          <t>
            At present each IETF Working Group is responsible for deciding its own
            IPR policy within the constraint of meeting the IETF RAND requirments.
            While this allows WGs great flexibility in chosing their IPR criteria
            it leads to a great deal of unnecessarily repetative discussion at both
            the Working Group and IETF level.
          </t>
          <t>
            A particular problem here is the fact that most IETF participants
            are engineers. Almost none are qualified lawyers. As a result discussions
            tend to revolve around the twin poles of ideological commitments and
            the concerns of those who have in the past become involuntary participants
            in patent litigation.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Weak Negotiating Position">
          <t>
            Allowing Working Groups to negotiate IPR terms with Patent Rights Holders
            directly is unsatisfactory because they are placed in a weak negotiating
            position. 
          </t>
          <section title="No Decision Maker">
            <t>
              Negotiating with a Working Group as a whole is entirely unsatisfactory
              for the Patent Rights Holder as no party in the Working Group has decision
              making power, either for the Working Group itself or the IETF as a whole.
              Any concession made by one member of the Working Group can be repudiated by 
              the group as a whole and even if the Working Group comes to agreement with 
              the Patent Rights Holder this agreement may be repudiated at the IETF
              level
            </t>
            <t>
              The result is a negotiating posture similar to Axelrod's Prisoner's 
              Dilema in which the rules of the game cause the parties to choose an
              outcome that is suboptimal for all concerned. 
            </t>
          </section>
          <section title="Unequal Precedent">
            <t>
              Any
              concession made by a Patent Rights Holder to one Working Group becomes
              an unequal precedent. Having revealled their bargaining position, the
              Patent Rights Holder knows that in the future it will be expected to provide
              terms that are at least as favorable to any other Working Group. The
              precedent established is only one way however, the Patent Rights Holder
              has no assurance that its competitors will be required to provide equally
              favorable terms in the same circumstance.
            </t>
            <t>
              Unequal precedence encourages Patents Rights Holders to offer the
              least favorable terms that are likely to be acceptable to the Working
              Group and is thus counter to the spirit of mutuality on which the IETF
              is based.
            </t>
          </section>


        </section>

        <section title="Unenforceable Patent Claims">
          <t>
            The mere assertion of a patent claim does not by itself mean that the claim
            is valid or enforceable. Patent applications are particularly problematic in
            this respect as nobody knows if the application will be granted.
          </t>
          <t>
            Bad faith assertions of patent claims are far from unknown. The most famous
            example being perhaps the notorious Selden 'automobile patent' which prevented
            production of low cost volume automobiles until the patent was disqualified in
            1911 at the conclusion of a case brought against Henry Ford.
          </t>
          <t>
            A bad faith patent claim might be raised in a standards process in the hope
            of receiving unjust royalty payments or to influence the process itself.
            A rule against inclusion of any technology against which a patent claim has
            been asserted would require the IETF to either examine the validity of the
            patent claim or allow the Patent Rights Holder to exercise a veto.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Uncertainty">
          <t>
            Uncertainty imposes costs on all legitimate stakeholders. A Patent Rights
            Holder seeking to fairly obtain royalties for use of their technology has little
            incentive to invest in engagement in a standards process if it is uncertain
            that Royalty RAND terms will be acceptable. Equally an implementor is
            likely to object if having engaged in a standards process under the expectation
            that the royalty terms will be RANDZ and find that this is not the
            case at a late stage.
          </t>
          <t>
            The disadvantage created by uncertainty might be used to advantage by a
            bad faith Patent Rights Holder, encouraging development of the specification
            to proceed on the expectation that RANDZ terms will be available without
            the intention of ever doing so. This is not as great a concern in standards
            bodies where implementation and deployment follow agreement of the
            specification. In the IETF and other Internet standards bodies deployment
            and use is considered an essential criterion for recognition of a standard.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Access, not Licenses">
          <t>
            Conventional consideration of patent policy has centered on patent
            license terms, this despite the fact that few parties have in fact
            obtained licenses when offered.
          </t>
          <t>
            In most cases the interest of the implementor is not to obtain a
            patent license, it is to obtain an assurance that a lawsuit will not
            be brought for infringement. Nor is it likely to be in the interests of
            a Patent Rights Holder to litigate for infringement of a RANDZ patent
            license except as a countersuit to an infringement case brought by
            the alleged infringer.
          </t>
          <t>
            The objectives of the parties is therefore to grant and obtain
            Patent Access as opposed to a Patent License. In the Microsoft
            Open Specification Promise this takes the form of an irrevocable
            promise not to assert any Microsoft Necessary Claims in connection
            with an implementation that conforms to a covered specification
            provided that no similar claims are made against Microsoft. This
            approach meets Microsoft's goal of
            ensuring the enforcability of the Reciprocal Rights clause in the
            patent license while avoiding the need for any party to actually
            obtain a license.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Non Participant Claims">
          <t>
            Any changes made to the IETF patent policy must bear in mind the fact
            that it is only binding on IETF participants. If the policy is changed
            in ways that Patent Rights Holders who are also Implementors consider
            to be too onerous, they may cease participating.
          </t>
          <t>
            Patent claims by non-participants have in practice proved far more
            problematic than those brought by participants. A Patent Rights Holder
            who is also an Implementor has to consider both the
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>
      <section title="Other Standards Bodies">
        <section title="World Wide Web Consortium">
          <t>

          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="OASIS">
          <t>

          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Other">
          <t>
            Some standards bodies begin all proceedings, including face to face meetings
            and conference calls with a formal recitation of the IPR (and frequently
            anti-trust) requirements.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Stakeholder Concerns in IETF Process">
          <t>

          </t>
          <section title="Disclosure">
            <t>
              All parties should have equal understanding of the consequences of a 
              decision. Effective disclosure of IPR claims is thus essential.
            </t>
          </section>
          <section title="Predicatability">
            <t>
              When a proposal is made the parties should be able to predict the 
              likely response. 
            </t>
          </section>
          <section title="Fairness">
            <t>
              No party should be able to benefit from unfair practices such as
              concealling the existence of IPR or bad-faith offers of Patent
              Access on deliberately ambiguous terms.
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Proposals">
      <section title="Increased NOTE WELL visibility">
        <t>
          Display of NOTE WELL advice should be more prominent than is currently
          the case. In particular ackinowledgement of NOTE WELL notification
          should become a required element of subscription to all IETF 
          mailing lists, including lists discussing formation of BOFs.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Specify IPR terms in chartering discussion">
        <t>
          The charter of a Working Group SHOULD specify the IPR terms which
          proposals MUST meet in order to be accepted as Working Group
          work items. In cases where the IPR situation is unclear the
          chater SHOULD specify clarification of the IPR terms as a
          work item.
        </t>
        <t>
          While a Working Group does not always meet the objectives
          set out in its charter, the objectives should always be understood 
          at the outset. It is exceptionally unlikely that a Working Group 
          that is founded with the purpose of developing a RANDZ protocol
          is going to subsequently choose a Royalty RAND alternative.
         
        </t>
        <t>
           In some cases a Working Group will be chartered to create a 
           protocol for a technology that is subsequently discovered
           to be subject to credible Patent claims. While this situation
           is unavoidable it does not have to necessarily lead to the 
           collapse of the Working Group as has happened in the past. 
           Stating the criteria for acceptable IPR terms at the outset
           puts the Patent Rights Holder on notice of the criteria
           they must meet for acceptance and provides them with an 
           assurance that the terms will be accepted if offered.
        </t>
        <t>
          The purpose of a Working Group charter is to avoid unnecessary and
          repetative discussions that are unproductive. Working Groups
          are routinely chartered to rule out of scope discussions that
          would duplicate the work of other Working Groups or have been found
          to be unproductive in the past. These include definitions of SPAM,
          development of PKIs in groups not charterted for that express 
          purpose, development of new cryptographic algorithms and the like.
          The authors of Working Group Charters should be encouraged to add
          discussion of IPR terms to this list.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Reuse already existing IPR Policy terms">
        <t>
          Working Groups should be encouraged to require compliance with 
          IPR policy that has already been developed rather than develop
          new IPR terms within IETF process. In particular requiring
          compliance with the existing W3C policy requirements is recommended.
        </t>
        <t>
          Reuse of existing IPR terms reduces the work that Implementors and
          must perform to decide if the terms are
          acceptable and for Patent Rights Holders to arrive at acceptable 
          terms. 
        </t>
        <t>
           The less decision time required by the lawyers, the greater
          the chance of a satisfactory result. Standardized terms transform
          a legal question to be decided by the legal department into 
          a business question to be decided by the business unit.
        </t>
        <t>
          Standardized terms have the further benefit of being more predictable
          if the parties do end up in a potential litigation situation.
          Standardized terms make it more likely that an applicable precedent 
          can be found. While precedent is not binding in all legal traditions 
          it  is still informative in jurisdictions where it is not binding.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Liase with in Discussion in Appropriate Venues">
            <t>
          Development of IPR policy terms is not core to the mission of
          the IETF or any othe Internet Standards body. If extended 
          discussion of such issues is required
          this should be persued in a venue that has the appropriate
          domain expertise.
        </t>
        <t>
          In addition to developing the policy requirements themselves such
          a forum might assist in the development of mutually acceptable
          support materials such as standard Patent Access terms, 
          standard Patent License contracts, NOTE WELL and disclosure
          agreements for pre-standards activity and the like.
        </t>
        <t>
          Standardization of the legal layer of the Internet becomes 
          increasingly critical as the Internet becomes a social 
          infrastructure.
        </t>
      </section>    
    </section>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>

      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        This draft does not require any action by IANA.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        IPR management rasies critical security issues for all the
        stakeholders involved. IPR is an asset which stakeholders must
        carefully consider in deciding to grant access
      </t>

    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC2560;

    </references>


  </back>
</rfc>

