<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3748 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3748.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4017 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4017.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4282 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4282.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4634 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4634.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3232 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3232.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-eap-keying PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-eap-keying.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4086 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4086.xml'>
]>
    
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="no"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="full3978" category="std">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="EAP-GPSK">EAP Generalized Pre-Shared Key (EAP-GPSK)</title>
    <author initials="T." surname="Clancy" fullname="T. Charles Clancy">
      <organization abbrev="LTS">DoD Laboratory for Telecommunications Sciences</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>8080 Greenmead Drive</street>
          <city>College Park</city>
          <region>MD</region>
          <code>20740</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>clancy@ltsnet.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Hannes Tschofenig" initials="H." surname="Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Otto-Hahn-Ring 6</street>
          <city>Munich</city>
          <region>Bavaria</region>
          <code>81739</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@nsn.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2007"/>
    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>EMU Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>EAP</keyword>
    <keyword>EAP-GPSK</keyword>
    <keyword>Pre-shared Key</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This Internet Draft defines an Extensible Authentication Protocol method called EAP
        Generalized Pre-Shared Key (EAP-GPSK). This method is a lightweight shared-key
        authentication protocol supporting mutual authentication and key derivation.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>EAP Generalized Pre-Shared Key (EAP-GPSK) is an EAP method defining a generalized
        pre-shared key authentication technique. Mutual authentication is achieved through a
        nonce-based exchange that is secured by a pre-shared key.</t>

      <t>EAP-GPSK addresses a large number of design goals with the intention of being applicable in
        a broad range of usage scenarios.</t>

      <t>The main design goals of EAP-GPSK are </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Simplicity:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> EAP-GPSK should be easy to implement. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Security Model:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>EAP-GPSK has been designed in a threat model where the attacker
            has full control over the communication channel. This is the EAP threat model that is
            presented in Section 7.1 of <xref target="RFC3748"/>.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Efficiency:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>EAP-GPSK does not make use of public key cryptography and fully
            relies of symmetric cryptography. The restriction on symmetric cryptographic
            computations allows for low computational overhead. Hence, EAP-GPSK is lightweight and
            well suited for any type of device, especially those with processing power, memory and
            battery constraints. Additionally it seeks to minimize the number of round trips.
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Flexibility:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>EAP-GPSK offers cryptographic flexibility. At the beginning, the
            EAP server proposes a list of ciphersuites. The client then selects one. The current
            version of EAP-GPSK comprises two ciphersuites, but additional ones can be easily
              added.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Extensibility:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The design of EAP-GPSK allows to securely exchange information
            between the EAP peer and the EAP server using protected data fields. These fields might,
            for example, be used to exchange channel binding information or to provide support for
            identity confidentiality. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>In this document, several words are used to signify the requirements of the specification.
        These words are often capitalized. The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document
        are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      <t>This section describes the various variables and functions used in the EAP-GPSK method.</t>
      <t>Variables:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="CSuite_List:"> An octet array listing available ciphersuites (variable
              length)<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="CSuite_Sel:"> Ciphersuite selected by the peer (6 octets)<vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="ID_Peer:"> Peer NAI <xref target="RFC4282"/>
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="ID_Server:"> Server identity as an opaque blob.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="KS:"> Integer representing the key size in octets of the selected ciphersuite
            CSuite_Sel. The key size is one of the ciphersuite parameters.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="PD_Payload:"> Data carried within the protected data payload<vspace
              blankLines="1"/></t>
          <t hangText="PD_Payload_Block:"> Block of possibly multiple PD_Payloads carried by a GPSK
              packet<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
          <t hangText="PL:"> Integer representing the length of the PSK in octets (2 octets) <vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="RAND_Peer:"> Random integer generated by the peer (32 octets)<vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="RAND_Server:"> Random integer generated by the server (32 octets)<vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Operations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="A || B:"> Concatenation of octet strings A and B<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="A**B:"> Integer exponentiation <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="truncate(A,B):"> Returns the first B octets of A<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
          <t hangText="ENC_X(Y):"> Encryption of message Y with a symmetric key X, using a defined
            block cipher<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="KDF_X(Y):"> Key Derivation Function that generates an arbitrary number of
            octets of output using secret X and seed Y<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
          <t hangText="length(X):"> Function that returns the length of input X in octets, encoded
            as a 2-octet integer in network byte order<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="MAC_X(Y):"> Keyed message authentication code computed over Y with symmetric
            key X<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="SEC_X(Y):"> SEC is a function that provides integrity protection based on the
            chosen ciphersuite. The function SEC uses the algorithm defined by the selected
            ciphersuite and applies it to the message content Y with key X. In short, SEC_X(Y) = Y
            || MAC_X(Y). <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="X[A..B]:"> Notation representing octets A through B of octet array X<vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>The following abbreviations are used for the keying material:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="EMSK:"> Extended Master Session Key is exported by the EAP method (64
              octets)<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="MK:"> Master Key between the peer and EAP server from which all other EAP
            method session keys are derived (KS octets)<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="MSK:"> Master Session Key exported by the EAP method (64 octets)<vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="PK:"> Session key generated from the MK and used during protocol exchange to
            encrypt protected data (KS octets)<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="PSK:"> Long-term key shared between the peer and the server (PL
              octets)<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="SK:"> Session key generated from the MK and used during protocol exchange to
            demonstrate knowledge of the PSK (KS octets)<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="overview" title="Overview">
      <t>The EAP framework (see Section 1.3 of <xref target="RFC3748"/>) defines three basic steps
        that occur during the execution of an EAP conversation between the EAP peer, the
        Authenticator and the EAP server.</t>
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>The first phase, discovery, is handled by the underlying protocol.</t>
          <t>The EAP authentication phase with EAP-GPSK is defined in this document.</t>
          <t>The secure association distribution and secure association phases are handled
            differently depending on the underlying protocol.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>EAP-GPSK performs mutual authentication between EAP peer ("Peer") and EAP server ("Server")
        based on a pre-shared key (PSK). The protocol consists of four message exchanges (GPSK-1,
        ..., GPSK-4), in which both sides exchange nonces and their identities, compute and exchange
        a Message Authentication Code (MAC) over the previously exchanged values, keyed with the
        pre-shared key. This MAC is considered as proof of possession of the pre-shared key.</t>

      <t>A successful protocol exchange is shown in <xref target="eap-gpsk-success"/>.</t>

      <t>
        <figure anchor="eap-gpsk-success" title="EAP-GPSK: Successful Exchange">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
+--------+                                     +--------+
|        |                EAP-Request/Identity |        |
|  EAP   |<------------------------------------|  EAP   |
|  peer  |                                     | server |
|        | EAP-Response/Identity               |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        |                  EAP-Request/GPSK-1 |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        | EAP-Response/GPSK-2                 |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        |                  EAP-Request/GPSK-3 |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        | EAP-Response/GPSK-4                 |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        |          EAP-Success                |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
+--------+                                     +--------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>The full EAP-GPSK protocol is as follows: <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="GPSK-1:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> ID_Server, RAND_Server, CSuite_List <vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="GPSK-2:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> SEC_SK(ID_Peer, ID_Server, RAND_Peer,
            RAND_Server, CSuite_List, CSuite_Sel, [ ENC_PK(PD_Payload_Block) ] ) <vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="GPSK-3:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> SEC_SK(RAND_Peer, RAND_Server, ID_Server,
            CSuite_Sel, [ ENC_PK(PD_Payload_Block) ] ) <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="GPSK-4:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> SEC_SK( [ ENC_PK(PD_Payload_Block) ] )
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>The EAP server begins EAP-GPSK by selecting a random number RAND_Server and by encoding the
        supported ciphersuites into CSuite_List. A ciphersuite consists of an encryption algorithm,
        a key derivation function and a message authentication code.</t>
      <t>In GPSK-1, the EAP server sends its identity ID_Server, a random number RAND_Server and a
        list of supported ciphersuites CSuite_List. The decision which ciphersuite to offer and
        which ciphersuite to pick is policy- and implementation-dependent and therefore outside the
        scope of this document.</t>
      <t>In GPSK-2, the peer sends its identity ID_Peer and a random number RAND_Peer. Furthermore,
        it repeats the received parameters of the GPSK-1 message (ID_Server, RAND_Server,
        CSuite_List) and the selected ciphersuite. It computes a Message Authentication Code over
        all the transmitted parameters.</t>
      <t>The EAP server verifies the received Message Authentication Code. In case of successful
        verification, the EAP server computes a Message Authentication Code over the session
        parameter and returns it to the peer (within GPSK-3). Within GPSK-2 and GPSK-3, peer and EAP
        server have the possibility to exchange encrypted protected data parameters.</t>
      <t>The peer verifies the received Message Authentication Code. If the verification is
        successful, GPSK-4 is prepared. This message can optionally contain the peer's protected
        data parameters.</t>
      <t>Upon receipt of GPSK-4, the server processes any included PD_Payload_Block. Then, the EAP
        server sends an EAP Success message to indicate the successful outcome of the
        authentication.</t>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="keyderivation" title="Key Derivation">
      <t>EAP-GPSK provides key derivation in compliance to the requirements of <xref
          target="RFC3748"/> and <xref target="I-D.ietf-eap-keying"/>. Note that this section
        provides an abstract description for the key derivation procedure that needs to be
        instantiated with a specific ciphersuite. </t>
      <t>The long-term credential shared between EAP peer and EAP server SHOULD be a strong
        pre-shared key PSK of at least 16 octets, though its length and entropy is variable. While
        it is possible to use a password or passphrase, doing so is NOT RECOMMENDED as it would make
        EAP-GPSK vulnerable to dictionary attacks.</t>
      <t>During an EAP-GPSK authentication, a Master Key MK, a Session Key SK and a Protected Data
        Encryption Key PK (if using an encrypting ciphersuite) are derived using the
        ciphersuite-specified KDF and data exchanged during the execution of the protocol, namely
        'RAND_Peer || ID_Peer || RAND_Server || ID_Server' referred as inputString as its short-hand
        form.</t>
      <t>In case of successful completion, EAP-GPSK derives and exports an MSK and EMSK both in
        length of 64 octets.</t>
      <t>The following notation is used: KDF-X(Y, Z)[A..B], whereby <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="X">is the length, in octets, of the desired output,</t>
          <t hangText="Y">is a secret key,</t>
          <t hangText="Z">is the inputString,</t>
          <t hangText="[A..B]">extracts the string of octets starting with octet A finishing with
            octet B from the output of the KDF function.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> This keying material is derived using the ciphersuite-specified KDF as follows:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>inputString = RAND_Peer || ID_Peer || RAND_Server || ID_Server</t>
          <t>zero = 0x00 || 0x00 || ... || 0x00 (KS times) <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
          <t>MK = KDF-KS(zero, PL || PSK || CSuite_Sel || inputString)[0..KS-1]</t>
          <t>MSK = KDF-{128+2*KS}(MK, inputString)[0..63]</t>
          <t>EMSK = KDF-{128+2*KS}(MK, inputString)[64..127]</t>
          <t>SK = KDF-{128+2*KS}(MK, inputString)[128..127+KS]</t>
          <t>PK = KDF-{128+2*KS}(MK, inputString)[128+KS..127+2*KS] (if using an encrypting
            ciphersuite)</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Additionally, the EAP keying framework <xref target="I-D.ietf-eap-keying"/> requires the
        definition of a Method-ID, Session-ID, Peer-ID, and Server-ID. These values are defined as:</t>

      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>zero = 0x00 || 0x00 || ... || 0x00 (KS times)</t>
          <t>Method-ID = KDF-16(zero, "Method ID" || EAP_Method_Type || CSuite_Sel ||
            inputString)[0..15]</t>
          <t>Session-ID = Type_Code || Method_ID</t>
          <t>Peer-ID = ID_Peer</t>
          <t>Server-ID = ID_Server</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>EAP_Method_Type refers to the integer value of the IANA allocated EAP Type code. </t>
      <t>
        <xref target="keyderiv"/> depicts the key derivation procedure of EAP-GPSK.</t>
      <t>
        <figure title="EAP-GPSK Key Derivation" anchor="keyderiv">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
+-------------+     +-------------------------------+
|   PL-octet  |     | RAND_Peer || ID_Peer ||       |
|     PSK     |     | RAND_Server || ID_Server      |
+-------------+     +-------------------------------+
       |                            |            |
       |     +------------+         |            |
       |     | CSuite_Sel |         |            |
       |     +------------+         |            |
       |           |                |            |
       v           v                v            |
+--------------------------------------------+   |
|                    KDF                     |   |
+--------------------------------------------+   |
                          |                      |
                          v                      |
                   +-------------+               |
                   |   KS-octet  |               |
                   |     MK      |               |
                   +-------------+               |
                          |                      |
                          v                      v
+---------------------------------------------------+
|                      KDF                          |
+---------------------------------------------------+
     |             |             |            | 
     v             v             v            v
+---------+   +---------+  +----------+  +----------+
| 64-octet|   | 64-octet|  | KS-octet |  | KS-octet |
|   MSK   |   |  EMSK   |  |    SK    |  |   PK     |
+---------+   +---------+  +----------+  +----------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Ciphersuites">
      <t>The design of EAP-GPSK allows cryptographic algorithms and key sizes, called ciphersuites,
        to be negotiated during the protocol run. The ability to specify block-based and hash-based
        ciphersuites is offered. Extensibility is provided with the introduction of new
        ciphersuites; this document specifies an initial set. The CSuite/Specifier column in <xref
          target="ciphersuites"/> uniquely identifies a ciphersuite.</t>
      <t>For a vendor-specific ciphersuite the first three octets are the vendor-specific Object
        Identifier (OID) contains the IANA assigned "SMI Network Management Private Enterprise
        Codes" value (see <xref target="RFC3232"/>), encoded in network byte order. The last three
        octets are vendor assigned for the specific ciphersuite.</t>
      <t>The following ciphersuites are specified in this document: </t>
      <t>
        <figure title="Ciphersuites" anchor="ciphersuites">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
+-----------+----+-------------+--------------+----------------+
| CSuite/   | KS | Encryption  | Integrity /  | Key Derivation |
| Specifier |    |             | KDF MAC      | Function       |
+-----------+----+-------------+--------------+----------------+
| 0x000001  | 16 | AES-CBC-128 | AES-CMAC-128 | GKDF           |
+-----------+----+-------------+--------------+----------------+
| 0x000002  | 32 | NULL        | HMAC-SHA256  | GKDF           |
+-----------+----+-------------+--------------+----------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>Ciphersuite 1, which is based on AES as a cryptographic primitive, is mandatory to
        implement. This document specifies also a second ciphersuite, but its support is optional.
        Both ciphersuites defined in this document make use of the GKDF, as defined in <xref
          target="gkdf-section"/>. The following aspects need to be considered to ensure that the
        PSK that is used as input to the GKDF is sufficiently long (in case it is longer it needs to
        be truncated): </t>
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t> The PSK used with ciphersuite 1 MUST be 128 bits in length or longer. </t>
          <t>The PSK used with ciphersuite 2 MUST be 256 bits in length or longer. </t>
          <t> It is RECOMMENDED that 256 bit keys be provisioned in all cases to provide enough
            entropy for all current and many possible future ciphersuites. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Ciphersuites defined in the future that make use of the GKDF need to specify a minimum PSK
        size (as it is done with the ciphersuites listed in this document). </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="gkdf-section" title="Generalized Key Derivation Function (GKDF)">

      <t>Each ciphersuite needs to specify a key derivation function. The ciphersuites defined in
        this document make use of the Generalized Key Derivation Function (GKDF) that utilizes the
        MAC function defined in the ciphersuite. Future ciphersuites can use any other formally
        specified KDF that takes as arguments a key and a seed value, and produces at least 128+2*KS
        octets of output.</t>

      <t>GKDF has the following structure: </t>
      <t>GKDF-X(Y, Z)</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="X">length, in octets, of the desired output</t>
          <t hangText="Y">secret key</t>
          <t hangText="Z">inputString</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
GKDF-X (Y, Z) 
{
  n = ceiling integer of ( X / KS ); 
     /* determine number of output blocks */

  M_0 = "";
  result = "";

  for i = 1 to n {
    M_i = MAC_Y (i || Z);
    result = result || M_i;
  }

  return truncate(result, X)
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>Note that the variable 'i' in M_i is represented as a 2-octet value in network byte
      order.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Ciphersuites Processing Rules">
      <section title="Ciphersuite #1">
        <section title="Encryption">
          <t>With this ciphersuite all cryptography is built around a single cryptographic
            primitive, AES-128 (<xref target="AES"/>). Within the protected data frames, AES-128 is
            used in Cipher Block Chaining (CBC) mode of operation (see <xref target="CBC"/>). This
            EAP method uses encryption in a single payload, in the protected data payload (see <xref
              target="protected-data"/>). </t>
          <t>In a nutshell, the CBC mode proceeds as follows. The IV is XORed with the first
            plaintext block before it is encrypted. Then for successive blocks, the previous
            ciphertext block is XORed with the current plaintext, before it is encrypted.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Integrity">
          <t>Ciphersuite 1 uses CMAC as Message Authentication Code. CMAC is recommended by NIST.
            Among its advantages, CMAC is capable to work with messages of arbitrary length. A
            detailed description of CMAC can be found in <xref target="CMAC"/>.<vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t>The following instantiation is used: AES-CMAC-128(SK, Input) denotes the MAC of Input
            under the key SK.</t>
          <t>where Input refers to the following content:</t>
          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Value of SEC_SK(Value) in message GPSK-2</t>
              <t>Value of SEC_SK(Value) in message GPSK-3</t>
              <t>Value of SEC_SK(Value) in message GPSK-4</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Key Derivation">
          <t>This ciphersuite instantiates the KDF in the following way:</t>
          <t>inputString = RAND_Peer || ID_Peer || RAND_Server || ID_Server</t>
          <t>MK = GKDF-16 (PSK[0..127], PL || PSK || CSuite_Sel || inputString)</t>
          <t>MSK = GKDF-160 (MK, inputString)[0..63]</t>
          <t>EMSK = GKDF-160 (MK, inputString)[64..127]</t>
          <t>SK = GKDF-160 (MK, inputString)[128..143]</t>
          <t>PK = GKDF-160 (MK, inputString)[144..159]</t>
          <t>Method-ID = GKDF-16 (zero, "Method ID" || EAP_Method_Type || CSuite_Sel ||
          inputString)</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Ciphersuite #2">
        <section title="Encryption">
          <t>Ciphersuite 2 does not include an algorithm for encryption. With a NULL encryption
            algorithm, encryption is defined as:</t>
          <t>E_X(Y) = Y </t>
          <t>When using this ciphersuite, the data exchanged inside the protected data block is not
            encrypted. Therefore this mode MUST NOT be used if confidential information appears
            inside the protected data block.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Integrity">
          <t>Ciphersuite 2 uses the keyed MAC function HMAC, with the SHA256 hash algorithm (see
              <xref target="RFC4634"/>).</t>
          <t>For integrity protection the following instantiation is used:</t>
          <t>HMAC-SHA256(SK, Input) denotes the MAC of Input under the key SK where Input refers to
            the following content:</t>
          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Value of SEC_SK(Value) in message GPSK-2</t>
              <t>Value of SEC_SK(Value) in message GPSK-3</t>
              <t>Value of SEC_SK(Value) in message GPSK-4</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Key Derivation">
          <t>This ciphersuite instantiates the KDF in the following way:</t>
          <t>inputString = RAND_Peer || ID_Peer || RAND_Server || ID_Server</t>
          <t>MK = GKDF-32 (PSK[0..255], PL || PSK || CSuite_Sel || inputString)</t>
          <t>MSK = GKDF-160 (MK, inputString)[0..63]</t>
          <t>EMSK = GKDF-160 (MK, inputString)[64..127]</t>
          <t>SK = GKDF-160 (MK, inputString)[128..159]</t>
          <t>Method-ID = GKDF-16 (zero, "Method ID" || EAP_Method_Type || CSuite_Sel ||
          inputString)</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Packet Formats">
      <t>This section defines the packet format of the EAP-GPSK messages.</t>
      <section title="Header Format">
        <t>The EAP-GPSK header has the following structure:</t>
        <figure anchor="gpskpacket">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
--- bit offset --->
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Code      |  Identifier   |            Length             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |    OP-Code    |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                                                               |
...                         Payload                           ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>The Code, Identifier, Length, and Type fields are all part of the EAP header, and defined
          in <xref target="RFC3748"/>. IANA has allocated EAP Method Type XX for EAP-GPSK, thus the
          Type field in the EAP header MUST be XX.</t>
        <t>The OP-Code field is one of four values:</t>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>0x01 : GPSK-1</t>
            <t>0x02 : GPSK-2</t>
            <t>0x03 : GPSK-3</t>
            <t>0x04 : GPSK-4</t>
            <t>0x05 : GPSK-Fail</t>
            <t>0x06 : GPSK-Protected-Fail</t>
          </list> All other values of this OP-Code field are available via IANA registration. </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Ciphersuite Formatting">
        <t>Ciphersuites are encoded as 6-octet arrays. The first four octets indicate the
          CSuite/Vendor field. For vendor-specific ciphersuites, this represents the vendor Object
          Identifier (OID) contains the IANA assigned "SMI Network Management Private Enterprise
          Codes" value (see <xref target="RFC3232"/>), encoded in network byte order. The last two
          octets indicate the CSuite/Specifier field, which identifies the particular ciphersuite.
          The 4-octet CSuite/Vendor value 0x00000000 indicates ciphersuites allocated by the IETF.</t>
        <t>Graphically, they are represented as<figure anchor="thing">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
--- bit offset --->
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        CSuite/Vendor = 0x00000000 or OID                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      CSuite/Specifier         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>CSuite_Sel is encoded as a 6-octet ciphersuite CSuite/Vendor and CSuite/Specifier pair.</t>
        <t>CSuite_List is a variable-length octet array of ciphersuites. It is encoded by
          concatenating encoded ciphersuite values. Its length in octets MUST be a multiple of
        6.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Payload Formatting">
        <t>Payload formatting is based on the protocol exchange description in <xref
            target="overview"/>.</t>
        <t>The GPSK-1 payload format is defined as follows:</t>
        <t>
          <figure anchor="payload-gpsk-1" title="GPSK-1 Payload">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
--- bit offset --->
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       length(ID_Server)       |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                                                               |
...                         ID_Server                         ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                   32-octet RAND_Server                    ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      length(CSuite_List)      |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                                                               |
...                        CSuite_List                        ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>The GPSK-2 payload format is defined as follows:</t>
        <t>
          <figure anchor="payload-gpsk-2" title="GPSK-2 Payload">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
--- bit offset --->
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        length(ID_Peer)        |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                                                               |
...                         ID_Peer                         ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       length(ID_Server)       |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                                                               |
...                         ID_Server                         ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                     32-octet RAND_Peer                    ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                    32-octet RAND_Server                   ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      length(CSuite_List)      |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                                                               |
...                        CSuite_List                        ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           CSuite_Sel                          |
+                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                               |   length(PD_Payload_Block)    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                 optional PD_Payload_Block                 ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                   KS-octet payload MAC                    ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>If the optional protected data payload is not included, then length(PD_Payload_Block)=0
          and the PD payload is excluded.</t>
        <t>The GPSK-3 payload is defined as follows:</t>
        <t>
          <figure anchor="payload-gpsk-3" title="GPSK-3 Payload">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
--- bit offset --->
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                    32-octet RAND_Peer                   ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                    32-octet RAND_Server                   ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       length(ID_Server)       |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                                                               |
...                         ID_Server                         ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           CSuite_Sel                          |
+                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                               |   length(PD_Payload_Block)    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                 optional PD_Payload_Block                 ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                   KS-octet payload MAC                    ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>If the optional protected data payload is not included, then length(PD_Payload_Block)=0
          and the PD payload is excluded.</t>
        <t>The GPSK-4 payload format is defined as follows:</t>
        <t>
          <figure anchor="payload-gpsk-4" title="GPSK-4 Payload">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
--- bit offset --->
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   length(PD_Payload_Block)    |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                                                               |
...                 optional PD_Payload_Block                 ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                   KS-octet payload MAC                    ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>If the optional protected data payload is not included, then length(PD_Payload_Block)=0
          and the PD payload is excluded. The MAC MUST always be included, regardless of the
          presence of PD_Payload_Block.</t>

        <t>The GPSK-Fail payload format is defined as follows:</t>
        <t>
          <figure anchor="payload-gpsk-fail" title="GPSK-Fail Payload">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
--- bit offset --->
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         Failure-Code                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>The GPSK-Protected-Fail payload format is defined as follows:</t>
        <t>
          <figure anchor="payload-gpsk-protected-fail" title="GPSK-Protected-Fail Payload">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
--- bit offset --->
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         Failure-Code                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                   KS-octet payload MAC                    ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>The Failure-Code field is one of three values, but can be extended:</t>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>0x00000001: PSK Not Found</t>
            <t>0x00000002: Authentication Failure</t>
            <t>0x00000003: Authorization Failure</t>
          </list> All other values of this field are available via IANA registration. </t>
        <t>"PSK Not Found" indicates a key for a particular user could not be located, making
          authentication impossible. "Authentication Failure" indicates a MAC failure due to a PSK
          mismatch. "Authorization Failure" indicates that while the PSK being used is correct, the
          user is not authorized to connect.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="protected-data" title="Protected Data">
        <t>The protected data blocks are a generic mechanism for the peer and server to securely
          exchange data. If the specified ciphersuite has a NULL encryption primitive, then this
          channel only offers authenticity, and not confidentiality.</t>
        <t>These payloads are encoded as the concatenation of type-length-value (TLV) triples called
          PD_Payloads.</t>
        <t>Type values are encoded as a 6-octet string and represented by a 4-octet vendor and
          2-octet specifier field. The vendor field indicates the type as either standards-specified
          or vendor-specific. If these four octets are 0x00000000, then the value is
          standards-specified, and any other value represents a vendor-specific Object Identifier
          (OID).</t>
        <t>The specifier field indicates the actual type. For vendor field 0x00000000, the specifier
          field is maintained by IANA. For any other vendor field, the specifier field is maintained
          by the vendor.</t>
        <t>Length fields are specified as 2-octet integers in network byte order, and reflect only
          the length of the value, and do not include the length of the type and length fields.</t>
        <t>Graphically, this can be depicted as follows:</t>
        <t>
          <figure title="Protected Data Payload (PD_Payload) Formatting">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
--- bit offset --->
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                   PData/Vendor                |              ...
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
         PData/Specifier        |         PData/Length          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                        PData/Value                        ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>These PD_Payloads are concatenated together to form a PD_Payload_Block. The If the
          CSuite_Sel includes support for encryption, then the PD_Payload_Block includes fields
          specifying an initialization vector (IV), and the necessary padding. This can be depicted
          as follows:</t>

        <t>
          <figure title="Protected Data Block (PD_Payload_Block) Formatting if Encryption Supported">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
--- bit offset --->
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Initialization Vector                    |
...       (length is block size for encryption algorithm)     ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                        PD_Payload                         ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                 optional PD_Payload, etc                  ...
|                                                               |
+               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|               |             Padding (0-255 octets)            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                               |  Pad Length   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t> The Initialization Vector is a randomly chosen value whose length is equal to the block
          length of the underlying encryption algorithm. Recipients MUST accept any value. Senders
          SHOULD either pick this value pseudo-randomly and independently for each message or use
          the final ciphertext block of the previous message sent. Senders MUST NOT use the same
          value for each message, use a sequence of values with low hamming distance (e.g., a
          sequence number), or use ciphertext from a received message. </t>

        <t>The concatenation of PD_Payloads along with the padding and padding length are all
          encrypted using the negotiated block cipher. If no block cipher is specified, then these
          fields are not encrypted. </t>

        <t>The Padding field MAY contain any value chosen by the sender, and MUST have a length that
          makes the combination of the concatenation of PD_Payloads, the Padding, and the Pad Length
          to be a multiple of the encryption block size. </t>

        <t>The Pad Length field is the length of the Padding field. The sender SHOULD set the Pad
          Length to the minimum value that makes the combination of the PD_Payloads, the Padding,
          and the Pad Length a multiple of the block size, but the recipient MUST accept any length
          that results in proper alignment. This field is encrypted with the negotiated cipher. </t>

        <t>If the negotiated ciphersuite does not support encryption, then the padding field MUST be
          of length zero. The padding length field MUST still be present, and contain the value
          zero. This is depicted in the following figure.</t>

        <t>
          <figure title="Protected Data Block (PD_Payload_Block) Formatting Without Encryption">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
--- bit offset --->
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                        PD_Payload                         ...
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
...                 optional PD_Payload, etc    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                               |      0x00     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>For PData/Vendor field 0x000000, the following PData/Specifier fields are defined: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>0x000000 : Reserved</t>
            <t>0x000001 : Protected Results Indication</t>
          </list> All other values of this field are available via IANA registration. </t>

        <section title="Protected Results Indication">
          <t>Based on the PData/Specifier allocation the following 8-bit payload is specified to be
            placed in the PD_Payload Value to provide the functionality of protected results
            indication. </t>
          <t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
     0                
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |I|R|R|R|R|R|R|R|
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

     I: Result Indicator
        
        The bits have the following meaning:
                
        (0): Success
        (1): Failure 

     R: Reserved 
        These bits are used for padding. 
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t>The 8 bits of protected results indication functionality, which does not require
            confidentiality protection, MUST only be sent in GPSK-3 from the EAP server to the EAP
            peer. </t>
        </section>

      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section title="Packet Processing Rules">

      <t>This section defines how the EAP peer and EAP server MUST behave when received packet is
        deemed invalid.</t>

      <t>Any EAP-GPSK packet that cannot be parsed by the EAP peer or the EAP server MUST be
        silently discarded. An EAP peer or EAP server receiving any unexpected packet (e.g., an EAP
        peer receiving GPSK-3 before receiving GPSK-1 or before transmitting GPSK-2) MUST silently
        discard the packet.</t>

      <t>GPSK-1 contains no MAC protection, so provided it properly parses, it MUST be accepted by
        the peer. Note that the ciphersuite list provided by the EAP server in CSuite_List MUST
        always include the mandatory-to-implement ciphersuite defined in this document. Hence, there
        is always at least one ciphersuite in common between the EAP peer and the EAP server. If the
        EAP peer decides the ID_Server is that of a AAA server to which it does not wish to
        authenticate, the EAP peer should respond with an EAP-NAK.</t>

      <t>For GPSK-2, if ID_Peer is for an unknown user, the EAP server MUST send either a "PSK Not
        Found" GPSK-Fail message, or an "Authentication Failure" GPSK-Fail, depending on its policy,
        and discard the received packet. If the MAC validation fails, the server MUST transmit a
        GPSK-Fail message specifying "Authentication Failure" and discard the received packet. If
        the RAND_Server or CSuite_List field in GPSK-2 does not match the values in GPSK-1, the
        server MUST silently discard the packet. If server policy determines the peer is not
        authorized and the MAC is correct, the server MUST transmit a GPSK-Protected-Fail message
        indicating "Authorization Failure" and discard the received packet.</t>

      <t>A peer receiving a GPSK-Fail / GPSK-Protected-Fail message in response to a GPSK-2 message
        MUST replay the received GPSK-Fail / GPSK-Protected-Fail message. Then, the EAP server
        returns an EAP-Failure after receiving the GPSK-Fail / GPSK-Protected-Fail message to
        correctly finish the EAP conversation. If MAC validation on a GPSK-Protected-Fail packet
        fails, then the received packet MUST be silently discarded.</t>

      <t>For GPSK-3, a peer MUST silently discard messages where the RAND_Peer, the RAND_Server, or
        the CSuite_Sel fields do match those transmitted in GPSK-2. An EAP peer MUST silently
        discard any packet whose MAC fails.</t>

      <t>For GPSK-4, a server MUST silently discard any packet whose MAC fails validation.</t>

      <t>If a decryption failure of a protected payload is detected, the recipient MUST silently
        discard the GPSK packet.</t>

    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section title="Example Message Exchanges">

      <t>This section shows a couple of example message flows. </t>

      <t> A successful EAP-GPSK message exchange is shown in <xref target="eap-gpsk-success"/>.</t>
      <t>
        <figure
          title="EAP-GPSK: Unsuccessful Exchange (Unacceptable AAA server identity; ID_Server)">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
+--------+                                     +--------+
|        |                EAP-Request/Identity |        |
|  EAP   |<------------------------------------|  EAP   |
|  peer  |                                     | server |
|        | EAP-Response/Identity               |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        |                  EAP-Request/GPSK-1 |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        | EAP-Response/EAP-NAK                |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        |          EAP-Failure                |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
+--------+                                     +--------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>


      <t>
        <figure title="EAP-GPSK: Unsuccessful Exchange (Unknown user)">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
+--------+                                     +--------+
|        |                EAP-Request/Identity |        |
|  EAP   |<------------------------------------|  EAP   |
|  peer  |                                     | server |
|        | EAP-Response/Identity               |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        |                  EAP-Request/GPSK-1 |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        | EAP-Response/GPSK-2                 |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        | EAP-Request/GPSK-3 (GPSK-Fail       |        |
|        | (PSK Not Found or Authentication    |        |
|        | Failure))                           |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        | EAP-Response/GPSK-4 (GPSK-Fail      |        |
|        | (PSK Not Found or Authentication    |        |
|        | Failure))                           |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        |          EAP-Failure                |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
+--------+                                     +--------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>
        <figure title="EAP-GPSK: Unsuccessful Exchange (Invalid MAC in GPSK-2)">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
+--------+                                     +--------+
|        |                EAP-Request/Identity |        |
|  EAP   |<------------------------------------|  EAP   |
|  peer  |                                     | server |
|        | EAP-Response/Identity               |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        |                  EAP-Request/GPSK-1 |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        | EAP-Response/GPSK-2                 |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        | EAP-Request/GPSK-3 (GPSK-Fail       |        |
|        | (Authentication Failure))           |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        | EAP-Response/GPSK-4 (GPSK-Fail      |        |
|        | (Authentication Failure))           |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        |          EAP-Failure                |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
+--------+                                     +--------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>
        <figure title="EAP-GPSK: Unsuccessful Exchange (Authorization failure)">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
+--------+                                     +--------+
|        |                EAP-Request/Identity |        |
|  EAP   |<------------------------------------|  EAP   |
|  peer  |                                     | server |
|        | EAP-Response/Identity               |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        |                  EAP-Request/GPSK-1 |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        | EAP-Response/GPSK-2                 |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        | EAP-Request/GPSK-3                  |        |
|        | GPSK-Protected-Fail                 |        |
|        | (Authorization Failure)             |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        | EAP-Request/GPSK-4                  |        |
|        | GPSK-Protected-Fail                 |        |
|        | (Authorization Failure)             |        |
|        |------------------------------------>|        |
|        |                                     |        |
|        |          EAP-Failure                |        |
|        |<------------------------------------|        |
+--------+                                     +--------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

    </section>


    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="seccons" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        <xref target="RFC3748"/> highlights several attacks that are possible against EAP since EAP
        itself does not provide any security.</t>
      <t>This section discusses the claimed security properties of EAP-GPSK as well as
        vulnerabilities and security recommendations in the threat model of <xref target="RFC3748"
        />.</t>
      <section anchor="mut" title="Mutual Authentication">
        <t>EAP-GPSK provides mutual authentication.</t>
        <t>The server believes that the peer is authentic when it successfully verifies the MAC in
          the GPSK-2 message and the peer believes that the server is authentic when it successfully
          verifies the MAC it receives with the GPSK-3 message.</t>
        <t>The key used for mutual authentication is derived based on the long-term secret PSK,
          nonces contributed by both parties and other parameters. The long-term secret PSK has to
          provide sufficient entropy and therefore sufficient strength. The nonces (RAND_Peer and
          RAND_Server) need to be fresh and unique for every session. In this way EAP-GPSK is not
          different than other authentication protocols based on pre-shared keys.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="protr" title="Protected Result Indications">
        <t>EAP-GPSK offers the capability to exchange protected result indications using the
          protected data payloads.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="int" title="Integrity Protection">
        <t>EAP-GPSK provides integrity protection based on the ciphersuites suggested in this
          document. Integrity protection is a minimum feature every ciphersuite must provide.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="repl" title="Replay Protection">
        <t>EAP-GPSK provides replay protection of its mutual authentication part thanks to the use
          of random numbers RAND_Server and RAND_Peer. Since RAND_Server is 32 octets long, one
          expects to have to record 2**64 (i.e., approximately 1.84*10**19) EAP-GPSK successful
          authentication before an protocol run can be replayed. Hence, EAP-GPSK provides replay
          protection of its mutual authentication part as long as RAND_Server and RAND_Peer are
          chosen at random, randomness is critical for replay protection. <xref target="RFC4086">RFC
            4086</xref> describes techniques for producing random quantities.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="refl" title="Reflection attacks">
        <t>EAP-GPSK provides protection against reflection attacks in case of an extended
          authentication because the messages are constructed in a different fashion.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="dic" title="Dictionary Attacks">
        <t>EAP-GPSK relies on a long-term shared secret (PSK) that MUST be based on at least 16
          octets of entropy to guarantee security against dictionary attacks. Users who use
          passwords are not guaranteed protection against dictionary attacks. Derivation of the
          long-term shared secret from a password is strongly discouraged.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="keyder" title="Key Derivation">
        <t>EAP-GPSK supports key derivation as shown in <xref target="keyderivation"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="dos" title="Denial of Service Resistance">
        <t>There are two forms of denial of service attacks relevant for this document, namely
          attacks that lead to vast amount of state being allocated and attacks against the
          computational resources. The latter onces are less problematic for EAP-GPSK since all
          computations are lightweight. We will consider the former one in more detail below.</t>
        <t>In an EAP-GPSK conversation the server has to maintain state, namely the 32-octet
          RAND_Server, when transmitting the GPSK-1 message to the peer. An adversary could
          therefore flood a server with a large number of EAP-GPSK communication attempts. An EAP
          server may therefore ensure that established state times out after a relatively short
          period of time when no further messages are received. This enables a sort of garbage
          collection. </t>
        <t>The client would have to potentially keep state information after receiving the GPSK-1
          message. Section 4.2 of <xref target="HM2004"/> describes a short of client-side denial of
          service attack and illustrates three possible solutions to avoid having the client to keep
          state when receiving the first message. When the client receives the GPSK-3 message then
          it needs to derive keying material based on the following information: RAND_Peer, ID_Peer,
          RAND_Server, ID_Server, RAND_Peer, RAND_Server. Hence, GPSK-3 includes all necessary
          parameters to allow the client to (a) avoid allocating state information with the arrival
          of GPSK-1 and (b) to enable deriving the keying material. </t>
        <t>The security considerations of EAP itself, see Section 5.2 and Section 7 of RFC 3748
            <xref target="RFC3748"/>, are also applicable to this specification (e.g., for example
          concerning EAP-based notifications). </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="ssi" title="Session Independence">
        <t>Thanks to its key derivation mechanisms, EAP-GPSK provides session independence: passive
          attacks (such as capture of the EAP conversation) or active attacks (including compromise
          of the MSK or EMSK) do not enable compromise of subsequent or prior MSKs or EMSKs. The
          assumption that RAND_Peer and RAND_Server are random is central for the security of
          EAP-GPSK in general and session independence in particular.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="expo" title="Exposition of the PSK">
        <t>EAP-GPSK does not provide perfect forward secrecy. Compromise of the PSK leads to
          compromise of recorded past sessions.</t>
        <t>Compromise of the PSK enables the attacker to impersonate the peer and the server and it
          allows the adversary to compromise future sessions.</t>
        <t>EAP-GPSK provides no protection against a legitimate peer sharing its PSK with a third
          party. Such protection may be provided by appropriate repositories for the PSK, which
          choice is outside the scope of this document. The PSK used by EAP-GPSK must only be shared
          between two parties: the peer and the server. In particular, this PSK must not be shared
          by a group of peers communicating with the same server.</t>
        <t>The PSK used by EAP-GPSK must be cryptographically separated from keys used by other
          protocols, otherwise the security of EAP-GPSK may be compromised.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="frag" title="Fragmentation">
        <t>EAP-GPSK does not support fragmentation and reassembly since the message size is
          relatively small.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="cbind" title="Channel Binding">
        <t>This document enables the ability to exchange channel binding information. It does not,
          however, define the encoding of channel binding information in the document.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="freco" title="Fast Reconnect">
        <t>EAP-GPSK does not provide the fast reconnect capability since this method is already at
          (or close to) the lower limit of the number of roundtrips and the cryptographic
          operations.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="idpro" title="Identity Protection">
        <t>Identity protection is not specified in this document. Extensions can be defined that
          enhance this protocol to provide this feature.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="pcn" title="Protected Ciphersuite Negotiation">
        <t>EAP-GPSK provides protected ciphersuite negotiation via the indication of available
          ciphersuites by the server in the first message and a confirmation by the peer in the
          subsequent message. </t>
        <t> Note, however, that the GPSK-2 message may optionally contain a payload,
          ENC_PK(PD_Payload_Block), protected with an algorithm based on a selected ciphersuite
          before the ciphersuite list has actually been authenticated. In the classical downgrading
          attack an adversary would chose a ciphersuite that it weak enough to that it could break
          it in real-time or to turn security off. The latter is not possible since any ciphersuite
          defined for EAP-GPSK must at least provide authentication and integrity protection.
          Confidentity protection is optional. When, some time in the future, a ciphersuite contains
          algorithms that can be broken in real-time then a policy on peers and the server needs to
          indicate that such a ciphersuite must not be selected by any of parties.</t>
        <t>Furthermore, an adversay may modify the selection of the ciphersuite to for the client to
          select a ciphersuite that does not provide confidentity protection. As a result this would
          cause the content of PD_Payload_Block to be transmitted in cleartext. When protocol
          designers extend EAP-GPSK to carry information in the PD_Payload_Block of the GPSK-2
          message then it must be indicated whether confidentiality protection is mandatory. In case
          such an extension requires a ciphersuite with confidentiality protection then the policy
          at the peer must not transmit information of that extension in the PD_Payload_Block of the
          GPSK-2 message. The peer may, if possible, delay the transmission of this information
          element to the GPSK-4 message where the ciphersuite negotiation has been confirmed
          already. In general, when a ciphersuite is selected that does not provide confidentiality
          protection then information that demands confidentility protection must not be included in
          any of the PD_Payload_Block objects. </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="conf" title="Confidentiality">
        <t>Although EAP-GPSK provides confidentiality in its protected data payloads, it cannot
          claim to do so as per Section 7.2.1 of <xref target="RFC3748"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="cryptobind" title="Cryptographic Binding">
        <t>Since EAP-GPSK does not tunnel another EAP method, it does not implement cryptographic
          binding.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document requires IANA to allocate a new EAP Type for EAP-GPSK.</t>

      <t>This document requires IANA to create a new registry for ciphersuites, protected data
        types, failure codes and op-codes. IANA is furthermore instructed to add the specified
        ciphersuites, protected data types, failure codes and op-codes to these registries as
        defined in this document. Values can be added or modified with informational RFCs defining
        either block-based or hash-based ciphersuites, protected data payloads, failure codes and
        op-codes. Each ciphersuite needs to provide processing rules and needs to specify how the
        following algorithms are instantiated: encryption, integrity, key derivation and key length. </t>

      <t><xref target="ciphersuites"/> represents the initial ciphersuite CSuite/Specifier registry
        setup. The CSuite/Specifier field is 16 bits long. All other values are available via IANA
        registration.</t>

      <t>The following is the initial protected data PData/Specifier registry setup:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>0x000000 : Reserved</t>
          <t>0x000001 : Protected Results Indication</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>The PData/Specifier field is 24 bits long and all other values are available via IANA
        registration. Each extension needs to indicate whether confidentiality protection for
        transmission between the EAP peer and the EAP server is mandatory. The following layout
        represents the initial Failure-Code registry setup:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>0x00000001: PSK Not Found</t>
          <t>0x00000002: Authentication Failure</t>
          <t>0x00000003: Authorization Failure</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>The Failure-Code field is 32 bits long and all other values are available via IANA
        registration. The following layout represents the initial OP-Code registry setup:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>0x01 : GPSK-1</t>
          <t>0x02 : GPSK-2</t>
          <t>0x03 : GPSK-3</t>
          <t>0x04 : GPSK-4</t>
          <t>0x05 : GPSK-Fail</t>
          <t>0x06 : GPSK-Protected-Fail</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>The OP-Code field is 8 bits long and all other values are available via IANA registration.
      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>This work is a joint effort of the EAP Method Update (EMU) design team of the EMU Working
        Group that was created to develop a mechanism based on strong shared secrets that meets RFC
        3748 <xref target="RFC3748"/> and RFC 4017 <xref target="RFC4017"/> requirements. The design
        team members (in alphabetical order) were:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Jari Arkko</t>
          <t>Mohamad Badra</t>
          <t>Uri Blumenthal</t>
          <t>Charles Clancy</t>
          <t>Lakshminath Dondeti</t>
          <t>David McGrew</t>
          <t>Joe Salowey</t>
          <t>Sharma Suman</t>
          <t>Hannes Tschofenig</t>
          <t>Jesse Walker</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Finally, we would like to thank Thomas Otto for his draft reviews, feedback and text
        contributions.</t>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>We would like to thank</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Jouni Malinen and Bernard Aboba for their early draft comments in June 2006. Jouni
            Malinen developed the first prototype implementation. It can be found at:
            http://hostap.epitest.fi/releases/snapshots/ </t>
          <t>Lakshminath Dondeti, David McGrew, Bernard Aboba, Michaela Vanderveen and Ray Bell for
            their input to the ciphersuite discussions between July and August 2006.</t>
          <t>Lakshminath Dondeti for his detailed draft review (sent to the EMU ML on the 12th July
            2006).</t>
          <t>Based on a review requested from NIST Quynh Dang suggested changes to the GKDF function
            (December 2006).</t>
          <t>Jouni Malinen and Victor Fajardo for their review in January 2007.</t>
          <t>Jouni Malinen for his suggestions regarding the examples and the key derivation
            function in February 2007.</t>
          <t>Bernard Aboba and Jouni Malinen for their review in February 2007.</t>
          <t>Vidya Narayanan for her review in March 2007.</t>
          <t/>
          <t>Joe Salowey, the EMU working group chair, provided a document review in April 2007.
            Jouni Malinen also reviewed the document during the same month. </t>
          <t>We would like to thank Paul Rowe, Arnab Roy, Prof. Andre Scedrov and Prof. John C.
            Mitchell for their analysis of EAP-GPSK and for pointing us to a client-side DoS attack,
            a downgrading attack and their input to the key derivation function. Based on their
            input the key derivation function has been modified and the text in the security
            consideration section has been updated.</t>
          <t>Finally, we would like to thank our working group chair, Joe Salowey, for his support
            and for the time he spend on discussing open issues with us.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"> &RFC2119; &RFC3748; &RFC4282; </references>
    <references title="Informative References"> &I-D.ietf-eap-keying; &RFC4017;
      &RFC4634; <reference anchor="AES">
        <front>
          <title>Specification for the Advanced Encryption Standard (AES)</title>
          <author>
            <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
          </author>
          <date day="26" month="November" year="2001"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Federal Information Processing Standards (FIPS)" value="197"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="CMAC">
        <front>
          <title>Recommendation for Block Cipher Modes of Operation: The CMAC Mode for
            Authentication</title>
          <author>
            <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="May" year="2005"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Special Publication (SP)" value="800-38B"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="CBC">
        <front>
          <title>Recommendation for Block Cipher Modes of Encryption. Methods and Techniques.</title>
          <author>
            <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2001"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Special Publication (SP)" value="800-38A"/>
      </reference> &RFC3232; &RFC4086; <reference anchor="HM2004">
        <front>
          <title>Analysis of the 802.11i 4-Way Handshake) </title>
          <author initials="C." surname="He" fullname="Changhua He">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Mitchell" fullname="John C. Mitchell">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2004"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo
          name="Proceedings of the Third ACM International Workshop on Wireless Security (WiSe'04), Philadelphia, PA"
          value="pages 43-50"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
