<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc1052 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1052.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2578 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2578.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2613 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2613.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2819 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2819.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2863 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2863.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2865 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2975 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2975.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3060 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3060.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3084 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3084.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3139 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3139.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3159 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3159.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3165 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3165.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3290 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3290.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3317 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3317.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3410 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3410.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3413 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3413.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3418 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3418.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3444 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3444.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3460 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3460.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3535 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3535.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3585 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3585.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3588 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3644 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3644.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3670 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3670.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3805 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3805.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4011 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4011.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4133 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4133.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4502 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4502.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4668 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4668.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4669 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4669.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4710 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4710.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4741 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4741.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4825 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4825.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4930 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4930.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-syslog-protocol SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-syslog-protocol.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-sipping-rtcp-summary SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-sipping-rtcp-summary.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-ietf-opsawg-operations-and-management-01"
     ipr="full3978">
  <!--
  $Id: draft-ietf-opsawg-operations-and-management.xml,v 1.1 2007/09/13 11:03:14 H73653 Exp $
  -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Ops and Mgmt Guidelines">Guidelines for Considering
    Operations and Management of New Protocols</title>

    <author fullname="David Harrington" initials="D" surname="Harrington">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies USA</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1700 Alma Dr, Suite 100</street>

          <city>Plano</city>

          <region>TX</region>

          <code>75075</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 603 436 8634</phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>dharrington@huawei.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2007" />

    <area>IETF Operations and Management Area</area>

    <keyword>management</keyword>

    <keyword>operations</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>New protocols or protocol extensions are best designed with due
      consideration of operations and management issues related to the
      protocol. Retrofitting operations and management recommendations to
      protocols is sub-optimal. The purpose of this document is to provide
      guidance to authors and reviewers of documents defining new protocols or
      protocol extensions, covering aspects of operations and management that
      should be considered.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Often when new protocols or protocol extensions are developed, not
      enough consideration is given to how the protocol will be deployed,
      operated and managed. Retrofitting operations and management mechanisms
      is often hard and architecturally unpleasant, and certain protocol
      design choices may make deployment, operations, and management
      particularly hard. Since operations and management issues may impact the
      success of IETF protocols, this document provides guidelines to help
      protocol designers and working groups consider the operations and
      management issues of their new IETF protocol or protocol extension at an
      earlier phase.</t>

      <t>This document recommends working groups consider operations and
      management needs, and then select appropriate standard management
      protocols and data models to address the relevant operations and
      management needs, just as the WG might consider which security threats
      are relevant to their protocol, and then select appropriate standard
      security protocols to mitigate the relevant threats.</t>

      <t>This document is organized to support such a progressive approach.
      Section 2 discusses the importance of considering operations and
      management. Section 3 discusses operational issues to consider. Section
      4 discusses management issues to consider. Section 5 discusses IETF
      standards-track management protocols and their uses. Section 6 discusses
      specific data models, such as MIB modules, that have been designed to
      address specific sets of issues.</t>

      <t>This document sets forth a list of subjective guidelines and a list
      of objective criteria by which a protocol designer can evaluate whether
      the protocol that he/she has developed addresses common operations and
      management needs. Operations and management is highly dependent on the
      environment in which it is used, so most guidelines are subjective
      rather than objective. We provide objective criteria to promote
      interoperability through the use of standard management interfaces, such
      as "did you design counters in a MIB module for monitoring packets
      in/out of an interface?", "did you write an XML-based data model for
      configuring your protocol with Netconf?", and "did you standardize
      syslog message content and structured data elements for reporting events
      that might occur when operating your protocol?"</t>

      <t>A balance is needed between ensuring operations and management have
      been considered, and getting a protocol specification published in a
      timely fashion. IETF standards-track protocol documents should contain
      enough information to understand how the protocol will be deployed and
      managed. It should be expected that initial considerations for
      operations and management may need to be updated in the future, after
      further operational experience has been gained. This document only
      provides guidelines; the (ever-changing membership of the) IESG can make
      a decision about how the guidelines should be used by the IETF over
      time.</t>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>This document deliberately does not use the (capitalized) key words
        described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>. RFC 2119 states
        the keywords must only be used where it is actually required for
        interoperation or to limit behavior which has potential for causing
        harm (e.g., limiting retransmissions). For example, they must not be
        used to try to impose a particular method on implementers where the
        method is not required for interoperability. This document is a set of
        guidelines based on current practices of protocol designers and
        operators. This document does not describe requirements, so the key
        words from RFC2119 have no place here.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>"new protocol" includes new protocols, protocol extensions,
            data models, or other functionality being designed.</t>

            <t>"working group" represents individuals and working groups
            involved in the development of new protocols.</t>

            <t>[DISCUSS] markers indicate a lack of consensus on what should
            be written.</t>

            <t>[TODO] markers indicate the editor has a reasonable
            understanding of what needs to be (re-)written. Contributions of
            text would be welcome.</t>
            
            <t>Note to RFC Editor - All [DISCUSS] or [TODO] marks should be 
            resolved before RFC publication. If any still exist, including in the
            Terminology section, then please return the 
            document to the editor for resolution.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Design for Operations and Management">
      <t>"Design for operations and management" means that the operational
      environment and manageability of the protocol should be considered from
      the start when new protocols are designed.</t>

      <section title="IETF Management Framework">

        <t>For years the IETF has stressed the use of the IETF Standard Management
        Framework and SMI MIB modules <xref target="RFC2578"></xref> for
        managing new protocols. The IETF designed the Standard Management
        Framework and SMI MIB modules to permit multiple protocols to utilize
        the MIB data <xref target="RFC1052"></xref>, but it became a common
        misunderstanding that a MIB module could only be used with the SNMP
        protocol (described in <xref target="RFC3410"></xref> and associated
        documents).</t>

        <t>In 2001, OPS Area design teams were created to document issues and
        requirements related to configuration of IP-based networks. One output
        was "Requirements for Configuration Management of IP-based Networks"
        <xref target="RFC3139"></xref>. The COPS-PR protocol was developed to address configuration.</t>

        <t>In 2003, the Internet Architecture Board (IAB) held a workshop on
        Network Management <xref target="RFC3535"></xref> that discussed the
        strengths and weaknesses of some IETF network management protocols,
        and compared them to operational needs, especially configuration. </t>
        
       <t>One issue raised was the user-unfriendliness of the binary format of SNMP 
       and COPS-PR, so it was recommended that the IETF explore and XML-based 
       Structure of Management Information, and an XML-based protocol for configuration.</t>
        
        <t>Another issue was that deployed tools for event/alarm correlation, root cause
       analysis and logging are not sufficient, and there is a need to support a human interface 
       and a programmatic interface. The IETF decided to standardize aspects of the defacto
       standard for system logging, especially security and the need for better programmatic
       support.</t>

        <t>In 2006, the IETF discussed how the Management Framework should
        be updated to accommodate multiple IETF standard SMI languages, and multiple 
        IETF standard protocols for doing network management.</t>

        <t>This document provides some initial guidelines for considering operations and management
        in this environment of multiple protocols and multiple data models, with an eye toward being flexible
        while also striving for interoperability.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Operational Considerations">
      <t>When a new protocol is deployed in a network, it may affect the
      network negatively. A working group should consider deployment of a new
      protocol or protocol extension in a network, impact on the network
      operations, traffic levels and operation of other protocols or previous
      versions of the protocol, how the new protocol will be operated, and how
      its presence might affect the existing deployment.</t>

      <t>Operations and manageability considerations should focus on
      interoperability of externally observable behaviors.</t>

      <section title="Operations Model">
        <t>Protocol designers can analyze the operational environment and mode
        of work in which the new protocol or extension will work. Such an
        exercise needs not be reflected directly by text in their document,
        but could help in visualizing the operational model related to the
        applicability of the protocol in the Internet environments where it
        will be deployed. The operational model should take into account
        issues like: <list style="symbols">
            <t>what type of management entities will be involved (agents,
            network management systems)?</t>

            <t>what is the possible architecture (client-server,
            manager-agent, polling-driven or event-driven, autoconfiguration,
            two levels or hierarchical)?</t>

            <t>what are the basic management operations - initial
            configuration, dynamic configuration, alarms and exceptions
            reporting, logging, performance monitoring, performance
            reporting?</t>

            <t>how are these operations performed - locally, remotely, atomic
            operation, scripts?</t>

            <t>what are the typical user interfaces - Command line (CLI) or
            graphical user interface (GUI)?</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Working groups should consider how the new protocol will be managed
        in different deployment scales. It might be sensible to use a local
        management interface to manage the new protocol on a single device,
        but in a large network, remote management using a centralized server
        and/or using distributed management functionality might make more
        sense. Auto-configuration might be possible for some new
        protocols.</t>

        <t>There may be a need to support a human interface, e.g., for
        troubleshooting, and a programmatic interface, e.g., for automated
        monitoring and root cause analysis. It might be important that the
        internal method routines for both interfaces should be the same to
        ensure that data exchanged between these two interfaces is always
        consistent.</t>

        <!--A human interface, such as a command line interface, is
        useful for troubleshooting, while a programmatic interface is
        important for managing multiple devices in a consistent manner, and
        automating repetitive functions. Graphical user interfaces can help an
        operator comprehend an overview of the network quickly (one picture is
        worth a thousand words), but an operator may also require seeing the
        raw data to better understand just what is happening in the network.
        Ease of use is a key requirement for any network management technology
        from the operators point of view. Working groups should consider how
        various protocol choices might impact ease of use in different
        scenarios. -->

        <t>Working groups should consider what management operations are
        expected to be performed as a result of the deployment of the protocol
        - such as whether write operations will be allowed on routers and on
        hosts, or if notifications for alarms or other events will be
        expected.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Installation and Initial Setup">
        <t>Working groups should consider default values that make protocol
        sense, to simplify configuration, including default modes and
        parameters. For example, it could be helpful or necessary to specify
        default values for modes, timers, default state of logical control
        variables, default transports, and so on. Even if default values are
        used, it must be possible to retrieve all the actual values or at
        least an indication that known default values are being used.</t>

        <t>Working groups should consider how to enable operators to
        concentrate on the configuration of the network as a whole rather than
        individual devices.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Migration Path">
        <t>If the new protocol is a new version of the protocol, or is
        replacing another technology, the working group should consider how
        deployments should transition to the new protocol. This should include
        co-existence with previously deployed protocols and/or previous
        versions of the same protocol, incompatibilities between versions,
        translation between versions, and side effects that might occur. Are
        older protocols or versions disabled or do they co-exist in the
        network with the new protocol?</t>

        <t>Another point to consider is extensibility of the management
        approach - How open to future protocol extensions are the management
        techniques you are defining?</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements on Other Protocols and Functional Components">
        <t>Working groups should consider the requirements that the new
        protocol might put on other protocols and functional components, and
        should also document the requirements from other protocols that have
        been considered in designing the new protocol.</t>

        <t>These considerations should generally remain illustrative to avoid
        creating restrictions or dependencies, or potentially impacting the
        behavior of existing protocols, or restricting the extensibility of
        other protocols, or assuming other protocols will not be extended in
        certain ways.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Impact on Network Operation">
        <t>The introduction of a new protocol or extensions to an existing
        protocol may have an impact on the operation of existing networks.
        Protocol designers should outline such impacts (which may be positive)
        including scaling concerns and interactions with other protocols. For
        example, a new protocol that doubles the number of active, reachable
        addresses in use within a network might need to be considered in the
        light of the impact on the scalability of the IGPs operating within
        the network.</t>

        <t>The working group should consider the potential impact on the
        behavior of other protocols in the network and on the traffic levels
        and traffic patterns that might change, including specific types of
        traffic such as multicast. Also consider the need to install new
        components that are added to the network as result of the changes in
        the operational model, such as servers performing auto-configuration
        operations.</t>

        <t>The working group should consider also the impact on applications
        and registries, for example DNS entries, or the size of routing
        tables.</t>
        
<t>The impact on performance may also be noted - increased delay or jitter
in real-time traffic applications, or response time in client-server
applications when encryption or filtering are applied.</t>

        <t>It is important to minimize the impact caused by configuration
        changes. Given configuration A and configuration B, it should be
        possible to generate the operations necessary to get from A to B with
        minimal state changes and effects on network and systems.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Verifying Correct Operation">
        <t>The working group should consider techniques for testing the effect
        that the protocol has had on the network by sending data through the
        network and observing its behavior. Working groups should consider how
        the correct end-to-end operation of the new protocol in the network
        can be tested, and how the correct data or forwarding plane function
        of each network element can be verified to be working properly with
        the new protocol.</t>

        <t>It must be easy to do consistency checks of configurations over
        time and between the ends of a link in order to determine the changes
        between two configurations and whether those configurations are
        consistent.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Management Considerations">
      <t>The considerations of manageability should start from describing the
      operational model, which includes identifying the entities to be
      managed, how the respective protocol is supposed to be installed,
      configured and monitored, who are the managers and what type of
      management interfaces and protocols they would use.</t>

      <t>Considerations for management should include a discussion of what
      needs to be managed. This document, for better or worse, talks mainly
      about management of a protocol endpoint on a single device. It doesn't
      talk about managing the *protocol* (it manages one end at a time), and
      doesn't even come near managing the *service* (which includes a lot of
      stuff that's very far away from the box). In a client/server protocol,
      it may be more important to instrument the server end of a protocol than
      the client end.</t>

      <t>One issue that the IETF has always struggled with (and for which we
      still have no good guidance) is the problem of how to configure multiple
      related/co-operating devices and how to back off if one of those
      configurations fails or causes trouble. NETCONF addresses this somewhat
      by allowing an operator to lock the configuration on multiple devices,
      perform the configuration settings/changes, check that they are OK (undo
      if not) and then unlock the devices.</t>

      <t>Protocol debugging is not part (and should not be part) of the
      Network Management tools/hooks in a system. Debugging is an
      implementation-dependent issue, not a protocol standardization
      issue.</t>

      <section title="Interoperability">
        <t>Just as when deploying protocols that will inter-connect devices,
        our primary goal in considering management should be interoperability,
        whether across devices from different vendors, across models from the
        same vendor, or across different releases of the same product.</t>

        <t>Some product designers and protocol designers assume that if a
        device can be managed individually using a command line interface or a
        web page interface, that such a solution is enough. But when equipment
        from multiple vendors is combined into a large network, scalability of
        management becomes a problem. It is important to have consistency in
        the management interfaces so network-wide operational processes can be
        automated.</t>

        <t>Getting everybody to agree on a certain syntax and the protocol
        associated with that has proven to be difficult. So management systems
        tend to speak whatever the boxes support, whether the IETF likes this
        or not. The IETF is moving from support for a single management data
        modeling language and a single management protocol towards support for
        multiple management protocols and multiple data models suited to
        different purposes, such as logging (syslog), configuration (netconf),
        and usage accounting (ipfix). Other Standard Development Organizations
        (e.g. DMTF, TMF) also define management mechanisms and these
        mechanisms may be more suitable than IETF mechanisms in some
        cases.</t>

        <t>Interoperability needs to be considered on the syntactic level and
        the semantic level. While it can be irritating and time-consuming,
        application designers including operators who write their own scripts
        can make their processing conditional to accommodate differences
        across vendors or models or releases of product.</t>

        <t>Semantic differences are much harder to deal with on the manager
        side - once you have the data, its meaning is a function of the
        managed entity. For example, if a single counter provided by vendor A
        counts three types of error conditions, while the corresponding
        counter provided by vendor B counts seven types of error conditions,
        these counters cannot be compared effectively - they are not
        interoperable counters.</t>

        <t>Information models are helpful to try to focus interoperability on
        the semantic level - they establish standards for what information
        should be gathered, and how gathered information might be used
        regardless of which management interface carries the data or which
        vendor produces the product. The use of an information model might
        help improve the ability of operators to correlate messages in
        different protocols where the data overlaps, such as a SYSLOG message
        and an SNMP notification about the same event. An information model
        might identify which error conditions should be counted separately,
        and which error conditions can be counted together in a single
        counter. Then, whether the counter is gathered via SNMP or a CLI
        command or a SYSLOG message, the counter will have similar
        meaning.</t>

        <t>Protocol designers should consider which information might be
        useful for managing the new protocol or protocol extensions.</t>

        <figure title="Figure 1">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[             IM                --> conceptual/abstract model
              |                    for designers and operators
   +----------+---------+
   |          |         |
   DM        DM         DM     --> concrete/detailed model
                                   for implementers
]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Information Models and Data Models</postamble>
        </figure>

        <t>On the Difference between Information Models and Data Models <xref
        target="RFC3444"> </xref> may be useful in determining what
        information to consider regarding information models, as compared to
        data models.</t>

        <t>Information models should come from the protocol WGs and include
        lists of events, counters and configuration parameters that are
        relevant. There are a number of information models contained in
        protocol WG RFCs. Some examples:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t><xref target="RFC3060"></xref> - Policy Core Information Model
            version 1</t>

            <t><xref target="RFC3290"></xref> - An Informal Management Model
            for DiffServ Routers</t>

            <t><xref target="RFC3460"></xref> - Policy Core Information Model
            Extensions</t>

            <t><xref target="RFC3585"></xref> - IPsec Configuration Policy
            Information Model</t>

            <t><xref target="RFC3644"></xref> - Policy Quality of Service
            Information Model</t>

            <t><xref target="RFC3670"></xref> - Information Model for
            Describing Network Device QoS Datapath Mechanisms</t>

            <t><xref target="RFC3805"></xref> - Printer MIB v2 (contains both
            an IM and a DM</t>
          </list>Management protocol standards and management data model
        standards often contain compliance clauses to ensure interoperability.
        Manageability considerations should include discussion of which level
        of compliance is expected to be supported for interoperability.</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Management Information">
        <t>Operators find it important to be able to make a clear distinction
        between configuration data, operational state, and statistics. They
        need to determine which parameters were administrative configured and
        which parameters have changed since configuration as the result of
        mechanisms such as routing protocols.</t>

        <t>It is important to be able to separately fetch configuration data,
        operational state data, and statistics from devices, and to be able to
        compare current state to initial state, and to compare data between
        devices.</t>

        <t>A management information model should include a discussion of what
        is manageable, which aspects of the protocol need to be configured,
        what types of operations are allowed, what protocol-specific events
        might occur, which events can be counted, and for which events should
        an operator be notified.</t>

        <t>What is typically difficult to work through are relationships
        between abstract objects. Ideally an information model would describe
        the relationships between the objects and concepts in the information
        model.</t>

        <t>Is there always just one instance of this object or can there be
        multiple instances? Does this object relate to exactly one other
        object or may it relate to multiple? When is it possible to change a
        relationship?</t>

        <t>Do objects (such as rows in tables) share fate? For example, if a
        row in table A must exist before a related row in table B can be
        created, what happens to the row in table B if the related row in
        table A is deleted? Does the existence of relationships between
        objects have an impact on fate sharing?</t>

        <t><!---
        <t>[DISCUSS} There have been recommendations that templates be
        provided for such things as SNMP notifications and SYSLOG messages, so
        working groups just need to fill in the blanks. if "reusable
        manageability" was easy to do, domain-specific WGs would be inclined
        to provide more NM features in their protocol. Translation: Pick the
        integration points, and create procedures and tools to let WGs create
        consistent NM more easily. Notification content and configuration
        management have the most room for improvement. Every protocol should
        define critical and severe fault notifications in a consistent manner
        (e.g. template for SMIv2 NOTIFICATION-TYPE or SYSLOG or XML PDU).
        Every protocol should identify, for every sub-feature and PDU field,
        whether it is (a) standard-fixed, (b) vendor-fixed, or (c)
        user-configurable parameter (e.g., template for a MIB module). just
        require the WGs to put the template(s) in the NM Considerations
        section of every RFC. real integrations comes from an underlying
        common understanding of the informal information model. Once an
        information model exists, it is usually easy for people to cast it
        into MIBs or other data models.</t>

        <t>[DISCUSS] One approach would be to provide a standardized
        information-model text template that a working group could fill in,
        which could then be converted from its information model format to a
        data model format, such as an SNMP notification or a SYSLOG message or
        a NETCONF XSD specification. It might be possible to develop tools to
        do the conversion, similar to the SMING approach developed by the NMRG
        to generate MIBs and PIBs from a common specification. Working groups
        should have an easier way to produce consistent network management
        data models that support several IETF standard protocols.</t>

        <t>[DISCUSS] What about recommending for each WG designing a protocol
        to define - the management informational model (what is manageable,
        what type of operations are allowed) - applicability statement or
        mapping of the informational model to existing management protocols. I
        was thinking (for the template) of something like the IPFIX info-model
        document that Juergen Q. wrote a couple years ago.</t>

        <t>[DISCUSS] There is a risk to moving toward having working groups
        just identify what is manageable, without actually producing a
        standardized data model, such as a MIB module or XML document or
        SYSLOG messages or LDAP schemas. This could lead to vendors producing
        proprietary MIB modules all containing the same information, but using
        different OIDs and descriptors. That is not interoperable. We need to
        have standard addressing and naming for interoperability, as well as
        common semantic understanding</t>

        <t>[DISCUSS] a well defined info model is the minimum and mandatory
        management model that needs to be put in place. Standard addressing
        and naming can be made part of this model, as well as the min and
        max-access for each object. We should not however push for one
        mandatory data modeling language, this does not help and leads
        eventually to protocol designers towards finessing the process. As an
        example, in IP telephony the tentative to impose SMIv2 and SNMP are
        failing and IP phones almost never have a SNMP agent. The people who
        designed SIP believe that SNMP is not deployable behind firewalls and
        that in-band SIP can be used to carry management information. What
        they need is an information model and an access model that would allow
        carrying management information between authenticated entities.</t>

--></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Fault Management">
        <t>The working group should consider how faults information will be
        propagated. Will it be done using asynchronous notifications or
        polling of health indicators?</t>

        <t>If notifications are used to alert operators to certain conditions,
        then the working group should discuss mechanisms to throttle
        notifications to prevent congestion. Will there be a hierarchy of
        faults, and will the fault reporting be done by each fault in the
        hierarchy, or will only the lowest fault be reported and the higher
        levels be suppressed? should there be aggregated status indicators 
        based on concatenation of propagated faults from a given domain 
        or device?</t>

        <t>SNMP notifications and SYSLOG messages can alert an operator when
        an aspect of the new protocol fails or encounters an error condition,
        and SNMP is frequently used as a heartbeat monitor.</t>

        <section title="Liveness Detection and Monitoring">
          <t>Liveness detection and monitoring applies both to the control
          plane and the data plane. Mechanisms for detecting faults in the
          control plane or for monitoring its liveness are usually built into
          the control plane protocols or inherited from underlying data plane
          or forwarding plane protocols. These mechanisms do not typically
          require additional management capabilities. However, when a system
          detects a control plane fault, there is often a requirement to
          coordinate recovery action through management applications or at
          least to record the fact in an event log.</t>

          <t>Where the protocol is responsible for establishing data or user
          plane connectivity, liveness detection and monitoring usually need
          to be achieved through other mechanisms. In some cases, these
          mechanisms already exist within other protocols responsible for
          maintaining lower layer connectivity, but it will often be the case
          that new procedures are required to detect failures in the data path
          and to report rapidly, allowing remedial action to be taken.</t>

          <t>Protocol designers should always build in basic testing features
          (e.g. ICMP echo, UDP/TCP echo service, NULL RPC calls) that can be
          used to test for liveness, with an option to enable and disable
          them.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Fault Determination">
          <t>It can be helpful to describe how faults can be pinpointed using
          management information. For example, counters might record instances
          of error conditions. Some faults might be able to be pinpointed by
          comparing the outputs of one device and the inputs of another device
          looking for anomalies.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Fault Isolation">
          <t>It might be useful to isolate faults, such as a system that emits
          malformed messages necessary to coordinate connections properly.
          Spanning tree comes to mind. This might be able to be done by
          configuring next-hop devices to drop the faulty messages to prevent
          them from entering the rest of the network.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Corrective Action">
          <t>What sort of corrective action can be taken by an operator for
          each of the fault conditions that are being identified?</t>
          
          <t>[DISCUSS: this should be expanded or eliminated.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Configuration Management">
        <t>RFC3139 <xref target="RFC3139"></xref> discusses requirements for
        configuration management. This document includes discussion of
        different levels of management, including high-level-policies,
        network-wide configuration data, and device-local configuration.</t>

        <t>A number of efforts have existed in the IETF to develop
        policy-based management. RFC3198 was written to standardize the
        terminology for policy-based management across these efforts.</t>

        <t>It is highly desirable that text processing tools such as diff, and
        version management tools such as RCS or CVS or SVN, can be used to
        process configurations. This approach simplifies comparing the current
        operational state to the initial configuration.</t>

        <t>With structured text such as XML, simple text diffs may be found to
        be inadequate and more sophisticated tools may be needed to make any
        useful comparison of versions.</t>

        <t>To simplify such configuration comparisons, devices should not
        arbitrarily reorder data such as access control lists. If a working
        group defines mechanisms for configuration, it would be desirable to
        standardize the order of elements for consistency of configuration and
        of reporting across vendors, and across releases from vendors.</t>

        <t>Network wide configurations are ideally stored in central master
        databases and transformed into formats that can be pushed to devices,
        either by generating sequences of CLI commands or complete
        configuration files that are pushed to devices. There is no common
        database schema for network configuration, although the models used by
        various operators are probably very similar. It is desirable to
        extract, document, and standardize the common parts of these network
        wide configuration database schemas. A working group should consider
        how to standardize the common parts of configuring the new protocol,
        while recognizing the vendors will likely have proprietary aspects of
        their configurations.</t>

        <t>It is important to distinguish between the distribution of
        configurations and the activation of a certain configuration. Devices
        should be able to hold multiple configurations. NETCONF <xref
        target="RFC4741"></xref>, for example, differentiates between the
        "running" configuration and "candidate" configurations.</t>

        <t>It is important to enable operators to concentrate on the
        configuration of the network as a whole rather than individual
        devices. Support for configuration transactions across a number of
        devices would significantly simplify network configuration management.
        The ability to distribute configurations to multiple devices, or
        modify "candidate configurations on multiple devices, and then
        activate them in a near-simultaneous manner might help.</t>

        <t>Consensus of the 2002 IAB Workshop was that textual configuration
        files should be able to contain international characters.
        Human-readable strings should utilize UTF-8, and protocol elements
        should be in case insensitive ASCII.</t>

        <t>A mechanism to dump and restore configurations is a primitive
        operation needed by operators. Standards for pulling and pushing
        configurations from/to devices are desirable.</t>

        <t>Given configuration A and configuration B, it should be possible to
        generate the operations necessary to get from A to B with minimal
        state changes and effects on network and systems. It is important to
        minimize the impact caused by configuration changes.</t>

        <t>Many protocol specifications include timers that are used as part
        of operation of the protocol. These timers may need default values
        suggested in the protocol specification and do not need to be
        otherwise configurable.</t>

        <section title="Verifying Correct Operation">
          <t>An important function that might be provided is a tool set for
          verifying the correct operation of a protocol. This may be achieved
          to some extent through access to information and data models that
          report the status of the protocol and the state installed on network
          devices. It may also be valuable to provide techniques for testing
          the effect that the protocol has had on the network by sending data
          through the network and observing its behavior.</t>

          <t>Protocol designers should consider how to test the correct
          end-to-end operation of the network, and how to verify the correct
          data or forwarding plane function of each network element.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Control of Function and Policy ">
          <t>A working group should consider the configurable items that exist
          for the control of function via the protocol elements described in
          the protocol specification. For example, Sometimes the protocol
          requires that timers can be configured by the operator to ensure
          specific policy-based behavior by the implementation.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Accounting Management">
        <t>A working group should consider whether it would be appropriate to
        collect usage information related to this protocol, and if so, what
        usage information would be appropriate to collect?</t>

        <t>RFC2975 <xref target="RFC2975"></xref> Introduction to Accounting
        Management discusses a number of issues that arise when monitoring
        usage of protocols for purposes of capacity and trend analysis, cost
        allocation, auditing, and billing. This document also discusses how
        RADIUS, TACACS+, and SNMP protocols are used for these purposes. These
        issues should be considered when designing a protocol whose usage
        might need to be monitored, or when recommending a protocol to do
        usage accounting. While this discussion is now dated, many of the
        issues remain relevant, and new protocols might be better to address
        those issues.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Performance Management">
        <t>Consider information that would be useful when trying to determine
        the performance characteristics of a deployed system using the target
        protocol.</t>

        <t>What are the principal performance factors that need to be looked
        at when measuring the efficiency of the protocol implementations? Is
        it important to measure setup times? throughput? quality versus
        throughput? interruptions? end-to-end throughput? end-to-end quality?
        hop-to-hop throughput?</t>

        <t>Consider scaling issues, such as whether performance will be
        affected by the number of protocol connections. If so, then it might
        be useful to provide information about the maximum number of table
        entries that should be expected to be modeled, how many entries an
        implementation can support, the current number of instances, and the
        expected behavior when the current instances exceed the capacity of
        the implementation. This should be considered in a data-modeling
        independent manner - what makes managed-protocol sense, not what makes
        management-protocol-sense. If it is not managed-protocol-dependent,
        then it should be left for the management-protocol data modelers to
        decide.</t>

        <t>For example, VLAN identifiers have a range of 1..4095 because of
        the VLAN standards.</t>

        <t>Consider operational activity, such as the number of message in and
        the messages out, the number of received messages rejected due to
        format problems, the expected behaviors when a malformed message is
        received.</t>

        <t>Consider the expected behaviors for counters - what is a reasonable
        maximum value for expected usage? should they stop counting at the
        maximum value and retain the maximum value, or should they rollover?
        How can users determine if a rollover has occurred, and how can users
        determine if more than one rollover has occurred?</t>

        <t>What information should be maintained across reboots of the device,
        or restarts of the management system?</t>

        <t>Could events, such as hot-swapping a blade in a chassis, cause
        discontinuities in information? Does this make any difference in
        evaluating the performance of a protocol?</t>

        <t>Consider whether multiple management applications will share a
        counter; if so, then no one management application should be allowed
        to reset the value to zero since this will impact other
        applications.</t>

        <t>For performance monitoring, it is often important to report the
        time spent in a state rather than the current state. Snapshots are of
        less value for performance monitoring.</t>

        <t>The Benchmarking Methodology WG (bmwg) has defined recommendations
        for the measurement of the performance characteristics of various
        internetworking technologies in a laboratory environment, including
        the systems or services that are built from these technologies. Each
        recommendation describes the class of equipment, system, or service
        being addressed; discuss the performance characteristics that are
        pertinent to that class; clearly identify a set of metrics that aid in
        the description of those characteristics; specify the methodologies
        required to collect said metrics; and lastly, present the requirements
        for the common, unambiguous reporting of benchmarking results.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Security Management">
        <t>Protocol designers should consider how to monitor and to manage
        security aspects and vulnerabilities of the new protocol.</t>

        <t>There will be security considerations related to the new protocol.
        To make it possible for operators to be aware of security-related
        events, it is recommended that system logs should record events, such
        as failed logins, but the logs must be secured.</t>

        <t>Should a system automatically notify operators of every event
        occurrence, or should an operator-defined threshold control when a
        notification is sent to an operator?</t>

        <t>Should certain statistics be collected about the operation of the
        new protocol that might be useful for detecting attacks, such as the
        receipt of malformed messages, or messages out of order, or messages
        with invalid timestamps? If such statistics are collected, is it
        important to count them separately for each sender to help identify
        the source of attacks?</t>

        <t>Manageability considerations that are security-oriented might
        include discussion of the security implications when no monitoring is
        in place, the regulatory implications of absence of audit-trail or
        logs in enterprises, exceeding the capacity of logs, and security
        exposures present in chosen / recommended management mechanisms.</t>

        <t>The granularity of access control needed on management interfaces
        needs to match operational needs. Typical requirements are a
        role-based access control model and the principle of least privilege,
        where a user can be given only the minimum access necessary to perform
        a required task.</t>

        <t>It must be possible to do consistency checks of access control
        lists across devices. Working groups should consider information
        models to promote comparisons across devices and across vendors to
        permit checking the consistency of security configurations.</t>

        <t>Working groups should consider how to provide a secure transport,
        authentication, identity, and access control which integrates well
        with existing key and credential management infrastructure.</t>

        <t>Working groups should consider how ACLs (access control lists) are
        maintained and updated.</t>

        <t>Standard SNMP notifications or SYSLOG messages <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-syslog-protocol"></xref> might already exist, or can
        be defined, to alert operators to the conditions identified in the
        security considerations for the new protocol. [TODO: find existing
        notificiations or syslog messages related to security]</t>

        <t>An analysis of existing counters might help operators recognize the
        conditions identified in the security considerations for the new
        protocol before they can impact the network.</t>

        <t>RADIUS and DIAMETER can provide authentication and authorization. A
        working group should consider which attributes would be appropriate
        for their protocol.</t>

        <t>Different protocols use different assumptions about message
        security and data access controls. A working group that recommends
        using different protocols should consider how security will be applied
        in a balanced manner across multiple management interfaces. SNMP
        access control is data-oriented, while CLI access control is usually
        command (task) oriented. Depending on the management function,
        sometimes data-oriented or task-oriented access control makes more
        sense. Working groups should consider both data-oriented and
        task-oriented access control.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Existing Protocols">
      <t>[DISCUSS: Section 5 reviews which protocols the IETF has to offer for
      management and, what I really like, the text discusses for which
      applications they were designed or already successfully deployed. I like
      to perhaps see even stronger guidelines;]</t>

      <t>Existing protocols and data models can provide the management
      functions identified in the previous section. WGs should consider how
      using these existing protocols and data models might impact network
      operations.</t>

      <t>In choosing existing protocol solutions to meet the information model
      requirements, it is recommended that the strengths and weaknesses of
      IETF protocols, as documented in <xref target="RFC3535"></xref> be
      considered, and working groups should consider asking for help from the
      IETF directorates knowledgeable in available existing solutions. This is
      especially true since some of the recommendations from the 2002 IAB
      workshop have become outdated, some have been implemented, and some are
      being realized.</t>

      <t>We want to avoid seeming to impose a solution by putting in place a
      strict terminology - for example implying that a formal data model, or
      even using a management protocol is mandatory. If a WG considers that
      its technology can be managed solely by using proprietary CLIs, and no
      structured or standardized data model needs to be in place, this should
      be fine, but this is a requirement that needs to be explicit in the
      manageability discussion, so that the WG reaches consensus in full
      awareness that this is how the protocol will need to be operated and
      managed. Working groups should avoid having manageability pushed for a
      later/never phase of the development of the standard.</t>

      <t>Listed here are a number of protocols that have reached Proposed
      Standard status or higher within the IETF.</t>

      <section title="SNMP">
        <t>SNMP is widely used for monitoring fault and performance data. Some
        operators use SNMP for configuration in various
        environments/technologies while others find SNMP an inappropriate
        choice for configuration in their environments. SNMPv1 is a Full
        Standard, but is not recommended due to its lack of security features.
        SNMPv3 is a Full Standard that includes security features. An overview
        of the SNMPv3 document set is in <xref target="RFC3410"></xref>.</t>

        <t>SNMP relies on the MIB. MIB module support is uneven across
        vendors, and even within devices. The lack of standard MIB module
        support for all functionality in a device forces operators to use
        other protocols such as a CLI to do configuration of some aspects of
        their managed devices, and it is easier to use one protocol for all
        configuration than to split the task across multiple protocols.</t>

        <t>SNMP is good at determining operational state of specific
        functionality, but not necessarily for the complete operational state
        of a managed device.</t>

        <t>SNMP is good for statistics gathering for specific functionality.
        The wide-spread use of counters in standard MIB modules permits the
        interoperable comparison of statistics across devices from different
        vendors. SNMP is often used to poll a device for sysUpTime, which
        serves to check for operational liveness and discontinuity in
        counters.</t>

        <t>SNMP traps and informs can alert an operator or an application when
        an aspect of the new protocol fails or encounters an error condition,
        and the contents of a notification can be used to guide subsequent
        SNMP polling to gather additional information about an event.</t>

        <t>SNMPv1 and SNMPv2c lack strong security, and are not recommended by
        the IETF. SNMPv3 does offer strong security and is recommended by the
        IETF.</t>

        <t>Stardards exist to run SNMP over multiple network protocols,
        including UDP, Ethernet, Appletalk, OSI, and others..</t>
      </section>

      <section title="SYSLOG">
        <t>The SYSLOG protocol <xref target="I-D.ietf-syslog-protocol"></xref>
        allows a machine to send event notification messages across networks
        to event message collectors. The protocol is simply designed to
        transport these event messages. No acknowledgement of the receipt is
        made. One of the fundamental tenets of the SYSLOG protocol and process
        is its simplicity. No stringent coordination is required between the
        transmitters and the receivers. Indeed, the transmission of SYSLOG
        messages may be started on a device without a receiver being
        configured, or even actually physically present. Conversely, many
        devices will most likely be able to receive messages without explicit
        configuration or definitions. This simplicity has greatly aided the
        acceptance and deployment of SYSLOG.</t>

        <t>Since each process, application and operating system was written
        somewhat independently, there has been little uniformity to the
        message format or content of SYSLOG messages.</t>

        <t>The IETF has developed a new Proposed Standard version of the
        protocol that allows the use of any number of transport protocols
        including reliable transports and secure transports, and standardized
        the application of message security to SYSLOG messages. The IETF
        standardized a new message header format, including timestamp,
        hostname, application, and message ID, to improve filtering, and
        interoperability and correlation between compliant
        implementations.</t>

        <t>SYSLOG message content has traditionally been unstructured natural
        language text. This content is human-friendly, but difficult for
        applications to parse and correlate across vendors, or correlate with
        other event reporting such as SNMP traps. The IETF standard syslog
        protocol includes structured data elements to aid application-parsing.
        The structured data element design allows vendors to define their own
        structured data elements to supplement standardized elements.</t>

        <t>Working groups are encouraged to standardize structured data
        elements, extensible human-friendly text, and consistent
        facility/severity values for SYSLOG to report events specific to their
        protocol.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IPFIX">
        <t>There are several applications e.g., usage-based accounting,
        traffic profiling, traffic engineering, intrusion detection, QoS
        monitoring, that require flow-based traffic measurements.</t>

        <t>IPFIX <xref target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol"></xref> is a Proposed
        Standard approach for transmitting IP traffic flow information over
        the network from an exporting process to an information collecting
        process.</t>

        <t>IPFIX defines a common representation of flow data and a standard
        means of communicating the data over a number of transport
        protocols.</t>

        <t>Some extensions to IPFIX are in development and have not yet become
        Proposed Standards.</t>

        <t>[TODO: update as needed]</t>
      </section>

      <section title="PSAMP">
        <t>Several applications require sampling packets from specific data
        flows, or across multiple data flows, and reporting information about
        the packets. Measurement-based network management is a prime example.
        The PSAMP standard includes support for packet sampling in IPv4, IPv6,
        and MPLS-based networks.</t>

        <t>PSAMP standardizes sampling, selection, metering, and reporting
        strategies for different purposes.</t>

        <t>To simplify the solution, the IPFIX protocol is used for exporting
        the reports to collector applications.</t>

        <t>[TODO: this is in IESG review to become a PS. update as needed]</t>
      </section>

      <section title="NETCONF">
        <t>The NETCONF protocol <xref target="RFC4741"></xref> is a Proposed
        Standard that defines a simple mechanism through which a network
        device can be managed, configuration data information can be
        retrieved, and new configuration data can be uploaded and manipulated.
        The protocol allows the device to expose a full, formal application
        programming interface (API). Applications can use this straightforward
        API to send and receive full and partial configuration data sets.</t>

        <t>The NETCONF protocol uses a remote procedure call (RPC) paradigm. A
        client encodes an RPC in XML and sends it to a server using a secure,
        connection-oriented session. The server responds with a reply encoded
        in XML.</t>

        <t>A key aspect of NETCONF is that it allows the functionality of the
        management protocol to closely mirror the native command line
        interface of the device. This reduces implementation costs and allows
        timely access to new features. In addition, applications can access
        both the syntactic and semantic content of the device's native user
        interface.</t>

        <t>The contents of both the request and the response can be fully
        described in XML DTDs or XML schemas, or both, allowing both parties
        to recognize the syntax constraints imposed on the exchange. As of
        this writing, no standard has been developed for data content
        specification.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="COPS-PR">
        <t>COPS-PR and the Structure of Policy Provisioning Information (SPPI)
        have been approved as Proposed Standards. COPS-PR <xref
        target="RFC3084"></xref> uses the Common Open Policy Service (COPS)
        protocol for support of policy provisioning. The COPS-PR specification
        is independent of the type of policy being provisioned (QoS, Security,
        etc.) but focuses on the mechanisms and conventions used to
        communicate provisioned information between policy-decision-points
        (PDPs) and policy enforcement points (PEPs). COPS-PR does not make any
        assumptions about the policy data model being communicated, but
        describes the message formats and objects that carry the modeled
        policy data. Policy data is modeled using Policy Information Base
        modules (PIB modules).</t>

        <t>COPS-PR has not had wide deployment, and operators have stated that
        its use of binary encoding (BER) for management data makes it
        difficult to develop automated scripts for simple configuration
        management tasks in most text-based scripting languages. In an IAB
        Workshop on Network Management <xref target="RFC3535"></xref>, the
        consensus of operators and protocol developers indicated a lack of
        interest in PIB modules for use with COPS-PR.</t>

        <t>As a result, the IESG has not approved any policy models (PIB
        modules) as an IETF standard, and the use of COPS-PR is not
        recommended.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="RADIUS">
        <t>RADIUS <xref target="RFC2865"></xref>, the remote Authentication
        Dial In User Service, is a Draft Standard that describes a protocol
        for carrying authentication, authorization, and configuration
        information between a Network Access Server which desires to
        authenticate its links and a shared Authentication Server.</t>

        <t>This protocol is widely implemented and used. RADIUS is widely used
        in environments, such as enterprise networks, where a single
        administrative authority manages the network, and protects the privacy
        of user information.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Diameter">
        <t>DIAMETER <xref target="RFC3588"></xref> is a Proposed Standard that
        provides an Authentication, Authorization and Accounting (AAA)
        framework for applications such as network access or IP mobility.
        DIAMETER is also intended to work in both local Authentication,
        Authorization &amp; Accounting and roaming situations.</t>

        <t>Diameter is designed to resolve a number of known problems with
        RADIUS. Diameter supports server failover, transmission-level
        security, reliable transport over TCP, agents for proxy and redirect
        and relay, server-initiated messages, auditability, capability
        negotiation, peer discovery and configuration, and roaming support.
        Diameter also provides a larger attribute space than RADIUS.</t>

        <t>Diameter features make it especially appropriate for environments
        where the providers of services are in different administrative
        domains than the maintainer (protector) of confidential user
        information.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="EPP">
        <t>The Extensible Provision Protocol <xref target="RFC4930"></xref> is
        a Draft Standard that describes an application layer client-server
        protocol for the provisioning and management of objects stored in a
        shared central repository. EPP permits multiple service providers to
        perform object provisioning operations using a shared central object
        repository, and addresses the requirements for a generic registry
        registrar protocol.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="VCCV">
        <t>VCCV is a Proposed Standard protocol that provides a control
        channel associated with a Pseudowire. It is used for operations and
        management functions such as connectivity verification over the
        control channel. VCCV applies to all supported access circuit and
        transport types currently defined for PWs.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="XCAP">
        <t>XCAP <xref target="RFC4825"></xref> is a Proposed Standard protocol
        that allows a client to read, write, and modify application
        configuration data stored in XML format on a server.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Other Protocols">
        <t>A command line interface (CLI) might be used to provide initial
        configuration of the target functionality. Command line interfaces are
        usually proprietary, but working groups could suggest specific
        commands and command parameters that would be useful in configuring
        the new protocol, so implementers could have similarities in their
        proprietary CLI implementations.</t>

        <t>[DISCUSS: Routing and control plane people may prefer NETCONF since
        it is close to CLIs which seem to rule in this space. ]</t>

        <t>[DISCUSS] Other PS-level NM protocols? SIP NM?</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Existing IETF Data Models">
      <t>[DISCUSS: JS: The weakest part of the document is IMHO section 6. It
      is not clear to me what David's intention were here; sometimes he gives
      general advise while at other places he kind of surveys data models and
      such things. I am also not sure all the stuff listed there is actually
      useful to list; for example, has anybody ever deployed the technology
      which came out of the snmpconf working group? So we need to be more
      selective and probably also organize our pointers based on the protocol
      layer people are working on (transmission specific MIB modules are kind
      of widely used, people managing application servers usually do not use
      much of SNMP; the IETF application management MIBs we have produced have
      not gained large deployments as far as I can tell). ]</t>

      <t>[DISCUSS: David: Some MIB modules may not be deployed because few
      people know about them and has never tried them. Others may have been
      tried and been found to be inadequate. We have very little feedback
      concerning which ones are useful and which are widely deployed, which
      have been found useful by operators, and which have been found to be
      junk. ;-) I hesitate to make recommendations that people should avoid a
      MIB unless there is real evidence that is is unsuitable for its designed
      task. Even then, I hesitate because maybe the MIB would be found useful
      in a different environment that is just emerging. Maybe we need to
      perform a de-crufting operation for data models, similar to that done
      for protocols a few years ago. But I think that would require feedback
      from LOTS of operators and application developers - and these tend to be
      scarce in the IETF. ]</t>

      <t>The purpose of this section is to inform protocol designers about
      solutions for which components have already been standardized in the
      IETF, so they can reuse existing solutions or use those solutions to
      extract information models that could be applied to new solutions.</t>

      <t>This section discusses management data models that have reached at
      least Proposed Standard status in the IETF. Because making management
      information available through the MIB has long been the IETF-preferred
      approach for managing the Internet, there are a large number of MIB
      modules available. Rather than attempt to discuss each here, with a
      discussion of the tables they contain, this section will focus on those
      MIB modules that have reached at least Draft status, and some commonly
      deployed MIB modules. This is supplemented by an appendix that lists
      additional MIB modules that have reached Proposed Standard status.</t>

      <t>[TODO] discuss specific MIB modules, SDEs, XML schemas that are
      designed to solve generic problems. This might cover things like Textual
      Conventions, RFC3415 Target tables, SYSLOG SDEs defined in -protocol-,
      SYSLOG -sign-, IPFIX IEs, etc.</t>

      <section title="Fault Management">
        <t></t>

        <t>RFC 3418 <xref target="RFC3418"></xref>, part of STD 62 SNMP,
        contains objects in the system group that are often polled to
        determine if a device is still operating, and sysUpTime can be used to
        detect if a system has rebooted, and counters have been
        reinitialized.</t>

        <t>RFC3413 <xref target="RFC3413"></xref>, part of STD 62 SNMP,
        includes objects designed for managing notifications, including tables
        for addressing, retry parameters, security, lists of targets for
        notifications, and user customization filters.</t>

        <t>An RMON monitor <xref target="RFC2819"></xref> can be configured to
        recognize conditions, most notably error conditions, and continuously
        to check for them. When one of these conditions occurs, the event may
        be logged, and management stations may be notified in a number of
        ways. See further discussion of RMON under Performance Management.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Configuration Management">
        <t>It is expected that standard XML-based data models will be
        developed for use with NETCONF, and working groups might identify
        specific NETCONF data models that would be applicable to the new
        protocol. At the time of this writing, no such standard data models
        exist.</t>

        <t>For monitoring network configuration, such as physical and logical
        network topologies, existing MIB modules already exist that provide
        some of the desired capabilities. New MIB modules might be developed
        for the target functionality to allow operators to monitor and modify
        the operational parameters, such as timer granularity, event reporting
        thresholds, target addresses, and so on.</t>

        <t>RFC 3418 <xref target="RFC3418"></xref>, part of STD 62 SNMPv3,
        contains objects in the system group that are often polled to
        determine if a device is still operating, and sysUpTime can be used to
        detect if a system has rebooted and caused potential discontinuity in
        counters. Other objects in the system MIB are useful for identifying
        the type of device, the location of the device, the person responsible
        for the device, etc.</t>

        <t>RFC3413 <xref target="RFC3413"></xref>, part of STD 62 SNMPv3,
        includes objects designed for configuring notification destinations,
        and for configuring proxy-forwarding SNMP agents, which can be used to
        forward messages through firewalls and NAT devices.</t>

        <t>Draft Standard RFC2863 <xref target="RFC2863"></xref>, the
        Interfaces MIB is used for managing Network Interfaces. This includes
        the 'interfaces' group of MIB-II and discusses the experience gained
        from the definition of numerous media-specific MIB modules for use in
        conjunction with the 'interfaces' group for managing various
        sub-layers beneath the internetwork-layer.</t>
        
        <t>Proposed Standard RFC3165 <xref target="RFC3165"></xref> supports the use of user-written 
        scripts to delegate management functionality.</t>
        
        <t>Proposed Standard RFC4011 <xref target="RFC4011"></xref> defines
        objects that enable policy-based monitoring using SNMP, using a scripting 
        language, and a script execution environment. </t>
        
       <t> Few vendors have not implemented MIB modules that support scripting.
        Some vendors consider running user-developed scripts within the 
        managed device as a violation of support agreements.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Accounting Management">
        <t>TODO: RADIUS Accounting MIBs are PS; are there any DS data models
        for accounting? ]</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Performance Management">
        <t>Working groups should consider how performance can be monitored for
        the new protocol.</t>

        <t>MIB modules typically contain counters to determine the frequency
        and rate of an occurrence.</t>

        <t>RFC2819, STD 59 RMON, defines objects for managing remote network
        monitoring devices. An organization may employ many remote management
        probes, one per network segment, to manage its internet. These devices
        may be used for a network management service provider to access a
        client network, often geographically remote. Most of the objects in
        the RMON MIB module are suitable for the management of any type of
        network, and there are some which are specific to managing Ethernet
        networks.</t>

        <t>RMON allows a probe to be configured to perform diagnostics and to
        collect statistics continuously, even when communication with the
        management station may not be possible or efficient. The alarm group
        periodically takes statistical samples from variables in the probe and
        compares them to previously configured thresholds. If the monitored
        variable crosses a threshold, an event is generated.</t>

        <t>The RMON host group discovers hosts on the network by keeping a
        list of source and destination MAC Addresses seen in good packets
        promiscuously received from the network, and contains statistics
        associated with each host. The hostTopN group is used to prepare
        reports that describe the hosts that top a list ordered by one of
        their statistics. The available statistics are samples of one of their
        base statistics over an interval specified by the management station.
        Thus, these statistics are rate based. The management station also
        selects how many such hosts are reported.</t>

        <t>The RMON matrix group stores statistics for conversations between
        sets of two addresses. The filter group allows packets to be matched
        by a filter equation. These matched packets form a data stream that
        may be captured or may generate events. The Packet Capture group
        allows packets to be captured after they flow through a channel. The
        event group controls the generation and notification of events from
        this device.</t>

        <t>The RMON-2 MIB <xref target="RFC4502"></xref> extends RMON by
        providing RMON analysis up to the application layer. The SMON MIB
        <xref target="RFC2613"></xref> extends RMON by providing RMON analysis
        for switched networks.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Security Management">
        <t>Working groups should consider existing data models that would be
        relevant to monitoring and managing the security of the new
        protocol.</t>

        <t>The IETF has no standard data models for managing security
        protocols such as TLS and SSH.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Documentation Guidelines">
      <t>The purpose of this document is to provide guidance about what to
      consider when thinking about the management and deployment of a new
      protocol, and to provide guidance about documenting the considerations
      should a working group choose to do so. The following guidelines are
      designed to help writers provide a reasonably consistent format to such
      documentation. Separate manageability and operational considerations
      sections are desirable in many cases, but their structure and location
      is a decision that can be made from case to case.</t>

      <t>Making a Management Considerations section a mandatory publication
      requirement is the responsibility of the IESG, or specific area
      directors, or working groups, and this document avoids recommending any
      mandatory publication requirements. For a complex protocol, a completely
      separate draft on operations and management might be appropriate, or
      even a completely separate WG.</t>

      <t>This document is focused on what to think about, and how to document
      the considerations of the working group.</t>

      <section title="Recommended Discussions">
        <t>A Manageability Considerations section should include discussion of
        the management and operations topics raised in this document, and when
        one or more of these topics is not relevant, it would be useful to
        contain a simple statement explaining why the topic is not relevant
        for the new protocol. Of course, additional relevant topics should be
        included as well.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Null Manageability Considerations Sections">
        <t>A working group may seriously consider the manageability
        requirements of a new protocol, and determine that there are no
        manageability issues related to the new protocol. It would be helpful
        to those who may update or write extensions to the protocol in the
        future or to those deploying the new protocol to know the thinking of
        the working regarding the manageability of the protocol at the time of
        its design.</t>

        <t>If there are no new manageability or deployment considerations, it
        is recommended that a Manageability Considerations section contain a
        simple statement such as "There are no new manageability requirements
        introduced by this document," and a brief explanation of why that is
        the case. The presence of such a Manageability Considerations section
        would indicate to the reader that due consideration has been given to
        manageability and operations.</t>

        <t>In the case where the new protocol is an extension, and the base
        protocol discusses all the relevant operational and manageability
        considerations, it would be helpful to point out the considerations
        section in the base document.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Placement of Operations and Manageability Considerations Sections ">
        <t>If a working group develops a Manageability Considerations section
        for a new protocol, it is recommended that the section be placed
        immediately before the Security Considerations section. Reviewers
        interested in such sections could find it easily, and this placement
        could simplify the development of tools to detect the presence of such
        a section.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not introduce any new codepoints or name spaces
      for registration with IANA. Note to RFC Editor: this section may be
      removed on publication as an RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document is informational and provides guidelines for
      considering manageability and operations. It introduces no new security
      concerns.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document started from an earlier document edited by Adrian
      Farrel, which itself was based on work exploring the need for
      Manageability Considerations sections in all Internet-Drafts produced
      within the Routing Area of the IETF. That earlier work was produced by
      Avri Doria, Loa Andersson, and Adrian Farrel, with valuable feedback
      provided by Pekka Savola and Bert Wijnen.</t>

      <t>Some of the discussion about designing for manageability came from
      private discussions between Dan Romascanu, Bert Wijnen, Juergen
      Schoenwaelder, Andy Bierman, and David Harrington.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc1052;

      &rfc2119;

      &rfc2578;

      &rfc2613;

      &rfc2819;

      &rfc2863;

      &rfc2865;

      &rfc2975;

      &rfc3060;

      &rfc3084;

      &rfc3139;

      &rfc3159;
      
      &rfc3165;

      &rfc3290;

      &rfc3317;

      &rfc3410;

      &rfc3413;

      &rfc3418;

      &rfc3444;

      &rfc3460;

      &rfc3535;

      &rfc3585;

      &rfc3588;

      &rfc3644;

      &rfc3670;

      &rfc3805;

      &rfc4011;

      &rfc4133;

      &rfc4502;
      
      &rfc4668;
      &rfc4669;

      &rfc4710;

      &rfc4741;

      &rfc4825;

      &rfc4930;

      &I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol;

      &I-D.ietf-syslog-protocol;

      &I-D.ietf-sipping-rtcp-summary;
    </references>

    <section title="Operations and Management Checklist">
      <t>This appendix provides a quick summary of issues to consider.</t>

      <t><list>
          <t>are configuration parameters clearly identified?</t>

          <t>are configuration parameters normalized?</t>

          <t>does each configuration parameter have a reasonable default
          value?</t>

          <t>is protocol state information exposed to the user? How?</t>

          <t>is protocol performance information exposed to the user? How?</t>

          <t>are significant state transitions logged?</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Additional Data Models on the Standards Track">
      <t>The IETF SYSLOG protocol <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-syslog-protocol"></xref> is a Proposed Standard that
      includes a mechanism for defining structured data elements (SDEs). The
      SYSLOG protocol document defines an initial set of SDEs that relate to
      content time quality, content origin, and meta-information about the
      message, such as language. Proprietary SDEs can be used to supplement
      the IETF-defined SDEs.</t>

      <t>SIP Package for Voice Quality Reporting <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-sipping-rtcp-summary"></xref> defines a SIP event
      package that enables the collection and reporting of metrics that
      measure the quality for Voice over Internet Protocol (VoIP)
      sessions.</t>

      <t>DISMAN-EVENT-MIB in RFC 2981 and DISMAN-EXPRESSION-MIB in RFC 2982
      provide a superset of the capabilities of the RMON alarm and event
      groups. These modules provide mechanisms for thresholding and reporting
      anomalous events to management applications.</t>

      <t>RAQMON <xref target="RFC4710"></xref> describes Real-Time Application
      Quality of Service Monitoring.</t>

      <t>The IPPM WG has defined metrics for accurately measuring and
      reporting the quality, performance, and reliability of Internet data
      delivery services. The metrics include connectivity, one-way delay and
      loss, round-trip delay and loss, delay variation, loss patterns, packet
      reordering, bulk transport capacity, and link bandwidth capacity. [TODO:
      detail the RFCs - 4737, 3393, 2681, 2680, 2679, 2678</t>

      <t>The IPFIX protocol <xref target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol"></xref> can
      collect information related to IP flows, and existing Information
      Elements (IEs) may be appropriate to report flows of the new protocol.
      New IPFIX Information Elements might be useful for collecting flow
      information useful only in consideration of the new protocol. As of this
      writing, no IEs have reached Proposed Standard status yet, but a base
      set of IEs has been submitted to IESG for advancement. These include IEs
      for Identifying the scope of reporting, Metering and Export Process
      configuration, IP and Transport and Sub-IP header fields, Packet and
      Flow properties, timestamps, and counters.</t>

      <t>RFC3159 discusses the Proposed Standard Structure of Policy
      Provisioning Information (SPPI), an extension to the SMI standard for
      purposes of policy-based provisioning, for use with the COPS-PR protocol
      defined in RFC3084. Informational RFC3317 defines a DiffServ QoS PIB,
      and Informational RFC3571 defines policy classes for monitoring and
      reporting policy usage feedback, as well as policy classes for
      controlling reporting intervals, suspension, resumption and
      solicitation. At the time of this writing, there are no standards-track
      PIBs During the IAB Workshop on Network Management, the workshop had
      rough consensus from the protocol developers that the IETF should not
      spend resources on SPPI PIB definitions, and the operators had rough
      consensus that they do not care about SPPI PIBs.</t>

      <t>Proposed Standard RFC4011 <xref target="RFC4011"></xref> defines
      objects that enable policy-based monitoring and management of SNMP
      infrastructures, a scripting language, and a script execution
      environment.</t>
      
      <t>DIAMETER <xref target="RFC3588"></xref> accounting might be collected
      for services, and working groups might document some of the
      RADIUS/DIAMETER attributes that could be used. [TODO: what data
      models?]</t>

      <t>RADIUS Authentication Client MIB <xref target="RFC4668"></xref> and
      RADIUS Authentication Server MIB <xref target="RFC4669"></xref> allow the
      gathering of accounting data.</t>

      <t>Proposed Standard RFC4133 <xref target="RFC4133"></xref> the Entity
      MIB is used for managing multiple logical and physical entities managed
      by a single SNMP agent. This module provides a useful mechanism for
      identifying the entities comprising a system. There are also event
      notifications defined for configuration changes that may be useful to
      management applications.</t>



      <t>RFC3159 <xref target="RFC3159"></xref> discusses the Structure of
      Policy Provisioning Information, an extension to the SMI standard for
      purposes of policy-based provisioning, for use with the COPS-PR protocol
      defined in RFC3084 <xref target="RFC3084"></xref>. RFC3317 <xref
      target="RFC3317"></xref> defines a DiffServ QoS PIB. At the time of this
      writing, there are no standards-track PIBs. During the IAB Workshop on
      Network Management, the workshop had rough consensus from the protocol
      developers that the IETF should not spend resources on SPPI PIB
      definitions, and the operators had rough consensus that they do not care
      about SPPI PIBs.</t>

      <t>The ALARM MIB in RFC 3877 and the Alarm Reporting Control MIB in RFC
      3878 specify mechanisms for expressing state transition models for
      persistent problem states. There is also a mechanism specified to
      correlate a notification with subsequent state transition notifications
      about the same entity/object.</t>

      <t>Other MIB modules that may be applied to Fault Management include:
      <list>
          <t>NOTIFICATION-LOG-MIB in RFC 3014</t>

          <t>ENTITY-STATE-MIB in RFC 4268</t>

          <t>ENTITY-SENSOR-MIB in RFC 4268</t>
        </list></t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Open Issues">
<t><list>
	<t>[TODO: need to verify all citations have references (in xref format)]</t>
	<t>Organize data models by layer? both section 6 and appendix.</t>
	<t>start to identify bullets for appendix checklist</t>
	<t>Is section 2 needed?</t>
	
</list></t>
        </section>
    <section title="Change Log">
      <t>Changes from opsawg-00 to opsawg-01</t>

      <t><list>
          <t>moved Proposed Standard data models to appendix</t>
          <t>moved advice out of data model survey and into considerations section </t>
          <t>addressed comments from Adrian and Dan</t>
          <t>modified the Introduction and Section 2 in response to many comments.</t>
          <t>expanded radius and syslog discussion, added psamp and VCCV, modified ipfix, </t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Changes from harrington-01 to opsawg-00</t>

      <t><list>
          <t>added text regarding operational models to be managed.</t>

          <t>Added checklist appendix (to be filled in after consensus is
          reached on main text )</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Changes from harrington-00 to harrington-01</t>

      <t><list>
          <t>modified unclear text in "Design for Operations and
          Management"</t>

          <t>Expanded discussion of counters</t>

          <t>Removed some redundant text</t>

          <t>Added ACLs to Security Management</t>

          <t>Expanded discussion of the status of COPS-PR, SPPI, and PIBs.</t>

          <t>Expanded comparison of RADIUS and Diameter.</t>

          <t>Added placeholders for EPP and XCAP protocols.</t>

          <t>Added Change Log and Open Issues</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>