<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2026 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2418 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2418.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3184 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3184.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3929 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3929.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4677 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4677.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->


<rfc category="info" docName="draft-dusseault-consensus-00" ipr="full3978">

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>

    <title abbrev="Consensus">Notes on IETF Rough Consensus</title>

    <author fullname="Lisa Dusseault" initials="L. M."
            surname="Dusseault">
      <organization>CommerceNet</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>169 University Ave.</street>
          <city>Palo Alto</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94301</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>1-650-279-7365</phone>
        <email>ldusseault@commerce.net</email>

      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="December" year="2007" />

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>ietf process rough consensus voting working group</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract> <t>The IETF makes decisions using what we refer to as rough consensus, using
    	a great deal of flexibility and judgement depending on the situation.  This document
    documents various approaches to determining rough consensus.</t> </abstract> </front>

  <middle> <section title="Introduction"> <t>Consensus is a way for people to make 
  	decisions and generate commitment to those decisions. Coming to decisions by 
  	consensus is difficult and time-consuming.  It's a much broader and more flexible
  	process than simply picking a position and seeing if everybody agrees.  The process cannot be reduced 
  	to an algorithm; consensus is complex, human and messy. We choose skilled people 
  	to help us come to consensus, and they do so based on their experience and
    judgement.  </t>
  
   <t>The IETF has much folklore about its "rough" consensus. Many people, not just chairs, make
  statements about a group's consensus. There are many opinions about what approaches are OK or not
  in determining consensus. The IETF also has some unique approaches to determining consensus,
  including "hums" taken to gauge consensus in meeting rooms by volume of sound generated.</t>
  
   <t>This document attempts to provide detail on how rough consensus works on IETF mailing lists and
  in IETF meetings, with some suggestions for dealing with exceptions and difficult cases. The
  "Alternative Decision Making Process for Consensus Blocked Decisions" described in <xref
  target="RFC3929"/> contains valuable approaches for certain difficult cases. In contrast, this
  document describes more of the common context and practice of the IETF. The reader is particularly
  recommended to read Section 2 of <xref target="RFC3929"/>.</t>
  
   <t>Most of the information here can be construed as either advice and ideas for chairs or an 
   	explanation for participants of what they might see. The last section is advice for
  individual participants.</t>
  
   <t>Information provided here is not intended to create any IETF process requirements that are not
  already extant: nor is there any intent to limit chairs from trying other approaches. There are
  many ways to develop and determine rough consensus. In choosing approaches, 
   	chairs need be guided the goals of the Internet Standards Process in <xref target="RFC2026"/>. 
   	There are many difficult tradeoffs. </t>
  
   	<section title="Terminology"> 
	<t>The word "chair" is used in this document to identify the person
  running the consensus call. Sometimes this person is not the Working Gropu (WG) chair. The phrase
  "WG chair" or "meeting chair" is used when it's necessary to be specific about context.</t>
  
   <t>The word "vote" is used informally in this specification and doesn't usually imply formal vote counting
  -- it's just that the phrase "to vote" is shorter than "to express one's preference on the mailing
  list or in a meeting room". </t> 

		</section> 
	</section>
	
	<section title="Consensus">
	
	<t>This section discusses what consensus is, including some of the subtler ways 
	consensus differs from voting, what silence means in consensus, and a couple areas that 
	are sometimes problematic.</t>

		<section title="Comparing Decision-Making Processes">
			<t>
				Formal, classic consensus cultures <xref target="BUJ"/> are rather rare.  They can be found 
				in quite a few intentional communities and in a small number of boards, committees and 
			project teams.  In many thriving consensus cultures, any veto by any member really
			can, and does, block decision making until some opinion or proposal changes.  
			</t>
			
			<t> There are many organizations that do weak consensus; they prefer to get consensus but 
				not if it's too difficult.
				These organizations may depart from formal consensus by limiting who can veto, by limiting 
				who can make proposals or how many proposals there
    			can be, by limiting discussion that might lead to new proposals or
			consensus changes, or by having fallback non-consensus processes (e.g. the development manager decides) 
				when consensus takes too long.
			</t>
			
			<t>Parliamentary rules such as Robert's Rules of Order are not part of most consensus processes.
				They are not formally used in the IETF, although some parliamentary rules are adopted ad-hoc as 
				useful habits.  One notable difference from many parliamentary rules sets is that 
				the chair of an IETF group or meeting may vote. 
			</t>
						
			<t>Majority rule is common, easy and fast.  However, it often compares a limited and closed 
				set of proposals.  In the worst case, time pressure (real or imagined) could cause a group to do a vote on the first proposal at hand, 
				which could pass by a slim margin despite the suspicion of a few participants that it has flaws. 
				Technical excellence requires the creative exploration of alternatives. A consensus process doesn't guarantee
				creativity, but it does encourage it.  It's up to chairs (with help from participants)
				to note when an important decision is at hand, and wait for multiple proposals before calling for
				a decision.</t>
			
			<t>Another problem with majority rule systems, in the context of the IETF, is they tend to 
				involve competition in 'winning' a vote.  Since IETF standards are only adopted voluntarily
				by implementors, that means that adversarial position-taking
				can hamper the acceptance and adoption of a standard.</t>
			
			
			<t><xref target="BUJ">Building United Judgement</xref> has extensive discussion 
				and examples comparing majority rule to consensus.</t>
			
		</section>
		
		<section title="Consensus as a Process">
	
	<t>Consensus is not simply a decision.  It can't entirely be described in a moment 
		in time despite the immediacy of our hums; it's an 
	evolving balance.  The hum is a snapshot of the current state of the evolving consensus 
	among the present population.  A chair pays attention to the whole changing picture to 
	decide whether there is already a consensus, whether more discussion is needed, and when 
	to do a formal call for consensus.</t>
	
	<t>A chair must continue to pay attention to the balance after a consensus call to see 
	if it has shifted and if that's important enough to go back and fix.  </t>

	<t>A chair can weight the balance according to the experience of those offering views 
	and whether there have been convincing arguments about some option simply not working.  
	We allow and value input from those with experience and those without, but the "running 
	code" part of the catchy "rough consensus and running code" phrase means that we pay special 
	attention to input based on implementation experience.  It's good if the chair can make this 
	explicit:  
		<list><t>
		"I think we've heard a convincing argument from Aaron that this leaves servers 
		open to DOS attacks, so I conclude this feature can't be added as-is."</t></list>
	</t>
	
		</section>
		
		<section title="Informality">

	<t>Consensus is not always formally called or determined.  Sometimes draft editors (or authors) 
		ask for opinions to help decide what to write.  Sometimes editors make assumptions about what 
		the consensus is.  If the editor gets the sense of consensus right, there may be no need to do a 
		formal consensus call. If the editor at least takes a reasonable stab at sensing the consensus there 
		should be no reason for reproach.  If there's a problem, anybody can ask the WG chair to do an explicit
		consensus call.</t>

	<t>In meetings, it's not always the meeting chair who asks for consensus and figures out how to word 
		the question.  It can be anybody who thinks they have grasped the issue and is helping by asking 
		for consensus.  In these cases it's polite to turn to the meeting chair to state the outcome, but 
		sometimes in difficult cases the meeting chair turns to respected, experienced or unbiased members 
		of the community to help determine the outcome of a consensus call. </t>

	<t>Votes on a mailing list may be simply "+1" or may express misgivings or caveats, and it's up to the 
		chair to interpret or ask for clarification.  Votes in a meeting room are often hums, but sometimes 
		the chair asks for hands to be raised instead, or simply interprets a bunch of negative comments at 
		the microphone as demonstrating a consensus against a proposal.</t>

		</section>
		<section title="Who may participate">

	<t>The IETF is extremely open about allowing participation in consensus calls.  You may see some of the 
		following:

		<list><t>1.  A hum from a person in a meeting room who does not follow the list.  </t>
		<t>2.  A mailing list vote from a person who is not subscribed to the list.  </t></list>
	</t>

	<t>Note that it may be impossible to determine that somebody does not read the list -- lists may be read 
		through the list archive site or mailing list mirror services.

		<list><t>3.  Multiple votes, whether the same or different, from multiple people from the same organization.</t>
		<t>4.  An individual deferring to somebody else in their organization who has already voted.</t></list>
	</t>

	<t>We count individuals at the IETF, not organizations, but don't force everybody to vote.

		<list><t>5.  Votes in the jabber room during a meeting.</t>
		<t>6.  Votes at the microphone, in Jabber, by humming and on the list -- even from the same person. </t></list>
	</t>

	<t>We rely on chairs to roughly adjust for repeat voting.  We don't encourage this, but we allow it 
		because we hope that people explain their preference each time apart from the hum.

		<list><t>7. Votes from chairs, ADs, secretaries, document authors and editors.  </t></list>
	</t>

	<t>Sometimes the author's vote is implicit in their proposal but we don't stop them from voting.</t>

	<t>When chairs do contribute their own opinions to a debate (which is not required but is certainly allowed) it helps to be explicit.  Example: 

	<list><t>"Chair hat OFF: I don't like requiring resolvability, it gives 
		no benefit beyond uniqueness which we have already.  Chair hat ON: 
		So far I see only weak support for resolvability, and several against it, 
		so I don't think we have consensus to add that to the spec so far. "</t></list>
		
	</t>
		</section>

		<section title="When Silence is Consent">

	<t>One way of calling consensus is to summarize what might be the consensus position (e.g. to accept a
		 particular proposal) and explicitly ask the group if there are any objections.  This is a little 
		different from calling consensus when two alternatives are provided, because the WG chair may assume 
		that a lack of clear objections constitutes approval of the consensus call as stated.  Obviously a 
		chair can steer consensus towards proposals in this way, but the IETF tries to pick chairs who have 
		technical and engineering judgement in order to help us reach quick decisions when it's appropriate.</t>

	<t>When a consensus call in the meeting room has a clear result and the result is minuted and posted to 
		the mailing list, silence can be taken to mean consent -- the consensus has been confirmed.   
		WG participants who cannot make it to a meeting 
		are given ample opportunities (Jabber participation, audio feeds and minutes on the list) to learn
		about the consensus call and raise objections.</t>

	<t>One situation that might be abused is when 20% of a WG favour one approach, 20% favour another, and the 
		rest are silent.  It is possible to construct questions in a biased manner so that the chair assumes 
		that the silent majority agree with the approach the chair favours.  In meeting rooms we frequently 
		ask for "hums for" and "hums against" in order to make sure that we don't see consensus where there 
		is none (or even "hums for option A", "hums for option B", "don't care" and "something else").  On 
		mailing lists it's easier for people to advocate directly for the the outcome they think best so we 
		don't typically ask both sides of the question.  Chairs try to be responsible about seeing when the 
		group's expressed opinion is balanced and try to get more input or encourage further discussion.  </t>

	<t>Sometimes silence means disinterest.  On the principle that unimportant work crowds out the attention 
		available for important work, the IETF should not in general encourage much time spent on unimportant 
		work.  To help make that happen, chairs need to determine how important a proposal is before accepting 
		it as a WG work item.  It's not enough for an author to explain a proposal and answer a few questions; 
		there must also be enough explicit interest to adopt a work item.  It's up to the WG chair to be the 
		bad guy if necessary and tell the author that there is not a strong enough consensus to adopt the work 
		item.  </t>

	<t>The same principle can be applied to new features suggested for addition, or even to features which are 
		part of an important proposal (when the specification can be simplified without reducing its utility).</t>

	<t>Here's an example from real life of an issue where the person who raised the issue only
		suggested a problem with text, not a resolution.  The issue 
		was resolved with the text unchanged because of silence.  In this case, the chair usefully made
		 this explicit rather than implicitly allowing the text to remain unchanged.

	<list><t>"There has been no additional discussion on this issue since draft -02
		came out. This issue is now considered closed.</t></list>
		</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Questionable tactics in consensus calls">

	<t>Once in a while the IETF also sees what may appear to be attempts to stack a vote.  
		Some possibilities:

	<list style="numbers">
		<t>bringing extra people to a meeting to hum on cue</t>
	 	<t>causing extra participants (perhaps even dummy accounts) to voice opinions in a Jabber room or mailing list</t>
	 	<t>humming into the microphone</t>
		<t>very loud humming</t>
	</list>
	</t>

	<t>We can't always tell if these are inappropriate or intentional.  Case 1 might appear to arise when 
		experts in a security technology come to offer an opinion on the security choices in a 
		WG they don't normally participate in.  This may create a difficult situation for the chair to 
		overcome, but these are still valid and appropriate community opinions.  Case 4 actually illustrates one of the 
		strengths of humming, because it allows us to express and hear urgency and strength of feeling in 
		both directions (chairs have at times heard such apathetic hums about how a feature should work that 
		they proposed dropping the feature).  </t>

	<t>If there is a suspicion of foul play, the chair can quickly ask for participants to behave better and 
		call for consensus again, or even repeat the call later on a mailing list.  However, the chair is not 
		required to overturn a consensus just because of accusations of foul play.  Because of the many ways 
		that IETF consensus calls can possibly be gamed, chairs must at times make judgement calls about what 
		the consensus really is rather than have it be mechanically tallied.  </t>

	<t>Working group participants are advised to keep their mouths closed while humming, as it not only encourages 
		fair humming but is also more attractive.</t>

		</section>
	
		<section title="Backroom dealing">

	<t>When a small number of people get together for a technical conversation, and information learned
		in this conversation 
		informs their opinions and proposals in meetings and on the public mailing lists, we generally 
		consider this to be a *good* thing.  Sometimes it's easier to explore an idea or explain a difficult 
		point in small groups.  Chairs and ADs frequently interact with small groups of participants in order 
		to break down a consensus block or solve an issue that's not getting far on the mailing list.  Often 
		the outcome of such a conversation becomes quite naturally public even though the conversation itself 
		wasn't.  Sometimes the conversation remains private because to relate it publicly would be tedious, 
		pointless or somehow harmful.</t>

	<t>As always, it's up to everybody involved to balance openness with other values including fairness, 
		efficiency and technical correctness. </t>

	<t>Note also that the IETF has rules about design teams <xref target="RFC2418"/>.</t>

		</section>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Consensus calls in meeting rooms">

	<t>We know from organizational psychology research that in-person decision-making has different 
		characteristics than computer-mediated decision-making.  Some examples:
		<list style="symbols"><t>
			When we evaluate hums and hand-raising compared to email votes, we use much different cognitive tools.
			In-person voting is nearly instantaneous and relies on visual and auditory impressions, 
			whereas email voting relies on interpretation, abstraction and memory.  
		</t>
			<t>Emotional influence is probably stronger in meeting rooms.  On the one hand, there may be 
				more pressure to conform (probably bad when technical judgement is needed).  On the other hand, 
				there may be valuable information channels in meeting rooms that 
			we just don't have access to in email, such as judging when somebody is uncertain about a 
			statement or position.</t>
			<t>Email tends to polarize and is prone to flames <xref target="AA"/>.</t>
			<t>Groups that solve problems in-person tend to share more hidden information than 
				computer-mediated groups <xref target="Hol"/>.</t>
		</list>
	</t>
		<t>The IETF approach is to combine computer-mediated distributed interactions with in-person
			meetings.  Sometimes a protracted on-list argument can be resolved by bringing 
		participants together.</t>

	<t>In meeting room consensus calls, we always assume we are asking for a complete sense of the room, not 
		just new votes. This is quite different from mailing list consensus calls discussed shortly, where 
		frequently chairs solicit only new opinions or information.</t>
		
	<t>Chairs frequently ask who has read a document before doing a consensus call related to that document.
		This can be useful for a number of reasons:
		<list style="symbols"><t>Can weigh opinions from informed partipants more heavily</t>
		<t>Might shame people who haven't read documents from expressing uninformed opinions in the first place</t>
		<t>Can gauge if there is enough expertise to even ask the consensus question and expect a good result</t>
		<t>Can gauge if there's insufficient interest for the work in the first place</t>
		</list>
		</t>

		
		<t>Once the consensus call is made, the creative discussion of alternatives is over at least for the 
			time being.  If a participant has a new contribution -- a new alternative, a flaw 
		in one of the alternatives or a new reason to consider one of the alternatives better -- this should 
		be brought to the attention of the chair as a polite interrupt if time permits.  </t>

	<t>Chairs often pay careful attention to the wording of consensus calls in meetings, as do attendees.  Once 
		in a while, nuances the wording of the alternatives makes a significant difference in outcome.  </t>

	<t>For the minutes, jabber logs and audio recording, the chair should state the outcome after the consensus 
		call (in particular, raised hands cannot be seen via jabber or audio feeds).  Even though hums taken in
		meetings can be confirmed or not on the mailing lists (see section 4.3), chairs sometime state the 
		consensus as if it were final.  We also see phrases like "The Bar BoF consensus was..."  which is 
		obviously also limited to the participants of the Bar BoF, not to an official WG.  
		Since this is often simply a shorthand for a more accurate but no more helpful formulation, 
		one should not quibble with this wording.</t>

	<t>It may be worth pointing out that not every decision should be taken with hums in the room; that would be 
		very inefficient.  Good issues to address in meeting hums are often difficult issues involving preference 
		tradeoffs rather than pure technical feasibility.</t>
  	
		<section title="Easy consensus calls">
		

	<t>If a discussion isn't too heated the chair might simply take a stab at declaring consensus, ready to back
		off if the declaration was premature.

	<list><t>e.g. "Will suggests we deprecate error code 410.  Shall we do that then?  [hears approval noises]  Good"
	</t></list></t>

	<t>Alternatively:

	<list><t>e.g. "Will suggests we deprecate error code 410.  Shall we do that then?  [hears objections]  Ok, 
		it seems we don't all agree.  Can we hear from the objectors?"</t></list>
	</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Fine-tuning consensus calls">

	<t>A chair can fine-tune the wording of consensus calls on the fly.</t>

	<t><list><t>Chair:  Those in favour of proposal A, hum</t>
		<t>WEAK HUM</t>
		<t>Chair: Those against?</t>
		<t>SOME HUMS and MUTTERING about wording of consensus call</t>
		<t>Chair: Let me restate.   Those in favour of proposal B?</t>
		<t>WEAK HUM</t>
		<t>Chair:  That was rather indecisive.  Those who would accept either proposal? </t>
		<t>[silence]</t>
		<t>Chair:  Do we have a problem with the two alternatives?</t>
		<t>... group explores more solutions</t>
	</list></t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Chains of consensus calls">

	<t>In a meeting, a chair can make a related chain of consensus calls. An 
		experienced chair can make progress quickly by narrowing down the solution 
		set at a high level first then at lower levels.  </t>

	<t>One specific use of this is to first call for consensus on how to make a 
		decision on a difficult issue, then to call for consensus on the issue itself. </t>

	<t>Example consensus call chain</t>

	<t><list>
		<t>Chair:  We've been arguing about the details of this for quite a while.  
			Do we have enough information to make a decision on Sue's proposal?  
			Those who believe we're ready to make a decision, hum.</t>
		<t>		STRONG HUM</t>
		<t>Chair: Those who don't believe we're ready, hum.</t>
		<t>		[silence]</t>
		<t>Chair:  That's in favour of making a decision, so here's the decision: 
			Do we generally believe that we want the ability to fragment?  
			Those who want fragmentation, hum.</t>
		<t>		STRONG HUM</t>
		<t>Chair: Those who don't want fragmentation at all, hum</t>
		<t>		WEAK HUM</t>
		<t>Chair:  Assuming we want fragmentation capability then.  Do we want 
			fragmentation to be limited to messages over a certain size, not 
			picking the size just yet but in principle?  Those in favour of 
			allowing fragmentation all the time, hum</t>
		<t>		WEAK HUM</t>
		<t>	Those in favour of allowing fragmentation only on large messages, hum</t>
		<t>		STRONG HUM</t>
		<t>Chair:  Ok, so only on large messages.  Those in favour of fragmentation 
			allowed only on messages over 10,000...  </t>
	</list></t>

		</section>
	</section>
  	
  	<section title="Consensus Calls in Mailing Lists">
  		
  		<t>Some WGs only do consensus calls in mailing lists.  Sometimes these are 
  			WGs that never meet (and difficulties may be created in the long run by 
  			never meeting face to face -- but that's a topic for another document).  
  			In other cases, the WG may meet but have a preference for doing consensus 
  			calls on-list only.  </t>
  		
  		<t>Consensus calls on mailing lists are more obviously a continuum, a balance 
  			arrived at over time.  An initial proposal might inspire a few agreements 
  			or disagreements immediately, creating the first sense of possible consensus.  
  			It's actually quite frequent for an early decision to be obvious to everybody.</t> 
  		
  		<t>If consensus isn't obvious immediately, the discussion typically plays on for a 
  			while and additional opinions get added to the mix, and alternative proposals 
  			may be made.  At some point the chair may explicitly make a consensus call.  
  			Some WGs expect that even participants who have already stated a position will 
  			repeat their opinions after an explicit consensus call, while other WGs expect 
  			that any positions already stated still stand, and only new or changed 
  			positions need to be stated.  It can't hurt for chairs to be explicit about 
  			the expectation.</t>
  		
  		<t>Mailing list consensus calls need not be exclusive to a small set of alternatives.  
  			The discussion sparked by the consensus call can and should include new 
  			alternatives or creative compromises if any are thought of. </t>
  		
  		<section title="Sample effective consensus call on-list">
  			
  			<t>This email is effective in that it's clear that only new opinions are 
  				solicited, and how a participant can avoid confusion over what issue is discussed.</t>
  			
  			<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   From: Steve
   To: Example WG
   Subject: Open issues status

   We have three open issues:

   #87  Section 3.3  inconsistent use of word "modify"
   #89  Security Considerations needs to address DoS
   #90  Retry limits

   Are there any *new* (or changed) positions on these issues 
   before I declare consensus based on the discussion so far?  
   Please send one email per issue and include the issue number 
   in the subject.
		]]></artwork></figure>
  			
  			
  		</section>
  		<section title="Declaring consensus on-list">
  			
  			<t>It's helpful to be explicit about consensus reached.  Chairs need to 
  				state what an outcome is for those who aren't paying attention, for 
  				the record, and to remind those still arguing for different alternatives 
  				to present new information or accept the outcome.</t>
  			
  			<t>Sample</t>
  			
  			<figure><artwork>
   From: Alexander
   To: Example WG
   Subject: Issue #xxxx ReSubmission -- summary
  				
   So far I see some support for and elaboration of the 
   resubmission proposal,  although there was some dissent.  
   I think there's a consensus around allowing resubmission 
   even without a server error.  I saw the proposal to require 
   servers to accept resubmission but I didn't see any tangible 
   benefit to that.  
   Thus, the proposed resolution is that clients MAY resubmit, and 
   servers MAY accept or reject resubmissions.
  				
   We don't have consensus on whether the resubmit must have the 
   same message ID, so I'd like to see more input on that.
  			</artwork></figure>
  			
  			
  		</section>
  		
  		<section title="Confirming in-room consensus on Mailing List">
  			
  			<t>Although consensus calls in meetings must be confirmed on the list, 
  				we have flexibility in how this is done.  Often the consensus 
  				call is noted in the meeting minutes and silence (of two weeks or more) is considered to be consent.  
  				Although <xref target="RFC4677"/> says that "Any decision made 
  				at a face-to-face meeting must also gain consensus on the WG mailing 
  				list", <xref target="RFC2418"/> requires that the in-person opinions remain part of
  				the consensus, and implies that once mailing list participants have been
  				given the opportunity to understand and consider objections, the in-meeting 
  				consensus may well prevail without calling consensus from scratch: "the volume 
  				of messages on a topic is not, by itself, a good indicator of consensus".  </t>
  			
  			<t>The population that votes on a mailing list can be somewhat different 
  				than the population that votes meeting room.  Between meetings, people are more likely to 
  				vote against the consensus than bother to send a vote 
  				confirming the consensus so far, and this bias can magnify the appearance of dissent.  </t>
  				
			<t>The redress for people who disagree with the result of an in-room consensus call is to 
  				dissent on the mailing list, ideally within two weeks of meeting minutes being
				published (which, regrettably, is often a month or more after the meeting itself).  
			</t>
  			
  			<t>When chairs do review a meeting decision on the mailing list, since the votes made
  					during the meeting (and possibly from before the meeting) are already taken into account,  
  					it's not very helpful for participants to provide redundant opinion statements.  
  					In rare cases, a WG chair may have to ask everybody to restate their opinion 
  					even if they have already given it, in which case chairs must be very explicit about requesting
  					this.
  				</t>
  			
  			
  		</section>
  	</section>
  	
  	
    <section title="Alternative Approaches">
  				
 		<t>Sometimes proposals are too hotly debated or too close to call consensus 
 			easily.  These are a number of approaches that a chair might use to arrive 
 			at a decision, including those recommended in [RFC3929] (external or mixed 
 			review team, short straw, and random assignment).</t>
  				

    	<section title="Taking Time">
  				
  			<t>It's often quite effective for the chair to put off a consensus call, 
  				or having made a consensus call, to put off declaring an outcome.  
  				Although this sounds like an inefficient use of time, it can allow the 
  				WG to make progress on easier issues until more information is in.  
  			    Recall that consensus is not just about making a decision, it's also 
  			    about exploring alternatives, understanding a problem and creating 
  			commitment among participants; extra time can help particularly if one or more
  			of these facets needs more work.</t>
  				
  			<t>Examples:
  				
    		<list>
  				<t>"We're still having significant technical discussion on this.  
  					I know Shuichi had a strong opinion and he's not here, and it's 
  					possible his opinion could change based on some of this.  But we've 
  					run out of time in this meeting, so let's bring this discussion back 
  					to the mailing list.  Amy can you explain the race condition on the 
  					list?..."</t>
  				
  				<t>"I just heard weak hums on both sides of this issue, yet since it's 
  					an important issue, I think we want a stronger consensus.  Does 
  					anybody have any other solutions to suggest?  ... [silence]  ...  
  					Let's let this one marinate a bit.  We've got fourteen other open
  					issues to work on, I think that will take us a couple months, and 
  					we can revisit this later."</t>
    		</list>
  			</t>
    		
  			<t>Taking extra long time should not be the first choice if quicker 
  				solutions are available.  A chair that finds too many decisions taking 
  				too long should start to try to find shortcuts.  A pattern of long and 
  				difficult decision-making  might be an indication of a WG that needs to 
  				have a few beers together, or has grown too small and entrenched.  New 
  				people can be brought in temporarily (external review) or permanently, 
  				or the chair can compromise on the goals, leaving more work undone than 
  				previously intended.  
  			</t>
    	</section>
    	
		<section title="Deciding to Make a Decision">
  			<t>Sometimes opinion is narrowly split between two or more alternatives 
  				even after lengthy discussion, yet in the end the WG is willing to 
  				accept an arbitrary outcome once one is fairly chosen.  The WG may 
  				choose to use a non-consensus way to pick an alternative (e.g. counting 
  				votes) and we may still consider the outcome to be rough consensus.</t>
  				
  			<t>Often this "meta-decision" -- the decision to accept a decision -- is 
  				made in one consensus call in an in-person meeting, followed by the 
  				decision itself.  In-person meetings are great for the quick turnaround 
  				to make this possible.  It's always nice to have explicit WG permission 
  				to take an alternative approach. </t>
  				
 			<t><list><t>
 				"Let the minutes note that the WG agreed to a plurality vote in order 
 				to make a decision on this issue"

 			</t></list></t>
		</section>
    	<section title="Using votes and plurality decision-making">
  				
  			<t>When a chair decides to count votes carefully, this can mean that the 
  				WG explicitly chose plurality decision-making to resolve an impasse. 
  				(It can also mean that the chair is covering their ass in a WG where 
  				an individual is being difficult about what is actually a rough 
  				consensus that the individual would rather not have to accept.)</t>
  				
  			<t>It's usually obvious how to count votes in a mailing list, or if it's 
  				not obvious the longer time scale can allow clarification.  Chairs 
  				should encourage participants to vote openly.  Votes in private email 
  				to the chair make consensus more difficult, and the outcome less 
  				transparently justifiable.  A close call should not depend on private 
  				votes if at all possible.  </t>
  				
  			<t>It's somewhat less obvious how to vote in a room.  Chairs may sometimes 
  				want to make statements on how the voting will proceed before attempting 
  				to call the vote and count the results.
  				<list style="symbols">
  					<t>Is it OK to vote for two proposals?  If allowed, this can help 
  						show whether one proposal is acceptable to many, even if it's 
  						not the favourite proposal for most.  </t>
  					<t>Will votes in the Jabber room be counted?</t>
  				    <t>Who will do the counting?  </t>
  					
  				</list>
  			</t>
    	</section>
    	
    	<section title="Let the Editor Choose">
  				
	  		<t>Many decisions are not suitable for consensus calls.  If a participant 
	  			argues for a particular document organization, but the document author 
	  			prefers the document organization they have already, a chair should 
	  			usually defer to the author.  The choice of names for error codes or 
	  			namespaces is frequently up to the author.  We do not write documents 
	  			(even WG documents) by committee in the IETF.  Editorial discretion is
	  			still a valid part of our rough consensus.</t>
  				
  			<t>When the WG chair chooses a document editor and makes a point to use 
  				that term rather than 'author', it's typically with the understanding 
  				that the editor will take his cues from the WG and put the WG decisions 
  				in the document.  That doesn't mean that the editor can't have technical 
  				or editorial opinions and contribute them to the consensus.  In fact, 
  				the editor's opinion should not be taken lightly, on the grounds that 
  				they are paying attention, are knowledgeable about the domain, and were 
  				selected as editor for their abilities to think about and explain 
  				technical issues as well as for listening carefully to a variety of 
  				opinions.</t>
    	</section>
    	
  		<section title="Flipping a coin">
  				
  			<t>It's OK to flip a coin. A coin-flip may be perfectly appropriate to 
  				make a minor decision quickly and fairly, or to choose between two 
  				alternatives that are well-balanced in support and tradeoffs.  
  				If there are two element names under consideration for an XML element, 
  				after a brief argument about which name is better, a chair may flip a 
  				coin (or allow the editor to flip a coin)  and declare one the winner.</t>  
  				
  			<t>It's OK even to virtually flip a coin.  Again, with two alternative names 
  				having been discussed for five minutes, a chair might say "Ok, enough of 
  				this, let's pick the first one and move on."  Participants can assume 
  				that the chair is acting out of a desire for efficiency and not in order
  				to destroy fairness.</t>
  		</section>
    </section>
  	
  	<section title="Accountability">
  		<t>Those who call consensus are accountable to the community and responsible for outcomes.
  			They should be prepared to explain their decisions, and at times even review and revisit
  			their decisions.  To explain consensus decisions, it always helps to
  		have a good record.  Where possible, the consensus record can be public:
  		well-minuted consensus decisions in proceedings (required anyway), along with clear conclusions to 
  		consensus calls on public mailing lists. </t>
  		
  		
  		<t>Chairs who use design teams and creative consensus calls (e.g. plurality votes) are more
  			likely to be called to account for decisions, and appropriately so.</t>

  		
  		<section title="Challenging Consensus Call Results">
  			<t>Chairs and ADs make great efforts to attend 
  				meetings and read every email on a mailing list in order to have an 
  				ongoing sense of consensus on all important issues.  In addition, there 
  				may be hallway discussions or phone conversations with information or opinions
  				relating to a consensus decision.  We can't second-guess every consensus call.
  				Sometimes we have to trust the decision history and long-term performance of 
  				the person chosen to make consensus calls.</t>
  			
  			<t>It is appropriate to discuss the process details of a consensus call at times.  
  				For example, one might alert the 
  				community and its leaders to questionable aspects of an important and close 
  				consensus call.  An example of this was a meeting where participants voted either remotely via 
  				Jabber or in the physical room.  Later, the chairs learned from private input 
  				that several of the Jabber votes were from dynamically-generated nicknames 
  				that had all connected to Jabber at the same time from the same IP address. </t>
  			
  			<t>Sometimes, learning of an irregularity can lead a chair to reset and call 
  				for consensus again.  However, if there were a rule insisting on a reset, 
  				this could easily be manipulated by bad actors introducing procedural 
  				irregularities in order to force new consensus calls.  Even when informed 
  				of distasteful tactics and irregularities in the call, it's still up to 
  				the chairs whether to let a consensus stand.  </t>
  			
  			<t>When a previous decision is invoked, sometimes WG 
  				participants say something like "We decided this in Oslo", referring 
  				to a meeting.  If a consensus call was made in a meeting in Oslo and 
  				not shortly overturned on the list, then this statement is a reasonable 
  				approximation of history.  Rather than 
  				nitpick the wording of this, it's most helpful to say something like 
  				"Regardless, I think there's new information here and I'd like to see 
  				if the consensus has changed." A chair may or may not agree and call for 
  				consensus again.</t>  				
  			
  			
  		</section>
  	
  	<section title="Sample challenge to a mailing list consensus call">
  		<figure>
  			<artwork>
  From: Jay 
  To: Example Working Group
  Subject: Pushing back on Modified Property Consensus Call
  				
  I'd like to push back on this consensus call. I read through the
  threads and didn't see rousing support for this proposal and I 
  am currently -1 on it. Some of the problems were never brought
  to the surface during the discussion, the largest being that
  this adds a mandatory (MUST) level element to an entry, which
  the base spec never required.
  				
  				
  From: Michael
  To: Jay, Example Working Group
  Subject: Re: Pushing back on Modified Property Consensus Call
  				
  Hmm, upon further review, while this proposal did have some friendly 
  comment, "lots of support" might have been overstating it.   I seem 
  to have counted at least one person twice.  And Jay's point below 
  about the collision with the base spec seems pretty telling.  Would 
  anyone like to jump up and shout in favor of saving it?
  				
  			</artwork>
  		</figure>
  	</section>
  	
  	<section title="Overturning Consensus Call Outcomes">
  		<t>Consensus calls need not be final.  However, there can be some harm in overturning
  			a consensus call.
  			<list style="symbols"><t>A new consensus necessarily takes more time.</t>
  				<t>New discussions can be frustrating to those who participated in prior 
  					consensus calls, particular if long discussions were involved then.</t>
  				<t>A change can be destabilizing to the documents and editing process</t>
  				<t>The later consensus call can represent quite a different group of people, 
  					perhaps because new people are alerted to the issue, but perhaps because long-standing 
  					participants have given up or run out of time to dedicate.</t>
  			</list>
  		</t>
  		
  			<t>However, the harm may at times 
  			be more than balanced by the good that comes of making a decision that 
  			participants have more confidence in.   Chairs need to be very explicit 
  				about voiding the consensus so that people know to speak up again.</t>
  		
  		<t>One of the most difficult situations to handle is when a WG has consensus, but the WG
  			document proves not to have IETF consensus or IESG approval.  Both "community consensus" (which 
  			can include anybody since IETF and WG membership are not limited) and 
  			IESG approval are required by <xref target="RFC2026"/>, whereas WG consensus is not mentioned
  			(see also <xref target="RFC4677"/>).   
  			The first step is to allow the WG
  			an opportunity to evaluate the new input.  If the consensus on the WG mailing list 
  			remains the same, it becomes difficult to weight the IETF Last Call input to decide whether it
  			falls in the "rough" part of rough consensus.  We can rule out
  			weighting the new input at zero as well as weighting the original WG consensus at zero, 
  			but somewhere in between those two extremes is a difficult judgement call and a large region
  			where more consensus-developing effort is required.  It can
  			certainly take time to get the differing parties talking, but a standoff can take 
  			even more time and a standoff doesn't progress towards a good, well-approved technical standard. </t>
  		
  	</section>
  	
  	</section>  		
  	
    <section title="Recommendations for Individual Participants">
  			
    		<t>Participants are naturally important in determining rough consensus 
    			when they voice opinions.  Participants can be even more valuable 
    			helping chairs gauge and reach consensus by listening, explaining, 
    			mediating, proposing clear actions, helping others participate and so 
    			on.  This section provides some specific tips or ideas to consider.  See
    		also <xref target="RFC3184"/> for the IETF Guidelines for Conduct.</t>
  		
    	<section title="What if you don't agree?">
  			<t>It can be difficult to find oneself in the "rough" part of rough 
  					consensus.  Strongly held personal convictions must sometimes make 
  					way for the consensus of the group.  These are some approaches to 
  					be considered once a participant has already attempted to voice 
  					their opinion and explain the technical basis for it, and still 
  					finds themselves  dissatisfied enough to take further action.</t>
    		
    		<t>Can convictions be assuaged by stating or restating them?
  				
    			<list><t>
  				"I'd like to state for the record that I still believe this feature 
    				is unnecessary, but I won't argue any further."</t>
    			</list>
    		</t>
    				
  			<t>Is it possible to seek elaboration either to become convinced or show 
  				those in the consensus so far that they don't necessarily agree?
  				
  				<list><t>"I don't understand if this decision is being made based on 
  					a belief that language negotiation is too difficult, or based on 
  					not seeing the need for negotiation.  Although Linda already 
  					declared the consensus call, it would help me understand whether 
  					it's worthwhile trying to convince people that it's easier than 
  					it looks, or if that's a wasted effort".</t></list>
  			</t>
  				
  			<t>Finally, it's each participant's job to build consensus rather than to 
  				demand it.  It can really help to talk to other individuals privately 
  				and find out why they agree or disagree with you.  </t>
    	</section>
    	
  		<section title="Avoiding blocked consensus">
  				
			<t>It helps not to state positions so strongly that one feels one's 
			reputation is staked on a particular outcome!
			<list><t>
  				BAD: "It's not acceptable to change this header in a way that's 
				not backwards-compatible."  
				</t><t>
				ALSO BAD: "I won't allow..." or "we 
				can't" (when there's no strict technical infeasibility.)</t>
			<t>
  				BETTER:  "I strongly feel that we should not change this header 
				unless we can do so in a way that is backwards-compatible."</t>
			<t>
  				EVEN BETTER: "Is there some way we can do this without breaking 
				backward compatibility?"</t>
			<t>
  				ALSO GOOD: "Why do people feel strongly enough about this to break 
				backwards compatibility?  I don't think I understand that tradeoff."</t>
			</list>
			</t>
  			
  			<t>Making an issue personal can bake people into firm oppositional 
  				positions.  Avoid the temptation to make personal accusations or to 
  				oppose a person per se.  Oppose the proposal, not the proposer.  
  				One specific tactic to reduce knee-jerk opposition is to ask somebody 
  				to explain the other position to show they understand it.</t>
  			
  		</section>
    	
    	<section title="Questioning the process">
  				
    		<t>First, remember that it looks bad for your technical position to 
    			challenge the outcome on a process basis!  Often challenging the 
    			process can be avoided by suggesting a process rather than criticizing 
    			what happened.  Example: </t>
    		
    		<t><list><t>"Can we take a hum on that issue?  I'm not sure everybody is 
    			really going along with Vlad's proposal."</t>
    		</list></t>
    		
    		<t> Often, a participant who disagrees with the way a decision was made also 
    			disagrees with the decision itself.  It helps to address these separately.  
    			The best way to dispute the decision
    		being made is to offer a technical or other reasonable opinion, perhaps with explicit
    		notes about tradeoff preferences, and ideally with new information.  In contrast, the 
    		best way to dispute the way the decision was reached is to question the process and appeal
    		to principles of fairness and openness.  </t>
  				
  			<t>When the situation merits criticizing the process, the critic needs to 
  				be clear about what went wrong or what needs to be remedied.  Cries of 
  				"unfair" are not usually helpful without more detail.  Again, to avoid 
  				making the issue personal, one can typically simply ask the chair to 
  				remedy the situation (and explain why) rather than accuse them of errors.
  				Example: 
  			</t>
    		
  			<t><list><t>"I'd like to ask the chair to take that consensus call to the 
  				list, from scratch.  I think this proposal is too complicated for us to 
  				really be able to hum for consensus right now."</t></list></t>
  				  				
    	</section>
    	
    	<section title="Final tips">
  				
  			<t>It helps to state why one is rejecting a proposal when the consensus 
  				call is yay/nay on a single proposal.</t>
  				
  			<t><list><t>"I'm -1 on this proposal.  We'll have to deal with difficult 
  				i18n concerns if we head down this path."</t></list></t>
    		
    		<t>When accepting a proposal it's fine to be very brief.
    		
    		<list>
    			<t>"+1".</t>
    		</list>
  				
    		</t>
  				
  			<t>It helps to state on what basis one chooses between two proposals.</t>
  				
  			<t><list><t>
  				"I prefer the stateless approach over the token approach.  Generally 
  				I like pushing the work to servers, but in this case keeping state can 
  				degrade performance noticeably."
  				
  			</t></list></t>
    		
  		</section>
  	</section>

	
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    	<t>Thanks to Harald Alvestrand, Mary Barnes, Steve Bellovin, Tim Bray, Joe Gregorio,
    		Tony Hansen, and Cullen Jennings.  Some provided comments directly, and others 
    		provided examples of good consensus practices or expressed its principles nicely on 
    		discussion lists.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>There are no IANA considerations introduced in this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>There are no security considerations arising from the information in this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>

    <references title="Informative References">

      &RFC2026;
      &RFC2418;
    	&RFC3184;
    	&RFC3929;
    	&RFC4677;
    	<reference anchor="BUJ">
      	<front>
      		<title>Building United Judgement -- A Handbook for Consensus Decision Making</title>
      		<author>
      			<organization>Center for Conflict Resolution</organization>
      		</author>
      		<date year="1981"/>
      	</front>
      </reference>
    	
    <reference anchor="Hol">
    	<front>
    		<title>The Rank-Order Effect in Group Decision Making</title>
    		<author surname="Hollingshead" initials="A.B">
    			<organization></organization>
    		</author>
    		<date month="December" year="1996"/>
    	</front>
    	<seriesInfo name="Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes, Vol. 68, No. 3., pp. 181-193." value=""/>
    </reference>
    	
	<reference anchor="AA">
		<front>
			<title>Flaming in electronic communication</title>
			<author surname="Alonzo" initials="M">
				<organization></organization>
			</author>
			<author surname="Aiken" initials="M">
				<organization></organization>
			</author>
			
			<date year="2004" month="January"/>
		</front>
		<seriesInfo name="Decision Support Systems, Vol. 36, No. 3., pp. 205-213." value=""/>
	</reference>
    	
    	
    	
    </references>
      

  </back>
</rfc>
