<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt'?>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc tocompact='yes'?>
<?rfc tocdepth='6'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<rfc ipr="full3978" docName="draft-ietf-rohc-ikev2-extensions-hcoipsec-07">


	<front>
		<title abbrev="IKEv2 Extensions to Support ROHCoIPsec">IKEv2 Extensions to Support Robust Header Compression over IPsec (ROHCoIPsec)</title>


		<date month="October" year="2008"/>


		<author initials="E." surname="Ertekin" fullname="Emre Ertekin">
			<organization>Booz Allen Hamilton</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>13200 Woodland Park Dr.</street>
					<city>Herndon</city>
					<region>VA</region>
					<code>20171</code>
					<country>US</country>
				</postal>
				<email>ertekin_emre@bah.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="C." surname="Christou" fullname="Chris Christou">
			<organization>Booz Allen Hamilton</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>13200 Woodland Park Dr.</street>
					<city>Herndon</city>
					<region>VA</region>
					<code>20171</code>
					<country>US</country>
				</postal>
				<email>christou_chris@bah.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="R." surname="Jasani" fullname="Rohan Jasani">
			<organization>Booz Allen Hamilton</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>13200 Woodland Park Dr.</street>
					<city>Herndon</city>
					<region>VA</region>
					<code>20171</code>
					<country>US</country>
				</postal>
				<email>jasani_rohan@bah.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="J." surname="Pezeshki" fullname="Jonah Pezeshki">
			<organization>Booz Allen Hamilton</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>13200 Woodland Park Dr.</street>
					<city>Herndon</city>
					<region>VA</region>
					<code>20171</code>
					<country>US</country>
				</postal>
				<email>pezeshki_jonah@bah.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		
		<abstract>
			<t>In order to integrate ROHC with IPsec [ROHCOIPSEC], a mechanism is needed to negotiate ROHC configuration parameters between end-points.  Internet Key Exchange (IKE) is a mechanism which can be leveraged to handle these negotiations.  This document specifies extensions to IKEv2 [IKEV2] that will allow ROHC and its associated configuration parameters to be negotiated for IPsec security associations (SAs).</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>


	<middle>
		

		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>Increased packet header overhead due to IPsec [IPSEC] can result in the inefficient utilization of bandwidth.  Coupling ROHC [ROHC] with IPsec offers an efficient way to transfer protected IP traffic.</t>
                        <t>The operation of ROHCoIPsec [ROHCOIPSEC] requires configuration parameters to be negotiated between the compressor and decompressor.  Current specifications for hop-by-hop ROHC negotiate these parameters through a link-layer protocol such as Point-to-Point Protocol (PPP) (i.e. ROHC over PPP [ROHCPPP]). Since key exchange protocols (e.g.  IKEv2) can be used to negotiate parameters between IPsec peers, this document defines extensions to IKEv2 to negotiate ROHC parameters for ROHCoIPsec.</t>
		</section>

		<section title="ROHC Channel Negotiation">
			<t>The initialization of a ROHC session requires the negotiation of a set of configuration parameters (e.g. MAX_CID, PROFILES, etc.).  The following subsections define extensions to IKEv2 which enables an initiator to propose a set of ROHC parameters; the responder selects the appropriate parameters from this list, and responds with the accepted parameters for the ROHC channel.</t>
                      			
			<section title="Negotiation of ROHC Channel Parameters">
				<t>ROHC configuration parameters will be negotiated at either the establishment or rekeying of a Child SA.  Specifically, a new Notify message type is used during the IKE_AUTH and CREATE_CHILD_SA exchanges to negotiate these parameters.  </t>
 				<t>The Notify payload sent by the initiator contains the configuration parameters for the ROHC implementation.  Upon receipt of the initiator's request, the responder will either ignore the payload (if it doesn't support ROHC or the proposed parameters) or respond with a Notify payload that contains the accepted ROHC channel parameters.  The accepted parameters are an intersection between the parameters proposed by the initiator and the parameters supported by the responder (e.g. if the initiator proposes a MAX_CID value of 15, but the responder only supports a MAX_CID value of 13, the responder will respond with a value of 13, which is supported by both parties).</t>
				<t>Note that only one Notify payload is used to convey ROHC parameters per exchange.  If multiple Notify payloads relaying ROHC parameters are received by the responder, all but the first such Notify payload must be dropped.   If the initiator does not receive a Notify Payload with the responder's accepted ROHC channel parameters, ROHC must not be enabled on the Child SA. </t>
				<t>A new Notify Message Type value, denoted ROHC_SUPPORTED, will indicate that the Notify payload is conveying ROHC channel parameters.  The Notify Payload (as defined in [IKEV2]) is illustrated in Figure 1 below:</t>
 				<t><figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="center" alt="" width="" height=""><artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
					<![CDATA[
                           1                   2                   3
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      ! Next Payload  !C!  RESERVED   !         Payload Length        !
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      !  Protocol ID  !   SPI Size    !      Notify Message Type      !
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      !                                                               !
      ~                Security Parameter Index (SPI)                 ~
      !                                                               !
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      !                                                               !
      ~                       Notification Data                       ~
      !                                                               !
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

                      Figure 1. Notify Payload format.

		]]></artwork></figure></t>
	      <t><postamble/></t>
<t>The fields of the Notify Payload are set as follows:</t>
		         <t>Next Payload (1 octet)
			 <list style="empty"><t>
			 Identifier for the payload type of the next payload in the message.  Further details can be found in [IKEV2].</t></list></t>
				<t>Critical (1 bit)
				<list style="empty"><t>
				Since all IKEv2 implementations must support the Notify Payload, this value is zero.</t></list></t>
				<t>Protocol ID (1 octet)
				<list style="empty"><t>
				Since this Notification message is used during the creation of a Child SA, this field must be set to zero.</t></list></t>
				<t>SPI Size (1 octet)
				<list style="empty"><t>
				This value must be set to zero, since no SPI is applicable (ROHC parameters are set at SA creation, thus the SPI has not been defined).</t></list></t>
				<t>Notify Message Type (2 octets)
				<list style="empty"><t>
				This field must be set to ROHC_SUPPORTED.</t></list></t>


				<t>ROHC configuration parameters will be communicated via a new Notify message type, denoted ROHC_SUPPORTED.  The ROHC configuration parameters will be listed within the Notification Data field of the Notify payload in the following format (default values for the configuration parameters are consistent with [ROHCPPP]):</t>
				<t>
			          <figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="center" alt="" width="" height="">
                                <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[
                           1                   2                   3
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      !            MAX_CID            |    RESERVED   |PROFILES_LENGTH!
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      !                                                               !
      ~                           PROFILES...                         ~
      !                                                               !
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      !                                                               !
      ~                     INTEGRITY ALGORITHMS...                   ~
      !                                                               !
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                                    ]]></artwork>
					<postamble>Figure 2.  Notification Data field for the ROHC_SUPPORTED Notify message type.  </postamble>
					</figure>

				</t>

				<t>MAX_CID (2 octets)
				<list style="empty"><t>
				The MAX_CID field indicates the maximum value of a context identifier.  This value must be at least 0 and at most 16383 (The value 0 implies having one context).</t></list></t>
				<t><list style="empty"><t>Suggested value: 15</t></list></t>
				<t>PROFILES_LENGTH (1 octet)
                        <list style="empty"><t>The total number of profiles contained within the PROFILES field (note that each ROHC profile is 2-octets in length).</t></list></t>
                        <t>PROFILES (variable)
				<list style="empty"><t>
				The set of profiles to be enabled for the ROHC process.  Profiles are further detailed in [ROHC].  In addition, several common profiles are defined in [ROHCPROF].  These 16-bit profile identifiers are to be sent in network byte order.</t></list></t>
                        <t>INTEGRITY ALGORITHMS
                        <list style="empty"><t>
			      The set of Integrity Algorithms that may be use to ensure the
                        integrity of the decompressed packets (i.e. ensure that the
                        packet headers are properly decompressed).  Each Integrity Algorithm is
                        represented by a 2-octet value that corresponds to the value
                        listed in [IKEV2-PARA] "For Transform Type 3 (Integrity
                        Algorithm)" section.</t>
				<t>It is noted that:
					<list style="numbers">
						<t>The length of this field is inferred from the Notify Payload's "Payload Length" field.</t>
						<t>The key for this Integrity Algorithm is computed using the same method as is used to compute IPsec's Integrity Algorithm key ([IKEV2], Section 2.17).</t>
                                    <t>A ROHCoIPsec implementation may choose to negotiate a value of "0" in this field (i.e., NONE, as defined in the Integrity Algorithm Transform ID registry).</t>
					</list></t>
				</list></t>
				<t>The negotiated set of ROHC parameters are associated with the inbound/outbound pair of SAs established by each IKEv2 CREATE_CHILD_SA exchange.</t>
		            <t>The following ROHC channel parameters are not negotiated:
				<list style="symbols">
				    <t>LARGE_CIDS: This value is implicitly determined by the value of MAX_CID (e.g. if MAX_CID is &lt;= 15, LARGE_CIDS is assumed to be 0).</t>
				    <t>MRRU: IPsec implementations will always implement path MTU discovery; therefore, ROHC packets will never need to use ROHC segmentation over an IPsec SA.  As a result, this value will always be zero, and does not need to be negotiated.</t>
				    <t>FEEDBACK_FOR: When a pair of SAs are created (one in each direction), the ROHC channel parameter FEEDBACK_FOR is set implicitly to the other SA of the pair (i.e. the SA pointing in the reverse direction).</t>                  
				</list></t>
				</section>
			</section>


		<section title="Security Considerations">
			<t>The ROHC channel parameters negotiated via IKEv2 do not add any new vulnerabilities beyond those associated with the normal operation of IKEv2.</t>
		</section>
		<section title="IANA Considerations">
			<t>This document defines a new Notify Message (Status Type).  Therefore, IANA is requested to allocate one value from the IKEv2 Notify Message registry to indicate ROHC_SUPPORTED.  Note that, since this Notify Message is a Status Type, values ranging from 0 to 16383 must not be allocated for ROHC_SUPPORTED.</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Acknowledgments">
			<t>The authors would like to thank Mr. Sean O'Keeffe, Mr. James Kohler, and Ms. Linda Noone of the Department of Defense, as well as Mr. Rich Espy of OPnet for their contributions and support in the development of this document.  The authors would also like to thank Mr. Tero Kivinen for providing his technical expertise for this document. In addition, the authors would like to thank the following for their numerous reviews and comments to this document:</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
<t>Dr. Stephen Kent</t>
<t>Dr. Carsten Bormann</t>
<t>Mr. Lars-Erik Jonnson</t>
<t>Mr. Pasi Eronen</t>
<t>Dr. Joseph Touch</t>
<t>Mr. Yoav Nir</t>
</list></t>
<t>Finally, the authors would also like to thank Mr. Tom Conkle, Ms. Michele Casey, and Mr. Etzel Brower.</t>
		</section>


	</middle>


	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			<reference anchor="ROHCOIPSEC">
				<front>
					<title>Integration of Robust Header Compression over IPsec Security Associations</title>
					<author initials="E." surname="Ertekin" fullname="E. Ertekin">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="C." surname="Christou" fullname="C. Christou">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="R." surname="Jasani" fullname="R. Jasani">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="October" year="2008"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="work in progress" value=""/>
			</reference>

			<reference anchor="ROHC">
				<front>
					<title>RObust Header Compression (ROHC): Framework and four profiles: RTP, UDP, ESP, and uncompressed</title>
					<author initials="C." surname="Bormann">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="C." surname="Burmeister">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="M." surname="Degermark">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="H." surname="Fukushima">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="H." surname="Hannu">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="L." surname="Jonsson">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="R." surname="Hakenberg">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="T." surname="Koren">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="K." surname="Le">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="Z." surname="Liu">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="A." surname="Martensson">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="A." surname="Miyazaki">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="K." surname="Svanbro">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="T." surname="Wiebke">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="T." surname="Yoshimura">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="H." surname="Zheng">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="July" year="2001"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3095"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="IPSEC">
				<front>
					<title>Security Architecture for the Internet Protocol</title>
					<author initials="S." surname="Kent" fullname="S. Kent">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="K." surname="Seo" fullname="K. Seo">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="December" year="2005"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4301"/>
			</reference>

			<reference anchor="IKEV2">
				<front>
					<title>Internet Key Exchange (IKEv2) Protocol</title>
					<author initials="C." surname="Kaufman">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="December" year="2005"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4306"/>
			</reference>

			<reference anchor="ROHCPPP">
				<front>
					<title>Robust Header Compression (ROHC) over PPP</title>
					<author initials="C." surname="Bormann">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="April" year="2002"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3241"/>
			</reference>
		</references>

		<references title="Informative References">
			<reference anchor="ROHCPROF">
				<front>
					<title>RObust Header Compression Version 2 (ROHCv2): Profiles for RTP, UDP, IP, ESP and UDP Lite</title>
					<author initials="G." surname="Pelletier">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="K." surname="Sandlund">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="May" year="2007"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="www.iana.org/assignments/ROHC-pro-ids" value=""/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="IKEV2-PARA">
				<front>
					<title>IKEv2 Parameters, http://www.iana.org/assignments/ikev2-parameters</title>
					<date month="January" year="2008"/>
					<author surname="IANA">
            				<organization />
          				</author>
		            </front>
			</reference>
		</references>
	</back>
</rfc>
