<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5213 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3315 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4861 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4282 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4282.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xslt/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<?rfc notedraftinprogress="yes"?>
<rfc docName="draft-neumann-netlmm-inter-domain-02" ipr="trust200811">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Inter-Domain PMIP">Inter-Domain Handover and Data
    Forwarding between Proxy Mobile IPv6 Domains</title>

    <author fullname="Niklas Neumann" initials="N." surname="Neumann">
      <organization abbrev="University of Goettingen">University of
      Goettingen</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Computer Networks Group</street>

          <street>Goldschmidtstrasse 7</street>

          <code>37077</code>

          <city>Goettingen</city>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <email>neumann@cs.uni-goettingen.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Xiaoming Fu" initials="X." surname="Fu">
      <organization abbrev="University of Goettingen">University of
      Goettingen</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Computer Networks Group</street>

          <street>Goldschmidtstrasse 7</street>

          <code>37077</code>

          <city>Goettingen</city>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <email>fu@cs.uni-goettingen.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jun Lei" initials="J." surname="Lei">
      <organization abbrev="University of Goettingen">University of
      Goettingen</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Computer Networks Group</street>

          <street>Goldschmidtstrasse 7</street>

          <code>37077</code>

          <city>Goettingen</city>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <email>lei@cs.uni-goettingen.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Gong  Zhang" initials="G." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Corporate Research Department</street>

          <street>B-1 Building, Longgang</street>

          <code>518129</code>

          <city>Shenzhen</city>

          <country>P.R.China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>Nicholas@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2009" />

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>proxy mobile ip inter-domain handover</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies mechanisms to setup and maintain handover and
      data forwarding procedures that allow a mobile node to move between
      different domains that provide (localized) network-based mobility
      support based on Proxy Mobile IPv6 for that node.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>A mobile node in the current Internet needs to maintain a fixed
      endpoint when it moves to allow for seamless connectivity with its
      corresponding nodes. When the mobile nodes moves between network-based
      mobility domains that are under different administrative control, this
      becomes challenging. One network is responsible for the communication
      endpoint while the other network provides the actual mobility services
      to the mobile node. This document proposes an approach to solve this
      problem by using inter-domain signaling to setup session handover and
      data forwarding between the different domains.</t>

      <t>A network-based localized mobility management solution like Proxy
      Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6) <xref target="RFC5213"></xref> provides a mobile
      node with mobility within the PMIPv6-enabled domain it is deployed in.
      When the mobile node leaves the network, however, the mobility support
      breaks since the mobile node moves out of the administrative reach of
      the local mobility solution.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions &amp; Terminology ">
      <section title="Conventions used in this document ">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>Mobility Session<list style="empty">
            <t>The period of time in which the mobile node needs mobility
            support from the network. If the mobile node reaches a state where
            it currently does not need mobility support, the mobility session
            can safely be reset. During a mobility session the network-based
            mobility solution described in this document offers the mobile a
            fixed end-point for its communications, namely the session
            mobility anchor, which stays valid even when the mobile node moves
            between Proxy Mobile IP domains.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Session Mobility Anchor<list style="empty">
            <t>A fixed end-point which relays all the communication for the
            mobile node. This is the local mobility anchor of the first Proxy
            Mobile IP domain that a mobile node is connected to during a
            mobility session.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview">
      <t>In order to provide continuous mobility support for a mobile nodes
      that is moving between different mobility domains, a steady anchor point
      has to be provided for corresponding nodes. In Mobile IP, for example,
      this is the home agent while in Proxy Mobile IP this is the local
      mobility anchor (LMA). This anchor point allows the mobile node to
      change its point of attachment to a network without its corresponding
      nodes noticing that. All the mobile node's traffic is routed through the
      local mobility anchor which then forwards the traffic to the mobile
      node. When a mobile node leaves a Proxy Mobile IP domain, however, it
      moves beyond the control of the local mobility anchor and therefore its
      mobility breaks.</t>

      <t>When a mobile node initially attaches to a Proxy Mobile IP domain,
      the local mobility anchor becomes the session mobility anchor (SMA) for
      the mobile node. For the duration of the mobility session this session
      mobility anchor will handle all incoming and outgoing connections for
      the mobile node. As long as the mobile node stays within the local Proxy
      Mobile IP domain, this only includes regular Proxy Mobile IPv6
      operations as described in <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>. When the
      mobile node leaves the local Proxy Mobile IP domain, however, the new
      Proxy Mobile IP domain's local mobility anchor will initialize a tunnel
      to the session mobility anchor to allow the session mobility anchor to
      continue serving as an anchor point for the mobile node as shown in
      <xref target="figure_movement"></xref>. Within the new Proxy
      Mobile IP domain all regular Proxy Mobile IP operations still apply with
      the exception that all traffic for the mobile node is tunneled from the
      new local mobility anchor to the session mobility anchor which in turn
      communicates with the correspondent node.</t>

      <figure anchor="figure_movement" title="Movement">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
    [CN]
     ||
     ||
   [LMA_1   >===========================================> [LMA_3]
    = SMA]] >=================> [LMA_2]      Tunnel          |
     |           Tunnel           |                          |
     |                            |                          |
     |                            |                          |
     |                            |                          |
   [MAG]                        [MAG]                      [MAG]
     |                            |                          |
    MN ------------------------> MN ----------------------> MN
                Movement                     Movement

]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>For all intends and purposes from the point of view of the session
      mobility anchor, the current local mobility anchor of a mobile node can
      be seen as a mobile access gateway which performs the corresponding
      operations.</t>

      <section title="Finding the Session Mobility Anchor">
        <t>When a mobile node attaches to a Proxy Mobile IP domain, the local
        mobility anchor of this domain has to locate the session mobility
        anchor for this mobile node and initiate a tunnel between itself and
        the session mobility anchor. In case the Proxy Mobile IP domain is the
        first domain the mobile node attaches to within its mobility session,
        the current local mobility anchor becomes the session mobility anchor
        and continues with its regular Proxy Mobile IP operations. If the
        mobile node already has been attached to a different Proxy Mobile IP
        domain, it's session mobility anchor resides within this previous
        domain and the local mobility anchor needs to establish a binding with
        the session mobility anchor in order to send and receive the data for
        the mobile node through its session mobility anchor. Depending on the
        scenario, the local mobility anchor can directly or indirectly locate
        the session mobility anchor for a mobile node.</t>

        <section anchor="section_direct_location" title="Direct Location">
          <t>Direct location of a session mobility anchor for a mobile node
          requires some kind of look-up between associated Proxy Mobile IP
          domains. For example, this can be achieved by maintaining a common
          database where session mobility anchors deposit the information for
          which mobile node they are responsible for. Such a database can be
          established by service level agreements between the operators of
          Proxy Mobile IP domains. For a local mobility anchor to locate the
          session mobility anchor for a mobile node it will send a look-up
          request to the database using the mobile node's identity (e.g. its
          Network Access Identifier (NAI) <xref target="RFC4282"></xref>) as
          the look-up key. If the database does not have an entry for the
          mobile node, the local mobility anchor becomes the session mobility
          anchor for the mobility session of the mobile node.</t>

          <t>This common database can be implemented as a virtual mobility
          anchor (VMA) as shown in <xref target="figure_vma"></xref>.
          The virtual mobility anchor is shared across all mobility domains
          and processes specific proxy binding updates from their local
          mobility anchors. It is called virtual mobility anchor since it does not relay any
          traffic for mobile nodes. When a mobile node attaches to a PMIP
          domain the corresponding local mobility anchor sends a Proxy Binding
          Update to the virtual mobility anchor which includes the mobile
          node's identity (e.g. its Network Access Identifier (NAI) <xref
          target="RFC4282"></xref>) or it's link layer address) and the S flag
          set to 1 (see  <xref target="section_pbum"></xref>). It also includes the Session Destination option set to the
          global address of the local mobility anchor. If the virtual mobility
          anchor already has a binding for the mobile node, it forwards the
          Proxy Binding Update to the particular session mobility anchor. The
          session mobility anchor updates it's own bindings and responds with
          a Proxy Binding Acknowledgment to the virtual mobility anchor which
          also has the S flag set and includes a Session Mobility Anchor
          Address option which is set to the global address of the session
          mobility anchor (see  <xref target="section_pbam"></xref>). If the virtual mobility anchor does not have a
          binding for the particular mobile node, it creates one and replies
          with Proxy Binding Acknowledgment that indicates that no session
          mobility anchor was found by including a Session Mobility Anchor
          Address option which is set to an empty address. The local mobility
          anchor then regards itself as the session mobility anchor.</t>

          <figure anchor="figure_vma"
                  title="Direct location of the session mobility anchor using a virtual mobility anchor">
            <artwork><![CDATA[


              /---[VMA]---\      
         /---/    /   \    \---\ 
        /        /     \        \
       /   /----/       \----\   \
 3.   /   /  2.           1.  \   \  4.
 PBA /   /   PBU          PBU  \   \ PBA
    /   /                       \   \
   [SMA] >=================> [LMA_2] 
     |          5. Tunnel         |
     |                            |
     |                            |
     |                            |
   [MAG]                        [MAG]
     |                            |
    MN ------------------------> MN
                Movement           

]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="section_indirect_location" title="Indirect Location">
          <t>If no common database exists between Proxy Mobile IP domains, the
          local mobility anchor can use an indirect scheme to locate the
          session mobility anchor of a mobile node. For this purpose, the
          local mobility anchor infers the session mobility anchor assigned IP
          address of the mobile node and uses this address to send its session
          transfer request to. Since the session mobility anchor is
          responsible for this IP address, the local mobility anchor will
          indirectly reach the session mobility anchor. If there is no reply
          to the request, the local mobility anchor must assume that no
          previous session mobility anchor exists and itself become the
          session mobility anchor for the mobility session of the mobile node.
          The session mobility anchor assigned IP address of a mobile node is
          the IP address the mobile node got assigned when it initially
          attached to a Proxy Mobile IP domain. The local mobility anchor can
          try to infer this IP address, for example, by analyzing the mobile
          node's Router Solicitation messages <xref target="RFC4861"></xref>
          or DHCP requests <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Assumptions">
        <t>This document assumes that there are some operational agreements
        between the operators of the different Proxy Mobile IP domains. Part
        of this agreement are, for example, the conditions under which users
        are allowed to move between domains and the location method that is
        used to find the session mobility anchor.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Inter-Domain Mobility Support">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Registration of a new Mobile Node">
        <t>When a new mobile node attaches to a Proxy Mobile IP domain, the
        corresponding local mobility anchor registers itself as the new local
        mobility anchor for the mobile node with the session mobility anchor
        of the mobile node.</t>

        <figure anchor="figure_signal_flow" title="Signal Flow">
          <artwork><![CDATA[

   [MN]         [MAG]       [LMA]         [SMA]
     |            |           |             |
  Attaches        |           |             |
     |            |           |             |
     |--Rtr Sol ->|           |             |
     |            |           |             |
     |            |--PBU----->|             |
     |            |           |             |
     |            |           |------PBU--->|
     |            |           |             |
     |            |           |<-----PBA----|
     |            |           |===Tunnel====|
     |            |           |             |
     |            |<---PBA----|             |
     |            |==Tunnel===|             |
     |            |           |             |
     |<--Rtr Adv--|           |             |
     |            |           |             |

]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><xref target="figure_signal_flow"></xref> shows the
        signaling flow when a mobile node attaches to a Proxy Mobile IP
        domain. As in the normal Proxy Mobile IP case, the mobile node sends a
        Router Solicitation message that is received by the local mobile
        access gateway. The mobile access gateway then sends its Proxy Binding
        Update (PBU) to the local mobility anchor. To register itself with the
        session mobility anchor as the new local mobility anchor for the
        mobile node, the local mobility anchor forwards this Proxy Binding
        Update to the session mobility anchor. The session mobility anchor
        then determines the corresponding policies for the mobile node as it
        would for a local mobile node and constructs the Proxy Binding
        Acknowledgment (PBA). The Proxy Binding Acknowledgment is then sent to
        the local mobility anchor as if it were a local mobile access gateway
        and a bi-directional tunnel is established between the session
        mobility anchor and the local mobility anchor. The local mobility
        anchor forwards the received Proxy Binding Acknowledgment to its
        mobile access gateway which in turn uses the Proxy Binding
        Acknowledgment to configure the mobile node. Also, the local mobility
        anchor establishes the bi-direct tunnel to this mobile access gateway.
        All traffic for the mobile node is then routed from the session
        mobility anchor through the local mobility anchor and the mobile
        access gateway. All future movements of the mobile node within the new
        Proxy Mobile IPv6 domain are covered by local mobility operations as
        described in <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Local Routing">
        <t>Traffic might occur between nodes that are currently allocated in
        the same mobility domain but are associated with session mobility
        anchors outside this domain. The local mobility anchor of the domain
        MAY optimize the delivery of this traffic by locally routing the
        packets instead of sending them over the corresponding session
        mobility anchor(s). The flag EnableMAGLocalRouting MAY be used for
        controlling this behavior. For further local routing considerations,
        see Section 6.10.3. of the Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6) document <xref
        target="RFC5213"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Local Mobility Anchor Considerations">
      <section title="Support to find the Session Mobility Anchor">
        <t>The LMA is responsible to either act as a SMA for nodes that attach
        to its domain originally or to locate the corresponding SMA for nodes
        that move to its domain from another domain. In the first case, the
        LMA needs to support operations that allow it to be found and queried
        by other LMAs for mobility session related data. In the later case,
        the LMA needs to perform these locating and querying operations
        itself. This document describes two operating schemes for this
        purpose: the direct location of the SMA and the indirect location of
        the SMA.</t>

        <section title="Direct SMA Location">
          <t>As explained in <xref target="section_direct_location"></xref>
          the direct location of the SMA is performed using a common database
          between the participating PMIP domains.</t>

          <section title="Processing of an Initial Binding Registration">
            <t>Upon the reception of an Initial Binding Registration (cf.
            Section 5.3.2. <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>) the LMA MUST query
            the common database for a SMA for the corresponding mobile node.
            If a SMA is returned the LMA will act as a visited LMA and send a
            corresponding PBU to the SMA. If not SMA is returned, the LMA will
            act as a SMA for the mobile node and update the database
            accordingly. Afterwards the LMA processes the Initial Binding
            Registration as specified in <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Querying the Common Database">
            <t>...</t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Processing Proxy Binding Updates  ">
        <section title="LMA to SMA PBU">
          <t>If a SMA receives a PBU from a LMA it MUST assume that the mobile
          node moved to the PMIP domain the LMA is responsible for. The SMA
          MUST process the PBU as it would process a PBU from any of the MAGs
          in its own domain.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="MAG to LMA PBU">
          <t>If a LMA that is not the SMA for a mobile node receives a PBU
          which is not part of an Initial Binding Registration it MUST process
          the PBU as it would process any other PBU. If the PBU is successful
          it MUST also send a Binding Lifetime Extension PBU to the SMA.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="MAG to SMA PBU">
          <t>If a SMA receives a PBU from a MAG within its own domain it MUST
          process it like it would process the PBU as a LMA.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Message Formats">
      <t>This section defines extensions to the Proxy Mobile IPv6 <xref
      target="RFC5213"></xref> protocol messages.</t>

      <section anchor="section_pbum" title="Proxy Binding Update Message">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[    0               1               2               3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
                                   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                                   |            Sequence #         |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |A|H|L|K|M|R|P|S|Reserved       |            Lifetime           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   .                                                               .
   .                        Mobility options                       .
   .                                                               .
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>A new flag (S) is included in the Binding Update message. The rest
        of the Binding Update message format remains the same as defined in
        <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Session Forwarding Flag (S)<list style="empty">
            <t>A new flag (S) is included in the Binding Update message to
            indicate that the Binding Update message is a request from a local
            mobility anchor to a session mobility anchor to forward all data
            for a particular mobile node to the local mobility anchor. The
            flag MUST be set to 1 in case a local mobility anchor requests a
            session forwarding and to 0 otherwise.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Mobility Options<list style="empty">
            <t>In addition to the mobility options specified in <xref
            target="RFC5213"></xref> there can be at most one instance of the
            Session Destination Address option included in a Proxy Binding
            Update Message.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="section_pbam" title="Proxy Binding Acknowledgement Message">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
                                   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                                   |   Status      |K|R|P|S|Reserv.|
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |         Sequence #            |           Lifetime            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   .                                                               .
   .                        Mobility options                       .
   .                                                               .
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>A new flag (S) is included in the Binding Acknowledgement message.
        The rest of the Binding Acknowledgement message format remains the
        same as defined in <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Session Forwarding Flag (S)<list style="empty">
            <t>A new flag (S) is included in the Binding Acknowledgement
            message to indicate that the local mobility anchor that processed
            the corresponding Proxy Binding Update message supports session
            forwarding. The flag is set to a value of 1 only if the
            corresponding Proxy Binding Update had the Session Forwarding Flag
            (S) set to value of 1.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Mobility Options<list style="empty">
            <t>In addition to the mobility options specified in <xref
            target="RFC5213"></xref> there can be at most one instance of the
            Session Mobility Anchor Address option included in a Proxy Binding
            Acknowledgement.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Session Destination Address Option">
        <t>The Session Destination option indicates where a local mobility
        requests the data to be send in a session forwarding request.</t>

        <t>The Session Destination Address option is encoded in
        type-length-value (TLV) format as follows:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
                                   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                                   |  Option Type  | Option Length |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               +
   |                                                               |
   +                Session Destination Address                   +
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               +
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Option Type<list style="empty">
            <t>TBD</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Option Length<list style="empty">
            <t>8-bit unsigned integer. Length of the option, in octets,
            excluding the Option Type and Option Length fields. This field
            MUST be set to 16.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Session Destination Address<list style="empty">
            <t>The destination address for the session data of the mobile
            node. This is usually the address of the local mobility anchor
            which is responsible for the mobile node. This address MUST be a
            unicast routable address.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Session Mobilty Anchor Address Option">
        <t>The Session Mobility Anchor Address option indicates the address of
        the session mobility anchor which is ultimately responsible for a
        Proxy Binding Update request.</t>

        <t>The Session Mobility Anchor Address option is encoded in
        type-length-value (TLV) format as follows:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
                                   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                                   |  Option Type  | Option Length |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               +
   |                                                               |
   +              Session Mobilty Anchor Address                  +
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               +
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Option Type<list style="empty">
            <t>TBD</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Option Length<list style="empty">
            <t>8-bit unsigned integer. Length of the option, in octets,
            excluding the Option Type and Option Length fields. This field
            MUST be set to 16.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Session Mobility Anchor Address<list style="empty">
            <t>The address of the session mobility anchor. This address MUST
            be a unicast routable address.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Inter-Domain Security">
      <t>This document introduces signaling and data forwarding between
      different Proxy Mobile IP domains which needs to be protected. Proxy
      Mobile IP itself recommends using IPsec with established security
      associations to protect the signaling messages, Proxy Binding Update and
      Proxy Binding Acknowledgment message exchanges between the mobile access
      gateway and the local mobility anchor. This document extends this
      recommendation for all message exchanges between the session mobility
      anchor and the local mobility anchor including forwarded data for the
      mobile node. How the IPsec associations are established is beyond this
      document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="section_security_considerations"
             title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This section deals with the considerations related to intra-domain
      security within one Proxy Mobile IP domain and inter-domain security
      between different Proxy Mobile IP domains that are involved in managing
      a mobile nodes mobility.</t>

      <section title="Intra-domain securtiy considerations">
        <t>This document does not change any intra-domain mobility procedures
        and therefore does not introduce additional intra-domain security
        risks. The security considerations in <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>
        cover security risks inside a Proxy Mobile IPv6 domain.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Inter-domain security considerations">
        <t>The signaling and data forwarding between different Proxy Mobile IP
        domains where the session mobility anchor resides in one domain and
        the current local mobility anchor for a mobile node resides in the
        other domain is recommended to be protected by using IPsec with
        established security associations. This means that the local mobility
        anchor establishes and maintains an IPsec tunnel to the session
        mobility anchor which is used for communications. How these security
        associations are established is beyond this document. It is
        recommended, however, to establish some kind of service agreements
        between service providers to specify security constraints and to
        arrange the valid endpoints (i.e. the local mobility anchor and
        session mobility anchor addresses).</t>

        <t>In opposite to plain Proxy Mobile IPv6, the signaling between the
        session mobility anchor and the mobile node traverses not only the
        Internet but also the local network of the current Proxy Mobile IP
        domain. The signaling between the session mobility anchor and the
        mobile node is, therefore, at least exposed to the current local
        mobility anchor, and the corresponding mobile access gateways in the
        current Proxy Mobile IP domain. Especially for applicable
        authentication procedures between the session mobility anchor and the
        mobile node, the session mobility anchor is recommended to only use
        procedures that cannot be exploited by overhearing parties.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;

      &RFC5213;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC3315;

      &RFC4861;

      &RFC4282;
    </references>

    <section title="Open Issues">
      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>better definition of mobility session (when to start a new
          session)</t>

          <t>extend inter domain security issues</t>

          <t>De-Registration of a MN</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
