<?xml version="1.0"?>
  <!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY iabdns	PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.iab-dns-choices.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2821	PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2821.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC0974	PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0974.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2782	PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2782.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2489	PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2489.xml'>
  ]>
  
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
  <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
  <?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-crocker-dns-attrleaf-01" ipr="full3978">
    <front>
        <title>DNS Scoped Data Through Attribute Leaves</title>
        <author fullname="Dave Crocker" initials="D." surname="Crocker">
            <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
            <address>
<postal>
<street>675 Spruce Dr.</street>
<city>Sunnyvale</city> <region>CA</region> <code>94086</code>
<country>USA</country>
</postal>
<phone>+1.408.246.8253</phone>
<email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
<uri>http://bbiw.net/</uri>
</address>
        </author>
        <date month="June" year="2006"/>
        <area>Operations</area>
        <keyword>DNS</keyword>
        <keyword>Domain Name System> </keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>Historically, any DNS RR may occur for any domain name. Recent additions have defined
                DNS leaf nodes that contain a reserved node name, beginning with an underscore. The
                underscore construct is used to define a semantic scope for the name, within which
                the choice of valid RRs is limited to a defined set. Hence the underscore construct
                defines a basic paradigm modification to the DNS. This note explores the nature of
                this DNS usage and defines the procedures for registering new "underscore names"
                with IANA. </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>Historically, any DNS RR may occur for any domain name. The DNS technical
                specification assigns no semantics to domain names and no constraints upon which
                resource records may be associated with a particular name. Over time, some leaf node
                names, such as "www" and "ftp" have come to imply support for particular services,
                but this is a matter of operational convention, rather than defined semantics. This
                freedom in the basic technology has permitted a wide range of administrative and
                semantic policies to be used -- in parallel -- with the DNS. In the DNS data
                semantics have been limited to specifications for specific resource records, on the
                expectation that new ones would be added as needed. Although there remains an
                expectation that this method of enhancement is preferred, alternative approaches
                have been explored.</t>
            <t>Recent additions have defined DNS leaves that contain a reserved leaf node name,
                beginning with an underscore. The underscore construct is used to define a semantic
                scope for the name, within which the choice of valid RRs is limited to a defined
                set. Hence the underscore construct defines a basic paradigm modification to the
                DNS. Within the scope of a defined underscore leaf, the specific uses of specific
                resource records can be formally defined and constrained. An established example is
                the SRV record,<xref target="RFC2782"/> which generalizes concepts long-used for
                email routing in the MX record.<xref target="RFC0974"/><xref target="RFC2821"/> The
                use of special DNS names has significant benefits and detriments. Some of these are
                explored in <xref target="I-D.iab-dns-choices"/>.</t>
            <t>One use that has perhaps not been noticed is that the underscore construct
                substantially changes possible concerns for scaling effects. For example, different
                uses for the same RR, such as the free-form TXT record, become manageable when those
                are defined to be within different, scoped leaf nodes. </t>
            <t>This note disusses this enhancement, provides an explicit definition of it, and
                establishes an IANA registry for the reserved names beginning with underscore. </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Procedure">
            <t>
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="NOTE:  ">This procedure is modeled after that specified in <xref
                            target="RFC2489"/></t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>The author of a new DHCP option will follow these steps to obtain approval for the
                option and publication of the specification of the option as an RFC:<list
                    style="numbers">
                    <t>The author devises the new option.</t>
                    <t>The author documents the new option as an Internet Draft, choosing a node
                        name that has not yet been registered. </t>
                    <t>The author submits the Internet Draft for publication as an RFC, either as an
                        independent submission or as an IETF-approved document. </t>
                    <t>The specification of the new option is reviewed for publication by the
                        appropriate bodies. </t>
                    <t>At the time of publication as an RFC, IANA formally lists the node name.</t>
                </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>This memo raises no security issues</t>
        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t> IANA is requested to establish the DNS Underscore Name Registry, for DNS node names
                that begin with the underscore character and have been specified in any published
                RFC. </t>
            <figure title="DNS Underscore Name Registry Initial Values">
                <preamble>Initial entries in the registry comprise:</preamble>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
                        NAME                RFC
                        ==============     ========
                        _<service>         rfc2782
                        _<proto>           rfc2782
                        ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
            <t>
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="NOTE:  "> In the case of RFC2782, the set of
                        &lt;service&gt; names is defined in terms of other IANA tables,
                        namely any table with symbolic names. Even more problematic is that the set
                        of &lt;proto&gt; names is not explicitly defined, except in vague
                        terms. This makes it essentially impossible to guarantee that a new
                        underscore name is unambiguous!</t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="References -- Informative"> &RFC2821; &RFC0974; &RFC2782;
            &RFC2489; &iabdns; </references>
        <section title="Acknowledgements">
            <t>Thanks go to Tony Hansen for diligent review.</t>
        </section>
    </back>
</rfc>
