<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-mpls-tp-requirements-04"
     ipr="trust200811">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPLS-TP Requirements">MPLS-TP Requirements</title>

    <author fullname="Ben Niven-Jenkins" initials="B.P." role="editor"
            surname="Niven-Jenkins">
      <organization>BT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>208 Callisto House, Adastral Park</street>

          <city>Ipswich</city>

          <region>Suffolk</region>

          <code>IP5 3RE</code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>benjamin.niven-jenkins@bt.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Deborah Brungard" initials="D." role="editor"
            surname="Brungard">
      <organization>AT&amp;T</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Rm. D1-3C22 - 200 S. Laurel Ave.</street>

          <city>Middletown</city>

          <region>NJ</region>

          <code>07748</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dbrungard@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Malcolm Betts" initials="M." role="editor"
            surname="Betts">
      <organization>Nortel Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3500 Carling Avenue</street>

          <city>Ottawa</city>

          <region>Ontario</region>

          <code>K2H 8E9</code>

          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>

        <email>betts01@nortel.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Nurit Sprecher" initials="N." role="" surname="Sprecher">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3 Hanagar St. Neve Ne'eman B</street>

          <city>Hod Hasharon</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>45241</code>

          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>

        <email>nurit.sprecher@nsn.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Satoshi Ueno" initials="S." role="" surname="Ueno">
      <organization>NTT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <email>satoshi.ueno@ntt.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="5" month="February" year="2009" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies the requirements of an MPLS Transport Profile
      (MPLS-TP). This document is a product of a joint International
      Telecommunications Union (ITU)-IETF effort to include an MPLS Transport
      Profile within the IETF MPLS architecture to support the capabilities
      and functionalities of a packet transport network as defined by
      International Telecommunications Union - Telecommunications
      Standardization Sector (ITU-T).</t>

      <t>This work is based on two sources of requirements; MPLS architecture
      as defined by IETF, and packet transport networks as defined by
      ITU-T.</t>

      <t>The requirements expressed in this document are for the behavior of
      the protocol mechanisms and procedures that constitute building blocks
      out of which the MPLS transport profile is constructed. The requirements
      are not implementation requirements.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>For many years, transport networks (e.g. Synchronous Optical
      Networking (SONET)/Synchronous Digital hierarchy (SDH)) have provided
      carriers with a high benchmark for reliability and operational
      simplicity. With the accelerating growth and penetration of:<list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Packet-based services such as Ethernet, Voice over IP (VoIP),
          Layer 2 (L2)/Layer 3 (L3) Virtual Private Networks (VPNs), IP
          Television (IPTV), Radio Access Network (RAN) backhauling, etc.</t>

          <t>Applications with various bandwidth and QoS requirements.</t>
        </list>Carriers are in need of technologies capable of efficiently
      supporting packet-based services and applications on their transport
      networks. The need to increase their revenue while remaining competitive
      forces operators to look for the lowest network Total Cost of Ownership
      (TCO). Investment in equipment and facilities (Capital Expenditure
      (CAPEX)) and Operational Expenditure (OPEX) should be minimized.</t>

      <t>Carriers are considering migrating or evolving to packet transport
      networks in order to reduce their costs and to improve their ability to
      support services with guaranteed Service Level Agreements (SLAs). For
      carriers it is important that migrating from their existing transport
      networks to packet transport networks should not involve dramatic
      changes in network operation, should not necessitate extensive
      retraining, and should not require major changes to existing work
      practices. The aim is to preserve the look-and-feel to which carriers
      have become accustomed in deploying their transport networks, while
      providing common, multi-layer operations, resiliency, control and
      management for packet, circuit and lambda transport networks.</t>

      <t>Transport carriers require control and deterministic usage of network
      resources. They need end-to-end control to engineer network paths and to
      efficiently utilize network resources. They require capabilities to
      support static (Operations Support System (OSS) based) or dynamic
      (control plane) provisioning of deterministic, protected and secured
      services and their associated resources.</t>

      <t>Carriers will still need to cope with legacy networks (which are
      composed of many layers and technologies), thus the packet transport
      network should interwork as appropriate with other packet and transport
      networks (both horizontally and vertically). Vertical interworking is
      also known as client/server or network interworking. Horizontal
      interworking is also known as peer-partition or service interworking.
      For more details on each type of interworking and some of the issues
      that may arise (especially with horizontal interworking) see <xref
      target="ITU.Y1401.2008">Y.1401</xref>.</t>

      <t>MPLS is a maturing packet technology and it is already playing an
      important role in transport networks and services. However, not all of
      MPLS's capabilities and mechanisms are needed and/or consistent with
      transport network operations. There is therefore the need to define an
      MPLS Transport Profile (MPLS-TP) in order to support the capabilities
      and functionalities needed for packet transport network services and
      operations through combining the packet experience of MPLS with the
      operational experience of existing transport networks.</t>

      <t>MPLS-TP will enable the migration of transport networks to a
      packet-based network that will efficiently scale to support packet
      services in a simple and cost effective way. MPLS-TP needs to combine
      the necessary existing capabilities of MPLS with additional minimal
      mechanisms in order that it can be used in a transport role.</t>

      <t>This document specifies the requirements of an MPLS Transport Profile
      (MPLS-TP). The requirements are for the the behavior of the protocol
      mechanisms and procedures that constitute building blocks out of which
      the MPLS transport profile is constructed. That is, the requirements
      indicate what features are to be available in the MPLS toolkit for use
      by MPLS-TP. The requirements in this document do not describe what
      functions an MPLS-TP implementation supports. The purpose of this
      document is to identify the toolkit and any new protocol work that is
      required.</t>

      <t>Although this document is not a protocol specification, the key words
      "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD
      NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" are used as described in
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> and are to be interpreted as instructions
      to the protocol designers producing solutions that satisfy the
      requirements set out in this document.</t>

      <t>This document is a product of a joint ITU-IETF effort to include an
      MPLS Transport Profile within the IETF MPLS architecture to support the
      capabilities and functionalities of a packet transport network as
      defined by ITU-T.</t>

      <t>This work is based on two sources of requirements, MPLS architecture
      as defined by IETF and packet transport networks as defined by ITU-T.
      The requirements of MPLS-TP are provided below. The relevant functions
      of MPLS are included in MPLS-TP, except where explicitly excluded.</t>

      <t>Although both static and dynamic configuration of MPLS-TP transport
      paths (including Operations, Administration and Maintenance (OAM) and
      protection capabilities) is required by this document, it MUST be
      possible for operators to be able to completely operate (including OAM
      and protection capabilities) an MPLS-TP network in the absence of any
      control plane protocols for dynamic configuration.</t>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>Note: Mapping between the terms in this section and ITU-T
        terminology will be described in a subsequent document.</t>

        <t>Note: The definition of segment in a GMPLS/ASON context (i.e. as
        defined in <xref target="RFC4397">RFC4397</xref>) encompasses both
        segment and concatenated segment as defined in this document.</t>

        <t>Associated bidirectional path: A path that supports traffic flow in
        both directions but which is constructed from a pair of unidirectional
        paths (one for each direction) which are associated with one another
        at the path's ingress/egress points. The forward and backward
        directions may or may not follow the same route (links and nodes)
        across the network.</t>

        <t>Bidirectional path: A path where the forward and backward
        directions follow the same route (links and nodes) across the
        network.</t>

        <t>Concatenated Segment: A serial-compound link connection as defined
        in <xref target="ITU.G805.2000">G.805</xref>. A concatenated segment
        is a contiguous part of an LSP or multi-segment PW that comprises a
        set of segments and their interconnecting nodes in sequence.</t>

        <t>Co-routed bidirectional path: A bidirectional path where the
        forward and backward directions follow the same route (links and
        nodes) across its layer network.</t>

        <t>Domain: A domain represents a collection of entities (for example
        network elements) that are grouped for a particular purpose, examples
        of which are administrative and/or managerial responsibilities, trust
        relationships, addressing schemes, infrastructure capabilities,
        aggregation, survivability techniques, distributions of control
        functionality, etc. Examples of such domains include IGP areas and
        Autonomous Systems.</t>

        <t>Layer network: Layer network is defined in <xref
        target="ITU.G805.2000">G.805</xref>. A layer network provides for the
        transfer of client information and independent operation of the client
        OAM. A Layer Network may be described in a service context as follows:
        one layer network may provide a (transport) service to higher client
        layer network and may, in turn, be a client to a lower layer network.
        A layer network is a logical construction somewhat independent of
        arrangement or composition of physical network elements. A particular
        physical network element may topologically belong to more than one
        layer network, depending on the actions it takes on the
        encapsulation(s) associated with the logical layers (e.g. the label
        stack), and thus could be modeled as multiple logical elements. A
        layer network may consist of zero or more sublayers. For additional
        explanation of how layer networks relate to the OSI concept of
        layering see Appendix I of <xref
        target="ITU.Y2611.2006">Y.2611</xref>.</t>

        <t>Link: A physical or logical connection between a pair of LSRs that
        are adjacent at the (sub)layer network under consideration. A link may
        carry zero, one or more LSPs or PWs. A packet entering a link will
        emerge with the same label stack entry values.</t>

        <t>Logical Ring: An MPLS-TP logical ring is constructed from a set of
        LSRs and logical data links (such as MPLS-TP LSP tunnels or MSPL-TP
        pseudowires) and physical data links that form a ring topology.</t>

        <t>Path: See Transport path.</t>

        <t>Physical Ring: An MPLS-TP physical ring is constructed from a set
        of LSRs and physical data links that form a ring topology.</t>

        <t>Ring Topology: In an MPLS-TP ring topology each LSR is connected to
        exactly two other LSRs, each via a single point-to-point bidirectional
        MPLS-TP capable data link. A ring may also be constructed from only
        two LSRs where there are also exactly two links. Rings may be
        connected to other LSRs to form a larger network. Traffic originating
        or terminating outside the ring may be carried over the ring. Client
        network nodes (such as CEs) may be connected directly to an LSR in the
        ring.</t>

        <t>Section: A section is a server layer (which may be MPLS-TP or a
        different technology) which provides for encapsulation and OAM of a
        MPLS-TP transport path client layer. A section layer may provide for
        aggregation of multiple MPLS-TP clients. Note that <xref
        target="ITU.G805.2000">G.805</xref> defines the section layer as one
        of the two layer networks in a transmission media layer network. The
        other layer network is the physical media layer network.</t>

        <t>Segment: A link connection as defined in <xref
        target="ITU.G805.2000">G.805</xref>. A segment is the part of an LSP
        that traverses a single link or the part of a PW that traverses a
        single link (i.e. that connects a pair of adjacent {S|T}-PEs).</t>

        <t>Sublayer: Sublayer is defined in <xref
        target="ITU.G805.2000">G.805</xref>. The distinction between a layer
        network and a sublayer is that a sublayer is not directly accessible
        to clients outside of its encapsulating layer network and offers no
        direct transport service for a higher layer (client) network.</t>

        <t>Tandem Connection: A tandem connection is an arbitrary part of a
        transport path that can be monitored (via OAM) independently from the
        end-to-end monitoring (OAM). It may be a monitored segment, a
        monitored concatenated segment or any other monitored ordered sequence
        of contiguous hops and/or segments (and their interconnecting nodes)
        of a transport path.</t>

        <t>Transport path: A network connection as defined in <xref
        target="ITU.G805.2000">G.805</xref>. In an MPLS-TP environment a
        transport path corresponds to an LSP or a PW.</t>

        <t>Transport path layer: A layer network which provides point-to-point
        or point-to-multipoint transport paths which are used to carry a
        higher (client) layer network or aggregates of higher (client) layer
        networks, for example the transport service layer. It provides for
        independent OAM (of the client OAM) in the transport of the
        clients.</t>

        <t>Transport service layer: A layer network in which transport paths
        are used to carry a customer&rsquo;s (individual or bundled) service
        (may be point-to-point, point-to-multipoint or
        multipoint-to-multipoint services).</t>

        <t>Transmission media layer: A layer network which provides sections
        (two-port point-to-point connections) to carry the aggregate of
        network transport path or network service layers on various physical
        media.</t>

        <t>Unidirectional path: A path that supports traffic flow in only one
        direction.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Transport network overview">
        <t>The connection (or transport path) service is the basic service
        provided by a transport network. The purpose of a transport network is
        to carry its clients (i.e. the stream of client PDUs or client bits)
        between endpoints in the network (typically over several intermediate
        nodes). These endpoints may be service switching points or service
        terminating points. The connection services offered to customers are
        aggregated into large transport paths with long-holding times and
        independent OAM (of the client OAM), which contribute to enabling the
        efficient and reliable operation of the transport network. These
        transport paths are modified infrequently.</t>

        <t>Aggregation and hierarchy are beneficial for achieving scalability
        and security since: <list style="numbers">
            <t>They reduce the number of provisioning and forwarding states in
            the network core.</t>

            <t>They reduce load and the cost of implementing service assurance
            and fault management.</t>

            <t>Clients are encapsulated and layer associated OAM overhead is
            added. This allows complete isolation of customer traffic and its
            management from carrier operations.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>An important attribute of a transport network is that it is able to
        function regardless of which clients are using its connection service
        or over which transmission media it is running. The client, transport
        network and server layers are from a functional and operations point
        of view independent layer networks. Another key characteristic of
        transport networks is the capability to maintain the integrity of the
        client across the transport network. A transport network must provide
        the means to commit quality of service objectives to clients. This is
        achieved by providing a mechanism for client network service
        demarcation for the network path together with an associated network
        resiliency mechanism. A transport network must also provide a method
        of service monitoring in order to verify the delivery of an agreed
        quality of service. This is enabled by means of carrier-grade OAM
        tools.</t>

        <t>Clients are first encapsulated. These encapsulated client signals
        may then be aggregated into a connection for transport through the
        network in order to optimize network management. Server layer OAM is
        used to monitor the transport integrity of the client layer or client
        aggregate. At any hop, the aggregated signals may be further
        aggregated in lower layer transport network paths for transport across
        intermediate shared links. The encapsulated client signals are
        extracted at the edges of aggregation domains, and are either
        delivered to the client or forwarded to another domain. In the core of
        the network, only the server layer aggregated signals are monitored;
        individual client signals are monitored at the network boundary in the
        client layer network. Although the connectivity of the client of the
        transport path layer may be point-to-point, point-to-multipoint or
        multipoint-to-multipoint, the transport path layer itself only
        provides point-to-point or point-to-multipoint transport paths which
        are used to carry the client.</t>

        <t>Quality-of-service mechanisms are required in the packet transport
        network to ensure the prioritization of critical services, to
        guarantee BW and to control jitter and delay.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Layer network overview">
        <t>A layer network provides its clients with a transport service and
        the operation of the layer network is independent of whatever client
        happens to use the layer network. Information that passes between any
        client to the layer network is common to all clients and is the
        minimum needed to be consistent with the definition of the transport
        service offered. The client layer network can be connectionless,
        connection oriented packet switched, or circuit switched. The
        transport service transfers a payload (individual packet payload for
        connectionless networks, a sequence of packets payloads in the case of
        connection oriented packet switched networks, and a deterministic
        schedule of payloads in the case of circuit switched networks) such
        that the client can populate the payload without affecting any
        operation within the serving layer network.</t>

        <t>The operations within a layer network that are independent of the
        clients include the control of forwarding, the control of resource
        reservation, the control of traffic demerging, and the OAM of the
        transport service. All of these operations are internal to a layer
        network. By definition, a layer network does not rely on any client
        information to perform these operations and therefore all information
        required to perform these operations is independent of whatever client
        is using the layer network.</t>

        <t>A layer network will have common features in order to support the
        control of forwarding, resource reservation, and OAM. For example, a
        layer network will have a common addressing scheme for the end points
        of the transport service and a common set of transport descriptors for
        the transport service. However, a client may use a different
        addressing scheme or different traffic descriptors (consistent with
        performance inheritance).</t>

        <t>It is sometimes useful to independently monitor a smaller domain
        within a layer network (or the transport services as the traverse this
        smaller domain) but the control of forwarding or the control of
        resource reservation involved retain their common elements. These
        smaller monitored domains are sublayers.</t>

        <t>It is sometimes useful to independently control forwarding within
        smaller domain within a layer network but the control of resource
        reservation and OAM retain their common elements. These smaller
        domains are partitions of the layer network.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="MPLS-TP Requirements">
      <t></t>

      <section title="General requirements">
        <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
            <t>The MPLS-TP data plane MUST be a subset of the MPLS data plane
            as defined by the IETF. When MPLS offers multiple options in this
            respect, MPLS-TP SHOULD select the minimum sub-set (necessary and
            sufficient subset) applicable to a transport network
            application.</t>

            <t>Any new functionality that is defined to fulfil the
            requirements for MPLS-TP MUST be agreed within the IETF through
            the IETF consensus process and MUST re-use (as far as practically
            possible) existing MPLS standards.</t>

            <t>Mechanisms and capabilities MUST be able to interoperate,
            without a gateway function, with existing IETF MPLS <xref
            target="RFC3031"></xref> and IETF PWE3 <xref
            target="RFC3985"></xref> control and data planes where
            appropriate.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP and its interfaces, both internal and external, MUST be
            sufficiently well-defined that interworking equipment supplied by
            multiple vendors will be possible both within a single network,
            and between networks.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST be a connection-oriented packet switching model
            with traffic engineering capabilities that allow deterministic
            control of the use of network resources.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST support traffic engineered point to point (P2P)
            and point to multipoint (P2MP) transport paths.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST support the logical separation of the control and
            management planes from the data plane.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST allow the physical separation of the control and
            management planes from the data plane.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST support static provisioning of transport paths via
            an OSS, i.e. via the management plane.</t>

            <t>Mechanisms in an MPLS-TP network that satisfy functional
            requirements that are common to general transport networks (i.e.,
            independent of technology) SHOULD be operable in a way that is
            similar to the way the equivalent mechanisms are operated in other
            transport networks.</t>

            <t>Static provisioning MUST NOT depend on the presence of any
            element of a control plane.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST support the capability for network operation
            (including OAM and recovery) via the management plane (without the
            use of any control plane protocols).</t>

            <t>A solution MUST be provided to support dynamic provisioning of
            MPLS-TP transport paths via a control plane.</t>

            <t>The MPLS-TP data plane MUST be capable of forwarding data and
            taking recovery actions independently of the control or management
            plane used to operate the MPLS-TP layer network. That is, the
            MPLS-TP data plane MUST continue to operate normally if the
            management plane or control plane that configured the transport
            paths fails.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST support mechanisms to avoid or minimize traffic
            impact (e.g. packet delay, reordering and loss) during network
            reconfiguration.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST support transport paths through multiple
            homogeneous domains.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST NOT dictate the deployment of any particular
            network topology either physical or logical, however:<list
                style="letters">
                <t>It MUST be possible to deploy MPLS-TP in rings.</t>

                <t>It MUST be possible to deploy MPLS-TP in arbitrarily
                interconnected rings with one or two points of
                interconnection.</t>

                <t>MPLS-TP MUST support rings of at least 16 nodes in order to
                support the upgrade of existing TDM rings to MPLS-TP. MPLS-TP
                SHOULD support rings with more than 16 nodes.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST be able to scale at least as well as existing
            transport technologies with growing and increasingly complex
            network topologies as well as with increasing bandwidth demands,
            number of customers, and number of services.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP SHOULD support mechanisms to safeguard against the
            provisioning of transport paths which contain forwarding
            loops.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Layering requirements">
        <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
            <t>A generic and extensible solution MUST be provided to support
            the transport of one or more client layer networks (e.g. MPLS-TP,
            Ethernet, ATM, FR, etc.) over an MPLS-TP layer network.</t>

            <t>A solution MUST be provided to support the transport of MPLS-TP
            transport paths over one or more server layer networks (such as
            MPLS-TP, Ethernet, SONET/SDH, OTN, etc.). Requirements for
            bandwidth management within a server layer network are outside the
            scope of this document.</t>

            <t>In an environment where an MPLS-TP layer network is supporting
            a client network, and the MPLS-TP layer network is supported by a
            server layer network then operation of the MPLS-TP layer network
            MUST be possible without any dependencies on the server or client
            network.</t>

            <t>It MUST be possible to operate the layers of a multi-layer
            network that includes an MPLS-TP layer autonomously.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The above are not only technology requirements, but also
        operational. Different administrative groups may be responsible for
        the same layer network or different layer networks.</t>

        <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
            <t>It MUST be possible to hide MPLS-TP layer network addressing
            and other information (e.g. topology) from client layers.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Data plane requirements">
        <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
            <t>The identification of each transport path within its aggregate
            MUST be supported.</t>

            <t>A label in a particular link MUST uniquely identify the
            transport path within that link.</t>

            <t>A transport path's source MUST be identifiable at its
            destination within its layer network.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST be capable of using P2MP server (sub-)layer
            capabilities when supporting P2MP MPLS-TP transport paths (for
            example context-specific labels <xref
            target="RFC5331"></xref>).</t>

            <t>It MUST be possible to operate and configure the MPLS-TP data
            (transport) plane without any IP forwarding capability in the
            MPLS-TP data plane.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST support unidirectional, bidirectional and
            co-routed bidirectional point-to-point transport paths.</t>

            <t>The forward and backward directions of a co-routed
            bidirectional transport path MUST follow the same links and nodes
            within its (sub-)layer network.</t>

            <t>The intermediate nodes at each (sub-)layer MUST be aware about
            the pairing relationship of the forward and the backward
            directions belonging to the same bidirectional transport path.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MAY support transport paths with asymmetric bandwidth
            requirements, i.e. the amount of reserved bandwidth differs
            between the forward and backward directions.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST support unidirectional point-to-multipoint
            transport paths.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST be extensible in order to accommodate new types of
            client networks and services.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP SHOULD support mechanisms to enable the reserved
            bandwidth associated with a transport path to be increased without
            impacting the existing traffic on that transport path</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP SHOULD support mechanisms to enable the reserved
            bandwidth of a transport path to be decreased without impacting
            the existing traffic on that transport path, provided that the
            level of existing traffic is smaller than the reserved bandwidth
            following the decrease.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST support mechanisms which ensure the integrity of
            the transported customer's service traffic as required by its
            associated SLA. Loss of integrity may be defined as packet
            corruption, re-ordering or loss during normal network
            conditions.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST support mechanisms to detect when loss of
            integrity of the transported customer's service traffic has
            occurred.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP MUST support an unambiguous and reliable means of
            distinguishing users' (client) packets from MPLS-TP control
            packets (e.g. control plane, management plane, OAM and protection
            switching packets).</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Control plane requirements">
        <t>This section defines the requirements that apply to MPLS-TP when a
        control plane is deployed.</t>

        <t>The ITU-T has defined an architecture for Automatically Switched
        Optical and Transport Networks (ASON/ASTN) in <xref
        target="ITU.G8080.2006">G.8080</xref>. The control plane for MPLS-TP
        MUST fit within the ASON/ASTN architecture.</t>

        <t>An interpretation of the ASON/ASTN control plane requirements in
        the context of GMPLS can be found in <xref target="RFC4139"></xref>
        and <xref target="RFC4258"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Additionally:</t>

        <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
            <t>The MPLS&ndash;TP control pane SHOULD support control plane
            topology and data plane topology independence.</t>

            <t>The MPLS-TP control plane MUST be able to be operated
            independent of any particular client or server layer control
            plane.</t>

            <t>The MPLS-TP control plane MUST support establishing all the
            connectivity patterns defined for the MPLS-TP data plane (e.g.,
            unidirectional and bidirectional P2P, unidirectional P2MP, etc.)
            including configuration of protection functions and any associated
            maintenance functions.</t>

            <t>The MPLS-TP control pane MUST support the configuration and
            modification of OAM maintenance points as well as the
            activation/deactivation of OAM when the transport path or
            transport service is established or modified.</t>

            <t>An MPLS-TP control plane MUST support operation of the recovery
            functions described in Section 2.8.</t>

            <t>An MPLS-TP control plane MUST scale gracefully to support a
            large number of transport paths, nodes and links.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Network Management (NM) requirements">
        <t>For requirements related to NM functionality (Management Plane in
        ITU-T terminology) for MPLS-TP, see the MPLS-TP NM requirements
        document <xref target="I-D.gray-mpls-tp-nm-req"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Operation, Administration and Maintenance (OAM) requirements">
        <t>For requirements related to OAM functionality for MPLS-TP, see the
        MPLS-TP OAM requirements document <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-mpls-tp-oam-requirements"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Network performance management (PM) requirements">
        <t>For requirements related to PM functionality for MPLS-TP, see the
        MPLS-TP OAM requirements document <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-mpls-tp-oam-requirements"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Recovery &amp; Survivability requirements">
        <t>Network survivability plays a critical role in the delivery of
        reliable services. Network availability is a significant contributor
        to revenue and profit. Service guarantees in the form of SLAs require
        a resilient network that rapidly detects facility or node failures and
        restores network operation in accordance with the terms of the
        SLA.</t>

        <t>The requirements in this section use the recovery terminology
        defined in RFC 4427 <xref target="RFC4427"></xref>.</t>

        <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
            <t>MPLS-TP MUST provide protection and restoration
            mechanisms.<list style="letters">
                <t>Recovery techniques used for P2P and P2MP SHOULD be
                identical to simplify implementation and operation. However,
                this MUST NOT override any other requirement.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>MPLS-TP recovery mechanisms MUST be applicable at various
            levels throughout the network including support for link, path
            segment and end-to-end path, and pseudowire segment, and
            end-to-end pseudowire recovery.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP recovery paths MUST meet the SLA protection objectives
            of the service.<list style="letters">
                <t>MPLS-TP MUST provide mechanisms to guarantee 50ms recovery
                times from the moment of fault detection in networks with
                spans less than 1200 km.</t>

                <t>For protection it MUST be possible to require protection of
                100% of the traffic on the protected path.</t>

                <t>Recovery objectives SHOULD be configurable per transport
                path, and SHOULD include bandwidth and QoS.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The recovery mechanisms MUST all be applicable to any
            topology.</t>

            <t>The recovery mechanisms MUST operate in synergy with (including
            coordination of timing) the recovery mechanisms present in any
            underlying server transport network (for example, Ethernet, SDH,
            OTN, WDM) to avoid race conditions between the layers.</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP protection mechanisms MUST support priority logic to
            negotiate and accommodate coexisting requests (i.e., multiple
            requests) for protection switching (e.g., administrative requests
            and requests due to link/node failures).</t>

            <t>MPLS-TP recovery and reversion mechanisms MUST prevent frequent
            operation of recovery in the event of an intermittent defect.</t>
          </list></t>

        <section title="Data plane behavior requirements">
          <t>General protection and survivability requirements are expressed
          in terms of the behavior in the data plane.</t>

          <section title="Protection">
            <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
                <t>MPLS-TP MUST support 1+1 protection.<list style="letters">
                    <t>MPLS-TP 1+1 support MUST include bidirectional
                    protection switching for P2P connectivity, and this SHOULD
                    be the default behavior for 1+1 protection.</t>

                    <t>Unidirectional 1+1 protection for P2MP connectivity
                    MUST be supported.</t>

                    <t>Unidirectional 1+1 protection for P2P connectivity is
                    not required.</t>
                  </list></t>

                <t>MPLS-TP MUST support 1:n protection (including 1:1
                protection).<list style="letters">
                    <t>MPLS-TP 1:n support MUST include bidirectional
                    protection switching for P2P connectivity, and this SHOULD
                    be the default behavior for 1:n protection.</t>

                    <t>Unidirectional 1:n protection for P2MP connectivity
                    MUST be supported.</t>

                    <t>Unidirectional 1:n protection for P2P connectivity is
                    not required.</t>

                    <t>The action of protection switching MUST NOT cause user
                    data to loop. Backtracking is allowed.</t>
                  </list></t>
              </list>Note: Support for extra traffic (as defined in <xref
            target="ITU.G870.2008">G.870</xref>) is not required in
            MPLS-TP.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Restoration">
            <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
                <t>The restoration LSP MUST be able to share resources with
                the LSP being replaced (sometimes known as soft
                rerouting).</t>

                <t>Restoration priority MUST be supported so that an
                implementation can determine the order in which transport
                paths should be restored (to minimize service restoration time
                as well as to gain access to available spare capacity on the
                best paths).</t>

                <t>Preemption priority MUST be supported to allow restoration
                to displace other transport paths in the event of resource
                constraint.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Sharing of protection resources">
            <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
                <t>MPLS-TP SHOULD support 1:n (including 1:1) shared mesh
                restoration.</t>

                <t>MPLS-TP MUST support the sharing of protection bandwidth by
                allowing best effort traffic.</t>

                <t>MPLS-TP MUST support the definition of shared protection
                groups to allow the coordination of protection actions
                resulting from triggers caused by events at different
                locations in the network.</t>

                <t>MPLS-TP MUST support sharing of protection resources such
                that protection paths that are known not to be required
                concurrently can share the same resources.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Reversion">
            <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
                <t>MPLS-TP protection mechanisms MUST support revertive and
                non- revertive behavior. Reversion MUST be the default
                behavior.</t>

                <t>MPLS-TP restoration mechanisms MAY support revertive and
                non- revertive behavior.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Triggers for protection, restoration, and reversion">
          <t>Recovery actions may be triggered from different places as
          follows:<list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
              <t>MPLS-TP MUST support physical layer fault indication
              triggers.</t>

              <t>MPLS-TP MUST support OAM-based triggers.</t>

              <t>MPLS-TP MUST support management plane triggers (e.g., forced
              switch, etc.).</t>

              <t>There MUST be a mechanism to allow administrative recovery
              actions to be distinguished from recovery actions initiated by
              other triggers.</t>

              <t>Where a control plane is present, MPLS-TP SHOULD support
              control plane triggers.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Management plane operation of protection and restoration">
          <t>All functions described here are for control by the
          operator.<list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
              <t>It MUST be possible to configure of protection paths and
              protection-to-working path relationships (sometimes known as
              protection groups).</t>

              <t>There MUST be support for pre-calculation of recovery
              paths.</t>

              <t>There MUST be support for pre-provisioning of recovery
              paths.</t>

              <t>The external controls as defined in <xref
              target="RFC4427"></xref> MUST be supported.</t>

              <t>There MUST be support for the configuration of timers used
              for recovery operation.</t>

              <t>Restoration resources MAY be pre-planned and selected a
              priori, or computed after failure occurrence.</t>

              <t>When preemption is supported for recovery purposes, it MUST
              be possible for the operator to configure it.</t>

              <t>The management plane MUST provide indications of protection
              events and triggers.</t>

              <t>The management plane MUST allow the current protection status
              of all transport paths to be determined.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Control plane and in-band OAM operation of recovery">
          <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
              <t>The MPLS-TP control plane (which is not mandatory in an
              MPLS-TP implementation) MUST support: <list style="letters">
                  <t>establishment and maintenance of all recovery entities
                  and functions</t>

                  <t>signaling of administrative control</t>

                  <t>protection state coordination (PSC)</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>In-band OAM MAY be used for:<list style="letters">
                  <t>signaling of administrative control</t>

                  <t>protection state coordination</t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Topology-specific recovery mechanisms">
          <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
              <t>MPLS-TP MAY support recovery mechanisms that are optimized
              for specific network topologies. These mechanisms MUST be
              interoperable with the mechanisms defined for arbitrary topology
              (mesh) networks to enable protection of end-to-end transport
              paths.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Note that topology-specific recovery mechanisms are subject to
          the development of requirements using the normal IETF process.</t>

          <section title="Ring protection">
            <t>Several service providers have expressed a high level of
            interest in operating MPLS-TP in ring topologies and require a
            high level of survivability function in these topologies. The
            requirements listed below have been collected from these service
            providers and from the ITU-T.</t>

            <t>The main objective in considering a specific topology (such as
            a ring) is to determine whether it is possible to optimize any
            mechanisms such that the performance of those mechanisms within
            the topology is significantly better than the performance of the
            generic mechanisms in the same topology. The benefits of such
            optimizations are traded against the costs of developing,
            implementing, deploying, and operating the additional optimized
            mechanisms noting that the generic mechanisms MUST continue to be
            supported.</t>

            <t>Within the context of recovery in MPLS-TP networks, the
            optimization criteria considered in ring topologies are as
            follows: <list style="letters">
                <t>Minimize the number of OAM MEs that are needed to trigger
                the recovery operation &ndash; less than are required by other
                recovery mechanisms.</t>

                <t>Minimize the number of elements of recovery in the ring
                &ndash; less than are required by other recovery
                mechanisms.</t>

                <t>Minimize the number of labels required for the protection
                paths across the ring &ndash; less than are required by other
                recovery mechanisms.</t>

                <t>Minimize the amount of management plane transactions during
                a maintenance operation (e.g., ring upgrade) &ndash; less than
                are required by other recovery mechanisms.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>It may be observed that the requirements in this section are
            fully compatible with the generic requirements expressed above,
            and that no requirements that are specific to ring topologies have
            been identified.</t>

            <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
                <t>MPLS-TP MUST include recovery mechanisms that operate in
                any single ring supported in MPLS-TP, and continue to operate
                within the single rings even when the rings are
                interconnected.</t>

                <t>When a network is constructed from interconnected rings,
                MPLS-TP MUST support recovery mechanisms that protect user
                data that traverses more than one ring. This includes the
                possibility of failure of the ring-interconnect nodes and
                links.</t>

                <t>MPLS-TP recovery in a ring MUST protect unidirectional and
                bidirectional P2P transport paths.</t>

                <t>MPLS-TP recovery in a ring MUST protect unidirectional P2MP
                transport paths.</t>

                <t>MPLS-TP 1+1 and 1:1 protection in a ring MUST support
                switching time within 50 ms from the moment of fault detection
                in a network with a 16 nodes ring with less than 1200 km of
                fiber.</t>

                <t>The protection switching time in a ring MUST be independent
                of the number of LSPs crossing the ring.</t>

                <t>Recovery actions in a ring MUST be data plane functions
                triggered by different elements of control. The triggers are
                configured by management or control planes and are subject to
                configurable policy.</t>

                <t>The configuration and operation of recovery mechanisms in a
                ring MUST scale well with: <list style="letters">
                    <t>the number of transport paths (must be better than
                    linear scaling)</t>

                    <t>the number of nodes on the ring (must be at least as
                    good as linear scaling)</t>

                    <t>the number of ring interconnects (must be at least as
                    good as linear scaling)</t>
                  </list></t>

                <t>MPLS-TP recovery in ring topologies MAY support multiple
                failures without reconfiguring the protection actions.</t>

                <t>Recovery techniques used in a ring MUST NOT prevent the
                ring from being connected to a general MPLS-TP network in any
                arbitrary way, and MUST NOT prevent the operation of recovery
                techniques in the rest of the network.</t>

                <t>MPLS-TP Recovery mechanisms applicable to a ring MUST be
                equally applicable in physical and logical rings.</t>

                <t>Recovery techniques in a ring SHOULD be identical to those
                in general networks to simplify implementation. However, this
                MUST NOT override any other requirement.</t>

                <t>Recovery techniques in logical and physical rings SHOULD be
                identical to simplify implementation and operation. However,
                this MUST NOT override any other requirement.</t>

                <t>The default recovery scheme in a ring MUST be bidirectional
                recovery in order to simplify the recovery operation.</t>

                <t>The recovery mechanism in a ring MUST support revertive
                switching, which MUST be the default behaviour. This allows
                optimization of the use of the ring resources, and restores
                the preferred quality conditions for normal traffic (e.g.,
                delay) when the recovery mechanism is no longer needed.</t>

                <t>The recovery mechanisms in a ring MUST support ways to
                allow administrative protection switching, to be distinguished
                from protection switching initiated by other triggers.</t>

                <t>It MUST be possible to lockout (disable) protection
                mechanisms on selected links (spans) in a ring (depending on
                operator&rsquo;s need). This may require lockout mechanisms to
                be applied to intermediate nodes within a transport path.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
                <t>MPLS-TP recovery mechanisms in a ring MUST include a
                mechanism to allow an implementation to handle coexisting
                requests (i.e., multiple requests &ndash; not necessarily
                arriving simultaneously) for protection switching based on
                priority.</t>

                <t>MPLS-TP recovery and reversion mechanisms in a ring MUST
                offer a way to prevent frequent operation of recovery in the
                event of an intermittent defect.</t>

                <t>MPLS-TP MUST support the sharing of protection bandwidth in
                a ring by allowing best effort traffic.</t>

                <t>MPLS-TP MUST support sharing of ring protection resources
                such that protection paths that are known not to be required
                concurrently can share the same resources.</t>

                <t>MUST support the coordination of triggers caused by events
                at different locations in a ring. Note that this is the ring
                equivalent of the definition of shared protection groups.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="QoS requirements">
        <t>Carriers require advanced traffic management capabilities to
        enforce and guarantee the QoS parameters of customers&rsquo; SLAs.</t>

        <t>Quality of service mechanisms are REQUIRED in an MPLS-TP network to
        ensure:</t>

        <t><list counter="Requirements" style="format %d">
            <t>Support for differentiated services and different traffic types
            with traffic class separation associated with different
            traffic.</t>

            <t>Prioritization of critical services.</t>

            <t>Enabling the provisioning and the guarantee of Service Level
            Specifications (SLS), with support for hard and relative
            end-to-end bandwidth guaranteed.</t>

            <t>Support of services, which are sensitive to jitter and
            delay.</t>

            <t>Guarantee of fair access, within a particular class, to shared
            resources.</t>

            <t>Guaranteed resources for in-band control and management plane
            traffic regardless of the amount of data plane traffic.</t>

            <t>Carriers are provided with the capability to efficiently
            support service demands over the MPLS-TP network. This MUST
            include support for a flexible bandwidth allocation scheme.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Security requirements">
        <t>For a description of the security threats relevant in the context
        of MPLS and GMPLS and the defensive techniques to combat those threats
        see the Security Framework for MPLS &amp; GMPLS Networks <xref
        target="I-D.draft-ietf-mpls-mpls-and-gmpls-security-framework"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>For a description of the security threats relevant in the context of
      MPLS and GMPLS and the defensive techniques to combat those threats see
      the Security Framework for MPLS &amp; GMPLS Networks <xref
      target="I-D.draft-ietf-mpls-mpls-and-gmpls-security-framework"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank all members of the teams (the Joint
      Working Team, the MPLS Interoperability Design Team in the IETF, and the
      T-MPLS Ad Hoc Group in the ITU-T) involved in the definition and
      specification of MPLS Transport Profile.</t>

      <t>The authors would also like to thank Loa Andersson, Lou Berger, Italo
      Busi, John Drake, Adrian Farrel, Eric Gray, Neil Harrison, Huub van
      Helvoort, Wataru Imajuku, Julien Meuric, Tom Nadeau, Hiroshi Ohta,
      George Swallow, Tomonori Takeda and Maarten Vissers for their comments
      and enhancements to the text.</t>

      <t>An ad hoc discussion group consisting of Stewart Bryant, Italo Busi,
      Andrea Digiglio, Li Fang, Adrian Farrel, Jia He, Huub van Helvoort, Feng
      Huang, Harald Kullman, Han Li, Hao Long and Nurit Sprecher provided
      valuable input to the requirements for deployment and survivability in
      ring topologies.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <!-- Begin inclusion reference.RFC.2119.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
          Requirement Levels</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>

                <street>Cambridge</street>

                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>

              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>

              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1997" />

          <area>General</area>

          <keyword>keyword</keyword>

          <abstract>
            <t>In many standards track documents several words are used to
            signify the requirements in the specification. These words are
            often capitalized. This document defines these words as they
            should be interpreted in IETF documents. Authors who follow these
            guidelines should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of
            their document: <list>
                <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
                in RFC 2119.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Note that the force of these words is modified by the
            requirement level of the document in which they are used.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />

        <format octets="4723" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt"
                type="TXT" />

        <format octets="16553"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"
                type="HTML" />

        <format octets="5703"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"
                type="XML" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.2119.xml. -->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.I-D.gray-mpls-tp-nm-req.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="I-D.gray-mpls-tp-nm-req">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="MPLS-TP NM requirements">MPLS TP Network Management
          Requirements</title>

          <author fullname="H. Lam" initials="H." surname="Lam">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Mansfield" initials="S." surname="Mansfield">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="E. Gray" initials="E." surname="Gray">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2009" />

          <abstract></abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-gray-mpls-tp-nm-req-02" />

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-gray-mpls-tp-nm-req-01.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.I-D.gray-mpls-tp-nm-req.xml. -->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.I-D.ietf-mpls-tp-oam-requirements.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-mpls-tp-oam-requirements">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="MPLS-TP NM requirements">Requirements for OAM in MPLS
          Transport Networks</title>

          <author fullname="M. Vigoureux" initials="M." surname="Vigoureux">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Ward" initials="D." surname="Ward">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="M. Betts" initials="M." surname="Betts">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2008" />

          <abstract></abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-mpls-tp-oam-requirements-00" />

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-vigoureux-mpls-tp-oam-requirements-00"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.I-D.ietf-mpls-tp-oam-requirements.xml. -->
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.3031.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="RFC3031">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="MPLS Architecture">Multiprotocol Label Switching
          Architecture</title>

          <author fullname="E. Rosen" initials="E." surname="Rosen">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Viswanathan" initials="A."
                  surname="Viswanathan">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="R. Callon" initials="R." surname="Callon">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2001" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document specifies the architecture for Multiprotocol
            Label Switching (MPLS). [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3031" />

        <format octets="147175"
                target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3031.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.3031.xml. -->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.3985.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="RFC3985">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="PWE3 Architecture">Pseudo Wire Emulation Edge-to-Edge
          (PWE3) Architecture</title>

          <author fullname="S. Bryant" initials="S." surname="Bryant">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="P. Pate" initials="P." surname="Pate">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2005" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes an architecture for Pseudo Wire
            Emulation Edge-to-Edge (PWE3). It discusses the emulation of
            services such as Frame Relay, ATM, Ethernet, TDM, and SONET/SDH
            over packet switched networks (PSNs) using IP or MPLS. It presents
            the architectural framework for pseudo wires (PWs), defines
            terminology, and specifies the various protocol elements and their
            functions. This memo provides information for the Internet
            community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3985" />

        <format octets="95062" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3985.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.3985.xml. -->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.4139.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="RFC4139">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="ASON Signaling Requirements">Requirements for
          Generalized MPLS (GMPLS) Signaling Usage and Extensions for
          Automatically Switched Optical Network (ASON)</title>

          <author fullname="D. Papadimitriou" initials="D."
                  surname="Papadimitriou">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Drake" initials="J." surname="Drake">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Ash" initials="J." surname="Ash">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Farrel" initials="A." surname="Farrel">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="L. Ong" initials="L." surname="Ong">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2005" />

          <abstract>
            <t>The Generalized Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS) suite of
            protocols has been defined to control different switching
            technologies and different applications. These include support for
            requesting Time Division Multiplexing (TDM) connections, including
            Synchronous Optical Network (SONET)/Synchronous Digital Hierarchy
            (SDH) and Optical Transport Networks (OTNs).</t>

            <t>This document concentrates on the signaling aspects of the
            GMPLS suite of protocols. It identifies the features to be covered
            by the GMPLS signaling protocol to support the capabilities of an
            Automatically Switched Optical Network (ASON). This document
            provides a problem statement and additional requirements for the
            GMPLS signaling protocol to support the ASON functionality. This
            memo provides information for the Internet community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4139" />

        <format octets="36660" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4139.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.4139.xml. -->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.4258.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="RFC4258">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="ASON Routing Requirements">Requirements for
          Generalized Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS) Routing for the
          Automatically Switched Optical Network (ASON)</title>

          <author fullname="D. Brungard" initials="D." surname="Brungard">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2005" />

          <abstract>
            <t>The Generalized Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS) suite of
            protocols has been defined to control different switching
            technologies as well as different applications. These include
            support for requesting Time Division Multiplexing (TDM)
            connections including Synchronous Optical Network
            (SONET)/Synchronous Digital Hierarchy (SDH) and Optical Transport
            Networks (OTNs).</t>

            <t>This document concentrates on the routing requirements placed
            on the GMPLS suite of protocols in order to support the
            capabilities and functionalities of an Automatically Switched
            Optical Network (ASON) as defined by the ITU-T. This memo provides
            information for the Internet community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4258" />

        <format octets="48558" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4258.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.4258.xml. -->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.4397.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="RFC4397">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="ASON/GMPLS terminology lexicography">A Lexicography
          for the Interpretation of Generalized Multiprotocol Label Switching
          (GMPLS) Terminology within the Context of the ITU-T's Automatically
          Switched Optical Network (ASON) Architecture</title>

          <author fullname="I. Bryskin" initials="I." surname="Bryskin">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Farrel" initials="A." surname="Farrel">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2006" />

          <abstract>
            <t>The Generalized Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS) suite of
            protocols has been defined to control different switching
            technologies as well as different applications. These include
            support for requesting Time Division Multiplexing (TDM)
            connections including Synchronous Optical Network
            (SONET)/Synchronous Digital Hierarchy (SDH) and Optical Transport
            Networks (OTNs).</t>

            <t>This document concentrates on the routing requirements placed
            on the GMPLS suite of protocols in order to support the
            capabilities and functionalities of an Automatically Switched
            Optical Network (ASON) as defined by the ITU-T. This memo provides
            information for the Internet community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4397" />

        <format octets="40331" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4397.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.4397.xml. -->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.4427.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="RFC4427">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Recovery Terminology">Recovery (Protection and
          Restoration) Terminology for Generalized Multi-Protocol Label
          Switching (GMPLS)</title>

          <author fullname="E. Mannie" initials="E." surname="Mannie">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Papadimitriou" initials="D."
                  surname="Papadimitriou">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2006" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document defines a common terminology for Generalized
            Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS)-based recovery mechanisms
            (i.e., protection and restoration). The terminology is independent
            of the underlying transport technologies covered by GMPLS. This
            memo provides information for the Internet community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4427" />

        <format octets="43842" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4427.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.4427.xml. -->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.5331.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="RFC5331">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Upstream Label Assignment">MPLS Upstream Label
          Assignment and Context-Specific Label Space</title>

          <author fullname="R. Aggarwal" initials="R." surname="Aggarwal">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Y. Rekhter" initials="Y." surname="Rekhter">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="E. Rosen" initials="E." surname="Rosen">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2008" />

          <abstract>
            <t>RFC 3031 limits the MPLS architecture to downstream-assigned
            MPLS labels. This document introduces the notion of
            upstream-assigned MPLS labels. It describes the procedures for
            upstream MPLS label assignment and introduces the concept of a
            "Context-Specific Label Space". [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5331" />

        <format octets="30779" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5331.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.5331.xml. -->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.I-D.draft-ietf-mpls-mpls-and-gmpls-security-framework.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="I-D.draft-ietf-mpls-mpls-and-gmpls-security-framework">
        <front>
          <title
          abbrev="Security Framework for MPLS &amp; GMPLS Networks">Security
          Framework for MPLS and GMPLS Networks</title>

          <author fullname="L. Fang" initials="L." surname="Fang">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="M. Behringer" initials="M." surname="Behringer">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2008" />

          <abstract></abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-mpls-mpls-and-gmpls-security-framework-04" />

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-mpls-mpls-and-gmpls-security-framework-03"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.I-D.draft-ietf-mpls-mpls-and-gmpls-security-framework.xml. -->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.ITU.Y2611.2006.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="ITU.Y2611.2006">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Y.2611">High-level architecture of future
          packet-based networks</title>

          <author>
            <organization>International Telecommunications
            Union</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2006" />

          <abstract>
            <t>ITU-T Recommendation Y.2611 specifies a high-level architecture
            for future packet-based networks (FPBNs). This Recommendation also
            specifies the relationship between an FPBN and the NGN strata and
            the interfaces in an FPBN.</t>

            <t>In order to be able to provide a full suite of services
            (examples of which include data, video and voice telephony
            services) to their customers, operators may need to utilize both
            connectionless packet switched (cl-ps) and connection-oriented
            packet-switched (co-ps) transport modes. This is because each mode
            is well suited to the transport of some services and not so well
            suited to the transport of others.</t>

            <t>FPBNs provide the topmost layer(s) of the transport stratum as
            defined in ITU-T Recommendation Y.2011. The services mentioned
            above form part of the service stratum as defined in ITU-T
            Recommendation Y.2011.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation Y.2611" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.ITU.Y2611.2006.xml. -->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.ITU.Y1401.2008.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="ITU.Y1401.2008">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Y.1401">Principles of interworking</title>

          <author>
            <organization>International Telecommunications
            Union</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2008" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This Recommendation provides an architectural framework and
            general principles for transport stratum interworking in an NGN
            environment. It describes client/server and peer-partition
            interworking.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation Y.1401" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.ITU.Y1401.2008.xml. -->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.ITU.G805.2000.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="ITU.G805.2000">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="G.805">Generic functional architecture of transport
          networks</title>

          <author>
            <organization>International Telecommunications
            Union</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2000" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This Recommendation describes the functional architecture of
            transport networks in a technology independent way. The generic
            functional architecture may be used as the basis for a harmonized
            set of functional architecture Recommendations for ATM, SDH, PDH
            transport networks, and a corresponding set of Recommendations for
            management, performance analysis and equipment specification.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation G.805" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.ITU.G805.2000.xml.-->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.ITU.G870.2008.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="ITU.G870.2008">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="OTN Terms">Terms and definitions for optical
          transport networks (OTN)</title>

          <author>
            <organization>International Telecommunications
            Union</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2008" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This Recommendation describes the functional architecture of
            transport networks in a technology independent way. The generic
            functional architecture may be used as the basis for a harmonized
            set of functional architecture Recommendations for ATM, SDH, PDH
            transport networks, and a corresponding set of Recommendations for
            management, performance analysis and equipment specification.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation G.870" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.ITU.G870.2008.xml.-->

      <!--Begin inclusion reference.ITU.G8080.2000.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="ITU.G8080.2006">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="ASON architecture">Architecture for the automatically
          switched optical network (ASON)</title>

          <author>
            <organization>International Telecommunications
            Union</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2006" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This Recommendation describes the functional architecture of
            transport networks in a technology independent way. The generic
            functional architecture may be used as the basis for a harmonized
            set of functional architecture Recommendations for ATM, SDH, PDH
            transport networks, and a corresponding set of Recommendations for
            management, performance analysis and equipment specification.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation G.8080" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.ITU.G8080.2000.xml.-->
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
