<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
        'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2629 PUBLIC '' 
        'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2640 PUBLIC '' 
        'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2640.xml'>
    <!ENTITY raws PUBLIC ''
        'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.iab-raws-report.xml'>
    <!ENTITY lisp PUBLIC ''
        'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.farinacci-lisp.xml'>
    <!ENTITY hip PUBLIC ''
        'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-hip-base.xml'>
    <!ENTITY shim6 PUBLIC ''
        'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-shim6-proto.xml'>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc ipr="full3978" docName="draft-mrw-ram-trip-00.txt">
    <front>
    <title>Tiered Routing for IPv4 and IPv6 (TRIP)</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Wasserman" fullname="Margaret Wasserman">
        <organization>Sandstorm Enterprises</organization>
        <address>
        <postal>
            <street>14 Summer St. 4th Floor</street>
            <city>Malden</city> <region>MA</region>
            <code>02148</code>
            <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 781 333-3213</phone>
        <email>mrw@sandstorm.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.sandstorm.net</uri>
        </address>
    </author>
    <date month="December" year="2008" />
    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

<abstract>
<t>
This document describes a mechanism for scalable, tiered Internet
routing, called TRIP.  The goal of TRIP is to decrease the growth
rate of the core Internet routing tables by increasing route
aggregation and constraining the propagation of multihoming and
traffic engineering routes.
</t>
<t>
TRIP accomplishes this goal by defining separate routing domains for
edge networks and transit networks.  All current, non-TRIP-aware
networks and nodes are considered part of the transit domain.  Edge
network domains may be created by deploying TRIP at a domain-boundary
routers or within IP (v4 or v6) endpoints.
</t>
<t>
In addition to defining the basic TRIP mechanism, this document
describes an incremental deployment path that provides a means for
endpoints in TRIP-enabled edge networks to talk directly to
non-TRIP-aware end-points in transit domain.  This is accomplished
without the need to advertise edge network prefixes in the global
routing tables or to create a separate global routing domain for edge
network prefixes.
</t>
</abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
<t>
The growth rate of the core BGP routing tables has been identified as
a serious scaling problem for the Internet <xref
target="I-D.iab-raws-report"/>.  The core BGP routing tables are
growing faster than the number of Internet hosts for several reasons,
including: (1) the introduction of IPv6 routes, including IPv6 routes
to dual-stack networks that are already represented by IPv4 routes,
(2) end-user demand for provider-independent addressing, which reduces
the efficiency of route aggregation, and (3) the propagation of
multihoming and traffic engineering (VPN) routes into the core BGP
routing tables.  End user requirements for (2) and (3) are in direct
conflict with the route aggregation required for scalable Internet
routing.  The eFIT document (reference needed)
describes this conflict in more detail and makes a sound argument that
the number of routes propagated into the DFZ for these reasons can be
reduced or eliminated by separating the address space used on transit
networks from the address space used on edge networks.
</t>
<t>
This document describes a mechanism for scalable, tiered Internet
routing, called TRIP.  The goal of TRIP is to decrease the rate of
growth of the core Internet routing tables by increasing route
aggregation and constraining the propagation of multihoming and
traffic engineering routes.  TRIP also makes it possible to eliminate
redundant IPv4 and IPv6 routes to dual-stack networks when both
protocols are equally available at an edge network's Internet
attachment points.
</t>
<t>
TRIP conceptually divides the IP (v4 and v6) address space into two
sets: a set of topologically-assigned Global LOCators (GLOCs) that are
used for routing across transit networks, and a set of
provider-independent Endpoint IDentifiers (EIDs) that are used for
both routing and end-point identification within TRIP-enabled edge
networks.  A TRIP-enabled edge network is created by deploying TRIP
within one or more domain-boundary routers (DBRs) that create a border
between the edge network and its attached transit network(s).  TRIP
can be implemented entirely within DBRs, without any modifications to
endpoints or non-DBR routers.
</t>
<t>
TRIP can be deployed at any level of the topology, from an individual
end node, to an end-user/ISP boundary, to an ISP/ISP boundary.  As
specified, TRIP creates exactly two addressing and routing domains,
the edge network domain and the transit network domain.  Further
investigation would be required to determine how/if a TRIP-derived 
mechanism could be used to create more than two domains.
</t>
<t>
To allow TRIP to be incrementally deployed on individual networks or
nodes, TRIP DBRs include mechanisms that allow endpoints on
TRIP-enabled networks to communicate directly with non-TRIP-aware
endpoints, and vice versa.  These mechanisms do have some limitations,
but will provide a level of service equal to or better than an IPv4
NAT.  Many IPv4 enterprises have determined that such limitations are
an acceptable price to pay for provider-independent internal
addressing and/or local network topology hiding, both of which can be
provided using the TRIP mechanism.  A TRIP DBR could also be
integrated with a stateful firewall function, creating a boundary
router that provides essentially the same set of protections afforded
by an IPv4 NAT, with the same or fewer limitations.
</t> 
    </section>
    <section title="Requirements Terminology">
<t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>
    </section>
    <section title="TRIP Overview">
<t>
TRIP is a tiered routing mechanism that divides the Internet into two
addressing and routing domains: the transit network domain and the edge
network domain.  To accomplish this, TRIP conceptually divides the IP
(v4 or v6) address space into a set of Global LOCators (GLOCs) that
are used for routing within the transit domain, and a set of globally
unique Endpoint IDentifiers that are used to globally identify
individual endpoints.  EIDs can be used for routing only within their
local edge networks.  
</t>
<t>
From a TRIP perspective, all of the nodes that are currently attached
to the Internet are located in the transit domain, as their IP
addresses can be used to route packets across the global Internet.
Because their IP addresses can also be used for endpoint
identification, their IP addresses currently serve as both GLOCs and
EIDs.  The incremental deployment of TRIP involves moving individual
networks and nodes into the edge routing domain, where they will be
represented by separate EIDs and GLOCs, while retaining their ability
to communicate with nodes that remain in the transit domain.
</t>
<t>
The two separate routing domains are connected via Domain Boundary
Routers (DBRs) that use the TRIP mechanism to forward packets from
the edge network domain onto transit networks and from the transit
network domain onto edge network.  Except in cases where sufficent
IPv4 address space is not available (see below), GBRs maintain a
two-way, one-to-one mapping between GLOCs and EIDs.
</t>
        <section title="Example of a TRIP-Enabled Edge Network">
<t>
The diagram below shows a multi-homed TRIP-enabled edge network.  The
network has two DBRs, connecting the edge network to two different
Internet Service Providers (ISPs).  The enterprise administrator has
chosen to place a server (S) across the transit network/edge network
boundary, so that it will be easily accessible from Internet nodes
that remain in the transit domain, as well as from nodes in this and
other TRIP-enabled edge networks.  This example edge network also
contains a set of internal routers (R) and hosts (H).
</t>
<figure>
<artwork>
<![CDATA[

        _________________________________________________________
         \__                                                 __/
           \__                 INTERNET                   __/
              \__________________________________________/ 
                          ^                     ^
                          |                  ISP  #2
                       ISP  #1               TRANSIT
                       TRANSIT               NETWORK
                       NETWORK                  v
                          |      _________________________________
TRANSIT                   v                |           |
NETWORK                +-----+          +-----+      +---+
- - - - - - - - - - - -|-DBR-|- - - - - |-DBR-|- - - | S | - - - -
TRIP-ENABLED          +-----+          +-----+      +---+
EDGE                      |                |           |
NETWORK     ______________|________________|___________|__________
                  |                |               |
                +---+            +---+           +---+
                | R |            | R |           | R |
                +---+            +---+           +---+
                  |                |               |
            ______|______    ______|_______________|______________
             |  |   |  |      |         |     |         |     |
             H  H   H  H      H         H     H         H     H


            Figure 1:  Multi-homed TRIP-enabled edge network.
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
        </section>
        <section title="TRIP EID and GLOC Assignment">
<t>
Each TRIP-enabled edge network will be assigned at least one globally
unique, provider-independent EID prefix.  Internal subnet prefixes and
EIDs will be allocated from within the EID prefix(es).  EIDs will be
routable within the local network and can be used globally to identify
nodes within the edge network.  The EID prefix(es) will not be
advertised in the transit domain by either of the edge network's ISPs,
and will not be used for routing outside of the edge network.
</t>
<t>
Each ISP will assign at least one globally unique, globally routable
GLOC prefix to the edge network.  Although GLOCs will not be allocated
directly to the internal network nodes, the GLOC prefix should be
large enough to allow a unique GLOC to be associated with each edge
network EID.  Except in cases were insufficient IPv4 address space is
available (see below), each DBR will maintain a two-way, one-to-one
mapping between the GLOC(s) and EID(s) associated with each node on
its attached edge network(s).  In cases where topology hiding is not
required, this mapping may be a simple prefix-to-prefix mapping, with
the same subnet and host (or IID) values being used for corresponding
GLOCs and EIDs.
</t>
<t>
In the example edge network represented in Figure 1, each node in the
edge network will be assigned at least one EID from the local EID
prefix.  The EID(s) will be assigned directly to each node using a
current IP address assignment mechanism, such as manual configuration,
DHCP or IPv6 Address Autoconfiguration.  The nodes inside the edge
nework are unmodified IP nodes, so they will treat the EIDs as their
IP addresses.
</t>
<t>
There will also be at least two GLOC Prefixess assigned to the site,
one assigned by ISP #1 (GLOC Prefix #1), and one assigned by ISP #2
(GLOC Prefix #2).  The DBR attached to ISP #1 will associate a GLOC
from GLOC Prefix #1 with each EID in the edge network, and the DBR
attached to ISP #2 will associate a GLOC from GLOC Prefix #2 with each
EID in the edge network.  ISPs will advertise the GLOC prefixes into
the global Internet routing tables (perhaps as part of a larger
aggregation), and the GLOCs will be used to route traffic to/from edge
network nodes across the global Internet.  GLOCs will not be assigned
directly to edge network nodes, and they will not be used for
identification or routing within the edge network.
</t>
<t>
The server that is located at the edge network/transit network
boundary will be assigned at least one EID from the edge network's EID
prefix on its edge network interface.  Both GBRs will associate GLOCs
with the server's EID(s), as for any other edge network node.
However, the server will also be assigned an address from GLOC Prefix
#2 which will serve as both the GLOC and the EID for the server's
transit network interface.  Nodes in the transit network that wish to
reach the server will send packets to the server's transit network
EID/GLOC for server identification and routing.  Nodes within the
local edge network will use the server's edge network EID for both
identification and routing.  Nodes in other TRIP-enabled edge
networks will use the server's edge network EID for identification,
and their packets will be routed to either one of the GLOCs
corresponding to that EID.
</t>
        </section>
        <section title="TRIP DNS Configuration">
<t>
The DNS will be configured to return the EIDs in response to A and
AAAA record queries for nodes in TRIP-enabled edge networks.  The DNS
configuration for nodes on transit networks will be unmodified, and
the DNS will continue to return IP addresses (which can be used as
EIDs and GLOCs) for transit network nodes.
</t>
<t>
A new DNS record, the GLOC record, is defined below and can be used to
map an EID to its corresponding GLOC.  For TRIP to function properly,
a GLOC record must be configured for each edge network EID, and transit
network nodes must not be represented by GLOC records in the DNS.
</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Example TRIP Packet Exchange">
<t>
When a host in a TRIP-enabled edge network chooses to initiate
communication with a node outside of the edge network, it will first
determine the EID for the destination node, perhaps by performing a
DNS look-up.  The sending host will construct an IP packet that
contains the EID of the remote node as the destination address and the
EID of the sending host as the source address.  Since the destination
address is not on the local subnet, the sending host will forward the
packet to its default router.  The packet will then be routed normally
through the edge network towards the Internet, until it reaches a DBR.
</t>
<t>
When the DBR receives a packet from an edge network that will be
forwarded onto a transit network, it will use its local mapping to
determine the local GLOC associated with the source EID.  The GBR will
also look up the GLOC associated with the destination EID by checking
the local cache or, if necessary, by performing a DNS query using the
GLOC DNS record defined later in this document.
</t>
<t>
If the destination GLOC lookup is successful, then the destination
node is located in a TRIP-enabled edge network domain.  In this case,
the GBR will perform an IP-version-dependent SPRINT transformation
that will result in the source and destination GLOCs being copied into
the source and destination address fields of the outermost IP header,
and the original source and destination EIDs being stored elsewhere
(either in a tunneled IPv4 header, or in an IPv6 SPRINT Destination
Option defined later in this document.  The packet will then be
forwarded towards the destination GLOC).  This will result in the
packet traversing a remote GBR, where it will be transformed back into
its original form and forwarded to its final destination on an edge
network attached to the remote GBR..
</t>
<t>
If the GLOC look-up is unsuccesful, then the destination node is
presumed to be in the transit network domain, where its destination
GLOC will be the same as its destination EID.  In that case, the GBR
performs a different IP-version-dependent transformation that will
result in the packet being sent to its original destination EID/GLOC
from the source GLOC.  Because there will be no remote GBR to reverse
the transformation, the local GBR will also modify the next-layer
checksums to reflect the new source address in the IP header, and it
will replace any source addresses used in upper layer protocols with
the source GLOC, so that reply packets can be routed to the correct
edge network from the transit domain.  This transformation is very
similar to the the transformation performed by an IPv4 NAT box.
</t>
<t>
When a GBR receives a packet with one of its local GLOCs as its
destination address, the GBR first determines whether the packet was
sent from a remote GBR or from a transit node.  If the packet was sent
from a remote GBR, the packet will contain all of the information
necessary to reverse the IP-version-specific SPRINT transformation and
forward the packet to the original destination EID with the IP header
in its original form.  No changes to the upper layers will be
required.  In this case, the GBR will also cache the EID-to-GLOC
mapping, so that it can be used for return traffic.
</t>
<t>
If the packet was not sent from a remote GBR, the local GBR uses
its internal mapping to map the destination GLOC to the corresponding
local EID.  It copies the EID into the destination address field of the IP
header and performs a NAT-like transformation to adjust the next-layer
checksums before forwarding the packet to its final destination.
</t>
<t>
This mechanism results in a very clean separation between edge network
routing domains and the transit network domain.  Edge network (EID)
prefixes are never adverstised in the transit routing domain, and
transit domain (GLOC) prefixes are never advertised within edge
networks.  With the exception of transit domain nodes whose EIDs and
GLOCs are identical, edge network addresses (EIDs) are never used as
the source or destination addresses of IP packets being routed through
the transit domain, and transit network addresses (GLOCs) are never
used as source or destination addresses of IP packets being routed
through edge network domains.
</t>
    </section> 
    <section title="GLOC DNS Record">
<t>
Note: This section will define a GLOC DNS records that is used for
mapping EIDs to GLOCs if/when I find (or become?) someone with enough
DNS clue to write it.
</t>
        </section>
	</section>
    <section title="TRIP IPv6 Destination Option">
<t>
For IPv6 packets, TRIP uses a IPv6 Destination Option to hold the
EIDs while the packet is being routed across the transit domain.  This
option also includes a "Cache Time-To-Live" field that indicates the
amount of time, in seconds that a remote DBR should cache the EID to
GLOC mapping information contained in this packet.  
</t>
<figure> 
<artwork>
<![CDATA[

    + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                               |Version|4|T|S|D|   Reserved    |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                           Cache TTL                           |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                                                               |
    +                                                               +
    |                                                               |
    +                      Source EID or GLOC                       +
    |                                                               |
    +                                                               +
    |                                                               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                                                               |
    +                                                               +
    |                                                               |
    +                    Destination EID or GLOC                    +
    |                                                               |
    +                                                               +
    |                                                               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
<t>
TBD: Need to add explanation of destination option fields.
</t>
	</section>
    <section title="TRIP Translation Mechanisms">
<t>
TBD
</t>
        <section title="Recognized Upper Layer Protocols">
<t>
TBD
</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Comparison to IPv4 NAT">
<t>
TBD
</t>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section title="'No Translation Needed' ICMP Message"> 
<t>
TBD
</t>
    </section>
    <section title="DBR Transformations for IPv6">
<t>
This section describes how DBRs process IPv6 packets.
</t>
        <section title="IPv6 Edge-to-Transit Transformation">
<t>
When a DBR receives a packet from an edge network that will be forwarded
onto the transit network, it performs the following steps:
</t>
<list style='numbers'>
<t>
If there is already a TRIP IPv6 Destination Option in the packet,
indicating that another DBR has previously processed the packet, the
DBR checks the destination GLOC to see if it matches one of the local
GLOCs.  If the packet is not addressed to one of the DBRs local GLOCs,
the DBR forwards the packet onto the transit network without further
processing.  If the packet is addressed to one of the DBRs local
GLOCs, the DBR processes the packet as if it were received from the
transit network (see below).
</t>
<t>
The DBR uses its local EID to GLOC mapping information to map the
source EID (from the source address field of the IP header) to a GLOC.
If this mapping does not succeed, this indicates a configuration
problem within the edge network, and the packet will be
discarded. ICMP error?
</t>
<t>
The DBR will then attempt to lookup the destination GLOC associated
with the destination EID.  To accomplish this, the GBR MAY check the
local cache to see if it has an existing EID to GLOC mapping for the
destination EID (from the destination address of the IP header).  If
not, it performs a DNS query using the GLOC DNS record to map the
destination EID to a destination GLOC.  If a GLOC is returned, the GBR
MAY cache the implied EID-to-GLOC mapping for the length of time
indicated by the TTL in the DNS response.  If a DNS response was
received indicating that there is no GLOC corresponding to the
destination EID, the GBR MAY also cache that information for up to one
hour.  If no response is received from the DNS query, the packet is
processed as if no GLOC was returned, but the result MUST NOT be
cached.  If the GLOC lookup is successful, the GBR knows that the
destination is located in a TRIP-enabled edge network.  Otherwise,
the GBR assumes that the destination is located in the transit domain,
where the destination EID can also be used as the destination GLOC.
</t>
<t>
The DBR inserts a TRIP Source IPv6 Destination Option into the
packet.  It clears the "IPv4" field (sets it to zero) to indicate that
the original packet was an IPv6 packet.  It copies the original source
EID into the "Source EID or GLOC" field and clears the "Source" flag
(sets it to 0) to indicate that the "Source EID or GLOC" field
currently contains the source EID.  It also copies the destination EID
into the "Destination EID or GLOC field" and clears the "Destination"
flag, to indicate that the "Destination EID or GLOC" currently
contains an EID.
</t>
<t>
The GBR copies the source GLOC into the source address field of the 
IPv6 header.
</t>
<t>
If the packet is being sent to a TRIP-enabled edge network, the GBR
copies the destination GLOC into the destination address field of the
IPv6 header.  The GBR will clear the "Translated" flag in
the TRIP Destination Option, because the remote DBR will restore the
packet to its original form, so there is no need to modify the
next-layer checksums or to translate source addresses in upper layer
packets.
</t>
<t>
If the packet is being sent to a destination in the transit domain,
the GBR will adjust the next header checksum to compensate for the
source address change.  If the next header is not recognixed, the
checksum will not be changed.  It will also translate source addresses
used in the upper layer protocol from the original EID to the source
GLOC.  If an upper layer protocol is not recognized, no translation
will be performed.  A list of the next and upper layer protocols that
TRIP DBRs are required to recognize is included in a later section.
If any adjustment or translation has occurred, the DBR will set the
"Translated" flag in the TRIP Destination Option to indicate that the
packet has been translated to match the new source address.
</t>
<t>
The DBR will forward the resulting packet onto the transit network,
where it will be routed using the destination GLOC, which is now the
destination address in the IPv6 header.
</t>
</list>
        </section>
        <section title="IPv6 Transit-to-Edge Transformation">
<t>
When a DBR receives an IPv6 packet (typically from the transit
network) whose destination address matches one of the DBR's local
GLOCs, the DBR will perform the following steps:
</t>
    <list style='numbers'>
<t>
The DBR will first determine whether there is a TRIP Destination
Option present in the packet.  If a TRIP Destination Option is
present, that indicates that this packet was sent from a TRIP-enabled
edge network.  If not, the packet must have been sent from a node in
the transit domain.
</t>
<t>
If the TRIP Destination Option is not present, the DBR performs the following steps:
</t>
        <list style='symbols'>
<t>
The DBR MAY cache an indication that the IPv6 source address refers to an
EID that is located in the transit network domain, or it may refresh
the timeout for an existing cache entry for this EID.  The resulting
cache entry MUST NOT have a lifetime of more than 1 hour.
</t>
<t>
The DBR looks in its local mapping table to map the destination GLOC
(contained in the IPv6 destination address field) to a local EID and
copies that EID into the IPv6 destination address field.
</t>
<t>
If the next header value is recognized, the DBR adjusts the next-layer
checksum to reflect the modified destination address and fowards the resulting packet onto the edge network.
</t>
        </list>
<t>
If the TRIP Destination Option is present, the DBR will peform the
following checks to determine how/if the packet should be processed:
</t>
        <list style='symbols'>
<t>
The DBR will check the "IPv4" flag to determine if the original packet
was an IPv4 packet.  If so, the GBR will check the IPv4 destination
address to determine if it matches one of the local IPv4 EIDs.  If so,
the GBR will remove the outer IPv6 header and all associated extension
headers and forward the IPv4 packet onto the edge network.
</t>
<t>
The DBR will check the "Translated" flag in the TRIP Destination
Option to mae sure that translation was not performed on this packet.
If the flag is set, that indicates that the remote DBR was unaware
that the destination was on a TRIP-enabled Edge Network.  In this
case, the packet is dropped and an ICMP "No Translation Required"
message is returned to the IPv6 source address of the packet.
</t>
<t>
The DBR will check the "Destination flag and the "Destination EID or
GLOC" field in the TRIP Destination Option to determine if the field
contains an EID that matches the EID prefix assigned to (one of) the
GBRs attached edge network(s). the GBR will drop the packet. ICMP
error message?
</t>
        </list> 
<t>
If the packet has passed all of the previous checks without being
dropped or forwarded, the DBR will perform the following steps:
</t>
        <list style='symbols'>
<t>
The DBR will check the "Source" flag in the TRIP Destination Option
to determine if the source EID is currently stored in the TRIP
Destination Option (flag is 0) or in the source address field of the
IPv6 packet (flag is 1).  The DBR then knows that the source GLOC is
stored in the other location.  Once the DBR knows which address is
which, it MAY cache a GLOC to EID mapping, or refresh an existing
cache entry for the mapping, so that the DBR will be able to send
return traffic to the source EID without performing a DNS lookup.  The
lifetime of the cache entry MUST NOT exceed the the length of time
indicated by the "Cache TTL" field in the TRIP Destination Option.
</t>
<t>
The GBR will copy the destination EID into the destination address
field of the IPv6 packet.  It will store the destination GLOC in the
"Destination EID or GLOC" field of the TRIP Destination Option and
set the "Destination" flag to indicate that the field currently
contains a GLOC.
</t>
<t>
If the source address field in the IPv6 header currently contains a
GLOC, the DBR will copy the source EID into the source address field
of the IPv6 packet.  It will store the source GLOC in the "Source EID
or GLOC" field of the TRIP Destination Option and set the "Source"
flag to indicate that the field currently contains a GLOC.
</t>
<t>
Question: For AH to work properly, would the DBR need to remove the
TRIP Source option and the IPv6 Routing Header and restore the Next
Header field in the IPv6 header to its original value?
</t>
<t>
The GBR will resulting packet on to the edge network.
</t>
        </list>
    </list>
        </section>
        <section title="ICMPv6 Error Handling">
TBD
        </section>
    </section>
    <section title="TRIP Transformations for IPv4">
<t>
Due to protocol and operational difference between IPv4 and IPv6,
TRIP operates somewhat differently for IPv4 packets than it does for
IPv6.
</t>
        <section title="IPv4 Edge-to-Transit Transformation">
<t>
For IPv4 edge networks, IPv4 addresses are used for EIDs, but GLOCs
may be either IPv4 or IPv6 addresses.  Because IPv4 does not provide
an equivalent to IPv6 destination options, IP-in-IP encapsulation is
used between TRIP-enabled IPv4 networks, with the version of the outer
IP header being dependent upon the IP version of the GLOC.
</t>
<t>
More detail TBD.
</t>
        </section>
        <section title="IPv4 Transit-to-Edge Transformation">
<t>
TBD
</t>
        </section>
        <section title="ICMP(v4) Message Handling">
TBD
        </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Incremental Deployment of TRIP">
<t>
TBD
</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">
<t>
TBD
</t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
TBD
</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
<t>
Aspects of this work were inspired by earlier work in this area,
including: ENCAPS, GSE, HIP <xref target="I-D.ietf-hip-base"/>, SHIM6
<xref target="I-D.ietf-shim6-proto"/>, eFit, and LISP <xref
target="I-D.farinacci-lisp"/>.
</t>
<t>
The following people provided advice or review comments that
substantially improved this document: TBD.
</t>
<t>
This document was written using the xml2rfc tool described in RFC 2629
<xref target="RFC2629"/>.
</t>
    </section> 
    </middle>
        
    <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
	&rfc2119;
	&rfc2640;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
        &raws;
        &hip;
        &shim6;
        &efit;
        &lisp;
        &rfc2629;
    </references>
    </back>
</rfc>

