<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

 <!ENTITY rfc3315  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml'>
 <!ENTITY rfc3736  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3736.xml'>
 <!ENTITY rfc3971  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3971.xml'>
 <!ENTITY rfc4191  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4191.xml'>
 <!ENTITY rfc4192  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4192.xml'>
 <!ENTITY rfc4861  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml'>
 <!ENTITY rfc4862  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml'>

<rfc ipr="full3978" category="info" docName="draft-chown-v6ops-rogue-ra-00">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="Rogue IPv6 Router Advertisements">Rogue IPv6 Router Advertisement Problem Statement</title>
		<author fullname="Tim Chown" initials="T.J." surname="Chown">
			<organization> University of Southampton </organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street/>
					<city> Southampton </city>
					<code> SO17 1BJ </code>
					<region> Hampshire </region>
					<country> United Kingdom </country>
				</postal>
				<email> tjc@ecs.soton.ac.uk </email>
			</address>
		</author>
                <author fullname="Stig Venaas" initials="S." surname="Venaas">
                        <organization> UNINETT </organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <city> Trondheim </city>
                                        <code> NO 7465 </code>
                                        <country> Norway</country>
                                </postal>
                                <email> venaas@uninett.no </email>
                        </address>
                </author>
		<date month="November" year="2007"/>
		<area>Operations</area>
		<workgroup>IPv6 Operations</workgroup>
		<abstract>
<t>
When deploying IPv6 networks, whether IPv6-only or dual-stack, routers
are configured to use IPv6 Router Advertisements to convey information
to on link nodes that enable them to autoconfigure on the network.  This
information includes the implied default router address taken from the
observed source address of the Router Advertisement (RA) message.   
However, in some networks 'bogus' RAs are observed, which may be
present due to misconfigurations or possibly malicious attacks on the
network.   In this draft we summarise the scenarios in which rogue RAs
may be observed, and we present a list of possible solutions to the
problem.    The goal of this draft is to present a framework around which
solutions can be proposed and discussed.
</t>
		</abstract>
<!--
		<note title="Requirements Language">
			<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
&quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;,
&quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be
interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
</t>
		</note>
-->
	</front>
	<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
	<t>
The <xref target="RFC4861">Neighbor Discovery protocol</xref> describes
the operation of IPv6 Router Advertisements (RAs), which are used during
the IPv6 autoconfiguration process, whether stateful (via 
<xref target="RFC3315">DHCPv6</xref> or
<xref target="RFC3736">DHCPv6 Light</xref>)
or stateless (as
per <xref target="RFC4862">RFC4862</xref>).   In either case, the default
router address is drawn from the RA.   There is currently no DHCPv6
option to configure a default gateway address.
	</t>
	<t>
In observing the operation of deployed IPv6 networks, it is apparent that
there is a problem with undesired or 'bogus' IPv6 Router Advertisements (RAs)
appearing on network links or subnets.    By 'bogus' we mean RAs that
were not the intended configured RAs, rather RAs that have appeared for
some other reason.
	</t>
	<t>
The problem with rogue RAs is that they can cause partial or complete
failure of operation on an IPv6 link.   As such they are an operational
issue for which solution(s) are required, and for which best practice needs
to be conveyed.   
	</t>
	<t>
In the next section, we discuss
the scenarios that may give rise to rogue RAs being present.   In the
following section we present some candidate solutions for the problem,
some of which may be more practical to deploy than others.   
	</t>
</section>

<section title="Bogus RA Scenarios">

	<t>
There are three broad classes of scenario in which bogus RAs may be introduced to an IPv6 network.   
	</t>

	<section title="Administrator misconfiguration">
	<t>
Here an administrator incorrectly configures RAs on a router interface,
causing incorrect RAs to appear on links and hosts to generate incorrect
IPv6 address or other information.    In this case the default gateway
may be correct, but a host might for example become multi-addressed,
possibly with a correct and incorrect address based on a correct and
incorrect prefix.    In the case of a Layer 2 VLAN misconfiguration,
RAs may 'flood' to unintended links, causing hosts or more than one link
to potentially become incorrectly multiaddressed.    There is also
the possibility of bad lifetime information being configured.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="User misconfiguration">
	<t>
In this case a user's device 'accidentally' transmits RAs onto the local
link, adding an addition default gateway and prefix information.   This
is typically seen on wireless (though sometimes wired) networks where
a laptop has been used as a home gateway (e.g. a 6to4 gateway) and has
then been attached to another network with the gateway configuration still
active.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Malicious misconfiguration">
	<t>
Here an attacker is deliberately generating RAs on the local network in 
an attempt to perform some form of denial of service or man-in-the-middle
attack.
	</t>
	</section>

</section>

<section title="Methods to Mitigate against Rogue RAs">

	<t>
In this section we present a summary of methods suggested to date
for reducing or removing the possibility of rogue RAs being seen on
a network.
	</t>

	<section title="Manual configuration">
	<t>
The default gateway can usually be manually configured on a device.
This is of course a resource intensive solution, and also prone to
mistakes.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Secure Neighbor Discovery">
	<t>

The <xref target="RFC3971">SEND</xref> protocol provides a method for
hosts and routers to perform secure Neighbor Discovery.   At present
there are very few SEND implementations available, and SEND is perceived
as a complex protocol to deploy.   
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Introduce RA snooping">
	<t>
It should be possible to implement 'RA snooping' in Layer 2 switches in
a similar way to DHCP snooping, such that RAs observed from incorrect
sources are blocked or dropped, and not propagated through a subnet.
One candidate solution in this space called RA-Guard
<xref target="ra-guard"/> has recently been proposed.
This type of solution has appeal because it is a familiar model for
enterprise network managers.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Password option">
	<t>
Some form of password option a la RIP could be introduced.  It is
not clear how exactly this could be implemented or used, so it is
not considered a serious option at present.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Use the Router Preference Option">
	<t>
<xref target="RFC4191">RFC4191</xref> introduced router preference
options, such that an RA could carry one of three router preference
values: High, Medium (default) or Low.   Thus an administrator could
use High settings for managed RAs, and hope that 'accidental' RAs
would be medium priority, and that hosts implemented this optional
protocol.   
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Rely on Layer 2 admission control">
	<t>
In principle, if a technology such as IEEE 802.1x is used, devices
would first need to authenticate to the network before being able to
send or receive IPv6 traffic.    Ideally authentication would be
mutual.   This may mitigate against a malicious
attacker, but doesn't address the misconfiguration issues.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Use host-based packet filters">
	<t>
In a managed environment hosts could be configured via their 'personal
firewall' to only accept RAs from trusted sources.    However, the
problem is then pushed to keeping this configuration maintained and
correct.   If a router fails and is replaced, possibly with a new Layer 2
interface address, the link local source address in the filter may be
incorrect and no network exists to push the new information to the 
host.
	</t>
	<t>
Also, hosts could potentially be configured to discard 6to4-based RAs in
a managed enterprise environment.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Use an 'intelligent' deprecation tool">
	<t>
It could be possible to run a daemon on a link (perhaps on the router
on the link) to watch for incorrect RAs and to send a deprecating RA
with router lifetime of zero when such an RA is observed.
The KAME rafixd is an
example of such a tool, which has been used at IETF meetings with
some success.    Whether or not such a tool is the preferred method,
monitoring a link for observed RAs seems prudent from a network management
perspective.   Some such tools exist already, e.g. ndpmon.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Add a Default Gateway Option to DHCPv6">
	<t>
It may be possible to define a new Default Gateway Option for DHCPv6
that would allow network administrators to only have hosts use DHCPv6
for default gateway configuration in managed networks.   While such
an option could be defined, its ramifications remain unclear.   In
the absence of RAs, other configuration information would also be
missing, e.g. on-link prefix information.     Of course, it may be
that an RA is still required to inform the host to use DHCPv6, and
that may introduce a Catch-22 unless hosts are configured directly
to only use DHCPv6.
	</t>
	<t>
An advantage of DHCPv6 is that should an error be introduced, only
hosts that have refreshed their DHCP information since that time are
affected, while a rogue RA will most likely affect all hosts 
immediately.   DHCPv6 also allows different answers to be given to
different hosts.
	</t>
	<t>
One objection to introducing such an option is that DHCPv6 in itself
is not a secure protocol - use of Authenticated DHCP is currently
minimal and thus the (lack of) security is just pushed to another
place, albeit one that site administrators are more familiar and
(rightly or wrongly) comfortable with.
	</t>
	</section>

</section>

<section title="Other considerations">
	<t>
There are other general observations that have been made.
	</t>
	<t>
One is that it would generally be prudent for network monitoring or
management platforms to be able to observe and report on observed RAs,
and whether unintended RAs (possibly from unintended sources) are
present on a network.    Further, it may be useful for individual
hosts to be able to report their address status, e.g. this could be
useful during an IPv6 renumbering phased process as described in
<xref target="RFC4192">RFC4192</xref>.
	</t>
	<t>
The second is how readily a host can recover from bad configuration
information, e.g. considering the '2 hour rule' of Section 5.5.3 of
RFC4862 (though this applies to the prefix lifetime not the router
lifetime).   We should ensure that methods exist for a network
administrator to correct bad configuration information on a link or
subnet, and that OS platforms support these methods.   
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="Conclusions" title="Conclusions">
	<t>
In this text we have described scenarios via which rogue Router Advertisements
(RAs) may appear on a network, and some measures that could be used
to mitigate against these.   
	</t>
	<t>
While SEND perhaps offers the most robust solution, implementations are
not widely available, and the solution is perceived as complex (parallels
can possibly be drawn with Authenticated DHCP in terms of likely deployment).
Adding a new DHCPv6 Default Gateway Option would allow configuration by
DHCP, and be a method that IPv4 administrators are comfortable with
(for better or worse), but
one must recognise that the risk is then shifted elsewhere.
	</t>
	<t>
Further feedback on the solutions is certainly welcome.   In the meantime,
perhaps the
simplest initial step would be for RA snooping to be defined and deployed
for Layer 2 devices, in such a way that can address (shared) wireless 
as well as wired networks.   One draft proposal in this space, RA-Guard,
has recently been published  <xref target="ra-guard"/>.   
	</t>
	<t>
This topic has also highlighted that some DHCPv6 on-link prefix option
may be useful for some scenarios, caused in part by the change of the
'default on-link' rule.   This should be seen as independent of whether
DHCPv6 is extended to add a Default Gateway Option, which is another
open question at this time.
	</t>
	<t>
The material presented here is relevant to the IETF dhc and v6ops working
groups, but the text is labelled as v6ops due to its operational issue
focus.   Should new DHCP features be defined as a result, we assume these
would be presented within the dhc working group.
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
	<t>
There are no extra Security consideration for this document.
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
	<t>
There are no extra IANA consideration for this document.
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
	<t>
Thanks are due to members of the IETF IPv6 Operations and DHCP WGs for their
inputs on this topic, including but not limited to
Iljitsch van Beijnum,
David Malone,
Tony Hain,
Dave Thaler and
Tatuya Jinmei.
	</t>
</section>


</middle>
<back>

<references title="Informative References">

	&rfc3315;
	&rfc3736;
	&rfc3971;
	&rfc4191;
	&rfc4192;
	&rfc4861;
	&rfc4862;

    <reference anchor='ra-guard'>
        <front>
        <title>IPv6 RA-Guard (draft-vandevelde-v6ops-ra-guard-00)</title>
            <author initials='G.' surname='Van de Velde'></author>
            <author initials='E.' surname='Levy-Abegnoli'></author>
            <author initials='C.' surname='Popoviciu'></author>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Mohacsi'></author>


            <date month='November' year='2007' />
       </front>
    </reference>

<!--
    <reference anchor='bellovin'>
        <front>
       <title>Worm Propagation Strategies in an IPv6 Internet (http://www.cs.columbia.edu/~smb/papers/v6worms.pdf)</title>
            <author surname='Bellovin, S. et al'></author>
            <date month=';login:, February' year='2006' />
       </front>
    </reference>
-->

</references>
		<!--		<references title="Informative References">
		</references>
		-->
	</back>
</rfc>
