<?xml version='1.0' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" >
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>



<?rfc-ext xml2rfc-ext-include-references-in-index="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext xml2rfc-ext-justification="always" ?>
<?rfc-ext xml2rfc-ext-sec-no-trailing-dots="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext merge-sequential-page-numbers="merge" ?>


<rfc
	category="std"
	docName="draft-crocker-email-arch-13"
	ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
	<front>
		<title
			abbrev="EMail Architecture">Internet Mail Architecture</title>
		<author
			fullname="Dave Crocker"
			initials="D."
			surname="Crocker">
			<organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>675 Spruce Drive</street>
					<city>Sunnyvale</city>
					<region>CA</region>
					<code>94086</code>
					<country>USA</country>
				</postal>
				<phone>+1.408.246.8253</phone>
				<email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date
			day="15"
			month="May"
			year="2009" />
		<area>Applications</area>
		<workgroup>SMTP</workgroup>
		<keyword>email, e-mail, service, mime, rfc2822, rfc 2822, rfc822, rfc
			822, rfc2821, rfc 2821, rfc821, rfc 821, rfc5321, rfc5322, rfc
			5321, rfc 5322, architecture, mta, mua, msa, mda, admd, user,
			originator, recipient, transfer, message transfer, deliver,
			delivery, relay, header, gateway agent, gateway actor, sieve, dsn,
			mdn, tussle, mhs, Message handling service, message transfer
			agent, message user agent, mail submission agent, mail delivery
			agent, administrative management domain</keyword>

		<abstract>
			<t>Over its thirty-five year history, Internet Mail has changed
				significantly in scale and complexity, as it has become a
				global infrastructure service. These changes have been
				evolutionary, rather than revolutionary, reflecting a strong
				desire to preserve both its installed base and its usefulness.
				To collaborate productively on this large and complex system,
				all participants must work from a common view of it and use a
				common language to describe its components and the
				interactions among them. But the many differences in
				perspective currently make it difficult to know exactly what
				another participant means. To serve as the necessary common
				frame of reference, this document describes the enhanced
				Internet Mail architecture, reflecting the current
			service.</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>

	<middle>

		<section
			title="Introduction">
			<t>Over its thirty-five year history, Internet Mail has changed
				significantly in scale and complexity, as it has become a
				global infrastructure service. These changes have been
				evolutionary, rather than revolutionary, reflecting a strong
				desire to preserve both its installed base and its usefulness.
				Today, Internet Mail is distinguished by many independent
				operators, many different components for providing service to
				users, as well as many different components that transfer
				messages. </t>
			<t>The underlying technical standards for Internet Mail comprise a
				rich array of functional capabilities. These specifications
				form the core:</t>
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>
						<list
							style="symbols">
							<t>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP) <xref
									target="RFC0821" />, <xref
									target="RFC2821" />, <xref
									target="RFC5321" /> moves a message
								through the Internet.</t>
							<t>Internet Mail Format (IMF) <xref
									target="RFC0733" />, <xref
									target="RFC0822" />, <xref
									target="RFC2822" />, <xref
									target="RFC5322" /> defines a message
								object.</t>
							<t>Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) <xref
									target="RFC2045" /> defines an enhancement
								to the message object that permits using
								multi-media attachments.</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>Public collaboration on technical, operations, and policy
				activities of email, including those that respond to the
				challenges of email abuse, has brought a much wider range of
				participants into the technical community. To collaborate
				productively on this large and complex system, all
				participants must work from a common view of it and use a
				common language to describe its components and the
				interactions among them. But the many differences in
				perspective currently make it difficult to know exactly what
				another participant means.  </t>
			<t>It is the need to resolve these differences that motivates this
				document, which describes the realities of the current system.
				Internet Mail is the subject of ongoing technical, operations,
				and policy work, and the discussions often are hindered by
				different models of email service design and different
				meanings for the same terms.  </t>
			<t> To serve as the necessary common frame of reference, this
				document describes the enhanced Internet Mail architecture,
				reflecting the current service. The document focuses on: </t>
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>
						<list
							style="symbols">
							<t>Capturing refinements to the email model </t>
							<t>Clarifying functional roles for the
								architectural components </t>
							<t>Clarifying identity-related issues, across the
								email service </t>
							<t>Defining terminology for architectural
								components and their interactions </t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<section
				title="History">
				<t> The first standardized architecture for networked email
					specified a simple split between the user world, in the
					form of Message User Agents (MUA), and the transfer world,
					in the form of the Message Handling Service (MHS), which
					is composed of Message Transfer Agents (MTA) <xref
						target="RFC1506" />. The MHS accepts a message from
					one User and delivers it to one or more other users,
					creating a virtual MUA-to-MUA exchange environment. <iref
						item="Message User Agent" />
					<iref
						item="UA" />
					<iref
						item="MUA" />
					<iref
						item="User Agent" />
					<iref
						item="MHS" />
					<iref
						item="Message Handling Service" />
					<iref
						item="MTA" />
					<iref
						item="Message Transfer Agent" /></t>
				<t> As shown in <xref
						target="Basic" />, this defines two logical layers of
					interoperability. One is directly between Users. The other
					is among the components along the transfer path. In
					addition, there is interoperability between the layers,
					first when a message is posted from the User to the MHS
					and later when it is delivered from the MHS to the User. </t>
				<t>The operational service has evolved, although core aspects
					of the service, such as mailbox addressing and message
					format style, remain remarkably constant. The original
					distinction between the user level and transfer level
					remains, but with elaborations in each. The term "Internet
					Mail" is used to refer to the entire collection of user
					and transfer components and services. <iref
						item="Internet Mail" /><iref
						item="Mail" /></t>
				<t> For Internet Mail, the term "end-to-end" usually refers to
					a single posting and the set of deliveries that result
					from a single transit of the MHS. A common exception is
					group dialogue that is mediated, through a Mailing List;
					in this case, two postings occur before intended
					Recipients receive an Author's message, as discussed in <xref
						target="Mediator" />. In fact, some uses of email
					consider the entire email service, including Author and
					Recipient, as a subordinate component. For these services,
					"end-to-end" refers to points outside the email service.
					Examples are voicemail over email "<xref
						target="RFC3801" />, EDI over email <xref
						target="RFC1767" /> and facsimile over email <xref
						target="RFC4142" />. <iref
						item="end-to-end" />
					<iref
						item="posting" />
					<iref
						item="delivery" /></t>
				<figure
					align="center"
					anchor="Basic"
					title="Basic Internet Mail Service Model">
					<?rfc needLines="28" ?>
					<artwork
						align="center"
						alt="[ User, MHS, User Service Model ]"
						name="Basic Internet Mail Service Model"
						src="email-arch-fig-svcmodel.png"
						type="image/png"><![CDATA[                               +--------+
            ++================>|  User  |
            ||                 +--------+
            ||                      ^
+--------+  ||          +--------+  .
|  User  +==++=========>|  User  |  .
+---+----+  ||          +--------+  .
    .       ||               ^      .
    .       ||   +--------+  .      .
    .       ++==>|  User  |  .      .
    .            +--------+  .      .
    .                 ^      .      .
    .                 .      .      .
    V                 .      .      .
+---+-----------------+------+------+---+ 
|   .                 .      .      .   |
|   .................>.      .      .   |
|   .                        .      .   |
|   ........................>.      .   |
|   .                               .   |
|   ...............................>.   |
|                                       |
|     Message Handling Service (MHS)    |
+---------------------------------------+

Legend: == lines indicate primary (possibly indirect) transfers or roles
        ... lines indicate supporting transfers or roles]]></artwork>
					<postamble />
				</figure>
				<t>End-to-end Internet Mail exchange is accomplished by using
					a standardized infrastructure with these components and
					characteristics: </t>
				<t>
					<list>
						<t>
							<list
								style="symbols">
								<t>An email object </t>
								<t>Global addressing </t>
								<t>An asynchronous sequence of point-to-point
									transfer mechanisms </t>
								<t>No prior arrangement between MTAs or
									between Authors and Recipients </t>
								<t>No prior arrangement between point-to-point
									transfer services over the open Internet </t>
								<t>No requirement for Author, Originator, or
									Recipients to be online at the same
								time </t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t>The end-to-end portion of the service is the email object,
					called a “message.” Broadly, the message itself
					distinguishes control information, for handling, from the
					Author's content. <iref
						item="message"
						primary="true" /></t>
				<t>A precept to the design of mail over the open Internet is
					permitting user-to-user and MTA-to-MTA interoperability
					without prior, direct arrangement between the independent
					administrative authorities responsible for handling a
					message. All participants rely on having the core services
					universally supported and accessible, either directly or
					through Gateways that act as translators between Internet
					Mail and email environments conforming to other standards.
					Given the importance of spontaneity and serendipity in
					interpersonal communications, not requiring such
					prearrangement between participants is a core benefit of
					Internet Mail and remains a core requirement for it. </t>
				<t> Within localized networks at the edge of the public
					Internet, prior administrative arrangement often is
					required and can include access control, routing
					constraints, and configuration of the information query
					service. Although recipient authentication has usually
					been required for message access since the beginning of
					Internet Mail, in recent years it also has been required
					for message submission. In these cases, a server validates
					the client's identity, whether by explicit security
					protocols or by implicit infrastructure queries to
					identify "local" participants. </t>
			</section>

			<section
				title="The Role of This Architecture">
				<t>An Internet service is an integration of related
					capabilities among two or more participating nodes. The
					capabilities are accomplished across the Internet by one
					or more protocols. What connects a protocol to a service
					is an architecture. An architecture specifies how the
					protocols implement the service by defining the logical
					components of a service and the relationships among them.
					From that logical view, a service defines what is being
					done, an architecture defines where the pieces are (in
					relation to each other) and a protocol defines how
					particular capabilities are performed.</t>

				<t>As such, an architecture will more formally describe a
					service at a relatively high level. A protocol which
					implements some portion of a service will conform to the
					architecture to a greater or lesser extent, depending on
					the pragmatic tradeoffs they make when trying to implement
					the architecture in the context of real-world constraints.
					Failure to precisely follow an architecture is not a
					failure of the protocol, nor is failure to precisely cast
					a protocol a failure of the architecture. Where a protocol
					varies from the architecture, it should of course explain
					the reason for the variance. However, such variance is not
					a mark against a protocol: Happily, the IETF prefers
					running code to architectural purity.</t>

				<t>In this particular case, this architecture attempts to
					define the logical components of Internet email and does
					so post hoc, trying to capture the architectural
					principles that the current email protocols embody. To
					different extents, email protocols will conform to this
					architecture more or less well. Insofar as this
					architecture differs from those protocols, the reasons are
					generally well understood and are required for
					interoperation. The differences are not a sign that
					protocols need to be fixed. However, this architecture is
					a best attempt at a logical model of Internet email, and
					insofar as new protocol development varies from this
					architecture, it is necessary for designers to understand
					those differences and explain them carefully. </t>
			</section>

			<section
				title="Document Conventions">
				<t>References to structured fields of a message use a two-part
					dotted notation. The first part cites the document that
					contains the specification for the field and the second is
					the name of the field. Hence &lt;RFC5322.From&gt;
					is the IMF From: header field in an email content header
					and &lt;RFC5321.MailFrom&gt; is the address in the
					SMTP "Mail From" command. </t>
				<t>When occurring without the IMF (RFC 5322) qualifier, header
					field names are shown with a colon suffix. For example,
					From:. </t>
				<t>References to labels for actors, functions or components
					have the first letter capitalized. </t>
				<t> Also, the key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED",
					"SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
					"RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are
					to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
						target="RFC2119"> [RFC2119] </xref>. </t>
				<t>
					<list>
						<t>
							<list
								style="hanging">
								<t
									hangText="RFC EDITOR:  ">Remove the
									following paragraph before publication.</t>
								<t
									hangText="Discussion venue:  "> Please
									direct discussion about this document to
									the IETF-SMTP mailing list <eref
									target="http://www.imc.org/ietf-smtp" />. <iref
									item="Discussion of document" /></t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section
			anchor="Actors"
			title="Responsible Actor Roles">
			<t> Internet Mail is a highly distributed service, with a variety
				of actors playing different roles. These actors fall into
				three basic types: </t>
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>
						<list
							style="symbols">
							<t>User </t>
							<t>Message Handling Service (MHS)</t>
							<t>ADministrative Management Domain (ADMD)</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>Although related to a technical architecture, the focus on
				actors concerns participant responsibilities, rather than
				functionality of modules. For that reason, the labels used are
				different from those used in classic email architecture
				diagrams. </t>

			<section
				anchor="Users"
				title="User Actors">
				<t>Users are the sources and sinks of messages. Users can be
					people, organizations, or processes. They can have an
					exchange that iterates, and they can expand or contract
					the set of users that participate in a set of exchanges.
					In Internet Mail, there are four types of Users: </t>
				<t>
					<list>
						<t>
							<list
								style="symbols">
								<t>Authors </t>
								<t>Recipients</t>
								<t>Return Handlers</t>
								<t>Mediators </t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t><xref
						target="userrels" /> shows the primary and secondary
					flows of messages among them. </t>

				<figure
					align="center"
					anchor="userrels"
					title="Relationships Among User Actors">

					<?rfc needLines="27" ?>
					<artwork
						align="center"
						name="Relationships Among User Actors"
						src="email-arch-fig-userrel.png"
						type="image/png"><![CDATA[ ++==========++
 ||  Author  ||<..................................<..
 ++=++=++=++=++                                     .
    || || ||     ++===========++                    .
    || || ++====>|| Recipient ||                    .
    || ||        ++=====+=====++                    .
    || ||               .                           .
    || ||               ..........................>.+
    || ||                                           .
    || ||               ...................         .
    || ||               .                 .         . 
    || ||               V                 .         .
    || ||         +-----------+    ++=====+=====++  .
    || ++========>| Mediator  +===>|| Recipient ||  .
    ||            +-----+-----+    ++=====+=====++  .
    ||                  .                 .         . 
    ||                  ..................+.......>.+
    ||                                              .
    ||    ..............+..................         .
    ||    .             .                 .         .
    \/    V             V                 '         .
 +-----------+    +-----------+    ++=====+=====++  .
 | Mediator  +===>| Mediator  +===>|| Recipient ||  .
 +-----+-----+    +-----+-----+    ++=====+=====++  .
       .                .                 .         .
       .................+.................+.......>..

Legend: == lines indicate primary (possibly indirect) transfers or roles
        ... lines indicate supporting transfers or roles]]></artwork>
					<postamble />
				</figure>
				<t>From the user perspective, all message transfer activities
					are performed by a monolithic Message Handling Service
					(MHS), even though the actual service can be provided by
					many independent organizations. Users are customers of
					this unified service. </t>
				<t>Whenever any MHS actor sends information to back to an
					Author or Originator in the sequence of handling a
					message, that actor is a User. </t>
				<section
					anchor="author"
					title="Author">
					<t> The Author is responsible for creating the message,
						its contents, and its list of recipient addresses. The
						MHS transfers the message from the Author and delivers
						it to the Recipients. The MHS has an Originator role (<xref
							target="originator" />) that correlates with the
						Author role. <iref
							item="Author" /><iref
							item="role"
							subitem="Author" />
						<iref
							item="Actor"
							subitem="Author" /></t>
				</section>
				<section
					anchor="recipient"
					title="Recipient">
					<t> The Recipient is a consumer of the delivered message.
						The MHS has a Receiver role (<xref
							target="receiver" />) that correlates with the
						Recipient role. This is labeled Recv in <xref
							target="mhsrels" />. <iref
							item="MHS" /><iref
							item="Recipient" /><iref
							item="role"
							subitem="Recipient" />
						<iref
							item="Actor"
							subitem="Recipient" /></t>
					<t> Any Recipient can close the user communication loop by
						creating and submitting a new message that replies to
						the Author. An example of an automated form of reply
						is the Message Disposition Notification (MDN), which
						informs the Author about the Recipient's handling of
						the message. (See <xref
							target="Data" />.)<iref
							item="Message Disposition Notification" />
						<iref
							item="MDN" /></t>
				</section>
				<section
					title="Return Handler">
					<t>Also called "Bounce Handler", the Return Handler is a
						special form of Recipient tasked with servicing
						notifications that the MHS generates, as it transfers
						or delivers the message. These notices can be about
						failures or completions and are sent to an address
						that is specified by the Originator. This Return
						Handling address (also known as a Return address)
						might have no visible characteristics in common with
						the address of the Author or Originator. </t>
					<iref
						item="Originator"
						primary="true" />
					<iref
						item="MHS" />
					<iref
						item="Return Handler"
						primary="false" />
					<iref
						item="bounce handler" />
					<iref
						item="Actor"
						subitem="Return Handler" />
				</section>
				<section
					anchor="Mediator"
					title="Mediator">
					<t>A Mediator receives, aggregates, reformulates, and
						redistributes messages among Authors and Recipients
						who are the principals in (potentially) protracted
						exchanges. This activity is easily confused with the
						underlying MHS transfer exchanges. However, each
						serves very different purposes and operates in very
						different ways. </t>
					<t>When mail is delivered to the Mediator specified in the
						RFC5321.RcptTo command for the original message, the
						MHS handles it the same way as for any other
						Recipient. In particular, the MHS sees each posting
						and delivery activity between sources and sinks as
						independent; it does not see subsequent re-posting as
						a continuation of a process. Because the Mediator
						originates messages, it can receive replies. Hence,
						when submitting a reformulated message, the Mediator
						is an Author, albeit an author actually serving as an
						agent of one or more other authors. So a Mediator
						really is a full-fledged User. Mediators are
						considered extensively in <xref
							target="Mediators" />. <iref
							item="delivery" /><iref
							item="posting" /><iref
							item="MHS" /></t>
					<t> A Mediator attempts to preserve the original Author's
						information in the message it reformulates but is
						permitted to make meaningful changes to the message
						content or envelope. The MHS sees a new message, but
						users receive a message that they interpret as being
						from, or at least initiated by, the Author of the
						original message. The role of a Mediator is not
						limited to merely connecting other participants; the
						Mediator is responsible for the new message. <iref
							item="MHS" />
						<iref
							item="envelope" />
						<iref
							item="role" /></t>
					<t> A Mediator's role is complex and contingent, for
						example, modifying and adding content or regulating
						which users are allowed to participate and when. The
						common example of this role is a group Mailing List.
						In a more complex use, a sequence of Mediators could
						perform a sequence of formal steps, such as reviewing,
						modifying, and approving a purchase request. <iref
							item="content" /></t>

					<t> A Gateway is a particularly interesting form of
						Mediator. It is a hybrid of User and Relay that
						connects heterogeneous mail services. Its purpose is
						to emulate a Relay. For a detailed discussion, see <xref
							target="mhs-gateway" />. <iref
							item="Gateway" /></t>
				</section>
			</section>

			<section
				anchor="MHS"
				title="Message Handling Service (MHS) Actors">
				<t>The Message Handling Service (MHS) performs a single
					end-to-end transfer on behalf of the Author to reach the
					Recipient addresses specified in the original
					RFC5321.RcptTo commands. Exchanges that are either
					mediated or iterative and protracted, such as those used
					for collaboration over time are handled by the User
					actors, not by the MHS actors. <iref
						item="MHS" /><iref
						item="RcptTo" />
					<iref
						item="Message Handling System" />
					<iref
						item="MHS"
						subitem="Actors" />
					<iref
						item="Actors"
						subitem="MHS" /></t>

				<figure
					align="center"
					anchor="mhsrels"
					title="Relationships Among MHS Actors">
					<preamble><xref
							target="mhsrels" /> shows the relationships among
						transfer participants in Internet Mail. Although it
						shows the Originator (labeled Origin) as distinct from
						the Author and Receiver (labeled Recv) as distinct
						from Recipient,  each pair of roles usually has  the
						same actor. Transfers typically entail one or more
						Relays. However direct delivery from the Originator to
						Receiver is possible. Intra-organization mail services
						usually have only one Relay. <iref
							item="Author" />
						<iref
							item="Originator" />
						<iref
							item="Receiver" />
						<iref
							item="Recipient" />
						<iref
							item="delivery" />
						<iref
							item="transfer" />
						<iref
							item="relay" />
						<iref
							item="" /></preamble>
					<?rfc needLines="26" ?>
					<artwork
						align="center"
						name="Relationships Among MHS Actors"
						src="email-arch-fig-mhsactor.png"
						type="image/png"><![CDATA[  ++==========++                        ++===========++
  ||  Author  ||                        || Recipient ||
  ++====++====++   +--------+           ++===========++
        ||         | Return |                  /\
        ||         +-+------+                  ||
        \/           .    ^                    ||
    +---------+      .    .                +---++---+
    |         |      .    .                |        |
 /--+---------+----------------------------+--------+----\
 |  |         |      .    .      MHS       |        |    |
 |  | Origin  +<......    .................+  Recv  |    |
 |  |         |           ^                |        |    |
 |  +---++----+           .                +--------+    |
 |      ||                .                    /\        |
 |      ||  ..............+..................  ||        |
 |      \/  .             .                 .  ||        |
 |  +-------+-+        +--+------+        +-+--++---+    |
 |  |  Relay  +=======>|  Relay  +=======>|  Relay  |    |
 |  +---------+        +----++---+        +---------+    |
 |                          ||                           |
 |                          ||                           |
 |                          \/                           |
 |                     +---------+                       |
 |                    | Gateway +-->...                  |
 |                     +---------+                       |
 \-------------------------------------------------------/
 
 Legend: == lines indicate primary (possibly indirect) transfers or roles
        ... lines indicate supporting transfers or roles]]></artwork>
					<postamble />
				</figure>
				<section
					anchor="originator"
					title="Originator">
					<t>The Originator ensures that a message is valid for
						posting and then submits it to a Relay. A message is
						valid if it conforms to both Internet Mail standards
						and local operational policies. The Originator can
						simply review the message for conformance and reject
						it if it finds errors, or it can create some or all of
						the necessary information. In effect, the Originator
						is responsible for the functions of the Mail
						Submission Agent. <iref
							item="Originator" />
						<iref
							item="Actor"
							subitem="Originator" />
						<iref
							item="role"
							subitem="Originator" />
						<iref
							item="posting" />
						<iref
							item="MSA" />
						<iref
							item="Mail Submission Agent" /></t>
					<t>The Originator operates with dual allegiance. It serves
						the Author and can be the same entity. But its role in
						assuring validity means that it MUST also represent
						the local operator of the MHS, that is, the local
						ADministrative Management Domain (ADMD). <iref
							item="MHS" />
						<iref
							item="ADMD" /><iref
							item="accountability" />
						<iref
							item="Administrative Management Domain" /></t>
					<t>The Originator also performs any post-submission,
						Author-related administrative tasks associated with
						message transfer and delivery. Notably, these tasks
						pertain to sending error and delivery notices,
						enforcing local policies, and dealing with messages
						from the Author that prove to be problematic for the
						Internet. The Originator is accountable for the
						message content, even when it is not responsible for
						it. The Author creates the message, but the Originator
						handles any transmission issues with it. <iref
							item="content" />
						<iref
							item="transfer" />
						<iref
							item="delivery" />
						<iref
							item="accountable" />
						<iref
							item="responsible" /></t>
				</section>


				<section
					anchor="relay"
					title="Relay">
					<t> The Relay performs MHS-level transfer-service routing
						and store-and-forward, by transmitting or
						retransmitting the message to its Recipients. The
						Relay adds trace information <xref
							target="RFC2505" /> but does not modify the
						envelope information or the message content semantics.
						It can modify message content representation, such as
						changing the form of transfer encoding from binary to
						text, but only as required to meet the capabilities of
						the next hop in the MHS. <iref
							item="envelope" />
						<iref
							item="MHS" />
						<iref
							item="content" /></t>
					<t>A Message Handling System (MHS) network consists of a
						set of Relays. This network is above any underlying
						packet-switching network that might be used and below
						any Gateways or other Mediators. </t>
					<t> In other words, email scenarios can involve three
						distinct architectural layers, each providing its own
						type of data of store-and-forward service: </t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
								<list
									style="symbols">
									<t>User Mediators </t>
									<t>MHS Relays</t>
									<t>Packet Switches </t>
								</list>
							</t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>The bottom layer is the Internet's IP service. The most
						basic email scenarios involve Relays and Switches. </t>
					<t>When a Relay stops attempting to transfer a message, it
						becomes an Author because it must send an error
						message to the Return address. The potential for
						looping is avoided by omitting a Return address from
						this message. </t>
				</section>


				<section
					anchor="mhs-gateway"
					title="Gateway">
					<t>A Gateway is a hybrid of User and Relay that connects
						heterogeneous mail services. Its purpose is to emulate
						a Relay and the closer it comes to this, the better. A
						Gateway operates as a User when it needs the ability
						to modify message content. <iref
							item="content" />
						<iref
							item="Gateway" />
						<iref
							item="Actor"
							subitem="Gateway" /></t>
					<t>Differences between mail services can be as small as
						minor syntax variations, but they usually encompass
						significant, semantic distinctions. One difference
						could be email addresses that are hierarchical and
						machine-specific rather than a flat, global namespace.
						Another difference could be support for text-only
						content or multi-media. Hence the Relay function in a
						Gateway presents a significant design challenge, if
						the resulting performance is to be seen as nearly
						seamless. The challenge is to ensure user-to-user
						functionality between the services, despite
						differences in their syntax and semantics. </t>
					<t>The basic test of Gateway design is whether an Author
						on one side of a Gateway can send a useful message to
						a Recipient on the other side, without requiring
						changes to any components in the Author's or
						Recipient's mail services other than adding the
						Gateway. To each of these otherwise independent
						services, the Gateway appears to be a native
						participant. But the ultimate test of Gateway design
						is whether the Author and Recipient can sustain a
						dialogue. In particular, can a Recipient's MUA
						automatically formulate a valid Reply that will reach
						the Author?</t>
					<iref
						item="MUA" />
				</section>
				<section
					anchor="receiver"
					title="Receiver">
					<t>The Receiver performs final delivery or sends the
						message to an alternate address. It can also perform
						filtering and other policy enforcement immediately
						before or after delivery.<iref
							item="content" />
						<iref
							item="transfer" />
						<iref
							item="delivery" />
						<iref
							item="accountable" />
						<iref
							item="responsible" /></t>
				</section>
			</section>



			<section
				anchor="Administrative"
				title="Administrative Actors">
				<t> Administrative actors can be associated with different
					organizations, each with its own administrative authority.
					This operational independence, coupled with the need for
					interaction between groups, provides the motivation to
					distinguish among ADministrative Management Domains (ADMDs
					). Each ADMD can have vastly different operating policies
					and trust-based decision-making. One obvious example is
					the distinction between mail that is exchanged within an
					organization and mail that is exchanged between
					independent organizations. The rules for handling both
					types of traffic tend to be quite different. That
					difference requires defining the boundaries of each, and
					this requires the ADMD construct. <iref
						item="Administrative Actors" />
					<iref
						item="Actor"
						subitem="Administrative" />
					<iref
						item="ADMD" /></t>
				<t> Operation of Internet Mail services is carried out by
					different providers (or operators). Each can be an
					independent ADMD. This independence of administrative
					decision-making defines boundaries that distinguish
					different portions of the Internet Mail service. A
					department that operates a local Relay, an IT department
					that operates an enterprise Relay, and an ISP that
					operates a public shared email service can be configured
					into many combinations of administrative and operational
					relationships. Each is a distinct ADMD, potentially having
					a complex arrangement of functional components. <xref
						target="ADMD" />  depicts relationships among ADMDs.
					The benefit of the ADMD construct is to facilitate
					discussion about designs, policies and operations that
					need to distinguish between internal issues and external
					ones. <iref
						item="ADMD" /></t>
				<t> The architectural impact of the need for boundaries
					between ADMDs is discussed in <xref
						target="Tussle" />. Most significant is that the
					entities communicating across ADMD boundaries typically
					have the added burden of enforcing organizational policies
					concerning  external communications. At a more mundane
					level, routing mail between ADMDs can be an issue, such as
					needing to route mail between organizational partners over
					specially trusted paths. <iref
						item="ADMD" /></t>
				<t>These are three basic types of ADMDs: </t>
				<t>
					<list>
						<t>
							<list
								style="hanging">
								<t
									hangText="Edge:  "> Independent transfer
									services in networks at the edge of the
									open Internet Mail service. <iref
									item="Edge Actor" />
									<iref
									item="Actor"
									subitem="Edge" /></t>
								<t
									hangText="Consumer:  "> This might be a
									type of Edge service, as is common for
									web-based email access. <iref
									item="Consumer Actor" />
									<iref
									item="Actor"
									subitem="Consumer" /></t>
								<t
									hangText="Transit:  "> Mail Service
									Providers (MSP) that offer value-added
									capabilities for Edge ADMDs, such as
									aggregation and filtering. <iref
									item="Transit Actor" />
									<iref
									item="Actor"
									subitem="Transit" /></t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t>The mail-level transit service is different from
					packet-level switching. End-to-end packet transfers
					usually go through intermediate routers; email exchange
					across the open Internet can be directly between the
					Boundary MTAs of Edge ADMDs. This distinction between
					direct and indirect interaction  highlights the
					differences discussed in <xref
						target="relay" />
					<iref
						item="ADMD" />
					<iref
						item="boundary" />
					<iref
						item="MTA" /><iref
						item="MTA"
						subitem="boundary" /></t>
				<figure
					align="center"
					anchor="ADMD"
					title="Administrative Domain (ADMD) Example">

					<?rfc needLines="11" ?>
					<artwork
						align="center"
						name="ADministrative Management Domain      (ADMD)
						Example"
						src="email-arch-fig-admd.png"
						type="image/png"><![CDATA[+--------+     +---------+     +-------+     +-----------+
|  ADMD1 |<===>|  ADMD2  |<===>| ADMD3 |<===>|   ADMD4   |
|  ----- |     |  -----  |     | ----- |     |   -----   |
|        |     |         |     |       |     |           |
| Author |     |         |     |       |     | Recipient |
|   .    |     |         |     |       |     |     ^     |
|   V    |     |         |     |       |     |     .     |
|  Edge..+....>|.Transit.+....>|-Edge..+....>|..Consumer |
|        |     |         |     |       |     |           |
+--------+     +---------+     +-------+     +-----------+

Legend: == lines indicate primary (possibly indirect) transfers or roles 
        ... lines indicate supporting transfers or roles]]></artwork>
					<postamble />
				</figure>
				<t>Edge networks can use proprietary email standards
					internally. However the distinction between Transit
					network and Edge network transfer services is significant
					because it highlights the need for concern over
					interaction and protection between independent
					administrations. In particular, this distinction calls for
					additional care in assessing the transitions of
					responsibility and the accountability and authorization
					relationships among participants in message transfer. </t>
				<t>The interactions of ADMD components are subject to the
					policies of that domain, which cover concerns such as
					these: </t>
				<t>
					<list>
						<t>
							<list
								style="symbols">
								<t>Reliability </t>
								<t>Access control </t>
								<t>Accountability </t>
								<t>Content evaluation and modification </t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t> These policies can be implemented in different functional
					components, according to the needs of the ADMD. For
					example, see <xref
						target="RFC5068" />. </t>
				<t>Consumer, Edge, and Transit services can be offered by
					providers that operate component services or sets of
					services. Further, it is possible for one ADMD to host
					services for other ADMDs. </t>
				<t>These are common examples of ADMDs:  </t>

				<t>
					<list>
						<t>Enterprise Service Providers: </t>

						<t>
							<list>
								<t>These ADMDs operate the internal data
									and/or the mail services within an
									organization. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
					<list>

						<t>Internet Service Providers (ISP): </t>
						<t>
							<list>
								<t>These ADMDs operate the underlying data
									communication services, which are used by
									one or more Relay and User. ISPs are not
									responsible for performing email
									functions, but they can provide an
									environment in which those functions can
									be performed. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
					<list>
						<t>Mail Service Providers: </t>
						<t>
							<list>
								<t>These ADMDs operate email services, such as
									for consumers or client companies. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t>Practical operational concerns demand that providers be
					involved in administration and enforcement issues. This
					involvement can extend to operators of lower-level packet
					services. </t>
			</section>
		</section>


		<section
			title="Identities">
			<t>The forms of identity used by Internet Mail are: mailbox,
				domain name, message-ID and ENVID. Each must be globally
				unique. </t>
			<section
				title="Mailbox">
				<t>
					<list>
						<t> "A mailbox receives mail. It is a conceptual
							entity that does not necessarily pertain to file
							storage." <xref
								target="RFC5322" />
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t> A mailbox is specified as an Internet Mail address
					&lt;addr&nbhy;spec&gt;. It has two distinct
					parts, separated by an at&nbhy;sign (@). The right
					side is a globally interpreted domain name associated with
					an ADMD. Domain names are discussed in <xref
						target="DNS" />. Formal Internet Mail addressing
					syntax can support source routes, to indicate the path
					through which a message ought to be sent. The use of
					source routes is not common and has been deprecated in <xref
						target="RFC5321" />. </t>
				<t>The portion to the left of the at&nbhy;sign contains a
					string that is globally opaque and is called the
					&lt;local&nbhy;part&gt;. It is to be
					interpreted only by the entity specified by the address's
					domain name. Except as noted later in this section all
					other entities MUST treat the
					&lt;local&nbhy;part&gt; as an uninterpreted
					literal string and MUST preserve all of its original
					details. As such its public distribution is equivalent to
					sending a Web browser "cookie" that is only interpreted
					upon being returned to its creator. <iref
						item="local&nbhy;part"
						primary="true" /></t>
				<t> Some local&nbhy;part values have been standardized,
					for contacting personnel at an organization. These names
					cover common operations and business functions. <xref
						target="RFC2142" /></t>
				<t>It is common for sites to have local structuring
					conventions for the left-hand side
					&lt;local&nbhy;part&gt; of an
					&lt;addr&nbhy;spec&gt;. This permits
					sub-addressing, such as for distinguishing different
					discussion groups used by the same participant. However it
					is worth stressing that these conventions are strictly
					private to the user's organization and MUST NOT be
					interpreted by any domain except the one listed in the
					right side of the &lt;addr&nbhy;spec&gt;. The
					exceptions are those specialized services that conform to
					public, standardized conventions, as noted below. </t>
				<t>Basic email addressing defines the
					&lt;local&nbhy;part&gt; as being globally
					opaque. However there are some uses of email that add a
					standardized, global schema to the value, such as between
					an author and a Gateway. The
					&lt;local&nbhy;part&gt; details remain
					invisible to the public email transfer infrastructure, but
					provide addressing and handling instructions for further
					processing by the Gateway. Standardized examples of these
					conventions are the telephone numbering formats for VPIM <xref
						target="RFC3801" />, such as:<list>
						<t>
							<figure
								align="center">
								<artwork>+16137637582@vpim.example.com</artwork>
							</figure>
						</t>
					</list> and iFax <xref
						target="RFC3192" />, such as: <list>
						<t>
							<figure
								align="center">
								<artwork>FAX=+12027653000/T33S=1387@ifax.example.com</artwork>
							</figure>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section
				title="Scope of Email Address Use">
				<t> Email addresses are being used far beyond their original
					role in email transfer and delivery. In practical terms,
					an email address string has become the common identifier
					for representing online identity. Hence, it is essential
					to be clear about both the nature and role of an identity
					string in a particular context and the entity responsible
					for setting that string. For example, see <xref
						target="identref" />, <xref
						target="mda" /> and <xref
						target="Mediators" />. <iref
						item="delivery" />
					<iref
						item="role" />
				</t>
			</section>

			<section
				anchor="DNS"
				title="Domain Names">
				<t> A domain name is a global reference to an Internet
					resource, such as a host, a service, or a network. A
					domain name usually maps to one or more IP Addresses.
					Conceptually, the name can encompass an organization, a
					collection of machines integrated into a homogeneous
					service, or a single machine. A domain name can be
					administered to refer to an individual user, but this is
					not common practice. The name is structured as a
					hierarchical sequence of labels, separated by dots (.),
					with the top of the hierarchy being on the right end of
					the sequence. There can be many names in the sequence --
					that is, the depth of the hierarchy can be substantial.
					Domain names are defined and operated through the Domain
					Name System (DNS) <xref
						target="RFC1034" />, <xref
						target="RFC1035" />, <xref
						target="RFC2181" />. </t>
				<t>When not part of a mailbox address, a domain name is used
					in Internet Mail to refer to the ADMD or to the host that
					took action upon the message, such as providing the
					administrative scope for a message identifier or
					performing transfer processing. </t>

			</section>

			<section
				title="Message Identifier">
				<t>There are two standardized tags for identifying messages:
					Message-ID: and ENVID. A Message-ID: pertains to content,
					and an ENVID pertains to transfer. </t>
				<section
					anchor="msgid"
					title="Message-ID">
					<t> IMF provides for, at most, a single Message-ID:. The
						Message-ID: for a single message, which is a
						user-level IMF tag, has a variety of uses including
						threading, aiding identification of duplicates, and
						DSN tracking. The Originator assigns the Message-ID:.
						The Recipient's ADMD is the intended consumer of the
						Message-ID:, although any actor along the transfer
						path can use it. <iref
							item="ADMD" /><iref
							item="IMF" /></t>
					<t> Message-ID: MUST be globally unique. Its format is
						similar to that of a mailbox, with two distinct parts,
						separated by an at&nbhy;sign (@). Typically, the
						right side specifies the ADMD or host that assigns the
						identifier, and the left side contains a string that
						is globally opaque and serves to uniquely identify the
						message within the domain referenced on the right
						side. The duration of uniqueness for the message
						identifier is undefined. </t>
					<t> When a message is revised in any way, the decision
						whether to assign a new Message-ID: requires a
						subjective assessment to determine whether the
						editorial content has been changed enough to
						constitute a new message. <xref
							target="RFC5322" /> states that "a message
						identifier pertains to exactly one instantiation of a
						particular message; subsequent revisions to the
						message each receive new message identifiers." Yet
						experience suggests that some flexibility is needed.
						An impossible test is whether the recipient will
						consider the new message to be equivalent to the old
						one. For most components of Internet Mail, there is no
						way to predict a specific recipient's preferences on
						this matter. Both creating and failing to create a new
						Message-ID: have their downsides. <iref
							item="content" /></t>
					<t>Here are some guidelines and examples:  </t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
								<list
									style="symbols">
									<t>If a message is changed only in form,
									such as character encoding, it is
									still the same message. </t>
									<t>If a message has minor additions to the
									content, such as a mailing list tag at
									the beginning of the RFC5322.Subject
									header field, or some mailing list
									administrative information added to
									the end of the primary body-part text,
									it is probably the same message.</t>
									<t>If a message has viruses deleted from
									it, it is probably the same message. </t>
									<t>If a message has offensive words
									deleted from it, some recipients will
									consider it the same message, but some
									will not. </t>
									<t>If a message is translated into a
									different language, some recipients
									will consider it the same message, but
									some will not. </t>
									<t>If a message is included in a digest of
									messages, the digest constitutes a new
									message. </t>
									<t>If a message is forwarded by a
									recipient, what is forwarded is a new
									message. </t>
									<t>If a message is "redirected", such as
									using IMF "Resent-*" header fields,
									some recipients will consider it the
									same message, but some will not. </t>
								</list>
							</t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>The absence of both objective, precise criteria for
						regenerating a Message-ID: and strong protection
						associated with the string means that the presence of
						an ID can permit an assessment that is marginally
						better than a heuristic, but the ID certainly has no
						value on its own for strict formal reference or
						comparison. For that reason, the Message-ID: SHOULD
						NOT be used for any function that has security
						implications. </t>
				</section>

				<section
					anchor="envid"
					title="ENVID">
					<t> The ENVID (envelope identifier) can be used for
						message-tracking purposes (<xref
							target="RFC3885" />, <xref
							target="RFC3464" />) concerning a single
						posting/delivery transfer. The ENVID labels a single
						transit of the MHS by a specific message. So, the
						ENVID is used for one message posting, until that
						message is delivered. A re-posting of the message,
						such as by a Mediator, does not reuse that ENVID, but
						can use a new one, even though the message might
						legitimately retain its original Message-ID:. <iref
							item="envelope" />
						<iref
							item="posting" />
						<iref
							item="MHS" /></t>
					<t>The format of an ENVID is free form. Although its
						creator might choose to impose structure on the
						string, none is imposed by Internet standards. By
						implication, the scope of the string is defined by the
						domain name of the Return Address. </t>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section
			title="Services and Standards">
			<t> The Internet Mail architecture comprises six basic types of
				functionality, which are arranged to support a
				store-and-forward service. As shown in <xref
					target="Protocols" />, each type can have multiple
				instances, some of which represent specialized roles. This
				section considers the activities and relationships among these
				components, and the Internet Mail standards that apply to
				them. </t>
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>Message</t>
							<t>Message User Agent (MUA)<list>
									<t>Author MUA (aMUA)</t>
									<t>Recipient MUA (rMUA)</t>
								</list></t>
							<t>Message Submission Agent (MSA)<list>
									<t>Author-focused MSA functions (aMSA)</t>
									<t>MHS-focused MSA functions (hMSA)</t>
								</list></t>
							<t>Message Transfer Agent (MTA)</t>
							<t>Message Delivery Agent (MDA)<list>
									<t>Recipient-focused MDA functions (rMDA)</t>
									<t>MHS-focused MDA functions (hMDA)</t>
								</list>
							</t>
							<t>Message Store (MS)<list>
									<t>Author MS (aMS) </t>
									<t>Recipient MS (rMS) </t>
								</list></t>

						</list>
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>


			<figure
				align="center"
				anchor="Protocols"
				title="Protocols and Services">
				<preamble>This figure shows function modules and the
					standardized protocols used between them.<iref
						item="MHS" />
				</preamble>
				<?rfc needLines="45" ?>
				<artwork
					align="center"
					name="Protocols and Services"
					src="email-arch-fig-ptclsvc.png"
					type="image/png"><![CDATA[                 ++========++
                 ||        ||                             +-------+
      ...........++  aMUA  ||<............................+ Disp  |
      .          ||        ||                             +-------+
      .          ++=+==+===++                                 ^
      .  local,imap}|  |{smtp,submission                      .
      .  +-----+    |  |                          +--------+  .
      .  | aMS |<---+  | ........................>| Return |  .
      .  +-----+       | .                        +--------+  .
      .                | .    *****************       ^       .
      .          +-----V-.----*------------+  *       .       .
      .      MSA | +-------+  *   +------+ |  *       .       .
      .          | | aMSA  +-(S)->| hMSA | |  *       .       .
      .          | +-------+  *   +--+---+ |  *       .       .
      V          +------------*------+-----+  *       .       .
//==========\\                *      V {smtp  *       .       .
|| MESSAGE  ||                *   +------+    *  //===+===\\  .
||----------||            MHS *   | MTA  |    *  ||  dsn  ||  .
|| ENVELOPE ||                *   +--+---+    *  \\=======//  .
||  smtp    ||                *      V {smtp  *     ^   ^     .
|| CONTENT  ||                *   +------+    *     .   . //==+==\\
||  imf     ||                *   | MTA  +....*......   . || mdn ||
||  mime    ||                *   +--+---+    *         . \\=====//
\\==========//                * smtp}| {local *         .     ^
      .           MDA         *      | {lmtp  *         .     .
      .      +----------------+------V-----+  *         .     .
      .      | +----------+   *   +------+ |  *         .     .
      .      | |          |   *   |      | +..*..........     .
      .      | |   rMDA   |<-(D)--+ hMDA | |  *               .
      .      | |          |   *   |      | |<.*........       .
      .      | +-+------+-+   *   +------+ |  *       .       .
      .      +------+---------*------------+  *       .       .
      .  smtp,local}|         *****************       .       .
      .             V                                 .       .
      .          +-----+                         //===+===\\  .
      .          | rMS |                         || sieve ||  .
      .          +--+--+                         \\=======//  .
      .             |{imap,pop,local                  ^       .
      .             V                                 .       .
      .       ++==========++                          .       .
      .       ||          ||                          .       .
      .......>||   rMUA   ++...........................       .
              ||          ++...................................
              ++==========++
              
Legend: == lines indicate primary (possibly indirect) transfers or roles
        == boxes indicate data objects
        ... lines indicate supporting transfers or roles 
		*** lines indicate aggregated service]]></artwork>
				<postamble />
			</figure>
			<iref
				item="POP" />
			<iref
				item="IMAP" />
			<iref
				item="SMTP" />
			<iref
				item="MIME" />
			<iref
				item="IMF" />
			<iref
				item="LMTP" />
			<iref
				item="MDN" />
			<iref
				item="SIEVE" />
			<iref
				item="MDA" />
			<iref
				item="MUA" />
			<iref
				item="MS" />
			<iref
				item="MSA" />

			<section
				anchor="Data"
				title="Message Data">
				<t> The purpose of the Message Handling System (MHS) is to
					exchange an IMF message object among participants <xref
						target="RFC5322" />. All of its underlying mechanisms
					serve to deliver that message from its Author to its
					Recipients. A message can be explicitly labeled as to its
					nature <xref
						target="RFC3458" />. </t>
				<t> A message comprises a transit-handling envelope and the
					message content. The envelope contains information used by
					the MHS. The content is divided into a structured header
					and the body. The header comprises transit handling trace
					information and structured fields that are part of the
					Author’s message content. The body can be unstructured
					lines of text or a tree of multi-media subordinate
					objects, called “body-parts” or attachments <xref
						target="RFC2045" />, <xref
						target="RFC2046" />, <xref
						target="RFC2047" />, <xref
						target="RFC4288" />, <xref
						target="RFC4289" />, <xref
						target="RFC2049" />. <iref
						item="envelope" />
					<iref
						item="MHS" />
					<iref
						item="content" />
					<iref
						item="body-parts"
						primary="false" />
					<iref
						item="message" />
					<iref
						item="header" /></t>
				<t>In addition, Internet Mail has a few conventions for
					special control data, notably: </t>
				<t>
					<list>
						<t>Delivery Status Notification (DSN): </t>
						<t>
							<list>
								<t> A Delivery Status Notification (DSN) is a
									message that can be generated by the MHS
									(MSA, MTA, or MDA) and sent to the
									RFC5321.MailFrom address. An MDA and MTA
									are shown as sources of DSNs in <xref
									target="Protocols" />, and the
									destination is shown as Returns. DSNs
									provide information about message transit,
									such as transfer errors or successful
									delivery. <xref
									target="RFC3461" />
									<iref
									item="MHS" />
									<iref
									item="delivery" /></t>
							</list>
						</t>
						<t>Message Disposition Notification (MDN):</t>
						<t>
							<list>
								<t> A Message Disposition Notification (MDN)
									is a message that provides information
									about post-delivery processing, such as
									indicating that the message has been
									displayed <xref
									target="RFC3798" /> or the form of
									content that can be supported <xref
									target="RFC3297" />. It can be
									generated by an rMUA and is sent to the
									Disposition-Notification-To addresses. The
									mailbox for this is shown as Disp in <xref
									target="Protocols" />. <iref
									item="content" /></t>
							</list>
						</t>
						<t>Message Filtering (SIEVE): <iref
								item="SIEVE" /></t>
						<t>
							<list>
								<t> Sieve is a scripting language used to
									specify conditions for differential
									handling of mail, typically at the time of
									delivery <xref
									target="RFC5228" />. Scripts can be
									conveyed in a variety of ways, such as a
									MIME part in a message. <xref
									target="Protocols" /> shows a Sieve
									script  going from the rMUA to the MDA.
									However, filtering can be done at many
									different points along the transit path,
									and any one or more of them might be
									subject to Sieve directives, especially
									within a single ADMD. the <xref
									target="Protocols" /> shows only one
									relationship, for (relative) simplicity. <iref
									item="delivery" />
									<iref
									item="ADMD" /></t>
							</list>
						</t>

					</list>
				</t>
				<section
					title="Envelope">
					<t> Internet Mail has a fragmented framework for
						transit-related handling information. Information that
						is used directly by the MHS is called the "envelope."
						It directs handling activities by the transfer service
						and is carried in transfer service commands. That is,
						the envelope exists in the transfer protocol SMTP. <xref
							target="RFC5321" />
						<iref
							item="MHS" />
						<iref
							item="envelope"
							primary="true" />
					</t>
					<t> Trace information, such as  RFC5322.Received, is
						recorded in the message header and is not subsequently
						altered. <xref
							target="RFC5322" /></t>
				</section>
				<section
					anchor="Fields"
					title="Header Fields">
					<t> Header fields are attribute name/value pairs that
						cover an extensible range of email service parameters,
						structured user content, and user transaction
						meta-information. The core set of header fields is
						defined in <xref
							target="RFC5322" />. It is common practice to
						extend this set for different applications. Procedures
						for registering header fields are defined in <xref
							target="RFC3864" />. An extensive set of existing
						header field registrations is provided in <xref
							target="RFC4021" />. </t>
					<t>One danger of placing additional information in header
						fields is that Gateways often alter or delete them. </t>

				</section>
				<section
					title="Body">
					<t> The body of a message might be lines of ASCII text or
						a hierarchically structured  composition of
						multi-media body-part attachments, using MIME. <xref
							target="RFC2045" />, <xref
							target="RFC2046" />, <xref
							target="RFC2047" />, <xref
							target="RFC4288" />, <xref
							target="RFC2049" />
					</t>

				</section>

				<section
					anchor="identref"
					title="Identity References in a Message"
					toc="include">
					<t><xref
							target="layeredid" /> lists the core identifiers
						present in a message during transit. </t>
					<texttable
						align="center"
						anchor="layeredid"
						title="Layered Identities">
						<ttcol>Layer</ttcol>
						<ttcol>Field</ttcol>
						<ttcol>Set By</ttcol>

						<c>Message Body</c>
						<c>MIME Header</c>
						<c>Author</c>

						<c>Message header fields</c>
						<c>From:</c>
						<c>Author</c>

						<c />
						<c>Sender:</c>
						<c>Originator</c>

						<c />
						<c>Reply-To:</c>
						<c>Author</c>

						<c />
						<c>To:, CC:, BCC:</c>
						<c>Author</c>

						<c />
						<c>Message-ID:</c>
						<c>Originator</c>

						<c />
						<c>Received:</c>
						<c>Originator, Relay, Receiver</c>

						<c />
						<c>Return-Path:</c>
						<c>MDA, from MailFrom</c>

						<c />
						<c>Resent-*:</c>
						<c>Mediator</c>

						<c />
						<c>List-Id:</c>
						<c>Mediator</c>

						<c />
						<c>List-*:</c>
						<c>Mediator</c>

						<c>SMTP</c>
						<c>HELO/EHLO</c>
						<c>Latest Relay Client</c>

						<c />
						<c>ENVID</c>
						<c>Originator</c>

						<c />
						<c>MailFrom</c>
						<c>Originator</c>

						<c />
						<c>RcptTo</c>
						<c>Author</c>

						<c />
						<c>ORCPT</c>
						<c>Originator</c>

						<c>IP</c>
						<c>Source Address</c>
						<c>Latest Relay Client</c>
						<postamble> Legend: Layer - The part of the email
							architecture that uses the identifier; Field - The
							protocol construct that contains the identifier;
							Set By - The actor role responsible for specifying
							the identifier value (and this can be different
							from the actor that performs the fill-in function
							for the protocol construct) </postamble>
					</texttable>
					<t>These are the most common address-related fields:   </t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
								<list
									style="hanging">
									<t
									hangText="RFC5322.From:  "> Set by -
									Author </t>
									<t>Names and addresses for authors of the
									message content are listed in the
									From: field.</t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Reply-To:  "> Set by
									- Author </t>
									<t>If a Recipient sends a reply message
									that would otherwise use the
									RFC5322.From field addresses in the
									original message, the addresses in the
									RFC5322.Reply-To field are used
									instead. In other words, this field
									overrides the From: field for
									responses from Recipients. </t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Sender:  "> Set by -
									Originator </t>
									<t>This field specifies the address
									responsible for submitting the message
									to the transfer service. This field
									can be omitted if it contains the same
									address as RFC5322.From. However,
									omitting this field does not mean that
									no Sender is specified; it means that
									that header field is virtual and that
									the address in the From: field MUST be
									used. </t>
									<t>Specification of the notifications
									Return addresses, which are contained
									in RFC5321.MailFrom, is made by the
									RFC5322.Sender. Typically the Return
									address is the same as the Sender
									address. However, some usage scenarios
									require it to be different. </t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC5322.To/.CC:  "> Set by -
									Author </t>
									<t>These fields specify MUA Recipient
									addresses. However, some or all of the
									addresses in these fields might not be
									present in the RFC5321.RcptTo
									commands. </t>
									<t>The distinction between To and CC is
									subjective. Generally, a To addressee
									is considered primary and is expected
									to take action on the message. A CC
									addressee typically receives a copy as
									a courtesy. </t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC5322.BCC:  "> Set by -
									Author </t>
									<t> A copy of the message might be sent to
									an addressee whose participation is
									not to be disclosed to the RFC5322.To
									or RFC5322.CC Recipients and, usually,
									not to the other BCC Recipients. The
									BCC: header field indicates a message
									copy to such a Recipient. Use of this
									field is discussed in <xref
									target="RFC5322" />. </t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC5321.HELO/.EHLO:  "> Set
									by - Originator, MSA, MTA </t>
									<t>Any SMTP client -- including
									Originator, MSA, or MTA -- can specify
									its hosting domain identity for the
									SMTP HELO or EHLO command operation. </t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC3461.ENVID:  "> Set by -
									Originator </t>
									<t>The MSA can specify an opaque string,
									to be included in a DSN, as a means of
									assisting the Return address recipient
									in identifying the message that
									produced a DSN or message tracking. </t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC5321.MailFrom:  "> Set by
									- Originator </t>
									<t>This field is an end-to-end string that
									specifies an email address for
									receiving return control information,
									such as returned messages. The name of
									this field is misleading, because it
									is not required to specify either the
									Author or the actor responsible for
									submitting the message. Rather, the
									actor responsible for submission
									specifies the RFC5321.MailFrom
									address. Ultimately, the simple basis
									for deciding which address needs to be
									in the RFC5321.MailFrom field is to
									determine which address must be
									informed about transfer-level problems
									(and possibly successes.)</t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC5321.RcptTo:  "> Set by -
									Author, Final MTA, MDA.</t>
									<t>This field specifies the MUA mailbox
									address of a Recipient. The string
									might not be visible in the message
									content header. For example, the IMF
									destination address header fields,
									such as RFC5322.To, might specify a
									mailing list mailbox, while the
									RFC5321.RcptTo address specifies a
									member of that list. </t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC5321.ORCPT: "> Set by -
									Originator. </t>
									<t>This is an optional parameter to the
									RCPT command, indicating the original
									address to which the current RCPT TO
									address corresponds, after a mapping
									was performed during transit. An ORCPT
									is the only reliable way to correlate
									a DSN from a multi-recipient message
									transfer with the intended recipient. </t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC5321.Received:  "> Set by
									- Originator, Relay, Mediator, Dest </t>
									<t>This field contains trace information,
									including originating host, Relays,
									Mediators, and MSA host domain names
									and/or IP Addresses. </t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC5321.Return-Path:  "> Set
									by - Originator </t>
									<t>The MDA records the RFC5321.MailFrom
									address into the RFC5321.Return-Path
									field. </t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC2919.List-Id:  "> Set by
									- Mediator Author </t>
									<t> This field provides a globally unique
									mailing list naming framework that is
									independent of particular hosts. <xref
									target="RFC2919" /></t>
									<t>The identifier is in the form of a
									domain name; however, the string
									usually is constructed by combining
									the two parts of an email address. The
									result is rarely a true domain name,
									listed in the domain name service,
									 although it can be.</t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC2369.List-*:  "> Set by -
									Mediator Author </t>
									<t>
									<xref
									target="RFC2369" /> defines a
									collection of message header fields
									for use by mailing lists. In effect,
									they supply list-specific parameters
									for common mailing list user
									operations. The identifiers for these
									operations are for the list itself and
									the user-as-subscriber. <xref
									target="RFC2369" />
									</t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC0791.SourceAddr:  "> Set
									by - The Client SMTP sending host
									immediately preceding the current
									receiving SMTP server. </t>

									<t>
									<xref
									target="RFC0791" /> defines the
									basic unit of data transfer for the
									Internet:  the IP Datagram. It
									contains a Source Address field that
									specifies the IP Address for the host
									(interface) from which the datagram
									was sent. This information is set and
									provided by the IP layer, which makes
									it independent of mail-level
									mechanisms. As such, it is often taken
									to be authoritative, although it is
									possible to provide false addresses. </t>

								</list>
							</t>
						</list>
					</t>

				</section>
			</section>

			<section
				title="User-Level Services">
				<t> Interactions at the user level entail protocol exchanges,
					distinct from those that occur at lower layers of the
					Internet Mail MHS architecture that is, in turn, above the
					Internet Transport layer. Because the motivation for
					email, and much of its use, is for interaction among
					people, the nature and details of these protocol exchanges
					often are determined by the needs of interpersonal and
					group communication. To accommodate the idiosyncratic
					behavior inherent in such communication, only subjective
					guidelines, rather than strict rules, can be offered for
					some aspects of system behavior. Mailing Lists provide
					particularly salient examples. </t>
				<section
					anchor="service-mua"
					title="Message User Agent (MUA)">
					<t>A Message User Agent (MUA) works on behalf of User
						actors and User applications. It is their
						representative within the email service. </t>
					<t>The Author MUA (aMUA) creates a message and performs
						initial submission into the transfer infrastructure
						via a Mail Submission Agent (MSA). It can also perform
						any creation- and posting-time archival in its Message
						Store (aMS). An MUA aMS can organize messages in many
						different ways. A common model uses aggregations,
						called "folders"; in IMAP they are called "mailboxes".
						This model allows a folder for messages under
						development (Drafts), a folder for messages waiting to
						be sent (Queued or Unsent), and a folder for messages
						that have been successfully posted for transfer
						(Sent). But none of these folders is required. For
						example, IMAP allows drafts to be stored in any
						folder; so no Drafts folder needs to be present.</t>
					<t>The Recipient MUA (rMUA) works on behalf of the
						Recipient to process received mail. This processing
						includes generating user-level disposition control
						messages, displaying and disposing of the received
						message, and closing or expanding the user
						communication loop by initiating replies and
						forwarding new messages. </t>

					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
								<list
									style="hanging">
									<t
									hangText="NOTE:  "> Although not shown
									in <xref
									target="Protocols" />, an MUA
									itself can have a distributed
									implementation, such as a "thin" user
									interface module on a constrained
									device such as a smartphone, with most
									of the MUA functionality running
									remotely on a more capable server. An
									example of such an architecture might
									use IMAP <xref
									target="RFC3501" /> for most of
									the interactions between an MUA client
									and an MUA server. An approach for
									such scenarios is defined by <xref
									target="RFC4550" />. <iref
									item="MUA" /></t>
								</list>
							</t>
						</list>
					</t>

					<t> A Mediator is special class of MUA. It performs
						message re-posting, as discussed in <xref
							target="Users" />. <iref
							item="posting" />
						<iref
							item="MUA" /></t>
					<t>An MUA can be automated, on behalf of a user who is not
						present at the time the MUA is active. One example is
						a bulk sending service that has a timed-initiation
						feature. These services are not to be confused with a
						mailing list Mediator, since there is no incoming
						message triggering the activity of the automated
						service. </t>
					<t> A popular and problematic MUA is an automatic
						responder, such as one that sends out-of-office
						notices. This behavior might be confused with that of
						a Mediator, but this MUA is generating a new message.
						Automatic responders can annoy users of mailing lists
						unless they follow <xref
							target="RFC3834" />. </t>
					<t>The identity fields are relevant to a typical MUA: </t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
								<list
									style="hanging">
									<t>RFC5322.From </t>
									<t>RFC5322.Reply-To </t>
									<t>RFC5322.Sender </t>
									<t>RFC5322.To, RFC5322.CC </t>
									<t>RFC5322.BCC </t>

								</list>
							</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section
					title="Message Store (MS)">
					<t> An MUA can employ a long-term Message Store (MS). <xref
							target="Protocols" /> depicts an Author’s MS (aMS)
						and a Recipient’s MS (rMS). An MS can be located on a
						remote server or on the same machine as the MUA. </t>
					<t>An MS acquires messages from an MDA either proactively
						by a local mechanism or even with a standardized
						mechanism such as SMTP(!) or reactively by using POP
						or IMAP. The MUA accesses the MS either by a local
						mechanism or by using POP or IMAP. Using POP for
						individual message accesses, rather than for bulk
						transfer, is relatively rare and inefficient. <iref
							item="POP" /><iref
							item="IMAP" /></t>
				</section>

			</section>

			<section
				title="MHS-Level Services">

				<section
					anchor="msa"
					title="Mail Submission Agent (MSA)">
					<t> A Mail Submission Agent (MSA) accepts the message
						submitted by the aMUA and enforces the policies of the
						hosting ADMD and the requirements of Internet
						standards. An MSA represents an unusual functional
						dichotomy. It represents the interests of the Author
						(aMUA) during message posting, to facilitate posting
						success; it also represents the interests of the MHS.
						In the architecture, these responsibilities are
						modeled, as shown in <xref
							target="Protocols" />, by dividing the MSA into
						two sub-components, aMSA and hMSA, respectively.
						Transfer of responsibility for a single message, from
						an Author's environment to the MHS, is called
						"posting". In <xref
							target="Protocols" /> it is marked as the (S)
						transition, within the MSA. <iref
							item="MUA" />
						<iref
							item="ADMD" />
						<iref
							item="posting"
							primary="true" />
						<iref
							item="MSA" />
						<iref
							item="responsibility" />
						<iref
							item="transition" />
						<iref
							item="aMSA" />
						<iref
							item="hMSA" />
						<iref
							item="posting" /></t>
					<t> The hMSA takes transit responsibility for a message
						that conforms to the relevant Internet standards and
						to local site policies. It rejects messages that are
						not in conformance. The MSA performs final message
						preparation for submission and effects the transfer of
						responsibility to the MHS, via the hMSA. The amount of
						preparation depends upon the local implementations.
						Examples of oMSA tasks include adding header fields,
						such as Date: and Message-ID:, and modifying portions
						of the message from local notations to Internet
						standards, such as expanding an address to its formal
						IMF representation. </t>
					<t>Historically, standards-based MUA/MSA message postings
						have used SMTP. <xref
							target="RFC5321" /> The standard currently
						preferred is SUBMISSION. <xref
							target="RFC4409" /> Although SUBMISSION derives
						from SMTP, it uses a separate TCP port and imposes
						distinct requirements, such as access authorization. </t>
					<t>These identities are relevant to the MSA: </t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
								<list
									style="hanging">
									<t>RFC5321.HELO/.EHLO </t>
									<t>RFC3461.ENVID </t>
									<t>RFC5321.MailFrom </t>
									<t>RFC5321.RcptTo </t>
									<t>RFC5321.Received </t>
									<t>RFC0791.SourceAddr </t>
								</list>
							</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section
					title="Message Transfer Agent (MTA)">
					<t> A Message Transfer Agent (MTA) relays mail for one
						application-level "hop." It is like a packet-switch or
						IP router in that its job is to make routing
						assessments and to move the message closer to the
						Recipients. Of course, email objects are typically
						much larger than the payload of a packet or datagram,
						and the end-to-end latencies are typically much
						higher. Relaying is performed by a sequence of MTAs,
						until the message reaches a destination MDA. Hence, an
						MTA implements both client and server MTA
						functionality; it does not change addresses in the
						envelope or reformulate the editorial content. A
						change in data form, such as to MIME
						Content-Transfer-Encoding, is within the purview of an
						MTA, but removal or replacement of body content is
						not. An MTA also adds trace information. <xref
							target="RFC2505" />
						<iref
							item="envelope" />
						<iref
							item="content" /></t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
								<list
									style="hanging">
									<t
									hangText="NOTE:  "> Within a
									destination ADMD, email relaying
									modules can make a variety of changes
									to the message, prior to delivery. In
									such cases, these modules are acting
									as Gateways, rather than MTAs. </t>
								</list>
							</t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t> Internet Mail uses SMTP <xref
							target="RFC5321" />, <xref
							target="RFC2821" />, <xref
							target="RFC0821" /> primarily to effect
						point-to-point transfers between peer MTAs. Other
						transfer mechanisms include Batch SMTP <xref
							target="RFC2442" /> and ODMR <xref
							target="RFC2645" />. As with most network layer
						mechanisms, the Internet Mail SMTP supports a basic
						level of reliability, by virtue of providing for
						retransmission after a temporary transfer failure.
						Unlike typical packet switches (and Instant Messaging
						services), Internet Mail MTAs are expected to store
						messages in a manner that allows recovery across
						service interruptions, such as host system shutdown.
						The degree of such robustness and persistence by an
						MTA can vary. The base SMTP specification provides a
						framework for protocol response codes. An extensible
						enhancement to this framework is defined in <xref
							target="RFC5248" /></t>
					<t> Although quite basic, the dominant routing mechanism
						for Internet Mail is the DNS MX record <xref
							target="RFC1035" />, which specifies an MTA
						through which the queried domain can be reached. This
						mechanism presumes a public, or at least a common,
						backbone that permits any attached MTA to connect to
						any other. </t>
					<t>MTAs can perform any of these well-established roles: </t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
								<list
									style="hanging">


									<t
									hangText="Boundary MTA: "> An MTA that
									is part of an ADMD and interacts with
									MTAs in other ADMDs. This is also
									called a Border MTA. There can be
									different Boundary MTAs, according to
									the direction of mail-flow. <list
									style="hanging">
									<t
									hangText="Outbound MTA: "> An
									MTA that relays messages to
									other ADMDs. </t>
									<t
									hangText="Inbound MTA: "> An
									MTA that receives inbound SMTP
									messages from MTA  Relays in
									other ADMDs, for example, an
									MTA running on the host listed
									as the target of an MX
									record.</t>
									</list></t>
									<t
									hangText="Final MTA: "> The MTA that
									transfers a message to the MDA. </t>
								</list>
							</t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>These identities are relevant to the MTA: </t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
								<list
									style="hanging">
									<t
									hangText="RFC5321.HELO/.EHLO " />
									<t
									hangText="RFC3461.ENVID " />
									<t
									hangText="RFC5321.MailFrom " />
									<t
									hangText="RFC5321.RcptTo " />
									<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Received:  "> Set by
									- Relay Server </t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC0791.SourceAddr " />
								</list>
							</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section
					anchor="mda"
					title="Mail Delivery Agent (MDA)">
					<t> A transfer of responsibility from the MHS to a
						Recipient's environment (mailbox) is called
						"delivery." In the architecture, as depicted in <xref
							target="Protocols" />, delivery takes place within
						a Mail Delivery Agent (MDA) and is shown as the (D)
						transition from the MHS-oriented MDA component (hMDA)
						to the Recipient-oriented MDA component (rMDA). </t>
					<t>An MDA can provide distinctive, address-based
						functionality, made possible by its detailed
						information about the properties of the destination
						address. This information might also be present
						elsewhere in the Recipient's ADMD, such as at an
						organizational border (Boundary) Relay. However, it is
						required for the MDA, if only because the MDA is
						required to know where to deliver the message. </t>
					<t> Like an MSA, an MDA serves two roles, as depicted in <xref
							target="Protocols" />. Formal transfer of
						responsibility, called "delivery", is effected between
						the two components that embody these roles as shows as
						"(D)" in <xref
							target="Protocols" />. The MHS portion (hMDA)
						primarily functions as a server SMTP engine. A common
						additional role is to re-direct the message to an
						alternative address, as specified by the recipient
						addressee's preferences. The job of the recipient
						portion of the MDA (rMDA) is to perform any delivery
						actions that the Recipient specifies. </t>
					<t>Transfer into the MDA is accomplished by a normal MTA
						transfer mechanism. Transfer from an MDA to an MS uses
						an access protocol, such as POP or IMAP. <iref
							item="POP" /><iref
							item="IMAP" /></t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
								<list
									style="hanging">
									<t
									hangText="NOTE:  "> The term
									"delivery" can refer to the formal,
									MHS function specified here or to the
									first time a message is displayed to a
									Recipient. A simple, practical test
									for whether the MHS-based definition
									applies is whether a DSN can be
									generated. </t>
								</list>
							</t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>These identities are relevant to the MDA: </t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
								<list
									style="hanging">
									<t
									hangText="RFC5321.Return-Path:  "> Set
									by - Author Originator or Mediator
									Originator </t>
									<t>The MDA records the RFC5321.MailFrom
									address into the RFC5321.Return-Path
									field. </t>
									<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Received:  "> Set by
									- MDA server </t>
									<t>An MDA can record a Received: header
									field to indicate trace information,
									including source host and receiving
									host domain names and/or IP
									Addresses. </t>
								</list>
							</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
			</section>


			<section
				title="Transition Modes">
				<t> From the origination site to the point of delivery,
					Internet Mail usually follows a "push" model. That is, the
					actor that holds the message initiates transfer to the
					next venue, typically with SMTP <xref
						target="RFC5321" /> or LMTP <xref
						target="RFC2033" />. With a "pull" model, the actor
					that holds the message waits for the actor in the next
					venue to initiate a request for transfer. Standardized
					mechanisms for pull-based MHS transfer are ETRN <xref
						target="RFC1985" /> and ODMR <xref
						target="RFC2645" />. <iref
						item="posting" />
					<iref
						item="author" /><iref
						item="delivery" />
					<iref
						item="recipient" /><iref
						item="push" /><iref
						item="pull" />
					<iref
						item="SMTP" /><iref
						item="LMTP" /><iref
						item="ODMR" />
					<iref
						item="ETRN" /></t>
				<t> After delivery, the Recipient's MUA (or MS) can gain
					access by having the message pushed to it or by having the
					receiver of access pull the message, such as by using POP <xref
						target="RFC1939" /> and IMAP <xref
						target="RFC3501" />. <iref
						item="POP" /><iref
						item="IMAP" /></t>

			</section>
			<section
				title="Implementation and Operation">
				<t>A discussion of any interesting system architecture often
					bogs down when architecture and implementation are
					confused. An architecture defines the conceptual functions
					of a service, divided into discrete conceptual modules. An
					implementation of that architecture can combine or
					separate architectural components, as needed for a
					particular operational environment. For example, a
					software system that primarily performs message relaying
					 is an MTA, yet it might also include MDA functionality.
					That same MTA system might be able to interface with
					non-Internet email services and thus perform both as an
					MTA and as a Gateway. </t>
				<t> Similarly, implemented modules might be configured to form
					elaborations of the architecture. An interesting example
					is a distributed MS. One portion might be a remote server
					and another might be local to the MUA. As discussed in <xref
						target="RFC1733" />, there are three operational
					relationships among such MSs: </t>
				<t>
					<list>
						<t>
							<list
								style="hanging">
								<t
									hangText="Online:  "> The MS is remote,
									and messages are accessible only when the
									MUA is attached to the MS so that the MUA
									will re-fetch all or part of a message,
									from one session to the next. </t>
								<t
									hangText="Offline:  "> The MS is local to
									the user, and messages are completely
									moved from any remote store, rather than
									(also) being retained there. </t>
								<t
									hangText="Disconnected:  "> An rMS and a
									uMS are kept synchronized, for all or part
									of their contents, while they are
									connected. When they are disconnected,
									mail can arrive at the rMS and the user
									can make changes to the uMS. The two
									stores are re-synchronized when they are
									reconnected. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>



		<section
			anchor="Mediators"
			title="Mediators">
			<t>Basic message transfer from Author to Recipients is
				accomplished by using an asynchronous store-and-forward
				communication infrastructure in a sequence of independent
				transmissions through some number of MTAs. A very different
				task is a sequence of postings and deliveries through
				Mediators. A Mediator forwards a message, through a re-posting
				process. The Mediator shares some functionality with basic MTA
				relaying, but has greater flexibility in both addressing and
				content than is available to MTAs. </t>
			<t>This is the core set of message information that is commonly
				set by all types of Mediators:  </t>
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>
						<list
							style="hanging">
							<t
								hangText="RFC5321.HELO/.EHLO:  "> Set by -
								Mediator Originator </t>
							<t
								hangText="RFC3461.ENVID:  "> Set by - Mediator
								Originator </t>
							<t
								hangText="RFC5321.RcptTo:  "> Set by -
								Mediator Author </t>
							<t
								hangText="RFC5321.Received:  "> Set by -
								Mediator Dest </t>
							<t>The Mediator can record received information,
								to indicate the delivery to the original
								address and submission to the alias address.
								The trace of Received: header fields can
								include everything from original posting,
								through relaying, to final delivery. </t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>

			<t>The aspect of a Mediator that distinguishes it from any other
				MUA creating a message is that a Mediator preserves the
				integrity and tone of the original message, including the
				essential aspects of its origination information. The Mediator
				might also add commentary.</t>
			<t>Examples of MUA messages that a Mediator does not create
				include: </t>
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>New message that forwards an existing message: <list>
							<t>Although this action provides a basic template
								for a class of Mediators, its typical
								occurrence is not, itself, an example of a
								Mediator. The new message is viewed as being
								from the actor that is doing the forwarding,
								rather than from the original Author. </t>
							<t> A new message encapsulates the original
								message and is seen as from the new
								Originator. This Mediator Originator might add
								commentary and can modify the original message
								content. Because the forwarded message is a
								component of the message sent by the new
								Originator, the new message creates a new
								dialogue. However the final Recipient still
								sees the contained message as from the
								original Author. </t>
						</list></t>

					<t>Reply:  <list>
							<t> When a Recipient responds to the Author of a
								message, the new message is not typically
								viewed as a forwarding of the original. Its
								focus is the new content, although it might
								contain all or part of the material from the
								original message. The earlier material is
								merely contextual and secondary. This includes
								automated replies, such as vacation
								out-of-office notices, as discussed in <xref
									target="service-mua" />. </t>
						</list></t>


					<t>Annotation:  <list>
							<t>The integrity of the original message is
								usually preserved, but one or more comments
								about the message are added in a manner that
								distinguishes commentary from original text.
								The primary purpose of the new message is to
								provide commentary from a new Author, similar
								to a Reply. </t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>

			<t>The remainder of this section describes common examples of
				Mediators. </t>

			<section
				title="Alias">
				<t>One function of an MDA is to determine the internal
					location of a mailbox in order to perform delivery. An
					Alias is a simple re-addressing facility that provides one
					or more new Internet Mail addresses, rather than a single,
					internal one; the message continues through the transfer
					service, for delivery to one or more alternate addresses.
					Although typically implemented as part of an MDA, this
					facility is a Recipient function. It resubmits the
					message, although all handling information except the
					envelope recipient (rfc5321.RcptTo) address is retained.
					In particular, the Return address (rfc5321.MailFrom) is
					unchanged. <iref
						item="delivery" />
					<iref
						item="envelope" />
					<iref
						item="mailbox" />
					<iref
						item="MDA" />
					<iref
						item="Recipient" />
					<iref
						item="Mail From" />
					<iref
						item="Return address" /></t>
				<t>What is distinctive about this forwarding mechanism is how
					closely it resembles normal MTA store-and-forward
					relaying. Its only significant difference is that it
					changes the RFC5321.RcptTo value. Because this change is
					so small, aliasing can be viewed as a part of the
					lower-level mail relaying activity. However, this small
					change has a large semantic impact: The designated
					recipient has chosen a new recipient. </t>
				<t>
					<list>
						<t>
							<list
								style="hanging">
								<t
									hangText="NOTE:  ">When the replacement
									list includes more than one address, the
									alias is increasingly likely to have
									delivery problems. Any problem reports go
									to the original Author, not the
									administrator of the alias entry. This
									makes it more difficult to resolve the
									problem, because the original Author has
									no knowledge of the Alias mechanism.<iref
									item="ADMD" /></t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t>Including the core set of message information listed at the
					beginning of this section, Alias typically changes: <iref
						item="posting" /><iref
						item="envelope" />
				</t>
				<t>
					<list>
						<t>
							<list
								style="hanging">

								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.To/.CC/.BCC:  "> Set by
									- Author </t>
								<t>These fields retain their original
									addresses. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5321.MailFrom:  "> Set by -
									Author </t>
								<t> The benefit of retaining the original
									MailFrom value is to ensure that an actor
									related to the originating ADMD knows
									there has been a delivery problem. On the
									other hand, the responsibility for
									handling problems, when transiting from
									the original recipient mailbox to the
									alias mailbox usually lies with that
									original Recipient, because the Alias
									mechanism is strictly under that
									Recipient's control. Retaining the
									original MailFrom address prevents this.<iref
									item="delivery" /></t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>

			</section>

			<section
				title="ReSender">
				<t> Also called the ReDirector, the ReSender's actions differ
					from forwarding because the Mediator "splices" a message's
					addressing information to connect the Author of the
					original message with the Recipient of the new message.
					This connection permits them to have direct exchange,
					using their normal MUA Reply functions, while also
					recording full reference information about the Recipient
					who served as a Mediator. Hence, the new Recipient sees
					the message as being from the original Author, even if the
					Mediator adds commentary. </t>
				<t>Including the core set of message information listed at the
					beginning of this section, these identities are relevant
					to a resent message: </t>
				<t>
					<list>
						<t>
							<list
								style="hanging">
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.From:  "> Set by -
									original Author </t>
								<t>Names and addresses for the original Author
									 of the message content are retained. The
									free-form (display-name) portion of the
									address might be modified to provide
									informal reference to the ReSender. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Reply-To:  "> Set by -
									original Author </t>
								<t>If this field is present in the original
									message, it is retained in the resent
									message. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Sender:  "> Set by -
									Author's Originator or Mediator
									Originator. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.To/.CC/.BCC:  "> Set by
									- original Author </t>
								<t>These fields specify the original message
									Recipients. </t>

								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Resent-From: "> Set by -
									Mediator Author </t>
								<t>This address is of the original Recipient
									who is redirecting the message. Otherwise,
									the same rules apply to the Resent-From:
									field as to an original RFC5322.From
									field. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Resent-Sender:  "> Set
									by - Mediator Originator </t>
								<t>The address of the actor responsible for
									resubmitting the message. As with
									RFC5322.Sender, this field can be omitted
									when it contains the same address as
									RFC5322.Resent-From. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Resent-To/-CC/-BCC:  ">
									Set by: Mediator Author </t>
								<t>The addresses of the new Recipients who are
									now able to reply to the original author. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5321.MailFrom:  "> Set by -
									Mediator Originator </t>
								<t>The actor responsible for resubmission
									(RFC5322.Resent-Sender) is also
									responsible for specifying the new
									MailFrom address. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>

			<section
				title="Mailing Lists">
				<t>A Mailing List receives messages as an explicit addressee
					and then re-posts them to a list of subscribed members.
					The Mailing List performs a task that can be viewed as an
					elaboration of the ReSender. In addition to sending the
					new message to a potentially large number of new
					Recipients, the Mailing List can modify content, for
					example, by deleting attachments, converting the format,
					and adding list-specific comments. Mailing Lists also
					archive messages posted by Authors. Still the message
					retains characteristics of being from the original Author. </t>
				<t>Including the core set of message information listed at the
					beginning of this section, these identities are relevant
					to a mailing list processor, when submitting a message: </t>
				<t>
					<list>
						<t>
							<list
								style="hanging">
								<t
									hangText="RFC2919.List-Id:  "> Set by -
									Mediator Author </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC2369.List-*:  "> Set by -
									Mediator Author </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.From:  "> Set by -
									original Author </t>
								<t>Names and email addresses for the original
									Author of the message content are
									retained. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Reply-To:  "> Set by –
									Mediator or original Author  </t>
								<t>Although problematic, it is common for a
									Mailing List to assign its own addresses
									to the Reply-To: header field of messages
									that it posts. This assignment is intended
									to ensure that replies go to all list
									members, rather than to only the original
									Author. As a User actor, a Mailing List is
									the Author of the new message and can
									legitimately set the Reply-To: value. As a
									Mediator attempting to represent the
									message on behalf of its original Author,
									creating or modifying a Reply-To: field
									can be viewed as violating that Author's
									intent. When the Reply-To is modified in
									this way, a reply that is meant only for
									the original Author will instead go to the
									entire list. When the Mailing List does
									not set the field, a reply meant for the
									entire list can instead go only to the
									original Author. At best, either choice is
									a matter of group culture for the
									particular list.</t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Sender:  "> Set by -
									Author Originator or Mediator Originator </t>
								<t>This field usually specifies the address of
									the actor responsible for Mailing List
									operations. Mailing Lists that operate in
									a manner similar to a simple MTA Relay
									preserve as much of the original handling
									information as possible, including the
									original RFC5322.Sender field. (Note that
									this mode of operation causes the Mailing
									List to behave much like an Alias, with a
									possible difference in number of new
									addressees.) </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.To/.CC:  "> Set by -
									original Author </t>
								<t>These fields usually contain the original
									list of Recipient addresses. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5321.MailFrom:  "> Set by -
									Mediator Originator </t>
								<t>Because a Mailing List can modify the
									content of a message in any way, it is
									responsible for that content; that is, it
									is an Author. As such, the Return Address
									is specified by the Mailing List. Although
									it is plausible for the Mailing List to
									re-use the Return Address employed by the
									original Originator, notifications sent to
									that address after a message has been
									processed by a Mailing List could be
									problematic. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>

			<section
				title="Gateways">
				<t>A Gateway performs the basic routing and transfer work of
					message relaying, but it also is permitted to modify
					content, structure, address, or attributes as needed to
					send the message into a messaging environment that
					operates under different standards or potentially
					incompatible policies. When a Gateway connects two
					differing messaging services, its role is easy to identify
					and understand. When it connects environments that follow
					similar technical standards, but significantly different
					administrative policies, it is easy to view a Gateway as
					merely an MTA. </t>
				<t> The critical distinction between an MTA and a Gateway is
					that a Gateway can make substantive changes to a message
					to map between the standards. In virtually all cases, this
					mapping results in some degree of semantic loss. The
					challenge of Gateway design is to minimize this loss.
					Standardized gateways to Internet Mail are facsimile <xref
						target="RFC4143" />, voicemail <xref
						target="RFC3801" />, and MMS <xref
						target="RFC4356" /></t>
				<t>A Gateway can set any identity field available to an MUA.
					Including the core set of message information listed at
					the beginning of this section, these identities are
					typically relevant to Gateways: </t>
				<t>
					<list>
						<t>
							<list
								style="hanging">
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.From:  "> Set by -
									original Author </t>
								<t>Names and addresses for the original Author
									of the message content are retained. As
									for all original addressing information in
									the message, the Gateway can translate
									addresses as required to continue to be
									useful in the target environment. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Reply-To:  "> Set by -
									original Author </t>
								<t>The Gateway SHOULD retain this information,
									if it is present. The ability to perform a
									successful reply by a Recipient is a
									typical test of Gateway functionality. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.Sender:  "> Set by -
									Author Originator or Mediator Originator </t>
								<t>This field can retain the original value or
									can be set to a new address. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5322.To/.CC/.BCC:  "> Set by
									- original Recipient </t>
								<t>These fields usually retain their original
									addresses. </t>
								<t
									hangText="RFC5321.MailFrom:  "> Set by -
									Author Originator or Mediator Originator </t>
								<t>The actor responsible for handling the
									message can specify a new address to
									receive handling notices. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>

			<section
				title="Boundary Filter">
				<t>To enforce security boundaries, organizations can subject
					messages to analysis, for conformance with its safety
					policies. An example is detection of content classed as
					spam or a virus. A filter might alter the content, to
					render it safe, such as by removing content deemed
					unacceptable. Typically, these actions add content to the
					message that records the actions. </t>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section
			title="Considerations">

			<section
				title="Security Considerations">
				<t> This document describes the existing Internet Mail
					architecture. It introduces no new capabilities. The
					security considerations of this deployed architecture are
					documented extensively in the technical specifications
					referenced by this document. These specifications cover
					classic security topics, such as authentication and
					privacy. For example, email transfer protocols can use
					standardized mechanisms for operation over authenticated
					and/or encrypted links, and message content has similar
					protection standards available. Examples of such
					mechanisms include SMTP-TLS <xref
						target="RFC3207" />, SMTP-Auth <xref
						target="RFC4954" />, OpenPGP <xref
						target="RFC4880" />, and S/MIME <xref
						target="RFC3851" />. </t>
				<t>The core of the Internet Mail architecture does not impose
					any security requirements or functions on the end-to-end
					or hop-by-hop components. For example, it does not require
					participant authentication and does not attempt to prevent
					data disclosure. </t>
				<t> Particular message attributes might expose specific
					security considerations. For example, the blind carbon
					copy feature of the architecture invites disclosure
					concerns, as discussed in section 7.2 of <xref
						target="RFC5321" /> and section 5 of <xref
						target="RFC5322" />. Transport of text or non-text
					content in this architecture has security considerations
					that are discussed in <xref
						target="RFC5322" />, <xref
						target="RFC2045" />, <xref
						target="RFC2046" />, and <xref
						target="RFC4288" /> as well as the security
					considerations present in the IANA media types registry
					for the respective types. </t>
				<t> Agents that automatically respond to email raise
					significant security considerations, as discussed in <xref
						target="RFC3834" />. Gateway behaviors affect
					end-to-end security services, as discussed in <xref
						target="RFC2480" />. Security considerations for
					boundary filters are discussed in <xref
						target="RFC5228" />. </t>
				<t> See section 7.1 of <xref
						target="RFC5321" /> for a discussion of the topic of
					origination validation. As mentioned in <xref
						target="identref" />, it is common practice for
					components of this architecture to use the <xref
						target="RFC0791" />.SourceAddr to make policy
					decisions <xref
						target="RFC2505" />, although the address can be
					"spoofed". It is possible to use it without authorization.
					SMTP and Submission authentication <xref
						target="RFC4954" />, <xref
						target="RFC4409" /> provide more secure alternatives. </t>
				<t> The discussion of trust boundaries, ADMDs, actors, roles,
					and responsibilities in this document highlights the
					relevance and potential complexity of security factors for
					operation of an Internet mail service. The core design of
					Internet Mail to encourage open and casual exchange of
					messages has met with scaling challenges, as the
					population of email participants has grown to include
					those with problematic practices. For example, spam, as
					defined in <xref
						target="RFC2505" />, is a by-product of this
					architecture. A number of standards track or BCP documents
					on the subject have been issued. <xref
						target="RFC2505" />, <xref
						target="RFC5068" />, <xref
						target="RFC3685" />
				</t>
			</section>


			<section
				title="IANA Considerations">
				<t>This document has no actions for IANA. </t>
			</section>


			<section
				title="Internationalization">
				<t>The core Internet email standards are based on the use of
					US-ASCII. That is SMTP <xref
						target="RFC5321" /> and IMF <xref
						target="RFC5322" />, as well as their predecessors.
					They describe the transport and composition of messages as
					composed strictly of US-ASCII 7-bit encoded characters.
					The standards have been incrementally enhanced to allow
					for characters outside of this limited set, while
					retaining mechanisms for backwards-compatibility. Specifically:<list
						style="symbols">
						<t>The MIME specifications <xref
								target="RFC2045" />, <xref
								target="RFC2046" />, <xref
								target="RFC2047" /> and <xref
								target="RFC2049" /> allow for the use of coded
							character sets and character encoding schemes
							("charsets" in MIME terminology) other than
							US-ASCII. MIME's <xref
								target="RFC2046" /> allows the textual content
							of a message to have a label affixed that
							specifies the charset used in that content.
							Equally MIME's <xref
								target="RFC2047" /> allows the textual content
							of certain header fields in a message to be
							similarly labeled. However, since messages might
							be transported over SMTP implementations only
							capable of transporting 7-bit encoded characters,
							MIME's <xref
								target="RFC2045" /> also provides for "content
							transfer encoding" so that characters of other
							charsets can be re-encoded as an overlay to
							US-ASCII. </t>
						<t>MIME's <xref
								target="RFC2045" /> allows for the textual
							content of a message to be in an 8-bit character
							encoding scheme. In order to transport these
							without re-encoding them, the SMTP specification
							supports an option <xref
								target="RFC1652" /> that permits the transport
							of such textual content. However, the <xref
								target="RFC1652" /> option does not address
							the use of 8-bit content in message header fields,
							and therefore <xref
								target="RFC2047" /> encoding is still required
							for those. </t>
						<t>A series of experimental protocols on Email Address
							Internationalization (EAI) have been released that
							extend SMTP and IMF to allow for 8-bit encoded
							characters to appear in addresses and other
							information throughout the header fields of
							messages. <xref
								target="RFC5335" /> specifies the format of
							such message header fields (which encode the
							characters in UTF-8), and <xref
								target="RFC5336" /> specifies an SMTP option
							for the transport of these messages. </t>
						<t>MIME's <xref
								target="RFC2045" /> and <xref
								target="RFC2046" /> allow for the transport of
							true multimedia material, which has obvious
							applicability to internationalization.</t>
						<t>The formats for delivery status notifications (DSNs&mdash;<xref
								target="RFC3462" />, <xref
								target="RFC3463" />, <xref
								target="RFC3464" />) and message disposition
							notifications (MDNs&mdash;<xref
								target="RFC3798" />) include both a structured
							and unstructured representation of the
							notification. In the event that the unstructured
							representation is in the wrong language or is
							otherwise unsuitable for use, this allows an MUA
							to construct its own appropriately localized
							representation of notification for display to the
							user. </t>
						<t>POP and IMAP do not introduce internationalization
							issues. <iref
								item="POP" /><iref
								item="IMAP" /><iref
								item="MIME" /><iref
								item="EAI" /><iref
								item="IMF" /><iref
								item="SMTP" /><iref
								item="charset" /><iref
								item="7-bit" /><iref
								item="encoding" /><iref
								item="DSN" /><iref
								item="MDN" /></t>
					</list></t>
				<t>Hence, the use of UTF-8 is fully established in existing
					Internet mail. However support for long-standing encoding
					forms is retained and is still used. </t>

			</section>
		</section>
	</middle>


	<back>

		<references
			title="Normative">
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2119">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to
						Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
					<author
						fullname="Scott Bradner"
						initials="S."
						surname="Bradner">
						<organization>Harvard University</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>1350 Mass. Ave. </street>
                        <street>Cambridge</street>
                        <street>MA 02138</street>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
                     <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="March"
						year="1997" />
					<area>General</area>
					<keyword>keyword</keyword>
					<abstract>
						<t> In many standards track documents several words
							are used to signify the requirements in the
							specification. These words are often capitalized.
							This document defines these words as they should
							be interpreted in IETF documents. Authors who
							follow these guidelines should incorporate this
							phrase near the beginning of their document: </t>
						<t>
							<list>
								<t> The key words &quot;MUST&quot;,
									&quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
									&quot;REQUIRED&quot;,
									&quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL
									NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;,
									&quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;,
									&quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;,
									&quot;MAY&quot;, and
									&quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this
									document are to be interpreted as
									described in RFC 2119. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
						<t> Note that the force of these words is modified by
							the requirement level of the document in which
							they are used. </t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="BCP"
					value="14" />
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2119" />
				<format
					octets="14486"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"
					type="HTML" />
				<format
					octets="5661"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"
					type="XML" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC1034">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="Domain Concepts and Facilities">Domain names -
						concepts and facilities</title>
					<author
						fullname="P. Mockapetris"
						initials="P."
						surname="Mockapetris">
						<organization>Information Sciences Institute
						(ISI)</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						day="1"
						month="November"
						year="1987" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="STD"
					value="13" />
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="1034" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC1939">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="POP3">Post Office Protocol - Version 3</title>
					<author
						fullname="John G. Myers"
						initials="J.G."
						surname="Myers">
						<organization>Carnegie-Mellon University</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>5000 Forbes Ave</street>
                        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <code>15213</code>
                        <country>US</country>
                     </postal>
                     <email>jgm+@cmu.edu</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Marshall T. Rose"
						initials="M.T."
						surname="Rose">
						<organization>Dover Beach Consulting, Inc. </organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>420 Whisman Court</street>
                        <city>Mountain View</city>
                        <region>CA</region>
                        <code>94043-2186</code>
                        <country>US</country>
                     </postal>
                     <email>mrose@dbc.mtview.ca.us</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="May"
						year="1996" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="STD"
					value="53" />
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="1939" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC1035">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="Domain Implementation and Specification"
						>Domain names - implementation and specification</title>
					<author
						fullname="P. Mockapetris"
						initials="P."
						surname="Mockapetris">
						<organization>USC/ISI</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
                        <city>Marina del Rey</city>
                        <region>CA</region>
                        <code>90291</code>
                        <country>US</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 213 822 1511</phone>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						day="1"
						month="November"
						year="1987" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="STD"
					value="13" />
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="1035" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2045">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="Internet Message Bodies">Multipurpose Internet
						Mail Extensions (MIME) Part One: Format of Internet
						Message Bodies</title>
					<author
						fullname="Ned Freed"
						initials="N."
						surname="Freed">
						<organization>Innosoft International, Inc. </organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>1050 East Garvey Avenue South</street>
                        <city>West Covina</city>
                        <region>CA</region>
                        <code>91790</code>
                        <country>US</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 818 919 3600</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 818 919 3614</facsimile>
                     <email>ned@innosoft.com</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Nathaniel S. Borenstein"
						initials="N.S."
						surname="Borenstein">
						<organization>First Virtual Holdings</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>25 Washington Avenue</street>
                        <city>Morristown</city>
                        <region>NJ</region>
                        <code>07960</code>
                        <country>US</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 201 540 8967</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 201 993 3032</facsimile>
                     <email>nsb@nsb.fv.com</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="November"
						year="1996" />
					<abstract>
						<t>STD 11, RFC 822, defines a message representation
							protocol specifying considerable detail about
							US-ASCII message header fields, and leaves the
							message content, or message body, as flat US-ASCII
							text. This set of documents, collectively called
							the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions, or
							MIME, redefines the format of messages to allow
							for </t>
						<t>(1) textual message bodies in character sets other
							than US-ASCII,</t>
						<t>(2) an extensible set of different formats for
							non-textual message bodies,</t>
						<t>(3) multi-part message bodies, and</t>
						<t>(4) textual header information in character sets
							other than US-ASCII. </t>
						<t>These documents are based on earlier work
							documented in RFC 934, STD 11, and RFC 1049, but
							extends and revises them. Because RFC 822 said so
							little about message bodies, these documents are
							largely orthogonal to (rather than a revision of)
							RFC 822. </t>
						<t>This initial document specifies the various header
							fields used to describe the structure of MIME
							messages. The second document, RFC 2046, defines
							the general structure of the MIME media typing
							system and defines an initial set of media types.
							The third document, RFC 2047, describes extensions
							to RFC 822 to allow non-US-ASCII text data in
							Internet Mail header fields. The fourth document,
							RFC 2048, specifies various IANA registration
							procedures for MIME-related facilities. The fifth
							and final document, RFC 2049, describes MIME
							conformance criteria as well as providing some
							illustrative examples of MIME message formats,
							acknowledgements, and the bibliography. </t>
						<t>These documents are revisions of RFCs 1521, 1522,
							and 1590, which themselves were revisions of RFCs
							1341 and 1342. An appendix in RFC 2049 describes
							differences and changes from previous versions.
						</t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2045" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2046">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="Media Types">Multipurpose Internet Mail
						Extensions (MIME) Part Two: Media Types</title>
					<author
						fullname="Ned Freed"
						initials="N."
						surname="Freed">
						<organization>Innosoft International, Inc. </organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>1050 East Garvey Avenue South</street>
                        <city>West Covina</city>
                        <region>CA</region>
                        <code>91790</code>
                        <country>US</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 818 919 3600</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 818 919 3614</facsimile>
                     <email>ned@innosoft.com</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Nathaniel S. Borenstein"
						initials="N."
						surname="Borenstein">
						<organization>First Virtual Holdings</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>25 Washington Avenue</street>
                        <city>Morristown</city>
                        <region>NJ</region>
                        <code>07960</code>
                        <country>US</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 201 540 8967</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 201 993 3032</facsimile>
                     <email>nsb@nsb.fv.com</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="November"
						year="1996" />
					<abstract>
						<t>STD 11, RFC 822 defines a message representation
							protocol specifying considerable detail about
							US-ASCII message header fields, but which leaves
							the message content, or message body, as flat
							US-ASCII text. This set of documents, collectively
							called the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions,
							or MIME, redefines the format of messages to allow
							for</t>
						<t>(1) textual message bodies in character sets other
							than US-ASCII,</t>
						<t>(2) an extensible set of different formats for
							non-textual message bodies,</t>
						<t>(3) multi-part message bodies, and</t>
						<t>(4) textual header information in character sets
							other than US-ASCII. </t>
						<t>These documents are based on earlier work
							documented in RFC 934, STD 11 and RFC 1049, but
							extends and revises them. Because RFC 822 said so
							little about message bodies, these documents are
							largely orthogonal to (rather than a revision of)
							RFC 822. </t>
						<t>The initial document in this set, RFC 2045,
							specifies the various header fields used to
							describe the structure of MIME messages. This
							second document defines the general structure of
							the MIME media typing system and defines an
							initial set of media types. The third document,
							RFC 2047, describes extensions to RFC 822 to allow
							non-US-ASCII text data in Internet Mail header
							fields. The fourth document, RFC 2048, specifies
							various IANA registration procedures for
							MIME-related facilities. The fifth and final
							document, RFC 2049, describes MIME conformance
							criteria as well as providing some illustrative
							examples of MIME message formats,
							acknowledgements, and the bibliography. </t>
						<t>These documents are revisions of RFCs 1521 and
							1522, which themselves were revisions of RFCs 1341
							and 1342. An appendix in RFC 2049 describes
							differences and changes from previous versions.
						</t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2046" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2047">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="Message Header Extensions">MIME (Multipurpose
						Internet Mail Extensions) Part Three: Message Header
						Extensions for Non-ASCII Text</title>
					<author
						fullname="Keith Moore"
						initials="K."
						surname="Moore">
						<organization>University of Tennessee</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>107 Ayres Hall</street>
                        <street>Knoxville TN 37996-1301</street>
                     </postal>
                     <email>moore@cs.utk.edu</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="November"
						year="1996" />
					<area>Applications</area>
					<keyword>American Standard Code for Information
						Interchange</keyword>
					<keyword>mail</keyword>
					<keyword>multipurpose Internet Mail extensions</keyword>
					<abstract>
						<t>STD 11, RFC 822, defines a message representation
							protocol specifying considerable detail about
							US-ASCII message header fields, and leaves the
							message content, or message body, as flat US-ASCII
							text. This set of documents, collectively called
							the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions, or
							MIME, redefines the format of messages to allow
							for</t>
						<t>
							<list
								style="numbers">
								<t>(1) textual message bodies in character
									sets other than US-ASCII,</t>
								<t>(2) an extensible set of different formats
									for non-textual message bodies,</t>
								<t>(3) multi-part message bodies, and</t>
								<t>(4) textual header information in character
									sets other than US-ASCII. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
						<t>These documents are based on earlier work
							documented in RFC 934, STD 11, and RFC 1049, but
							extends and revises them. Because RFC 822 said so
							little about message bodies, these documents are
							largely orthogonal to (rather than a revision of)
							RFC 822. </t>
						<t>This particular document is the third document in
							the series. It describes extensions to RFC 822 to
							allow non-US-ASCII text data in Internet Mail
							header fields. Other documents in this series
							include:</t>
						<t>
							<list
								style="symbols">
								<t>+ RFC 2045, which specifies the various
									header fields used to describe the
									structure of MIME messages. </t>
								<t>+ RFC 2046, which defines the general
									structure of the MIME media typing system
									and defines an initial set of media types,</t>
								<t>+ RFC 2048, which specifies various IANA
									registration procedures for MIME-related
									facilities, and</t>
								<t>+ RFC 2049, which describes MIME
									conformance criteria and provides some
									illustrative examples of MIME message
									formats, acknowledgements, and the
									bibliography. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
						<t>These documents are revisions of RFCs 1521, 1522,
							and 1590, which themselves were revisions of RFCs
							1341 and 1342. An appendix in RFC 2049 describes
							differences and changes from previous versions.
						</t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2047" />
				<format
					octets="52141"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2047.html"
					type="HTML" />
				<format
					octets="39194"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2047.xml"
					type="XML" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC4289">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="MIME Registration">Multipurpose Internet Mail
						Extensions (MIME) Part Four: Registration Procedures</title>
					<author
						fullname="Ned Freed"
						initials="N."
						surname="Freed">
						<organization>Innosoft International, Inc. </organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>1050 East Garvey Avenue South</street>
                        <street>West Covina</street>
                        <street>CA 91790</street>
                        <country>USA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 818 919 3600</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 818 919 3614</facsimile>
                     <email>ned@innosoft.com</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="John Klensin"
						initials="J."
						surname="Klensin">
						<organization>MCI</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>2100 Reston Parkway</street>
                        <street>Reston</street>
                        <street>VA 22091</street>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 703 715-7361</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 703 715-7436</facsimile>
                     <email>klensin@mci.net</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Jon Postel"
						initials="J."
						surname="Postel">
						<organization>USC/Information Sciences Institute</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
                        <street>Marina del Rey</street>
                        <street>CA 90292</street>
                        <country>USA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 310 822 1511</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 310 823 6714</facsimile>
                     <email>Postel@ISI.EDU</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="December"
						year="2005" />
					<area>Applications</area>
					<keyword>mail</keyword>
					<keyword>media type</keyword>
					<keyword>multipurpose Internet Mail extensions</keyword>
					<abstract>
						<t>STD 11, RFC 822, defines a message representation
							protocol specifying considerable detail about
							US-ASCII message header fields, and leaves the
							message content, or message body, as flat US-ASCII
							text. This set of documents, collectively called
							the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions, or
							MIME, redefines the format of messages to allow
							for</t>
						<t>
							<list
								style="numbers">
								<t>(1) textual message bodies in character
									sets other than US-ASCII,</t>
								<t>(2) an extensible set of different formats
									for non-textual message bodies,</t>
								<t>(3) multi-part message bodies, and</t>
								<t>(4) textual header information in character
									sets other than US-ASCII. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
						<t>These documents are based on earlier work
							documented in RFC 934, STD 11, and RFC 1049, but
							extends and revises them. Because RFC 822 said so
							little about message bodies, these documents are
							largely orthogonal to (rather than a revision of)
							RFC 822. This fourth document, RFC 2048, specifies
							various IANA registration procedures for the
							following MIME facilities:</t>
						<t>
							<list
								style="numbers">
								<t>(1) media types,</t>
								<t>(2) external body access types,</t>
								<t>(3) content-transfer-encodings. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
						<t>Registration of character sets for use in MIME is
							covered here and is no longer addressed by this
							document. </t>
						<t>These documents are revisions of RFCs 1521 and
							1522, which themselves were revisions of RFCs 1341
							and 1342. An appendix in RFC 2049 describes
							differences and changes from previous versions.
						</t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="BCP"
					value="13" />
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="4289" />
				<format
					octets="54732"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc4289.html"
					type="HTML" />
				<format
					octets="43342"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc4289.xml"
					type="XML" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC4288">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="Media Registration">Media Type Specifications
						and Registration Procedures</title>
					<author
						fullname="Ned Freed"
						initials="N."
						surname="Freed">
						<organization>Innosoft International, Inc. </organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>1050 East Garvey Avenue South</street>
                        <street>West Covina</street>
                        <street>CA 91790</street>
                        <country>USA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 818 919 3600</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 818 919 3614</facsimile>
                     <email>ned@innosoft.com</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="John Klensin"
						initials="J."
						surname="Klensin">
						<organization>MCI</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>2100 Reston Parkway</street>
                        <street>Reston</street>
                        <street>VA 22091</street>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 703 715-7361</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 703 715-7436</facsimile>
                     <email>klensin@mci.net</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Jon Postel"
						initials="J."
						surname="Postel">
						<organization>USC/Information Sciences Institute</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
                        <street>Marina del Rey</street>
                        <street>CA 90292</street>
                        <country>USA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 310 822 1511</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 310 823 6714</facsimile>
                     <email>Postel@ISI.EDU</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="December"
						year="2005" />
					<area>Applications</area>
					<keyword>mail</keyword>
					<keyword>media type</keyword>
					<keyword>multipurpose Internet Mail extensions</keyword>
					<abstract>
						<t>STD 11, RFC 822, defines a message representation
							protocol specifying considerable detail about
							US-ASCII message header fields, and leaves the
							message content, or message body, as flat US-ASCII
							text. This set of documents, collectively called
							the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions, or
							MIME, redefines the format of messages to allow
							for</t>
						<t>
							<list
								style="numbers">
								<t>(1) textual message bodies in character
									sets other than US-ASCII,</t>
								<t>(2) an extensible set of different formats
									for non-textual message bodies,</t>
								<t>(3) multi-part message bodies, and</t>
								<t>(4) textual header information in character
									sets other than US-ASCII. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
						<t>These documents are based on earlier work
							documented in RFC 934, STD 11, and RFC 1049, but
							extends and revises them. Because RFC 822 said so
							little about message bodies, these documents are
							largely orthogonal to (rather than a revision of)
							RFC 822. This fourth document, RFC 2048, specifies
							various IANA registration procedures for the
							following MIME facilities:</t>
						<t>
							<list
								style="numbers">
								<t>(1) media types,</t>
								<t>(2) external body access types,</t>
								<t>(3) content-transfer-encodings. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
						<t>Registration of character sets for use in MIME is
							covered here and is no longer addressed by this
							document. </t>
						<t>These documents are revisions of RFCs 1521 and
							1522, which themselves were revisions of RFCs 1341
							and 1342. An appendix in RFC 2049 describes
							differences and changes from previous versions.
						</t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="BCP"
					value="13" />
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="4288" />
				<format
					octets="54732"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc4288.html"
					type="HTML" />
				<format
					octets="43342"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc4288.xml"
					type="XML" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2049">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="MIME Conformance">Multipurpose Internet Mail
						Extensions (MIME) Part Five: Conformance Criteria and
						Examples</title>
					<author
						fullname="Ned Freed"
						initials="N."
						surname="Freed">
						<organization>Innosoft International, Inc. </organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>1050 East Garvey Avenue South</street>
                        <street>West Covina</street>
                        <street>CA 91790</street>
                        <country>USA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 818 919 3600</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 818 919 3614</facsimile>
                     <email>ned@innosoft.com</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Nathaniel S. Borenstein"
						initials="N.S."
						surname="Borenstein">
						<organization>First Virtual Holdings</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>25 Washington Avenue</street>
                        <street>Morristown</street>
                        <street>NJ 07960</street>
                        <country>USA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 201 540 8967</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 201 993 3032</facsimile>
                     <email>nsb@nsb.fv.com</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="November"
						year="1996" />
					<area>Applications</area>
					<keyword>mail</keyword>
					<keyword>multipurpose Internet Mail extensions</keyword>
					<abstract>
						<t>STD 11, RFC 822, defines a message representation
							protocol specifying considerable detail about
							US-ASCII message header fields, and leaves the
							message content, or message body, as flat US-ASCII
							text. This set of documents, collectively called
							the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions, or
							MIME, redefines the format of messages to allow
							for</t>
						<t>
							<list
								style="numbers">
								<t>(1) textual message bodies in character
									sets other than US-ASCII,</t>
								<t>(2) an extensible set of different formats
									for non-textual message bodies,</t>
								<t>(3) multi-part message bodies, and</t>
								<t>(4) textual header information in character
									sets other than US-ASCII. </t>
							</list>
						</t>
						<t>These documents are based on earlier work
							documented in RFC 934, STD 11, and RFC 1049, but
							extends and revises them. Because RFC 822 said so
							little about message bodies, these documents are
							largely orthogonal to (rather than a revision of)
							RFC 822. </t>
						<t>The initial document in this set, RFC 2045,
							specifies the various header fields used to
							describe the structure of MIME messages. The
							second document defines the general structure of
							the MIME media typing system and defines an
							initial set of media types. The third document,
							RFC 2047, describes extensions to RFC 822 to allow
							non-US- ASCII text data in Internet Mail header
							fields. The fourth document, RFC 2048, specifies
							various IANA registration procedures for MIME-
							related facilities. This fifth and final document
							describes MIME conformance criteria as well as
							providing some illustrative examples of MIME
							message formats, acknowledgements, and the
							bibliography. </t>
						<t>These documents are revisions of RFCs 1521, 1522,
							and 1590, which themselves were revisions of RFCs
							1341 and 1342. Appendix B of this document
							describes differences and changes from previous
							versions. </t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2049" />
				<format
					octets="55000"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2049.html"
					type="HTML" />
				<format
					octets="41896"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2049.xml"
					type="XML" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2181">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="DNS Clarifications">Clarifications to the DNS
						Specification</title>
					<author
						fullname="Robert Elz"
						initials="R."
						surname="Elz">
						<organization>Computer Science</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>Parkville</street>
                        <street>Victoria</street>
                        <street>3052</street>
                        <street>Australia. </street>
                     </postal>
                     <email>kre@munnari.OZ.ADMD</email>
                     <uri>e</uri>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Randy Bush"
						initials="R."
						surname="Bush">
						<organization>RGnet, Inc. </organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>5147 Crystal Springs Drive</street>
                        <street>Bainbridge Island</street>
                        <street>Washington</street>
                        <street>98110</street>
                        <street>United States. </street>
                        <country>NE</country>
                     </postal>
                     <email>randy@psg.com</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="July"
						year="1997" />
					<area>Applications</area>
					<keyword>DNS</keyword>
					<keyword>domain name system</keyword>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2181" />
				<format
					octets="54106"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2181.html"
					type="HTML" />
				<format
					octets="38795"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2181.xml"
					type="XML" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC3798">
				<front>
					<title>Message Disposition Notification</title>
					<author
						fullname="T. Hansen"
						initials="T."
						surname="Hansen">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="G. Vaudreuil"
						initials="G."
						surname="Vaudreuil">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="May"
						year="2004" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3798" />
				<format
					octets="64049"
					target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3798.txt"
					type="TXT" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC3192">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="Minimal FAX address format">Minimal FAX
						address format in Internet Mail</title>
					<author
						fullname="C. Allocchio"
						initials="C."
						surname="Allocchio">
						<organization>GARR-Italy</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>Sincrotrone Trieste</street>
                        <street>SS 14 Km 163.5 Basovizza</street>
                        <city>Trieste</city>
                        <code>I 34012</code>
                        <country>Italy</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+39 40 3758523</phone>
                     <facsimile>+39 40 3758565</facsimile>
                     <email>Claudio.Allocchio@elettra.trieste.it</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="October"
						year="2001" />
					<area>Applications</area>
					<keyword>facsimile</keyword>
					<keyword>mail</keyword>
					<note
						title="IESG Note">
						<t>This memo describes a simple method of encoding
							PSTN addresses of facsimile devices in the
							local&nbhy;part of Internet email addresses. </t>
						<t>As with all Internet Mail addresses, the
							left-hand-side (local- part) of an address
							generated according to this specification, is not
							to be interpreted except by the MTA that is named
							on the right-hand-side (domain). </t>
					</note>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3192" />
				<format
					octets="22309"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/RFC3192.html"
					type="HTML" />
				<format
					octets="14696"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/RFC3192.xml"
					type="XML" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC4409">
				<front>
					<title>Message Submission for Mail</title>
					<author
						fullname="Randall Gellens"
						initials="R."
						surname="Gellens">
						<organization>QUALCOMM Incorporated</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>6455 Lusk Blvd. </street>
                        <city>San Diego</city>
                        <region>CA</region>
                        <code>92121-2779</code>
                        <country>USA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 619 651 5115</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 619 651 5334</facsimile>
                     <email>Randy@Qualcomm.Com</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="John C. Klensin"
						initials="J.C."
						surname="Klensin">
						<organization>MCI Telecommunications</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>800 Boylston St, 7th floor</street>
                        <city>Boston</city>
                        <region>MA</region>
                        <code>02199</code>
                        <country>USA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 617 960 1011</phone>
                     <email>klensin@mci.net</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="April"
						year="2006" />
					<area>Applications</area>
					<keyword>SMTP</keyword>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="4409" />
				<format
					octets="47918"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc4409.html"
					type="HTML" />
				<format
					octets="50997"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc4409.xml"
					type="XML" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2821">
				<front>
					<title>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol</title>
					<author
						fullname="J. Klensin"
						initials="J."
						surname="Klensin">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="April"
						year="2001" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2821" />
				<format
					octets="192504"
					target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2821.txt"
					type="TXT" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2822">
				<front>
					<title>Internet Message Format</title>
					<author
						fullname="P. Resnick"
						initials="P."
						surname="Resnick">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="April"
						year="2001" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2822" />
				<format
					octets="110695"
					target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2822.txt"
					type="TXT" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC3501">
				<front>
					<title>Internet Message Access Protocol - Version 4rev1</title>
					<author
						fullname="M. Crispin"
						initials="M."
						surname="Crispin">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="March"
						year="2003" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3501" />
				<format
					octets="227640"
					target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3501.txt"
					type="TXT" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2645">
				<front>
					<title>On-Demand Mail Relay (ODMR) SMTP with Dynamic IP
						Addresses</title>
					<author
						fullname="R. Gellens" surname="Gellens" initials="R.">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="August"
						year="1999" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2645" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC3864">
				<front>
					<title>Registration Procedures for Message Header Fields</title>
					<author
						fullname="G. Klyne"
						initials="G."
						surname="Klyne">
						<organization>Nine by Nine</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="M. Nottingham"
						initials="M."
						surname="Nottingham">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="J. Mogul"
						initials="J."
						surname="Mogul">
						<organization>HP Labs</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="September"
						year="2004" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3864" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2369">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="URLs as Meta-Syntax">The Use of URLs as
						Meta-Syntax for Core Mail List Commands and their
						Transport through Message Header Fields</title>
					<author
						fullname="Grant Neufeld"
						initials="G."
						surname="Neufeld">
						<organization>Calgary, Alberta</organization>
						<address>
                     <email>grant@acm.org</email>
                     <uri>http://www.nisto.com/</uri>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Joshua D. Baer"
						initials="J.D."
						surname="Baer">
						<organization>Box 273</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>4902 Forbes Avenue</street>
                        <street>Pittsburgh</street>
                        <street>PA 15213-3799</street>
                        <country>USA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <email>josh@skyweyr.com</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="July"
						year="1998" />
					<area>Applications</area>
					<keyword>mail</keyword>
					<keyword>uniform resource locater</keyword>
					<keyword>URL</keyword>
					<abstract>
						<t>The mailing list command specification header
							fields are a set of structured fields to be added
							to email messages sent by email distribution
							lists. Each field typically contains a URL
							(usually mailto ) locating the relevant
							information or performing the command directly.
							The three core header fields described in this
							document are List-Help, List-Subscribe, and
							List-Unsubscribe. </t>
						<t>There are three other header fields described here
							which, although not as widely applicable, will
							have utility for a sufficient number of mailing
							lists to justify their formalization here. These
							are List-Post, List-Owner and List-Archive. </t>
						<t>By including these header fields, list servers can
							make it possible for mail clients to provide
							automated tools for users to perform list
							functions. This could take the form of a menu
							item, push button, or other user interface
							element. The intent is to simplify the user
							experience, providing a common interface to the
							often cryptic and varied mailing list manager
							commands. </t>
						<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;,
							&quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
							&quot;REQUIRED&quot;,
							&quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL
							NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;,
							&quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;,
							&quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;,
							&quot;MAY&quot;, and
							&quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are
							to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119. </t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2369" />
				<format
					octets="45836"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2369.html"
					type="HTML" />
				<format
					octets="31893"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2369.xml"
					type="XML" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2919">
				<front>
					<title>List-Id: A Structured Field and Namespace for the
						Identification of Mailing Lists</title>
					<author
						fullname="R. Chandhok"
						initials="R."
						surname="Chandhok">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="G. Wenger"
						initials="G."
						surname="Wenger">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="March"
						year="2001" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2919" />
				<format
					octets="18480"
					target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2919.txt"
					type="TXT" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC5228">
				<front>
					<title>Sieve: A Mail Filtering Language</title>
					<author
						fullname="T. Showalter"
						initials="T."
						surname="Showalter">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month=""
						year="" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="5228" />
				<format
					octets="73582"
					target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5228.txt"
					type="TXT" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC3297">
				<front>
					<title>Content Negotiation for Messaging Services based on
						Email</title>
					<author
						fullname="G. Klyne"
						initials="G."
						surname="Klyne">
						<organization>Clearswift Corporation</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="R. Iwazaki"
						initials="R."
						surname="Iwazaki">
						<organization>Toshiba TEC</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="D. Crocker"
						initials="D."
						surname="Crocker">
						<organization>Brandenburg
						InternetWorking</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="July"
						year="2002" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3297" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC3458">
				<front>
					<title>Message Context for Internet Mail</title>
					<author
						fullname="E. Burger"
						initials="E."
						surname="Burger">
						<organization>SnowShore Networks</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="E. Candell"
						initials="E."
						surname="Candell">
						<organization>Comverse</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="C. Eliot"
						initials="C."
						surname="Eliot">
						<organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="G. Klyne"
						initials="G."
						surname="Klyne">
						<organization>Nine by Nine</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="January"
						year="2003" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3458" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC3461">
				<front>
					<title>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP) Service
						Extension for Delivery Status Notifications (DSNs)</title>
					<author
						fullname="K. Moore"
						initials="K."
						surname="Moore">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="January"
						year="2003" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3461" />
				<format
					octets="76076"
					target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3461.txt"
					type="TXT" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC4021">
				<front>
					<title>Registration of Mail and MIME Header Fields</title>
					<author
						fullname="G. Klyne"
						initials="G."
						surname="Klyne">
						<organization>University of Oxford</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="J. Palme"
						initials="J."
						surname="Palme">
						<organization>Stockholm University/KT</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="March"
						year="2005" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="4021" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC4550">
				<front>
					<title>Internet Email to Support Diverse Service
						Environments (Lemonade) Profile</title>
					<author
						initials="S."
						surname="Maes">
						<organization>Oracle</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Melnikov"
						initials="S.">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author>
						<organization>Isode Ltd. </organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="June"
						year="2006" />
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC0791">
				<front>
					<title>Internet Protocol</title>
					<author
						fullname="J. Postel"
						initials="J."
						surname="Postel">
						<organization>USC-ISI</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="1981"
						year="September" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="791" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC3834">
				<front>
					<title>Recommendations for Automatic Responses to
						Electronic Mail</title>
					<author
						fullname="K. Moore"
						initials="K."
						surname="Moore">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="August"
						year="2004" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3834" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC5248">
				<front>
					<title>A Registry for SMTP Enhanced Mail System Status
						Codes</title>
					<author
						fullname="T. Hansen"
						initials="T."
						surname="Hansen">
						<organization>AT&amp;T Laboratories</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="J. Klensin"
						initials="J."
						surname="Klensin">
						<organization />
					</author>

					<date
						month="June"
						year="2008" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="5248" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC5321">
				<front>
					<title>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol</title>
					<author
						fullname="J. Klensin"
						initials="J."
						surname="Klensin">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="October"
						year="2008" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="5321" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC5322">
				<front>
					<title>Internet Message Format</title>
					<author
						fullname="P. Resnick"
						initials="P."
						role="editor"
						surname="Resnick">
						<organization>Qualcomm Incorporated</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="October"
						year="2008" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="5322" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC5335">
				<front>
					<title>Internationalized Email Headers</title>
					<author
						fullname="Y. Abel" initials="Y." surname="Abel"
						role="editor">
						<organization>TWNIC</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="September"
						year="2008" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="5335" />
			</reference>


			<reference
				anchor="RFC3462">
				<front>
					<title>The Multipart/Report Content Type for the Reporting
						of Mail System Administrative Messages</title>
					<author
						fullname="G. Vaudreuil"
						initials="G."
						surname="Vaudreuil">
						<organization>Lucent Technologies</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="January"
						year="2003" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3462" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC3463">
				<front>
					<title>Enhanced Mail System Status Codes</title>
					<author
						fullname="G. Vaudreuil"
						initials="G."
						surname="Vaudreuil">
						<organization>Lucent Technologies</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="January"
						year="2003" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3463" />
			</reference>
		</references>

		<references
			title="Informative">
			<reference
				anchor="Tussle">
				<front>
					<title>Tussle in Cyberspace: Defining Tomorrow’s Internet</title>
					<author
						fullname="David D. Clark"
						initials="D"
						surname="Clark">
						<organization>MIT Lab for Computer Science</organization>
						<address>
                     <email>ddc@lcs.mit.edu</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="John Wroclawski"
						initials="J"
						surname="Wroclawski">
						<organization>MIT Lab for Computer Science</organization>
						<address>
                     <email>jtw@lcs.mit.edu</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Karen R. Sollins"
						initials="K"
						surname="Sollins">
						<organization />
						<address>
                     <email>sollins@lcs.mit.edu</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Robert Braden"
						initials="R"
						surname="Braden">
						<organization>USC Information Sciences Institute</organization>
						<address>
                     <email>braden@isi.edu</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						year="2002" />
					<note
						title="">
						<t />
					</note>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="ACM"
					value="SIGCOMM" />
			</reference>


			<reference
				anchor="RFC0821">
				<front>
					<title>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol</title>
					<author
						fullname="Jonathan B. Postel"
						initials="J.B."
						surname="Postel">
						<organization>University of Southern California
							(USC)/Information Sciences Institute</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
                        <city>Marina del Rey</city>
                        <region>CA</region>
                        <code>90291</code>
                        <country>US</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 213 822 1511</phone>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						day="1"
						month="August"
						year="1982" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="STD"
					value="10" />
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="821" />
			</reference>

			<reference
				anchor="RFC0733">
				<front>
					<title>Standard for the Format of ARPA Network Text
						Messages</title>
					<author
						fullname="David H. Crocker"
						initials="D.H."
						surname="Crocker">
						<organization>The Rand Corporation</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="John J. Vittal"
						initials="J.J."
						surname="Vittal">
						<organization>Bolt Beranek and Newman
						Inc.</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Kenneth T. Pogran"
						initials="K.T."
						surname="Pogran">
						<organization>Massachusets Institute of
						Technology</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="D. Austin Henderson, Jr."
						initials="D.A."
						surname="Henderson">
						<organization>Bolt Beranek and Newman
						Inc.</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						day="21"
						month="November"
						year="1977" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="733" />
			</reference>

			<reference
				anchor="RFC0822">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="Standard for ARPA Internet Text Messages"
						>Standard for the format of ARPA Internet text
						messages</title>
					<author
						fullname="David H. Crocker"
						initials="D.H."
						surname="Crocker">
						<organization>University of Delaware, Dept. of
							Electrical Engineering</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street />
                        <city>Newark</city>
                        <region>DE</region>
                        <code>19711</code>
                        <country>US</country>
                     </postal>
                     <email>DCrocker@UDel-Relay</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						day="13"
						month="August"
						year="1982" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="STD"
					value="11" />
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="822" />
			</reference>


			<reference
				anchor="RFC1652">
				<front>
					<title>SMTP Service Extension for 8bit-MIMEtransport</title>
					<author
						fullname="J. Klensin" initials="J." surname="Klensin">
						<organization>MCI</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="N. Freed" initials="N." surname="Freed"
						role="editor">
						<organization>Innosoft</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="M. Rose" initials="M." surname="Rose">
						<organization>Dover Beach Consulting,
						Inc.</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="E. Stefferud" initials="E." surname="Stefferud">
						<organization>Network Management Associates,
						Inc.</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="D. Crocker" initials="D." surname="Crocker">
						<organization>Silicon Graphics, Inc.</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="July"
						year="1994" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="1652" />
			</reference>


			<reference
				anchor="RFC1767">
				<front>
					<title>MIME Encapsulation of EDI Objects</title>
					<author
						fullname="Dave Crocker"
						initials="D."
						surname="Crocker">
						<organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>675 Spruce Drive</street>
                        <city>Sunnyvale</city>
                        <region>CA</region>
                        <code>94086</code>
                        <country>USA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1.408.246.8253</phone>
                     <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="March"
						year="1995" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="1767" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2033">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="Local Mail">Local Mail Transfer Protocol</title>
					<author
						fullname="John G. Myers"
						initials="J.G."
						surname="Myers">
						<organization>Carnegie-Mellon University</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>5000 Forbes Ave. </street>
                        <street>Pittsburgh</street>
                        <street>15213-3890</street>
                        <country>PA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <email>jgm+@cmu.edu</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="October"
						year="1996" />
					<area>Applications</area>
					<keyword>mail</keyword>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2033" />
				<format
					octets="27748"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2033.html"
					type="HTML" />
				<format
					octets="17426"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2033.xml"
					type="XML" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC2442">
				<front>
					<title>The Batch SMTP Media Type</title>
					<author
						fullname="N. Freed" surname="Freed" initials="N.">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="D. Newman" surname="Newman" initials="D.">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="J. Belissen" surname="Belissen" initials="J.">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="M. Hoy"  surname="Hoy" initials="M.">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="November"
						year="1998" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2442" />
			</reference>



			<reference
				anchor="RFC3464">
				<front>
					<title>An Extensible Message Format for Delivery Status
						Notifications</title>
					<author
						fullname="K. Moore"
						initials="K."
						surname="Moore">
						<organization>University of Tennessee</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="G. Vaudreuil"
						initials="G."
						surname="Vaudreuil">
						<organization>Lucent Technologies</organization>
					</author>

					<date
						month="January"
						year="2003" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3464" />
			</reference>



			<reference
				anchor="RFC3801">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="VPIMv2">Voice Profile for Internet Mail -
						version 2 (VPIMv2)</title>
					<author
						fullname="Gregory M. Vaudreuil"
						initials="G.M."
						surname="Vaudreuil">
						<organization>Lucent Technologies, Octel Messaging
							Division</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>17080 Dallas Parkway</street>
                        <city>Dallas</city>
                        <region>TX</region>
                        <code>75248-1905</code>
                        <country>USA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 972 733 2722</phone>
                     <email>GregV@Lucent.Com</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Glenn W. Parsons"
						initials="G.W."
						surname="Parsons">
						<organization>Northern Telecom</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>P.O. Box 3511</street>
                        <street>Station C</street>
                        <city>Ottawa</city>
                        <region>ON</region>
                        <code>K1Y 4H7</code>
                        <country>Canada</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1 613 763 7582</phone>
                     <facsimile>+1 613 763 4461</facsimile>
                     <email>Glenn.Parsons@Nortel.ca</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<date
						month="June"
						year="2004" />
					<area>Applications</area>
					<keyword>audio</keyword>
					<keyword>mail</keyword>
					<abstract>
						<t>A class of special-purpose computers has evolved to
							provide voice messaging services. These machines
							generally interface to a telephone switch and
							provide call answering and voice messaging
							services. Traditionally, messages sent to a
							non-local machine are transported using analog
							networking protocols based on DTMF signaling and
							analog voice playback. As the demand for
							networking increases, there is a need for a
							standard high-quality digital protocol to connect
							these machines. The following document is a
							profile of the Internet standard MIME and ESMTP
							protocols for use as a digital voice messaging
							networking protocol. The profile is referred to as
							VPIM (Voice Profile for Internet Mail) in this
							document. </t>
						<t>This profile is based on earlier work in the Audio
							Message Interchange Specification (AMIS) group
							that defined a voice messaging protocol based on
							X.400 technology. This profile is intended to
							satisfy the user requirements statement from that
							earlier work with the industry standard ESMTP/MIME
							mail protocol infrastructures already used within
							corporate intranets. This second version of VPIM
							is based on implementation experience and
							obsoletes RFC 1911 which describes version 1 of
							the profile. </t>
					</abstract>
					<note
						title="Working Group Summary">
						<t>This profile is not the product of an IETF working
							group, though several have reviewed the document.
							It is instead the product of the VPIM Work Group
							of the Electronic Messaging Association (EMA).
							This work group, which has representatives from
							most major voice mail vendors and several email
							vendors, has held several interoperability
							demonstrations between voice messaging vendors and
							is currently promoting VPIM trials and deployment.
						</t>
					</note>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3801" />
				<format
					octets="162050"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc3801.html"
					type="HTML" />
				<format
					octets="180600"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc3801.xml"
					type="XML" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC3885">

				<front>
					<title>SMTP Service Extension for Message Tracking</title>
					<author
						fullname="E. Allman"
						initials="E."
						surname="Allman">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="T. Hansen"
						initials="T."
						surname="Hansen">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="September"
						year="2004" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3885" />
				<format
					octets="17458"
					target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc3801.xml"
					type="XML" />
			</reference>
			<reference
				anchor="RFC4142">
				<front>
					<title>Full-mode Fax Profile for Internet Mail: FFPIM</title>
					<author
						fullname="Dave Crocker"
						initials="D."
						surname="Crocker">
						<organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
						<address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>675 Spruce Drive</street>
                        <city>Sunnyvale</city>
                        <region>CA</region>
                        <code>94086</code>
                        <country>USA</country>
                     </postal>
                     <phone>+1.408.246.8253</phone>
                     <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
                  </address>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="G. Klyne"
						initials="G."
						surname="Klyne">
						<organization>Nine By Nine</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="December"
						year="2005" />
				</front>
			</reference>

			<reference
				anchor="RFC5068">
				<front>
					<title>Email Submission Operations: Access and
						Accountability Requirements</title>
					<author
						fullname="Carl Hutzler"
						initials="C"
						surname="Hutzler">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Dave Crocker"
						initials="D"
						surname="Crocker">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Pete Resnick"
						initials="P"
						surname="Resnick">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Robert Sanderson"
						initials="R"
						surname="Sanderson">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="Eric Allman"
						initials="E"
						surname="Allman">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="Nov"
						year="2007" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="5068" />
				<seriesInfo
					name="BCP"
					value="134" />



			</reference>


			<reference
				anchor="RFC3685">
				<front>
					<title>SIEVE Email Filtering: Spamtest and VirusTest
						Extensions</title>
					<author
						fullname="C. Daboo"
						initials="C."
						surname="Daboo">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="February"
						year="2004" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3685" />
			</reference>



			<reference
				anchor="RFC1733">
				<front>
					<title>Distributed Electronic Models in IMAP4</title>
					<author
						fullname="M. Crispin"
						initials="M"
						surname="Crispin">
						<organization>University of Washington</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="December"
						year="1994" />
				</front>
			</reference>

			<reference
				anchor="RFC4356">
				<front>
					<title>Mapping Between the Multimedia Messaging Service
						(MMS) and Internet Mail</title>
					<author
						fullname="R. Gellens"
						initials="R."
						surname="Gellens">
						<organization>Qualcomm</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="January"
						year="2006" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="4356" />

			</reference>

			<!--         <reference anchor="RFC3965">
            <front>
               <title>A Simple Mode of Facsimile Using Internet Mail</title>
               <author fullname="K. Toyoda" initials="K." surname="Toyoda">
                  <organization />
               </author>
               <author fullname="H. Ohno" initials="H." surname="Ohno">
                  <organization />
               </author>
               <author fullname="J. Murai" initials="J." surname="Murai">
                  <organization />
               </author>
               <author fullname="D. Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
                  <organization />
               </author>
               <date month="December" year="2004" />
            </front>
         </reference>

-->
			<reference
				anchor="RFC4143">
				<front>
					<title>Facsimile Using Internet Mail (IFAX) Service of
						ENUM</title>
					<author
						fullname="K. Toyoda"
						initials="K."
						surname="Toyoda">
						<organization>PCC</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="D. Crocker"
						initials="D."
						surname="Crocker">
						<organization>Brandenburg</organization>
					</author>

					<date
						month="November"
						year="2005" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="4143" />

			</reference>

			<reference
				anchor="RFC2142">
				<front>
					<title>Mailbox Names for Common services, Roles and
						Functions</title>
					<author
						fullname="D. Crocker"
						initials="D."
						surname="Crocker">
						<organization>Internet Mail Consortium</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="May"
						year="1997" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2142" />
			</reference>

			<reference
				anchor="RFC2505">
				<front>
					<title>Anti-Spam Recommendations for SMTP MTAs</title>
					<author
						fullname="G. Lindberg"
						initials="G."
						surname="Lindberg">
						<organization>Chalmers University of
						Technology</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="February"
						year="1999" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2505" />
			</reference>


			<reference
				anchor="RFC3207">
				<front>
					<title>SMTP Service Extension for Secure SMTP over
						Transport Layer Security</title>
					<author
						fullname="P. Hoffman"
						initials="P."
						surname="Hoffman">
						<organization>Internet Mail Consortium></organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="February"
						year="2002" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3207" />
			</reference>


			<reference
				anchor="RFC4954">
				<front>
					<title
						abbrev="SMTP-Auth">SMTP Service Extension for
						Authentication</title>
					<author
						fullname="R. Siemborski"
						initials="R."
						role="editor"
						surname="Siemborski">
						<organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="A. Melnikov"
						initials="A."
						role="editor"
						surname="Melnikov">
						<organization />
					</author>

					<date
						month="July"
						year="2007" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="4954" />
			</reference>



			<reference
				anchor="RFC4880">
				<front>
					<title>OpenPGP Message Format</title>
					<author
						fullname="J. Callas"
						initials="J."
						surname="Callas">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="L. Donnerhacke"
						initials="L."
						surname="Donnerhacke">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="H. Finney"
						initials="H."
						surname="Finney">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="D. Shaw"
						initials="D."
						surname="Shaw">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="R. Thayer"
						initials="R."
						surname="Thayer">
						<organization />
					</author>

					<date
						month="November"
						year="2007" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="4880" />
			</reference>



			<reference
				anchor="RFC3851">
				<front>
					<title>Secure/Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions
						(S/MIME) Version 3.1 Message Specification </title>
					<author
						fullname="B. Ramsdell"
						initials="B."
						role="editor"
						surname="Ramsdell">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="July"
						year="2004" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="3851" />
			</reference>

			<reference
				anchor="RFC1985">
				<front>
					<title>SMTP Service Extension for Remote Message Queue
						Starting</title>
					<author
						fullname="J. De Winter"
						initials="J."
						surname="De       Winter">
						<organization />
					</author>
					<date
						month="August"
						year="1996" />
				</front>
			</reference>

			<reference
				anchor="RFC2480">
				<front>
					<title>Gateways and MIME Security Multiparts</title>
					<author
						fullname="N. Freed"
						initials="N."
						surname="Freed">
						<organization>Innosoft International,
						Inc.</organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="January"
						year="1999" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="2480" />
			</reference>


			<reference
				anchor="RFC1506">
				<front>
					<title>A Tutorial on Gatewaying between X.400 and Internet
						Mail</title>
					<author
						fullname="J. Houttuin"
						initials="J."
						surname="Houttuin">
						<organization>RARE Secretariat </organization>
					</author>
					<date
						month="August"
						year="1993" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="1506" />
			</reference>


			<reference
				anchor="RFC5336">
				<front>
					<title>SMTP Extension for Internationalized Email
						Addresses</title>
					<author
						fullname="J. Yao"
						initials="J."
						role="editor"
						surname="Yao">
						<organization>CNNIC</organization>
					</author>
					<author
						fullname="W. Mao"
						initials="W./"
						role="editor"
						surname="Mao">
						<organization>CNNIC</organization>
					</author>

					<date
						month="September"
						year="2008" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo
					name="RFC"
					value="5336" />
			</reference>


		</references>

		<section
			title="Acknowledgements">
			<t>This work began in 2004 and has evolved through numerous rounds
				of community review; it derives from a section in an early
				version of <xref
					target="RFC5068" />. Over its 5 years of development, the
				draft has gone through 13 incremental versions, with vigorous
				community review that produced many substantive changes.
				Review was performed in the IETF and other email technical
				venues. Although not a formal activity of the IETF, issues
				with the document's contents were resolved using the classic
				style of IETF community open, group decision-making. The
				document is already cited in other work, such as for IMAP and
				Sieve specifications and for academic classwork. The step of
				standardizing is useful to provide a solid and stable
				reference to the Internet's now-complex email service. </t>
			<t>Details of the Originator actor role was greatly clarified
				during discussions in the IETF's Marid working group. </t>
			<t>Graham Klyne, Pete Resnick and Steve Atkins provided thoughtful
				insight on the framework and details of the original drafts,
				as did Chris Newman for the final versions, while also serving
				as cognizant Area Director for the document. Tony Hansen
				served as document shepherd, through the IETF process.</t>
			<t>Later reviews and suggestions were provided by Eric Allman,
				Nathaniel Borenstein, Ed Bradford, Cyrus Daboo, Frank
				Ellermann, Tony Finch, Ned Freed, Eric Hall, Willemien
				Hoogendoorn, Brad Knowles, John Leslie, Bruce Valdis
				Kletnieks, Mark E. Mallett, David MacQuigg, Alexey Melnikov,
				der Mouse, S. Moonesamy, Daryl Odnert, Rahmat M.
				Samik-Ibrahim, Marshall Rose, Hector Santos, Jochen Topf, Greg
				Vaudreuil, Patrick Cain, Paul Hoffman, Vijay Gurbani, and Hans
				Lachman. </t>
			<t>Diligent early proof-reading was performed by Bruce Lilly.
				Diligent technical editing was provided by Susan Hunziker.</t>
			<t>The final stages of development for this document were guided
				by a design team comprising: Alexey Melnikov, Pete Resnick,
				Carl S. Gutekunst, Jeff Macdonald, Randall Gellens, Tony
				Hansen and Tony Finch. Pete Resnick developed the final
				version of the section on internationalization.</t>

		</section>
	</back>
</rfc>
