<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
	  <!ENTITY RFC1887 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1887.xml">
	  <!ENTITY I-D.narten-radir-problem-statement SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-radir-problem-statement.xml">
	  <!ENTITY I-D.irtf-rrg-design-goals SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.irtf-rrg-design-goals.xml">
	  ]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-irtf-rrg-recommendation-00" ipr="trust200811">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="RRG Recommendation">
      Preliminary Recommendation for a Routing Architecture 
    </title>

    <author fullname="Tony Li" initials="T." role="editor"
            surname="Li">
      <organization>Redback Networks, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>300 Holger Way</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95134</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 408 750 5160</phone>
        <email>tony.li@tony.li</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month='February' year="2009" />

    <area></area>
    <workgroup>Internet Research Task Force</workgroup>
    <keyword>routing</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
	It is commonly recognized that the Internet
	routing and addressing architecture is facing challenges in
	scalability, multi-homing, and inter-domain traffic
	engineering.  This document is the Routing Research Group's
	prelimnary recommendation for a new routing architecture.
      </t>
      <t>
	This document is a work in progress.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
	It is commonly recognized that the Internet routing and addressing
	architecture is facing challenges in scalability, multi-homing, and
	inter-domain traffic engineering.  The problem being addressed has
	been documented in
	<xref target='I-D.narten-radir-problem-statement'/>, and the design
	goals that we have agreed to can be found in
	<xref target='I-D.irtf-rrg-design-goals'/>.  This document is the
	Routing Research Group's (RRG's) preliminary recommendation for a
	new routing architecture.
      </t>
      <t>
	This document is a work in progress.
      </t>
      <section title="Structure of This Document">
	<t>
	  This document describes many of the different possible approaches
	  that could be taken in a new routing architecture, as well as a
	  summary of the current thinking of the overall group regarding
	  each approach.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology and Abbreviations">
      <t>
	This section describes the common terminology used in this
	document.  Particular architectures and discussions frequently
	define additional terms, qualify these terms or add additional
	semantics.
      </t>
      <t>
	<list style="hanging">
	  <t hangText="FIB">
	    Forwarding Information Base, also known as the forwarding
	    table.  Typically, the forwarding table contains the subset of
	    the information in the RIB that is actually needed at
	    forwarding time.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="GUID">
	    Globally Unique IDentifier
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="ISP">
	    Internet Service Provider
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="identifier">
	    An identifier is the name of an endpoint.  It has no topological
	    significance.  Identifiers may have other properties, such as the
	    scope of their uniqueness (global or local) and the probability
	    of their uniqueness (absolute or statistical).
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="locator">
	    A locator is a name that has topological significance.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="RIB">
	    Routing Information Base, also known as the routing table.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="RIR">
	    Regional Internet Registry
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="RLOC">
	    A Remote LOCator is a locator with global scope.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="SID">
	    Session IDentifier
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="TE">
	    Traffic Engineering is a technique for controlling the path that
	    traffic takes beyond baseline methods.
	  </t>
	</list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Taxonomies of the Solution Space">
      <t>
	In trying to understand the entirety of the solution space that we
	are confronted with, we have made multiple attempts to divide the
	space into comprehensible sectors.  The entire solution space is
	complex, and it seems difficult to capture all of the pertinent
	dimensions of the space with only a single perspective.  Different
	taxonomies seem to provide insight during different discussions,
	and we summarize all of them here to capture all of the useful
	perspectives.
      </t>
      
      <section title="A Mechanism Taxonomy">
	<t>
	  In this taxonomy, solutions are grouped by the primary mechanisms
	  that they use to achieve their goals.
	</t>
	<section anchor="Mechanism:Transport" title="Transport">
	  <t>
	    Transport solutions are characterized by their usage of
	    modifications soley at the transport layer to provide locator
	    and identifier independence.  For example, if a transport
	    protocol supports connections across multiple addresses as a
	    means of supporting multi-homed hosts, and can seamlessly and
	    transparently shift across these addresses, then it can provide
	    the multi-homing support that is required.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    However, in our discussions, it became clear that even with
	    transport level agility, host-level renumbering of sites would
	    still be necessary to support these types of solutions.  The
	    consensus of the group is that such site renumbering is a
	    completely unacceptable requirement and as such, these types of
	    solutions are not of interest for further exploration.
	  </t>
	</section>
	<section title="Translation">
	  <t>
	    Translation solutions are characterized by a translation
	    operation between an identifier to a locator and back to an
	    identifier as the packet traverses the network.  Translation
	    approaches do not add additional encapsulations to the packet
	    as they traverse the network, usually translating the fields in
	    their place in the packet.  Translation solutions can further
	    be categorized as those with separated fields for locators and
	    identifiers and those that continue to use a single address
	    field.  Translation solutions also can be categorized as having
	    the translation done in the host or in a middle box.
	  </t>
	</section>
	<section title="Map &amp; Encap">
	  <t>
	    Map &amp; Encap solutions are characterized by a lookup
	    operation from the identifier to a locator and then an
	    encapsulation of the packet payload into a tunnel that directs
	    the packet across the topology.  
	  </t>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section title="A Functional Taxonomy">
	<t>
	  EDITOR'S NOTE: Lixia to propose text here.
	</t>
	<section title="Separation">
	</section>
	<section title="Elimination">
	</section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="Herrin" title="The Herrin Taxonomy">
	<t>
	  As part of the mailing list discussion, the group constructed a
	  more detailed taxonomy of possible architectures, described as a
	  series of strategies.
	</t>

	<section title="Strategy A">
	  <t>
	    Local routing is based on an address, which functions as a GUID,
	    SID component and local locator, but have each packet flow
	    through an encoder which attaches a RLOC before the packet
	    enters the internetwork core.  Routing within the core is based
	    on the RLOC.  Only ISPs with significant interconnection have
	    their own RLOCs.  Fewer than 10,000 such "core ISPs" exist today
	    and the number is growing much more slowly than the routing
	    table overall. Once the packet reaches the network identified
	    by the RLOC, local routing by address takes over for final
	    delivery. Distribute RLOCs through the core via a typical
	    distance-vector or link-state routing protocol.
	  </t>
	  <section title="Variants">
	    <t>
	      <list style="hanging">
		<t hangText="A1a">
		  Each core ISP has one RLOC. The RLOC's existence and
		  reachability is flooded to the rest of the core.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A1b">
		  Each core ISP has a small number of RLOCs for TE. The
		  RLOCs' existence and reachability is flooded to the rest of
		  the core.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A1c">
		  Each core ISP has an aggregated set of RLOCs which it may
		  hierarchically assign to customers downstream and/or
		  disaggregate for TE. The aggregated RLOC's existence and
		  reachability is flooded to the rest of the core.
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="Mapping approaches">
	    <t>
	      <list style="hanging">
		<t hangText="A2a">
		  Addresses are statically mapped to RLOCs.  Map entries are
		  periodically pushed towards a central or distributed
		  registry. The full list is periodically downloaded to the
		  encoders which add RLOCs to the packets.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A2b">
		  Addresses are dynamically mapped to RLOCs.  Map entries are
		  pushed towards a central or distributed registry as they
		  change. The registry pushes all incremental changes in
		  near-real time to all encoders which add RLOCs to the
		  packets.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A2c">
		  Addresses are dynamically mapped to RLOCs.  Map entries are
		  pushed towards a central or distributed registry as they
		  change. Encoders request and briefly cache individual
		  mappings from the registry as needed.
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="Failure handling approaches">
	    <t>
	      Link failures in the Internet core cause the RLOCs to be
	      rerouted with no change to the address to RLOC mapping.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      <list style="hanging">
		<t hangText="A3a">
		  RLOC encoders detect when particular RLOCs are no longer
		  reachable at all and fall back on secondary RLOCs for a
		  particular address. Encoders rely on active failure messages
		  from some system in the RLOC-specified network to indicate
		  that a host is no longer available via that RLOC, causing
		  them to fall back on secondary RLOCs for that host.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A3b">
		  Link failures which prevent parts of the RLOC's network from
		  reaching a destination host or set of hosts it serves cause
		  an external analysis element to make a dynamic change to the
		  address-RLOC map, depreferencing or removing the affected
		  RLOC. The external analysis element may be under the control
		  of the end-user destination network, the RLOC network or a
		  third party under contract to one of them.
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>
	  
	  <section title="Compatibility approaches">
	    <t>
	      <list style="hanging">
		<t hangText="A4a">
		  Create a new IP protocol.  The new protocol would not be
		  compatible with IPv4 and IPv6.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A4b">
		  Modify the IP protocol.  The modified protocol would not
		  be compatible with IPv4 and IPv6 as deployed.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A4c">
		  Standard IPv4 and IPv6 packets are tunnelled while they
		  transit the Internet core. Path-MTU issues are handled
		  by setting an Internet-wide maximum packet size enforced
		  by the encoders and assuring that all core links support
		  that size.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A4d">
		  Standard IPv4 and IPv6 packets are tunnelled while they
		  transit the Internet core. Path-MTU issues are handled
		  by returning packets which breach the MTU while in the
		  core back to the encoder who must act as a proxy by
		  returning a sensible packet-too-big message to the
		  originating host.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A4e">
		  The IPv6 address space is partitioned into end-user address
		  space and Internet core address space. The address to RLOC
		  map is symmetric. Part of the IPv6 end-user address is
		  swapped for the RLOC when the packet enters the Internet core
		  and then restored when it leaves the Internet core. Use a
		  different A4 variant for IPv4.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A4f">
		  The IPv6 flow label or some other component(s) of the IPv6
		  header are used to contain the RLOC. The flow label is set
		  before the packet enters the core. Non-local packets are
		  routed based on the flow label. Use a different A4 variant
		  for IPv4.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A4g">
		  Steal bits from other functions in the IPv4 header
		  (e.g. checksum) to make space for an RLOC. Discard those
		  components and set the RLOC when the packet enters the
		  core. Restore the original bits when the packet leaves the
		  core. Use a different A4 variant for IPv6.
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>
	  
	  <section title="Core routing methods">
	    <t>
	      <list style="hanging">
		<t hangText="A5a">
		  Distribute RLOCs through the Internet core via BGP.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A5b">
		  Distribute RLOCs through the Internet core via a new
		  distance-vector protocol.
		</t>
		<t hangText="A5c">
		  Distribute RLOCs through the Internet core via a link-state
		  protocol.
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="Major criticisms">
	    <t>
	      There don't appear to be any genuinely clean ways of
	      implementing strategy A. Handling path-MTU is a usually
	      problem since the packets in the core are different than the
	      origin host would recognize. Extra bandwidth is consumed by
	      the ingress tunnel router figuring out whether the egress
	      tunnel router is still available and functioning. Border
	      filtering of source addresses becomes problematic. 
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Deployment may require heavy weight "for the public good"
	      relays in the non-upgraded part of the Internet to facilitate
	      migration.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      <!-- Added by tli -->
	      During the transition period, it appears difficult to remove
	      legacy prefixes from the global routing table.  The best that
	      can be done is to advertise aggregates of legacy prefixes
	      from the relays.  This may have an impact on stretch.
	    </t>
	  </section>
	</section>

	<section anchor="StrategyB" title="Strategy B">
	  <t>
	    Assign hierarchically aggregatable locators to every
	    host. Assign multiple locators to each host such that in the
	    network topology hosts appear as stubs in multiple locations
	    instead of forming distant connections in the graph. Assign one
	    aggregated set of locators to each core ISP where a core ISP is
	    one which has at least half a dozen major transit or peering
	    links. Flood the aggregated locator's existence and
	    reachability to the rest of the core.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    Having reduced the network topology to something relatively
	    close to a hierarchy, perform plain old hierarchical
	    aggregation on the locators. Add and remove locators to each
	    host dynamically during operation as needed to reflect changes
	    in the nearby network hierarchies.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    Attach source and destination locators when the packet leaves the
	    host. Route by first source then destination locator: move up the
	    source network hierarchy until you can move laterally toward
	    the destination locator in a permissioned manner.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    Identifier to locator maps are pushed from the host towards a
	    distributed registry as they change. Hosts request and
	    temporarily cache individual mappings from the registry as
	    needed.
	  </t>

	  <section title="Locator variants">
	    <t>
	      <list style="hanging">
		<t hangText="B1a">
		  A hierarchically aggregated numeric locator is
		  dynamically assigned to each host from each upstream
		  path.  Each router receives a less specific prefix from
		  upstream and assigns a more specific prefix downstream.
		  Link state changes in the path to the core are satisfied
		  by renumbering instead of rerouting: the host abandons
		  the locator hierarchically associated with the old
		  path. If a new path is available, the host acquires a
		  locator hierarchically associated with the new path.
		</t>
		<t hangText="B1b">
		  A locator is an administratively-assigned loose source
		  route instead of a single address. The first address in
		  the loose source route is a universally-known waypoint
		  router. The last address is the final destination. Link
		  state changes in the path to the core are satisfied by
		  rerouting in the appropriate routing domain when
		  possible. If rerouting in the affected domain is not
		  possible, the host abandons the impacted locator.
		</t>
		<t hangText="B1c">
		  Semi-hierarchical numeric locators are administratively
		  assigned.  Local reconnection during link state changes
		  is accomplished with rerouting instead of renumbering.
		</t>
	      </list>
	      </t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="Identifier variants">
	    <t>
	      <list style="hanging">
		<t hangText="B2a">
		  Each host has a single numeric identifer to which the
		  locators are attached. This identifier is used by the
		  layer-4/5 and higher protocols to compose the SID.
		</t>
		<t hangText="B2b">
		  Each service provided by a host has a globally unique,
		  hierarchical character-string identifier to which the
		  locators are attached.  Clients initiating communication
		  with that service negotiate a numeric SID which is unique
		  only within the scope of that service.
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>
	    
	  <section title="Major criticisms">
	    <t>
	      <list style="numbers">
		<t>
		  This strategy is probably not compatible with UDP or TCP
		  though B1a/c could be compatible with IPv6's layer 3. The
		  replacement layer-4/5 protocols should also be coaxable
		  to run on top of IPv4's layer 3 in the not-yet-upgraded
		  part of the network.
		</t>
		<t>
		  How do firewalls work if the locators are constantly in
		  flux in B1a?
		</t>
		<t>
		  How is theft of service avoided in B1b?
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>
	</section>

	<section title="Strategy C">
	  <t>
	    Suppress distant routes by aggregating them into sets expected
	    to be available in a given direction. Because locator reachability
	    info is not flooded, the routing tables each router must deal
	    with are relatively small.
	  </t>
	  <section title="Variants">
	    <t>
	      <list style="hanging">
		<t hangText="C1">
		  Aggregate locators based on geography.  All nodes within
		  some geographic boundary are assigned the same
		  locator. Routers move packets to any adjacent router
		  deemed to be "closer" to the locator in question.
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>
	  
	  <section title="Major criticisms">
	    <t>
	      No one has been able to construct a proposal under strategy C
	      without introducing constraints that are fundamentally
	      incompatible with the Internet's economic model. For example,
	      geographic aggregation has been shown to have uncorrectable
	      theft-of-service anomalies in networks as small as 8
	      autonomous systems and two geographic areas.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      <!-- Added by tli -->
	      Fundamentally, geographic aggregation requires that there be
	      a per-region interconnect that functions as the deaggregation
	      point for the region's traffic.  Funding such an interconnect
	      and compelling the affected ISPs to participate in the
	      interconnect requires external third party coercive controls.
	    </t>
	  </section>
	</section>
 
	<section anchor="StrategyD" title="Strategy D">
	  <t>
	    Use plain old BGP for the RIB. Algorithmically compress the FIB
	    in each router.
	  </t>
	  <section title="Variants">
	    <t>
	      <list style="hanging">
		<t hangText="D1a">
		  Aggregate any adjacent routes that have the same next hop.
		</t>
		<t hangText="D1b">
		  Insert a /0 route into the FIB which goes to the most
		  popular next hop for all the routes in the RIB. Step to the
		  /1 level. For each /1, if most of the routes in the RIB
		  within that /1 go to a different next hop than the longest
		  route above (the /0 route), add that /1 route to the
		  FIB. Step to the /2 level. Repeat until all routes in the
		  RIB go to the correct next hop in the FIB. Unrouted space
		  is treated as "don't care": it will route wherever the
		  algorithm happens to drop it and will rely on the TTL to
		  take packets off the network.
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>
	  <section title="Major criticisms">
	    <t>
	      <list style="numbers">
		<t>
		  The RIB can grow to up to an order of magnitude larger
		  than the FIB before it hits the wall too. One order of
		  magnitude doesn't gain us multihoming for small
		  office/home office sites.
		</t>
		<t>
		  FIBs towards the edge should aggregate well with this
		  strategy but there's no evidence to support a conclusion
		  that they'd aggregate well deep in the core.
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>
	</section> 

	<section anchor="StrategyE" title="Strategy E">
	  <t>
	    Make no routing architecture changes. Instead, create a billing
	    system through which the ISPs running core routers are paid by
	    the ISPs announcing prefixes. Let economics suppress growth to
	    a survivable level.
	  </t>

	  <section title="Variants">
	    <t>
	      <list style="hanging">
		<t hangText="E1a">
		  Everybody pays the RIRs. the RIRs pay the router
		  operators.
		</t>
		<t hangText="E1b">
		  Private negotiation between parties.
		</t>
		<t hangText="E1c">
		  Assisted private negotiation where router operators can
		  offer standardized contracts to carry prefixes and prefix
		  announcers can accept groups of identical contracts via
		  an automated third-party payment system moving funds
		  between the two easily.
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>
	  <section title="Major criticisms">
	    <t>
	      <list style="numbers">
		<t>
		  If it could be done without creating massive boondoggle,
		  why hasn't it been done already?  This has been discussed
		  previously and there are no obvious mechanisms to put
		  such a system in place without having a central authority
		  for the Internet.
		</t>
		<t>
		  This means giving up on a solution that genuinely enables
		  users and accepting one that merely keeps the Internet
		  viable.
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>
	</section>

	<section anchor="StrategyF" title="Strategy F">
	  <t>
	    Do nothing. (See <xref target="RFC1887"/> Section 4.4.1)
	  </t>

	  <section title="Major criticisms">
	    <t>
	      It costs "everybody else" a grand total of at least $6000 per
	      year for each prefix you announce. <xref target="BGPCost"/>
	      When we give away that $6000 of value for free, it inevitably
	      creates a "tragedy of the commons" problem.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      <!--- Added by tli -->
	      Given that the research group is chartered to 'do something',
	      this alternative does not fit within the charter.
	    </t>
	  </section>
	</section>

	<section anchor="StrategyG" title="Strategy G">
	  <t>
	    Change the topology so that all hosts attach to only one ISP
	    using IPv6 and the ISP's single set of provider assigned
	    addresses. <!-- tli: The following is incorrect. --> (Actual
	    result of <xref target="RFC1887"/> Section 4.4.3)
	  </t>
	  <section title="Major criticisms">
	    <t>
	      This strategy wasn't accepted by the operations community
	      because the IPv6 architecture makes renumbering every bit as
	      hard as in IPv4 and the multihoming described in
	      <xref target="RFC1887"/> Section 4.4.3 does not appear to
	      actually work.
	      <!-- tli: I don't think that this was properly -->
	      <!-- understood.  -->
	    </t>
	  </section>
	</section>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Recommendations">
      <section title="No manual renumbering of end hosts">
	<t>
	  There is clear consensus in the group that renumbering of sites
	  must not require manual intervention on a per-host basis.  This
	  does not scale adequately from a management cost structure.  This
	  effectively eliminates solutions that require that hosts have
	  only a single locator and renumber on topological changes, or if
	  hosts maintain multiple locators manually.
	</t>
	<t>
	  This implies that <xref target="Mechanism:Transport"> transport
	  solutions </xref> are unacceptable unless coupled with another
	  mechanism that would automate the distribution and management of
	  host renumbering, which appears to be a major undertaking all on
	  its own.  Further, variants of <xref target="StrategyB">Strategy
	  B</xref> that require manual locator assignment are similarly
	  unacceptable, as are solutions that do not significantly change
	  existing host behavior, such as
	  <xref target="StrategyD">Strategy
	  D</xref>, <xref target="StrategyE">Strategy
	  E</xref>, <xref target="StrategyF">Strategy F</xref>,
	  and <xref target="StrategyG">Strategy G</xref>. 
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Future progress">
	<t>
	  The RRG should continue to prune the solution space presented
	  here, attempting to find the overall maximally acceptable
	  solution within the bounds and constraints that have been
	  presented.  Whenever possible the research group will continue to
	  discuss architectural concepts and make architectural
	  recommendations rather than becoming embroiled in detailed
	  engineering implementation discussions.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The RRG should present a final recommendation by March, 2010.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
	This document represents a small portion of the overall work
	product of the Routing Research Group, who have developed all of
	these architectural approaches and many specific proposals within
	this solution space.
      </t>
      <t>
	In particular, Bill Herrin has been instrumental in constructing
	his <xref target="Herrin">taxonomy</xref>, with the input of the
	entire community.  This has been pivotal in helping to focus
	the discussions of the group.  We would also like to thank Joel
	Halpern for his insights and comments.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no requests to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>All solutions are required to provide security that is at least as
      strong as the existing Internet routing and addressing architecture.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

      &I-D.narten-radir-problem-statement;
      &I-D.irtf-rrg-design-goals;
      &RFC1887;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="BGPCost"
		 target="http://bill.herrin.us/network/bgpcost.html">
	<front>
	  <title>What does a BGP Route cost?</title>

	  <author initials="W." surname="Herrin">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	</front>
      </reference>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
