<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc colonspace='yes' ?>
<?rfc comments='yes' ?>
<?rfc inline='no' ?>

<rfc docName="DOCNAME"
     category="std"
     ipr="full3978"
     updates="3261"
>
<front>

<title abbrev="SIP EKU">
 Using Extended Key Usage (EKU) for Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)
 X.509 Certificates</title>

<author initials= "S." surname="Lawrence" fullname="Scott Lawrence">
  <organization>Bluesocket Inc.</organization>
  <address>
   <postal>
    <street>10 North Ave.</street>
    <city>Burlington</city> 
    <region>MA</region> <code>01803</code>
    <country>USA</country>
   </postal>
   <phone>+1 781 229 0533</phone>
   <email>slawrence@bluesocket.com</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials="V.K." surname="Gurbani" fullname="Vijay K. Gurbani">
 <organization>Bell Laboratories, Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
 <address>
  <postal>
   <street>2701 Lucent Lane</street>
   <street>Room 9F-546</street>
   <city>Lisle</city>
   <region>IL</region>
   <code>60532</code>
   <country>USA</country>
  </postal>
  <phone>+1 630 224-0216</phone>
  <email>vkg@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
 </address>
</author>

<date month="MONTH" day="DAY" year="YEAR" />

<area>Realtime Applications and Infrastructure</area>
<workgroup>SIP WG</workgroup>
<keyword>I-D</keyword>
<keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>This memo documents an extended key usage (EKU) X.509 certificate extension
for identifying the holder of a certificate as authoritative for a Session
Initiation Protocol (SIP) service in the domain named by the DNS name in 
the certificate.</t>
</abstract> 

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Terminology" >
<section title="Key Words">
<t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
"SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>. </t>
</section>

<section title="Abstract syntax notation">
<t>
All X.509 certificate <xref target="CCITT.X509.1988">X.509</xref>
extensions are defined using ASN.1 <xref target="CCITT.X680.1994">X.680
</xref>,<xref target="ITU.X690.1994">X.690</xref>.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Problem statement">

<t>Consider the SIP <xref target="RFC3261"/> trapezoid shown in <xref 
target="sip-trapezoid"/>.</t>

<figure anchor="sip-trapezoid" title="SIP Trapezoid">
 <artwork><![CDATA[

   proxyA.example.com ------------ proxyB.example.net
          |                           |
          |                           |
          |                           |
          |                         +---+
        0---0                       |   |
         /-\                        |___|
        +---+                      /    /
                                  +----+
   alice@example.com          bob@example.net

 ]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>Assume that alice@example.com creates an INVITE for bob@example.net; her 
user agent routes the request to some proxy in her domain, example.com.
Suppose also that example.com is a large organization that 
maintains several SIP proxies, and normal resolution rules cause her 
INVITE to be sent to an outbound proxy proxyA.example.com, which then 
uses <xref target="RFC3263">RFC 3263</xref> resolution and finds that 
proxyB.example.net is a valid proxy for example.net that uses TLS.  
proxyA.example.com requests a TLS connection to proxyB.example.net, and 
each presents a certificate to authenticate that connection.  This is
the basic mutual authentication model explored in depth in <xref target=
"I-D.domain-certs"/>.</t>

<t>However, there arise certain cases where one SIP proxy needs to know
whether it has reached an authoritative proxy in target SIP domain.  For
instance, billing transactions may be triggered when an authoritative SIP 
proxy in one domain sends messages to its equivalent in another domain.
In <xref target="sip-trapezoid"/>, proxyA.example.com performs certain DNS
queries to arrive at proxyB.example.net.  Because of the answers to the
DNS queries, proxyA has a certain expectation that proxyB is a valid
proxy in the example.net domain and is authorized to receive inbound
requests targeted to that domain.</t>

<t>However, the problem for proxyB is different; it is presented with a
connection from a specific host, but what it needs to determine is whether
or not that connection can be treated as coming from a particular SIP
domain.  If it receives a certificate that contains only the name
proxyA.example.com, then it cannot determine that proxyA is authorized to
act as a SIP outbound proxy for example.com, because example.com may
use different systems for inbound messages so SIP DNS resolution of
example.com may not lead to proxyA.example.com (if this is the case,
proxyB should not reuse this connection if it needs to send a request
to example.com).  The certificate usage in SIP should not require that
every outbound proxy for a domain must also be an inbound proxy for
that domain, but should provide for certificate based binding of the
SIP domain name to a particular connection.</t>

<t>Thus, there is a need for an extra attribute that allows a proxy to
know that its peer is an authorized proxy for that domain.  This memo
discusses such an attribute as part of the X.509 certificate exchanged
by the proxies when a TLS connection is first established.</t>

</section> <!-- Problem statement -->

<section title="Restricting usage to SIP" anchor="sipusage">

<t>This memo defines a certificate profile for binding a SIP
domain name to an entity.  A SIP domain name is frequently textually 
identical to the same DNS name used for other purposes.  For example, the DNS 
name example.com may serve as a SIP domain name, an email domain name, and 
web service name.  Since these different services within a single organization 
might be administered independently and hosted separately, it should be 
possible to create a certificate that binds the DNS name to its usage as a 
SIP domain name without creating the implication that the usage is also valid 
for some other purpose.  <xref target="RFC3280">RFC 3280</xref> section 
4.2.1.13 defines a mechanism for this purpose: an "Extended Key Usage" 
attribute.  Certificates whose purpose is to bind a SIP domain 
identity without binding other non-SIP identities MUST include an 
id-kp-SIPdomain attribute.
</t>

<section title="Extended Key Usage values for SIP domains">
  <t>
    <xref target="RFC3280">RFC 3280</xref> specifies the EKU
    X.509 certificate Extension for use in the Internet.  The 
    extension indicates one or more purposes for which the certified public 
    key may be used.  The EKU extension can be used in conjunction with 
    the key usage extension, which indicates how the public key in the 
    certificate may be used, in a more basic cryptographic way.
  </t>
  <figure>
    <preamble>
      The EKU extension syntax is repeated here for
      convenience:
    </preamble>
    <artwork>
      ExtKeyUsageSyntax  ::=  SEQUENCE SIZE (1..MAX) OF KeyPurposeId

      KeyPurposeId  ::=  OBJECT IDENTIFIER
    </artwork>
  </figure>
  <t>
    This specification defines the KeyPurposeId id-kp-sipDomain. Inclusion
    of this KeyPurposeId in a certificate indicates that any DNS Subject
    names in the certificate are intended to identify the holder as
    authoritative for a SIP service in the domain named by the
    subjectAltName values.  Whether or not to include this restriction is
    up to the certificate issuer, but if it is included, it MUST be marked
    as critical so that implementations that do not understand it will not
    accept the certificate for any other purpose.
  </t>

  <figure>
    <artwork>
      id-kp  OBJECT IDENTIFIER  ::=
         { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
           security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) 3 }

      id-kp-sipDomain  OBJECT IDENTIFIER  ::=  { id-kp VALUE-TBD }
    </artwork>
  </figure>

  <t>See <xref target='using-eku'/> for how the presence of an
  id-kp-sipDomain value affects the interpretation of the certificate.</t>

</section>

</section> <!-- problem-mutual -->

<section title="Using the SIP EKU in a certificate" anchor="using-eku">

<t>Section 7.1 of <xref target="I-D.domain-certs"/> contains two steps
for finding an identity (or a set of identities) in an X.509 certificate.
In order to determine whether a SIP proxy is authoritative for its
domain, implementations MUST perform the step given below first, and
then proceed with the steps in Section 7.1 of 
<xref target="I-D.domain-certs"/>.
</t>

<t>The Extended Key Usage value(s), if any, MUST be examined to determine
whether or not the certificate is valid for use in SIP:

<list style='symbols'>

  <t>If the certificate does not contain any EKU values (the Extended Key
  Usage extension does not exist), it is a matter of local policy whether
  or not to accept the certificate for use as a SIP certificate.</t>

  <t>If the certificate contains the id-kp-sipDomain EKU extension, then
  the certificate MUST be accepted as valid for use as a SIP
  certificate.</t>

  <t>If the certificate does not contain the id-kp-sipDomain EKU value, but
  does contain the id-kp-anyExtendedKeyUsage EKU value, it is a matter of
  local policy whether or not to accept it for use as a SIP
  certificate.</t>

  <t>If the certificate does not contain the id-kp-sipDomain EKU value, but
  does contain either the id-kp-serverAuth or id-kp-clientAuth EKU values,
  it is a matter of local policy whether or not to accept it for use as a
  SIP certificate.</t>

  <t>If EKU extension exists but does not contain any of the
  id-kp-sipDomain, id-kp-anyExtendedKeyUsage, id-kp-serverAuth, or
  id-kp-clientAuth EKU values, then the certificate MUST NOT be accepted as
  valid for use as a SIP certificate.</t>

</list>
</t>

</section> <!-- using-eku -->

<section title="Guidelines for a Certification Authority" anchor="ca">

<t>The procedures and practices employed by the certification authority
MUST ensure that the correct values for the EKU extension and subjectAltName 
are inserted in each certificate that is issued.  For certificates that
indicate authority over a SIP domain, but not over services other than
SIP, certificate authorities MUST include the id-kp-sipDomain EKU 
extension.</t>

</section> <!-- ca -->

<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec-cons">

<t>This memo defines an EKU X.509 certificate extension that enables
the holder of a certificate to be authoritative for a SIP service
belonging to an autonomous domain.  Relying parties may execute applicable
policies (such as those related to billing) on receiving a certificate
with the id-kp-sipDomain EKU value.  An id-kp-sipDomain EKU value
does not introduce any new security or privacy concerns.  At the very most,
it simply allows the relying party to know that the holder of the certificate
is authoritative for the SIP service in a certain domain.  In the absence
of the id-kp-sipDomain EKU value, this information can be collected over
time by a peer in any case.</t>

</section> <!-- Security Considerations -->

<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-cons">

<!-- This text is taken from rfc5055, S10. -->

<t>The id-kp-sipDomain purpose requires an object idenitifier (OID).
The objects are defined in an arc delegated by IANA to the PKIX 
working group.  No further action is necessary by IANA.</t>

</section> <!-- iana-cons -->

<section title="Acknowledgments">

<t>The following IETF contributors provided substantive input to this
document: Jeroen van Bemmel, Michael Hammer, Cullen Jennings, Paul Kyzivat,
Derek MacDonald, Dave Oran, Jon Peterson, Eric Rescorla, Jonathan
Rosenberg, Russ Housley, and Stephen Kent.</t>

<t>Sharon Boyen and Trevor Freeman reviewed the document and facilitated 
the discussion on id-kp-anyExtendedKeyUsage, id-kpServerAuth and 
id-kp-ClientAuth purposes in certificates.</t>

</section>

</middle>  

<back>

<references title= "Normative References" >

<reference anchor="RFC2119">
 <front>
  <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
  <author initials="S." surname="Bradner">
    <organization/></author>
  <date month="March" year="1997"/>
 </front>
 <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
 <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC3261">
 <front>
  <title>SIP: Session Initiation Protocol</title>
  <author initials="J." surname="Rosenberg">
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="H." surname="Schulzrinne">
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <author initials='G.' surname='Camarillo'>
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <author initials='A.' surname='Johnston'>
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <author initials='J.' surname='Peterson'>
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <author initials='R.' surname='Sparks'>
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <author initials='M.' surname='Handley'>
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <author initials='E.' surname='Schooler'>
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <date month="June"  year="2002"/>
 </front>
 <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3261"/>
 <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3261.txt"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC3280">
 <front>
  <title>Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure Certificate and
  Certificate Revocation List (CRL) Profile</title>
  <author initials="R." surname="Housley">
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="W." surname="Polk">
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="W." surname="Ford">
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="D." surname="Solo">
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <date year='2002' month='April' />
</front>
 <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3280"/>
 <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3280.txt"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="CCITT.X509.1988">
  <front>
    <title>Information Technology - Open Systems Interconnection - The Directory: Authentication Framework</title>
    <author>
      <organization>International International Telephone and Telegraph
      Consultative Committee</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="November" year="1988" />
  </front>

  <seriesInfo name="CCITT" value="Recommendation X.509" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="CCITT.X680.1994">
  <front>
    <title>Specification of Abstract Syntax Notation One (ASN.1): Specification of Basic Notation</title>
    <author>
      <organization>International International Telephone and Telegraph
      Consultative Committee</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="July" year="1994" />
  </front>

  <seriesInfo name="CCITT" value="Recommendation X.680" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="ITU.X690.1994">
  <front>
    <title>Information Technology - ASN.1 encoding rules: Specification of Basic Encoding Rules (BER), Canonical Encoding Rules (CER) and Distinguished Encoding Rules (DER)</title>
    <author>
      <organization>International Telecommunications Union</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="" year="1994" />
  </front>

  <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation X.690" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC3263">
 <front>
  <title>Session Initiation Protocol (SIP): Location SIP Servers</title>
  <author initials="J." surname="Rosenberg">
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="H." surname="Schulzrinne">
   <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <date month="June" year="2002"/>
 </front>
 <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3263"/>
 <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3263.txt"/>
</reference>

</references>

<references title= "Informative References" >

<reference anchor="I-D.domain-certs">
 <front>
  <title>Domain Certificates in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)</title>
  <author initials="V." surname="Gurbani"><organization/></author>
  <author initials="S." surname="Lawrence"><organization/></author>
  <author initials="A." surname="Jeffrey"><organization/></author>
  <date month="November" year="2007"/>
 </front>
 <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-sip-domain-certs-00.txt"/>
 <format type="TXT"
 target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-sip-domain-certs-00.txt"/>
</reference>
</references>

<section title="ASN.1 Module" anchor="asn1">

  <figure>
    <artwork>
   SIPDomainCertExtn
     { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
       security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) id-mod(0)
       id-mod-sip-domain-extns2007(VALUE-TBD) }

   DEFINITIONS IMPLICIT TAGS ::=
   BEGIN

   -- OID Arcs

   id-pe  OBJECT IDENTIFIER  ::=
      { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
        security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) 1 }

   id-kp  OBJECT IDENTIFIER  ::=
      { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
        security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) 3 }

   id-aca  OBJECT IDENTIFIER  ::=
      { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
        security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) 10 }

   -- Extended Key Usage Values

   id-kp-sipDomain  OBJECT IDENTIFIER  ::=  { id-kp VALUE-TBD }

   END
    </artwork>
  </figure>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
