<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="no"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-atlas-bryant-shand-lf-timers-04"
     ipr="full3978">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Abbreviated Title">Synchronisation of Loop Free Timer
    Values</title>

    <author fullname="Alia K, Atlas" initials="A" surname="Atlas">
      <organization>BT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <code></code>
        </postal>

        <email>akatlas@bt.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stewart Bryant" initials="S" surname="Bryant">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>250, Longwater Ave,</street>

          <city>Reading,</city>

          <code>RG2 6GB,</code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>stbryant@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mike Shand" initials="M" surname="Shand">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>250, Longwater Ave,</street>

          <city>Reading,</city>

          <code>RG2 6GB,</code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2008" />

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This draft describes a mechanism that enables routers to agree on a
      common convergence delay time for use in loop-free convergence.<vspace
      blankLines="2" /></t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Most of the loop-free convergence mechanisms <xref format="default"
      target="I-D.bryant-shand-lf-conv-frmwk"></xref> require one or more
      convergence delay timers that MUST have a duration that is consistent
      throughout the routing domain. This time is the worst case time that any
      router will take to calculate the new topology, and to make the
      necessary changes to the FIB. The timer is used by the routers to know
      when it is safe to transition between the loop- free convergence
      states.</t>

      <t>The time taken by a router to complete each phase of the loop-free
      transition will be dependent on the size of the network and the design
      and implementation of the router. It can therefore be expected that the
      optimum delay will need to be tuned from time to time as the network
      evolves.</t>

      <t>Manual configuration of the timer is fraught for two reasons, firstly
      it is always difficult to ensure that the correct value is installed in
      all of the routers, and secondly, if any change is introduced into the
      network that results in a need to change the timer, for example due to a
      change in hardware or software version, then all of the routers need to
      be reconfigured to use the new timer value.</t>

      <t>It is therefore desirable that a means be provided by which the
      convergence delay timer can be automatically synchronized throughout the
      network.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Required Properties">
      <t>The timer synchronization mechanism MUST have the following
      properties: <list>
          <t>o The convergence delay time must be consistent amongst all
          routers that are converging on the new topology.</t>

          <t>o The convergence delay time must be the highest delay required
          by any router in the new topology.</t>

          <t>o The mechanism must increase the delay when a new router in
          introduced to the network that requires a higher delay than is
          currently in use.</t>

          <t>o When the router that had the longest delay requirements is
          removed from the topology, the convergence delay timer value must,
          within some reasonable time, be reduced to the longest delay
          required by the remaining routers.</t>

          <t>o It must be possible for a router to change the convergence
          delay timer value that it requires.</t>

          <t>o A router which is in multiple routing areas, or is running
          multiple routing protocols may signal a different loop-free
          convergence delay for each area, and for each protocol.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>How a router determines the time that it needs to execute each
      convergence phase is an implementation issue, and outside the scope of
      this specification. However a router that dynamically determines its
      proposed timer value must do so in such a way that it does not cause the
      synchronized value to continually fluctuate.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Mechanism  ">
      <t>The following mechanism is proposed.</t>

      <t>A new information element is introduced into the routing protocol
      that specifies the maximum time (in milliseconds) that the router will
      take to calculate the new topology and to update its FIB as a result of
      any topology change.</t>

      <t>When a topology change occurs, the largest convergence delay time
      required by any router in the new topology is used by the loop-free
      convergence mechanism.</t>

      <t>If a routing protocol message is issued that changes the convergence
      delay timer value, but does not change the topology, the new timer value
      MUST be taken into consideration during the next loop-free transition,
      but MUST NOT instigate a loop-free transition.</t>

      <t>If a routing protocol message is issued that changes the convergence
      timer value and changes the topology, a loop-free transition is
      instigated and the new timer value is taken into consideration.</t>

      <t>The loop-free convergence mechanism should specify the action to be
      taken if a timer change (only) message and a topology change message are
      independently generated during the hold-off time. A suitable action
      would be to take the same action that would be taken if two uncorrelated
      topology changes occurred in the network.</t>

      <t>All routers that support loop-free convergence MUST advertise a
      loop-free convergence delay time. The loop-free convergence mechanism
      MUST specify the action to be taken if a router does not advertise a
      convergence delay time.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Details">
      <t>This section describes the protocol changes needed to implement the
      timer synchronization function.</t>

      <section title="ISIS"></section>

      <t>The controlled convergence timer value will be carried in a new
      Sub-TLV of the capability TLV as defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-isis-caps"></xref> .</t>

      <t>This draft defines one such SUB-TLV where the type is for the
      worst-case FIB compute/install time, the value is 16 bits and is
      specified in milliseconds; this gives a max value of about 65s.</t>

      <t>The format of the Sub-TLV is as shown below.<list>
          <t>Sub-TLV FIB-Convergence Timer</t>

          <t>TYPE: &lt;TBD&gt;</t>

          <t>Length: 2 octets</t>

          <t>Value: &lt;16-bit timer value expressed in milliseconds&gt;</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This MUST be carried in a capability TLV with the S-bit set to zero
      (indicating that it MUST NOT be leaked between levels).</t>

      <section title="OSPF"></section>

      <t>A new type-10 opaque LSA (the controlled convergence LSA) will be
      defined as part of OSPF changed needed to define the loop-free
      convergence mechanism. This will consist of one or more TLVs. This draft
      defines one such TLV where the type is for the worst-case FIB
      compute/install time, the value is 16 bits and is specified in
      milliseconds; this gives a max value of about 65s.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA considerations">
      <t>There will be IANA considerations that arise as a result of this
      draft, but they are not yet determined.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>If an abnormally large timer value is proposed by a router, the there
      is a danger that the loop-free convergence process will take an
      excessive time. If during that time the routing protocol signals the
      need for another transition, the loop-free transition will be abandoned
      and the default best case (traditional) convergence mechanism used.</t>

      <t>It is still undesirable that the routers select a convergence delay
      time that has an excessive value. The maximum value that can be
      specified in the LSP/LSA is limited through the use of a 16 bit field to
      about 65 seconds. When sufficient implementation experience is gained,
      an architectural constant will be specified which sets the upper limit
      of the convergence delay timer.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-isis-caps'?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.bryant-shand-lf-conv-frmwk'?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>