<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC3987 PUBLIC '' 
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3987.xml'>  

<!ENTITY RFC4395 PUBLIC '' 
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4395.xml'>  

<!ENTITY RFC5234 PUBLIC '' 
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml'>  

]>
<!-- John, if you want to make some modification in Reference which is IETF RFC, change here and add &RFC number in Reference tag at the end-->


<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-larmouth-oid-iri-00" ipr="full3978">
<!-- John, if you want to chage file name, change here -->
<front>
  <title abbrev="IRI/URI Namespace for International OIDs">
    An IRI/URI Namespace for International Object Identifiers (OIDs)
  </title>
  <author fullname="John Larmouth" initials="J." surname="Larmouth">
    <organization abbre="ISO/IEC JTC 1/SC 6/WG 9">ISO/IEC JTC 1/SC 6/WG 9</organization>
    <address>
      <email>j.larmouth@btinternet.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  <author fullname="Olivier Dubuisson" initials="O." surname="Dubuisson">
    <organization abbre="ITU-T SG17 ASN.1 &amp; OID">ITU-T SG17 ASN.1 &amp; OID</organization>
    <address>
      <email>olivier.dubuisson@orange-ftgroup.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  
  <date month="November" year="2008"></date>
<!-- John, you have to change here for month and yere of submission. -->
  <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>
<!-- John, you have to change here for target working group. -->

  <abstract>
    <t>This internet draft defines the IRI/URI scheme for International Object Identifiers.
  The syntax and semantics of the IRI is specified below using the International Object Identifier
 tree specified in [ITU-T X.660].</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<!-- John, you want to make sub section 2.n unsder section 2, juns put section tag with in the section tag for section 2. -->
<!-- John, during the converting from xml to txt, line break(enter key) will be ignored. -->

  <section title="Introduction">
    <t>The International Object Identifier tree provides a hierarchically based identification scheme for objects/resources,
 using almost all Unicode/ISO 10646 characters to identify arcs in the tree.  The first identifier in the sequence can be the name
 of any standards body or any other organization that requests an unambiguous identification of that organization, with subsequent
 identifications in the hierarchy being allocated by that organization.  The OID tree has been in existence since about 1984 in a
 numerical form, but the ability to have arcs identified by Unicode labels to identify arcs of the International Object Identifier
 tree was only standardized in 2008.</t>

<!-- Added by JL 7 Nov 2008 --> 
   <t>There are just under 100,000 allocated Object Identifiers that are recorded in the OID Repository at http://www.oid-info.com </t> 

   <t>This form of URI/IRI commences with "oid:/" and is followed by a series of Unicode labels separated by the SOLIDUS '/' character,
 identifying a node in the hierarchical International Object Identifier tree.</t>

    <t>NOTE - The SOLIDUS '/' character is not permitted in Unicode labels.</t>

    <t>An IRI can contain most of the Unicode characters, and in particular can contain all the characters allowed in a Unicode label.
 A URI is restricted to the ASCII character set, but [RFC3987], clause 3.1 specifies the conversion of the characters allowed in an IRI
 into the characters allowed in a URI, enabling both an IRI and a URI to carry the same semantics for the identification.  This mapping
 is an integral part of the "oid" URI/IRI scheme. This enables names based on the Unicode labels in the International OID tree to be used
 wherever an IRI or a URI is required.</t>
  </section>

  <section title="Information to be provided to IANA for registration">

    <section title="Declared registrant of the namespace">
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="J. Larmouth"></t>
          <t hangText="Rapporteur, ITU-T SG17 ASN.1 &amp; OID"></t>
          <t hangText="Convenor, ISO/IEC JTC 1/SC 6/WG 9"></t>
          <t hangText="International Telecommunication Union (ITU)"></t>
          <t hangText="Place des Nations"></t>
          <t hangText="CH-1211 Geneva 20"></t>
          <t hangText="Switzerland"></t>
          <t hangText="E-mail: tsbmail@itu.int"></t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="URI scheme name">
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="oid"></t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  
    <section title="Status">
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="permanent"></t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  
    <section title="URI/IRI scheme syntax">
      <t>This sub-clause uses the ABNF notation commonly used in IETF RFCs (see [RFC 5234]). An IRI in the "oid" scheme is syntactically
 the ABNF construct "oidiri" defined as follows (with the semantics specified in 2.5), and with no white-space between lexical items:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="oidiri = &quot;oid:/&quot; firstarcid subsequentarcid"></t>
          <t hangText="firstarcid = unicodelabel"></t>
          <t hangText="subsequentarcid = &quot;/&quot; unicodelabel [susequentarcid]"></t>
          <t hangText="unicodelabel = iunreserved"></t>
        </list>
      </t>      
      <t>When used as a URI, the transformations specified in [RFC 3987], clause 3.1 are applied.</t>
    </section>
  
    <section title="URI/IRI scheme semantics">
      <t>The "firstarcid" is required to be a Unicode label assigned to one of the arcs from the root of the International OID tree
 specified in [ITU-T X.660] (including long arcs) that identifies a node in the International OID tree.</t>

      <t>The next "unicodelabel" in the "subsequentarcid" is required to be a Unicode label that identifies an arc from that node to a lower level node.</t>
   
     <t>This repeats until the final Unicode label identifies an arc, and hence a node of the International OID tree, that is the referenced resource.</t>

      <t>NOTE - The last identified node is not necessarily a leaf of the tree, but is the identified resource.</t>
    </section>
  
    <section title="Encoding considerations">
      <t>The internationalized resource identifier is specified as an abstract sequence of Unicode characters.  The encoding of those characters
 depends on the specification of the protocol in which they are carried, but will normally be UTF8.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Applications/protocols that use this scheme">
      <t>This scheme can be used by any specification requiring an IRI or URI based on the international OID tree to identify an object.</t>
    </section>
  
    <section title="Interoperability considerations">
      <t>Matching rules are based on exact equality of the sequence of abstract Unicode characters forming the IRI.
  There are no other known interoperability issues.</t>
    </section>
   
    <section title="Security considerations">
      <t>There are no security implications in the use of this IRI scheme.</t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title=" Acknowledgements">
    <t>This document is a product of the joint ISO/IEC and ITU-T ASN.1 &amp; OID group. All members of the group are thanked for their
 efforts in this work.</t>
  </section>

</middle>

<back>
  <references title="Normative References">
    <reference anchor="ITU-T X.660">
      <front>
        <title>ITU-T X.660 | ISO/IEC 9834-1: Procedures for the operation of OSI Registration Authorities:
 General procedures and top arcs of the International Object Identifier tree</title>
      </front>
    </reference>
  </references>

  <references title="Informative References">
<!-- John, if you made some modification in Reference which is IETF RFC, add &RFC number here -->
    &RFC3987;
    &RFC4395;
    &RFC5234;
  </references>
</back>

</rfc>
