<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='../rfc2629xslt/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
    <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
    <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
    <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
    <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
    <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "../rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3024 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3024.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3344 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3344.xml'>
    <!ENTITY nemo PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base-08.xml'>
]>
<rfc category="std" ipr="full3978" docName="draft-ietf-mip4-nemov4-fa-02.txt">
    <front>
        <title>FA extensions to NEMOv4 Base</title>
        <author initials="G." surname="Tsirtsis" fullname="George Tsirtsis">
            <organization>Qualcomm</organization>
            <address>
                <phone>+908-443-8174</phone>
                <email>tsirtsis@googlemail.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="V." surname="Park" fullname="Vincent Park">
            <organization>Qualcomm</organization>
            <address>
                <phone>+908-947-7084</phone>
                <email>vpark@qualcomm.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="V." surname="Narayanan" fullname="Vidya Narayana">
            <organization>Qualcomm</organization>
            <address>
                <phone>+858-845-2483</phone>
                <email>vidyan@qualcomm.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="K." surname="Leung" fullname="Kent Leung">
            <organization>Cisco</organization>
            <address>
                <phone>+408-526-5030</phone>
                <email>kleung@cisco.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date month="February" year="2008"/>
        <abstract>
            <t>The base NEMOv4 specification defines extensions to Mobile IPv4
                for mobile networks. NEMOv4 extensions are defined for use only
                by the mobile node and the home agent. This specification
                introduces extensions for NEMO support on the foreign agent.</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Requirements notation">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
                NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
                in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Acknowledgments">
            <t>Alexandru Petrescu co-authored with Vidya (one of the co-authors
                of this I-D) an older document which included some of the
                mechanisms described herein.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <section title="Background">
                <t>The base NEMOv4 specification <xref
                        target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/> defines extensions
                    to <xref target="RFC3344">MIPv4</xref> for mobile networks.
                    NEMOv4 extensions are defined for use only by the mobile
                    node and the home agent so there are no extensions defined
                    for NEMOv4 support by foreign agent.</t>
                <t>NEMOv4 solution <xref target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/>
                    defines:</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t> - When the co-located care-of address model is used,
                            traffic to/from the mobile network prefixes can be
                            sent over a bidirectional tunnel between the mobile
                            node’s care-of address and the home agent address.</t>
                        <t> - When the care-of address model is used, traffic
                            to/from the mobile network prefixes must be sent
                            over a bidirectional tunnel between the mobile’s
                            home address and the home agent address. This
                            results in double tunneling since traffic to the
                            mobile’s home address is encapsulated inside the
                            tunnel between the mobile node’s care-of address and
                            home agent address.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t> Extensions defined in this document allow the mobile node
                    and/or a foreign agent to indicate to the home agent what
                    address should be used for tunneling traffic to the mobile
                    network prefixes during registration. Thus, this
                    specification removes the need for double encapsulation when
                    a foreign agent is used.</t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section anchor="system" title="Extension Formats">
            <t>The following extension is defined according to this
                specification.</t>
            <section title="NEMOv4 Tunneling Extension">
                <t>A new skippable extension to the Mobile IPv4 header in
                    accordance to the short extension format of <xref
                        target="RFC3344">MIPv4</xref> is defined here.</t>
                <figure>
                    <preamble>The presence of this extension indicates that the
                        sender supports the NEMOv4 and the tunnel selection
                        extensions defined in this specification.</preamble>
                    <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |   Length      |    Sub-Type   |   Reserved    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                        </artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>Type</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t>TBA (Mobile Network Extension) (skippable type range
                            to be assigned by IANA) <xref
                                target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/>
                        </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t>Length</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t>4</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t>Sub-Type</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t>TBA (NEMOv4 Tunneling Extension)</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t>Reserved</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t>Set to 0 by the sender and ignored by the
                        receiver.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Mobile IP registrations">
            <section title="Registration Requests">
                <t>A mobile node that supports <xref
                        target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/> and this
                    specification MAY include exactly one NEMOv4 tunneling
                    extension when it uses the co-located care-of address mode.</t>
                <t> When the NEMOv4 tunneling extension is used by the mobile
                    node, it MUST be placed after the registration request
                    header and before the mobile – home authentication extension
                    so, it MUST be included in the computation of any
                    authentication extension.</t>
                <t> A foreign agent that supports this specification MAY include
                    a NEMOv4 tunneling extension defined in the specification in
                    a registration request when the care-of address mode of
                    operation is used.</t>
                <t> When the NEMOv4 tunneling extension is used by a foreign
                    agent it MUST be placed after the mobile – home
                    authentication extensions and before the foreign – home
                    authentication extension so it MUST be included in the
                    computation of the foreign – home authentication extension
                    when one exists.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Registration Reply">
                <t>A foreign agent that supports this specification MAY include
                    a NEMOv4 tunneling extension defined in the specification in
                    a registration reply message</t>
                <t> When a NEMOv4 tunneling extension is used by a home agent it
                    MUST be placed after the registration reply header and
                    before the mobile – home authentication extension so, it
                    must be included in the calculation of any authentication
                    extension.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Home Agent Considerations">
                <t>A home agent that supports the extensions in this
                    specification MUST act as in <xref
                        target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/> with the addition
                    to the tunneling mode selection defined below.</t>
                <t> Tunneling mode selection, for mobile network traffic,
                    depends on the following parameters in a valid registration
                    request:</t>
                <t> 1) Registration request is received with one or more Mobile
                    Network Extensions <xref target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"
                    />. A NEMOv4 tunneling extension is NOT included.</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t> All mobile network traffic MUST be tunneled by the
                            home agent to the registered home address of the
                            mobile. The home agent MUST NOT include a NEMOv4
                            tunneling extension in the registration reply and it
                            MUST be prepared to accept reverse tunneled packets
                            from the IPv4 home address of the mobile
                            encapsulating packets sent by the mobile node.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t> 2) Registration request is received with one or more Mobile
                    Network Extensions <xref target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"
                    />. A NEMOv4 tunneling extension is included.</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t> All mobile network traffic SHOULD be tunneled by the
                            home agent to the registered care-of address of the
                            mobile. In that case, the home agent SHOULD include
                            the NEMOv4 Tunneling extension in the registration
                            reply message and it MUST be prepared to accept
                            reverse tunneled packets from the care-of address of
                            the mobile encapsulating packets sent by the mobile
                            network. Alternatively, the home agent MAY ignore
                            the presence of the NEMOv4 Tunneling extension and
                            act as in case (1) above.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t> As defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/>,
                    for each mobile network extension included in a valid
                    registration request, a home agent that supports this
                    specification includes a corresponding mobile network
                    acknowledgement extension.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Foreign Agent Considerations">
                <t>When a foreign agent receives a registration request with
                        <xref target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/> extensions
                    it has the following options:</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t> Ignore the <xref target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"
                            /> extension(s). The registration request is
                            forwarded as is with no NEMOv4 Tunneling extension
                            to the home agent.</t>
                        <t> Attach a NEMOv4 tunneling extension to the
                            registration request sent to the home agent.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t> If the foreign agent sets the R flag included in the
                    mobility agent advertisement <xref target="RFC3344"
                    >MIPv4</xref> and a mobile client uses the co-located
                    address model, the foreign agent MUST NOT include a NEMOv4
                    tunneling extension in the registration request messages
                    sent from that mobile client.</t>
                <t> When a successful Registration Reply is received the foreign
                    agent MUST act as defined by <xref target="RFC3344"
                    >MIPv4</xref>. In addition to that and according to this
                    specification the foreign agent SHOULD check for a NEMOv4
                    Tunnel extension.</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t> If the NEMOv4 Tunnel extension is included then the
                            foreign agent MUST establish a bidirectional tunnel.
                            The tunnel endpoints are the care-of address of the
                            foreign agent and the address of the home agent. In
                            addition to setting up a bi-directional tunnel with
                            the home agent, the foreign agent locally
                            establishes forwarding information such that all
                            packets originated by the clients in the mobile
                            network, or originated by the mobile router itself
                            (i.e., packets with source address any address under
                            the registered prefixes for that mobile router) and
                            destined to any correspondent node whose address is
                            topologically correct outside the mobile network are
                            encapsulated through the bi-directional tunnel. Note
                            that registered prefixes are only the prefixes
                            accepted by Mobile Network Acknowledgement
                            Extensions, with Code field set to “0”, included in
                            the Registration Reply message.</t>
                        <t> If the NEMOv4 Tunnel extension is not included then
                            the foreign agent SHOULD operate as defined in <xref
                                target="RFC3344">MIPv4</xref> and <xref
                                target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/>.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Mobile Client Considerations">
                <t> A mobile router that supports the <xref
                        target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/> extensions may use
                    these extensions to register its mobile networks as defined
                    in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/>.</t>
                <t> The mobile client MAY include exactly one NEMOv4 tunneling
                    extension if it uses the co-located care-of address model,
                    if it wants to specifically request that packets to the
                    mobile network are tunneled to its co-located care-of
                    address. Note that if the mobile client uses the co-located
                    care-of address model but it does not include the NEMOv4
                    tunneling extension, according to <xref
                        target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/>, the home agent
                    MAY tunnel mobile network packets to the mobile client’s
                    home address.</t>
                <t>
                    <xref target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/> also defines the
                    mobile client processing when a registration reply is
                    received. In addition that what is defined in <xref
                        target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/>, the following
                    processing MUST be done by the mobile client according to
                    this specification.</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t>If NEMOv4 Tunnel extension is not included, the
                            mobile client MUST act as defined by <xref
                                target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/>
                        </t>
                        <t> If NEMOv4 Tunnel extension is included then the
                            mobile client MUST act as follows:</t>
                        <t>
                            <list>
                                <t> If the care-of address mode is used, the
                                    mobile client MUST be prepared to
                                    send/receive traffic from/to the mobile
                                    network on its interface natively, unless
                                    reverse tunnel has been negotiated in which
                                    case all traffic MUST be reverse tunneled
                                    according to <xref target="RFC3024"
                                    >REVTUN</xref>.</t>
                                <t> If the co-located care-of address mode is
                                    used, the mobile client MUST be prepared to
                                    send/receive packets from/to the mobile
                                    network over the bidirectional tunnel
                                    between the home agent address and its
                                    co-located care-of address.</t>
                            </list>
                        </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Disparate Address Space Support ">
                <t>
                    <xref target="RFC3344">MIPv4</xref> assumes that all the
                    entities involved have addresses within the same globally
                    unique space. In many deployment scenarios this is not the
                    case, either because of the use of private address space or
                    because of the use of public address space that is only
                    advertised in not advertised globally. The analysis and
                    suggestions on how to deal with such deployments included in
                    Appendix A of <xref target="RFC3024">REVTUN</xref>] apply in
                    this specification if the prefixes that a mobile node
                    successfully registers according to <xref
                        target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/> and this
                    specification are treated in the same way <xref
                        target="RFC3024">REVTUN</xref> treats the home address
                    of the mobile node.</t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>This specification operates in the security constraints and
                requirements of <xref target="RFC3344">MIPv4</xref> and <xref
                    target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/>.</t>
            <t> A foreign agent that supports this specification SHOULD perform
                ingress filtering on all the packets received from the mobile
                router prior to reverse tunneling them to the Home Agent. The
                foreign agent SHOULD drop any packets that do not have a source
                address belonging to one of the registered prefixes. For traffic
                coming from the home agent and if the foreign agent has included
                a NEMOv4 Tunneling extension in the registration request, the
                foreign agent MUST be prepared to accept encapsulated packets to
                the home address of a registered mobile router as well as to any
                address belonging to any of the registered prefixes for the same
                mobile router.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>This document has the following action for IANA.</t>
            <t>A new value needs to be allocated for the NEMOv4 Tunneling
                Extension defined in this document, from the number space of the
                Sub-Type for Mobile Network Extensions defined in <xref
                    target="I-D.ietf-mip4-nemo-v4-base"/>. </t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">&rfc2119; &rfc3024;
            &rfc3344; &nemo;</references>
    </back>
</rfc>
