<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-irtf-dtnrg-cbhe-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="CBHE">Compressed Bundle Header Encoding (CBHE)</title>

    <author fullname="Scott Burleigh" initials="S" surname="Burleigh">
      <organization>Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of
      Technology</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4800 Oak Grove Drive, m/s 301-490</street>

          <city>Pasadena</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>91109</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Scott.C.Burleigh@jpl.nasa.gov</email>
        <phone>+1 818 393 3353</phone>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="5" month="March" year="2009" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a convention for representing Delay-Tolerant
      Networking (DTN) Bundle Protocol (BP) endpoint identifiers in a
      compressed manner within the primary blocks of bundles.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document describes a convention for representing Delay-Tolerant
      Networking (DTN) Bundle Protocol (BP) <xref target="RFC5050" /> endpoint
      identifiers in a compressed manner within the primary blocks of
      bundles.</t>

      <t>Each DTN bundle's primary block contains four BP endpoint identifiers
      (EIDs), of which any two, any three, or even all four may be lexically
      identical: the endpoint identifiers of the source, the destination, the
      report-to endpoint, and the current custodian. Each EID is a Uniform
      Record Identifier (URI) as defined by <xref target="RFC3986" />.</t>

      <t>A degree of block compression is provided by the design of the
      primary block: the scheme names and scheme-specific parts of the four
      endpoints' IDs &ndash; up to eight NULL-terminated strings &ndash; are
      concatenated at the end of the block in a variable-length character
      array called a "dictionary", enabling each EID to be represented by a
      pair of integers indicating the offsets (within the dictionary) of the
      EID's scheme name and scheme-specific part. Duplicate strings may be
      omitted from the dictionary, so the actual number of concatenated
      NULL-terminated strings in the dictionary may be less than eight and two
      or more of the scheme name or scheme-specific part offsets in the block
      may have the same value. Moreover, the eight offsets in the primary
      block are encoded as self-delimiting numeric values (SDNVs), which
      shrink to fit the encoded values; when the total length of the
      dictionary is less than 127 bytes, all eight offsets can be encoded into
      just eight bytes.</t>

      <t>However, these strategems do not prevent the scheme names and
      scheme-specific parts themselves from being lengthy strings
      of ASCII text. It is therefore still possible for the length of a
      bundle's primary header to be a very large fraction of the total length
      of the bundle when the bundle's payload is relatively small, as is
      anticipated for a number of DTN applications such as space flight
      operations.</t>

      <t>The Compressed Bundle Header Encoding (CBHE) convention was developed
      to improve DTN transmission efficiency for such applications by further
      reducing the number of bytes used to express EIDs in the primary blocks
      of bundles.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Compression convention">
      <section title="Constraints">
        <t>Compressed Bundle Header Encoding (CBHE) is possible only when
        all endpoint IDs in the primary block of a given bundle are
	"CBHE-conformant".  Two forms of endpoint ID are CBHE-conformant:
	(a) the null endpoint ID "dtn:none" and (b) any endpoint ID whose
	scheme name is "dtn" and whose authority component is "cbhe.ccsds.org".
	</t>

	<t>The specification for URIs formed within the "dtn" scheme
	requires that the path component of each such URI that is
	characterized by authority component "cbhe.ccsds.org"
	be a path-absolute of the form /NODE_NUMBER.SERVICE_NUMBER.</t>

        <t>By convention, node number is a natural number that identifies
	a BP node.  In a spacecraft flight operations context, for example,
	spacecraft identifier might be used as node number.</t>

        <t>Node number must be an integer in the range 1 to (2^64 - 1).
	Node number zero is reserved for representation of the null endpoint
	ID in the compressed form described later in this specification;
	decompressing a compressed null EID must always yield the
	standard null endpoint ID URI "dtn:none".  Negative integers and
	integers larger than (2^64 - 1) cannot be compressed into the SDNVs
	that are used for representation of endpoint ID references in the
	primary blocks of bundles and therefore could not be compressed as
	described later.</t>

        <t>By convention, service number is a non-negative integer that
        functions as a de-multiplexing token.  When the protocol encapsulated
        within BP has its own de-multiplexing identifiers, the service number
        may function in a manner similar to that of the protocol number in an
        IP packet, characterizing the bundle payload; alternatively, the
        service number may function in a manner similar to that of the port
        number in a UDP datagram.  Service numbers enable inbound bundles'
        application data units to be de-multiplexed to instances of application
        functionality that are designed to process them, so that effective
        communication relationships can be developed between bundle producers
        and consumers.</t>

        <t>Service number zero is reserved for BP administrative traffic,
	i.e., custody signals and bundle status reports.  Service number
	must be zero whenever a CBHE-conformant EID is used as the source
	or destination EID of a custody signal.  Service number may be
	zero whenever a CBHE-conformant EID is used as the source or
	destination EID of a bundle status report.  Service number must not
	be negative or exceed (2^64 - 1) for the same reason that node number
	must not do so.</t>

	<t>For example, "dtn://cbhe.ccsds.org/9.37" would be a 
	CBHE-conformant endpoint ID.</t>

        <t>Conversion of a CBHE-conformant EID to and from a tuple of two
	integers is therefore straightforward.  This ease of conversion
	enables an array of integers to serve the same function as a
	dictionary of EID ASCII strings.</t>

	<t>Note, however, that CBHE decompression cannot faithfully recreate
	the dictionary of a compressed primary block from an array of
	integers unless the order of the endpoint ID reference strings in
	the dictionary of the original, uncompressed block is known.  (The
	bundle protocol specification does not require that the strings in
	the dictionary appear in any particular order and does not require
	that redundant strings be omitted from the dictionary.)  Therefore,
	a further precondition to CBHE block compression is that the endpoint
	ID reference strings in the dictionary of the bundle to be compressed
	must be as follows:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>The scheme name of the destination endpoint ID.</t>

            <t>The scheme-specific part of the destination endpoint ID.</t>

            <t>The scheme name of the source endpoint ID, if and only if
	    different from any prior string in the dictionary.</t>

            <t>The scheme-specific part of the source endpoint ID, if and
	    only if different from any prior string in the dictionary.</t>

            <t>The scheme name of the report-to endpoint ID, if and only if
	    different from any prior string in the dictionary.</t>

            <t>The scheme-specific part of the report-to endpoint ID, if and
	    only if different from any prior string in the dictionary.</t>

            <t>The scheme name of the current custodian endpoint ID, if and
	    only if different from any prior string in the dictionary.</t>

            <t>The scheme-specific part of the current custodian endpoint ID,
	    if and only if different from any prior string in the
	    dictionary.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Method">
        <t>When the constraints summarized above are met, the CBHE block
        compression method can be applied. In a CBHE-compressed primary block,
        the eight SDNVs that normally contain EIDs' offsets within the
        dictionary are instead used to contain the eight integer values listed
        below, in the order shown:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>The node number of the destination endpoint ID, or zero if
            the destination endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The service number of the destination endpoint ID, or zero if
            the destination endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The node number of the source endpoint ID, or zero if the
            source endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The service number of the source endpoint ID, or zero if the
            source endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The node number of the report-to endpoint ID, or zero if the
            report-to endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The service number of the report-to endpoint ID, or zero if the
            report-to endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The node number of the current custodian endpoint ID, or
            zero if the current custodian endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The constant BP administration service number zero.</t>
          </list>Further, the dictionary is omitted from the primary block and
        the primary block's dictionary length is set to zero.</t>

        <t>This compression method is applied at the convergence layer: the
        transmitting convergence-layer adaptation compresses the primary block
        as shown above.  Upon reception the receiving convergence-layer
        adaptation de-compresses the block by simply reversing the
        process.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Specification">
      <t>CBHE compression is a convergence-layer adaptation. It is opaque to
      bundle processing. It therefore has no impact on the interoperability of
      different Bundle Protocol implementations, but instead affects only the
      interoperability of different convergence layer adaptation
      implementations.</t>

      <t>Bundle Protocol convergence-layer adapters that conform to the CBHE
      specification must implement the following procedures.</t>

      <section title="Transmission">
        <t>When and only when required by the bundle protocol agent to
        transmit to some CBHE-conformant convergence-layer adapter a bundle
        whose primary block's endpoint IDs satisfy the constraints identified
        in section 2.1 above and whose extension blocks (if any) contain no
        citations of endpoint IDs that are contained in the primary block's
        dictionary, the convergence layer adapter may encode the primary block
        of the bundle in accordance with the CBHE compression convention
        described in section 2.2 above.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reception">
        <t>Upon receiving a bundle whose dictionary length is zero (and only
        in this circumstance), the convergence layer adapter must decode the
        primary block of the bundle in accordance with the CBHE compression
        convention described in section 2.2 above before delivering it to the
        bundle protocol agent.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no IANA considerations.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>CBHE introduces no new security considerations beyond those discussed
      in the DTN Bundle Protocol and Bundle Security Protocol
      specifications.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3986.xml"?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5050.xml"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
