<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

    <!ENTITY rfc3588 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" ipr="full3978" docName="draft-lior-diameter-classifier-01.txt">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="Diameter Classifier"> Diameter Claissifier </title>
        <author initials="A" surname="Lior" fullname="Avi Lior">
            <organization>Bridgewater Systems</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>303 Terry Fox Drive, Suite 500</street>
                    <city>Ottawa</city>
                    <region>Ontario</region>
                    <code/>
                    <country>Canada K2K 3J1</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>+1 613-591-6655</phone>
                <email>avi@bridgewatersystems.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="M." surname="Jones" fullname="Mark Jones">
            <organization>Bridgewater Systems</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>303 Terry Fox Drive, Suite 500</street>
                    <city>Ottawa</city>
					<region>Ontario</region>
					<code>K2K 3J1</code>
					<country>Canada</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>+1 613-591-6655</phone>
                <email>mark.jones@bridgewatersystems.com</email>
            </address>	
	    </author>
        <date month="February" year="2008"/>
        <area>Internet</area>
        <keyword>RADIUS</keyword>
        <keyword>Diameter</keyword>
        <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
        <keyword>I-D</keyword>
        <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>Many Diameter applications require to classify packets.  Diameter base protocols 
            provides an IP Filter Rule type and a QoS Filter Rule type that is being used to 
            classify packets.  However, because these types were defined for specific uses and 
            defined in ways that are hard to extend and therefore are not generally applicable 
            for those applications that require packet classifiers.</t>
            
            <t>This document describes a set of Diameter types that are useful to create packet 
            classifiers.  The packet classier type can be used by various applications to express 
            packet classifiers that best match the application's specific needs.</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t> The Diameter base protocol <xref target="RFC3588"/> defines two data formats, 
            IPFilterRule and QoSFilterRule.  IPFilterRule is designed to implement packet filters 
            and QoSFilterRule tagging and metering of packets.  Both of these data formats are 
            expressed as an ASCII string which makes it impossible to extend and also makes it 
            difficult to parse and thus equipment suffer a performance hit.</t>
            
            <t>Many applications require the ability to express packet classifiers.  QoS based 
            applications need to be able to express which packets to apply a certain QoS treatment.
            Charging applications need to be able to express which packets should be have certain 
            charging rules applied to them.  Some applications need to be able to redirect certain 
            packets.</t>
            
            <t>The packet classifiers need to be able to classify packets at the various layers and 
            various protocols.  For example, it should be possible to build a classifier to work on 
            layer 2 protocols and build another classifier that works on layer 3 protocols such as 
            IPv4 or IPv6.  Classifiers must also be able to utilize various attributes that are 
            utilized in these layers and protocols.</t>
            
            
           
        </section>
        <section title="Terminology">
            <t> The keywords "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD
                NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
                described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>. </t>
        </section>
        
        <section title="Classifier Attribute Overview">
          <t>Classifiers are used in many applications to specify how to classify packets.  For example 
          in a QoS application, if a packet matches a classifier then that packet will be treated in 
          accordance with a QoS specification associated with that classifier.
          </t>          
          <t>The Classifiers are sent to on on-path element (e.g. a router) which uses the classifier to 
          match packets. <xref target="figure1"/> shows a typical deployement.</t>
          
           <figure anchor="figure1" title="Example of a Classifier Architecture">
                    <artwork><![CDATA[	
                                                        +-----------+
                                                       +-----------+|
    +--------+          +-------------+              +------------+||
    |        |   IN     |             |              |            |||
    |        +--------->|             +------------->|            |||
    |Managed |          | Classifying  |              | Unmanaged  |||
    |Terminal|   OUT    | Entity      |              | Terminal   |||
    |        |<---------+             |<-------------+            ||+
    |        |          |             |              |            |+
    +--------+          +-------------+              +------------+
                                ^
                                | Classifiers
                                |
                         +------+-------+
                         |              |
                         |      AAA     |
                         |              |              
                         +--------------+
                    ]]></artwork>
          </figure>                    
          <t>The managed terminal, the terminal for which the classifiers are being specified is 
          located on the left of the Classifer Entity.  The unmanged terminal, the terminal that 
          recieves packets from the Managed terminal or sends packets to the managed terminal is 
          located to the right side of the Classifier Entity.</t>
          <t>The Classifying Entity is reponsible for classifying packets that are incoming (IN) 
          from the Managed Terminal or packets outgoing (OUT) to the Managed Terminal.</t>
          <t>A Classifier consists of a group of attributes that specify how to match a packet. Each
          set of attributes expresses values about aspects of the packet - typically the packet header.
          Different protocols therefore would use different attributes.</t>
          
          <t>In general a Classifier consists of the following:</t>   
          
          <t>
             <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="Identifier:"> <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                The identifier uniquely identifies this classifier and maybe used to reference the 
                classifier from another structure.
                </t>
                <t hangText="From:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
                Specifies the rule for matching the source part of the packet.
                </t>
                <t hangText="To:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
                Specifies the rule for matching the destination part of the packet.
                </t>
                <t hangText="Protocol"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
                Specifies the matching protocol of the packet.
                </t>
                <t hangText="Direction:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
                Specifies whether the classifier is to apply to packets flowing from the Managed 
                Terminal (IN) or to packets flowing to the Managed Terminal (OUT), or packets flowing in both direction.
                </t>
                <t hangText="Options:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
                Associated with each protocol or layer, or various values specific to the header of the protocol or layer. 
                Options allow matching on those values.
                </t>
             </list>
          </t>
          <t>Each protocol type will have a specific set of attributes that can be used to specify a classifier for that protocol.  These attributes will be grouped under a grouped AVP called a Classifier AVP.</t>

      <!-- ====================================================================== -->

        <section title="Classifier AVP">
          <t>The Classifier AVP (AVP Code TBD) is a grouped AVP that consists of a set of attributes
        that specify how to match a packet.</t>
        <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
Classifier ::= < AVP Header: XXX >
               { Classifier-ID }
               { Protocol }
               { Direction }
             * [ From-Spec ]
             * [ To-Spec ]
             * [ Diffserv-Code-Point ]
               [ Fragmentation-Flag ]
             * [ IP-Option ]
             * [ TCP-Option ]
               [ TCP-Flags ]
             * [ ICMP-Type ]
             * [ AVP ]
                     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
          </t>
        </section>
  
      <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section title="Classifier-ID AVP">
          <t>The Classifier-ID AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type OctetString and uniquely identifies 
          the classifier. Each application will define the uniqueness scope of this identifier, 
          e.g. unique per terminal or globally unique.
          Exactly one Classifier-ID AVP MUST be contained within a Classifier AVP.</t>
        </section>
      <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section title="Protocol AVP">
          <t>The Protocol AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Enumerated and specifies the protocol 
          being matched. The attributes included in the Classifier AVP must be consistent with the
          value of the Protocol AVP. Exactly one Protocol AVP MUST be contained within a 
          Classifier AVP. The values for this AVP are managed by IANA under the Protocol Numbers
          registry <xref target="PROTOCOL"/>.</t>
        </section>
      <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section title="Direction AVP">
          <t>The Direction AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Enumerated that specifies in which 
          direction to apply the Classifier. The values of the enumeration are: "IN","OUT","BOTH".  
          In the "IN" and "BOTH" directions, the From-Spec refers to the address of the Managed 
          Terminal and the To-Spec refers to the unmanaged terminal. In the "OUT" direction, the 
          From-Spec refers to the Unmanaged Terminal whereas the To-Spec refers to the Managed 
          Terminal. </t>
          <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
  Value | Name and Semantic
  ------+------------------------------------------------------------
    0   | RESERVED
    1   | IN - The classifier applies to downlink flows only.
    2   | OUT - The classifier applies to uplink flows only.
    3   | BOTH - The classifier applies to both downlink 
        | and uplink flows.
     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
          </t>
        </section>
      <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section title="From-Spec AVP">
          <t>The From-Spec AVP (AVP Code TBD) is a grouped AVP that specifies the Source 
          Specification used to match the packet. Zero or more of these attributes may appear in the
          classifier. If this AVP is absent from the classifier then the source address is not being
          matched (wild card). If more than one instance of this AVP appears in the Classifier then 
          the source of the packet can match any From-Spec AVP. The contents of this AVP are protocol 
          specific.</t>
        <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
From-Spec ::= < AVP Header: XXX >
              [ IP-Address ]
              [ IP-Address-Range ]
              [ IP-Address-Mask ]
              [ MAC-Address ]
              [ Port ]
              [ Port-Range ]
              [ Negated ]
              [ Assigned ]
            * [ AVP ]
                     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
          </t>
        </section>
      <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section title="To-Spec AVP">
          <t>The To-Spec AVP (AVP Code TBD) is a grouped AVP that specifies the Destination 
          Specification used to match the packet. Zero or more of these attributes may appear in the
          classifier. If the attribute is absent from the classifier then the destination address is
          not being matched (wild card). If more than one instance of this AVP appears in the 
          Classifier then the destination of the packet can match any To-Spec AVP. The contents of 
          this AVP are protocol specific.</t>
        <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
To-Spec ::= < AVP Header: XXX >
            [ IP-Address ]
            [ IP-Address-Range ]
            [ IP-Address-Mask ]
            [ MAC-Address ]
            [ Port ]
            [ Port-Range ]
            [ Negated ]
            [ Assigned ]
          * [ AVP ]
                     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
          </t>
        </section>
        </section>
      <!-- ====================================================================== -->

          <section title="Source and Destination AVPs">
            <t>For packet classification the contents of the From-Spec and To-Spec can contain the 
            following AVPs.</t>
            <t>By combining several of these attributes within a From-Spec or To-Spec AVP and using
            more than one From-Spec or To-Spec AVP in the Classifier AVP, one can express many 
            different types of address pools.
            </t>
            
      <!-- ====================================================================== -->
            <section title="Negated AVP">
              <t>The Negated AVP (AVP Code TBD) of type Enumerated containing the values of True or 
              False.  Exactly zero or one of these attributes may appear in the From-Spec or To-Spec
              AVP. When set to True the meaning of the match in the To-Spec and From-Spec are 
              negated, causing all other addresses to be matched instead.</t>
              <t>When set to False, or when the attribute is not included in the From-Spec or 
              To-Spec AVP then the meaning of the match is not inverted, causing only the addresses 
              specified to be matched.</t>
              <t>Note that the negation does not impact the port comparisons.</t>
              <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
  Value | Name
  ------+--------
    0   | False
    1   | True
     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
              </t>
            </section>
      <!-- ====================================================================== -->
            <section title="IP-Address AVP">
              <t>The IP-Address AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Address and specifies a single 
              IP address (IPv4 or IPv6) address to match.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="IP-Address-Range AVP">
              <t>The IP-Address-Range AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Grouped and specifies an 
              inclusive IP address range.</t>
              <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
IP-Address-Range ::= < AVP Header: XXX >
                     [ IP-Address-Start ]
                     [ IP-Address-End ]
                   * [ AVP ]
                     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
              </t>
              <t>If the IP-Address-Start AVP is not included then the address range starts from the
              first valid IP address up to and including the specified IP-Address-End address.</t>
              <t>If the IP-Address-End AVP is not included then the address range starts at the 
              address specified by the IP-Address-Start AVP and includes all the remaining valid IP
              addresses.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="IP-Address-Start AVP">
              <t>The IP-Address-Start AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Address and specifies the 
              first IP address (IPv4 or IPv6) address of an IP address range.
              </t>
            </section>
            <section title="IP-Address-End AVP">
              <t>The IP-Address-End AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Address and specifies the 
              last IP address (IPv4 or IPv6) address of an address range.
              </t>
            </section>
            <section title="IP-Address-Mask AVP">
               <t>The IP-Address-Mask AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Grouped and specifies an IP 
               address range using a base IP address and the bit-width of the mask. For example, a 
               range expressed as 1.2.3.0/24 will match all IP addresses from 1.2.3.0 up to and 
               including 1.2.3.255. The bit-width MUST be valid for the type of IP address.</t>
              <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
IP-Address-Mask ::= < AVP Header: XXX >
                    [ IP-Address ]
                    [ IP-Bit-Mask-Width ]
                  * [ AVP ]
                     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
              </t>
            </section>
            <section title="IP-Mask-Bit-Mask-Width AVP">
               <t>The IP-Bit-Mask-Width AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type OctetString. The value is a
               single octet and specifies the width of an IP address bit-mask.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="MAC-Address AVP">
               <t>The MAC-Address AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type OctetString and specifies a single 
               MAC address. The value is a 6 octets encoding of the MAC address as it would appear 
               in the frame header.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Port AVP">
              <t>The Port AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Integer32 in the range of 0 to 65535 and 
              specifies the TCP or UDP port number to match.
              </t>
            </section>            
            <section title="Port-Range AVP">
            <t>The Port-Range AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Grouped and specifies an inclusive range 
            of ports.</t>
              <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
Port-Range ::= < AVP Header: XXX >
               [ Port-Start ]
               [ Port-End ]
             * [ AVP ]
                     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
              </t>
            <t>If the Port-Start AVP is omitted then port 0 is assumed. If the Port-End AVP is 
            omitted then port 65535 is assumed.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Port-Start AVP">
              <t>The Port-Start AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Integer32 and specifies the 
              first port number of an IP port range.
              </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Port-End AVP">
              <t>The Port-End AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Integer32 and specifies the 
              last port number of an IP port range.
              </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Assigned AVP">
            <t>In some scenarios, the AAA does not know the IP address assigned to the Managed 
            Terminal at the time that the Classifier is sent to the Classifying Entity.  
            The Assigned AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Enumerated and consists of the value 
            "Assigned".  When present, it represents the IP address assigned to the Managed 
            Terminal.</t>
            </section>
          </section>
      <!-- ====================================================================== -->
          <section title="Header Option AVPs">
            <t>The Classifer AVP may contain one or more of the following AVPs to match on 
            the various possible IP, TCP or ICMP header options.</t>
            <section title="Diffserv-Code-Point AVP">
            <t>The Diffserv-Code-Point AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Enumerated and specifies the
            Differentiated Services Field Codepoints to match in the IP header. The values
            are managed by IANA under the Differentiated Services Field Codepoints registry 
            <xref target="DSCP"/>.</t>
            </section>            
            <section title="Fragmentation-Flag AVP">
            <t>The Fragmentation-Flag AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Enumerated and specifies the
            packet fragmentation flags to match in the IP header.</t>
            <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
  Value | Name and Semantic
  ------+------------------------------------------------------------
    0   | RESERVED
    1   | Don't Fragment (DF)
    2   | More Fragments (MF)
     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
            </t>
            </section>
            <section title="IP-Option AVP">
            <t>The IP-Option AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Grouped and specifies an IP header 
            option that must be matched.</t>
              <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
IP-Option ::= < AVP Header: XXX >
              { IP-Option-Type }
            * [ IP-Option-Value ]
              [ Negated ]
            * [ AVP ]
                     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
              </t>
            <t>If one or more IP-Option-Value AVPs are present, one of the values MUST match
            the value in the IP header option. If the IP-Option-Value AVP is absent, the 
            option type MUST be present in the IP header but the value is wildcarded. </t>
            <t>The Negated AVP is used in conjuction with the IP-Option-Value AVPs to specify 
            IP header options which do not match specific values. The Negated AVP is used 
            without the IP-Option-Value AVP to specify IP headers which do not contain the
            option type.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="IP-Option-Type AVP">
            <t>The IP-Option-Type AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Enumerated and the values
            are managed by IANA under the IP Option Numbers registry <xref target="IPOPTIONS"/>.
            </t>
            </section>            
             <section title="IP-Option-Value AVP">
            <t>The IP-Option-Value AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type OctetString and contains the
            option value that must be matched.</t>
            </section>            
            <section title="TCP-Option AVP">
            <t>The TCP-Option AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Grouped and specifies a TCP header 
            option that must be matched.</t>
              <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
TCP-Option ::= < AVP Header: XXX >
               { TCP-Option-Type }
             * [ TCP-Option-Value ]
               [ Negated ]
             * [ AVP ]
                     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
              </t>
            <t>If one or more TCP-Option-Value AVPs are present, one of the values MUST match the
            value in the TCP header option. If the TCP-Option-Value AVP is absent, the option type
            MUST be present in the TCP header but the value is wildcarded. </t>
            <t>The Negated AVP is used in conjuction which the TCP-Option-Value AVPs to specify 
            TCP header options which do not match specific values. The Negated AVP is used 
            without the TCP-Option-Value AVP to specify TCP headers which do not contain the
            option type.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="TCP-Option-Type AVP">
            <t>The TCP-Option-Type AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Enumerated and the values are
            managed by IANA under the TCP Option Numbers registry <xref target="TCPOPTIONS"/>.
            </t>
            </section>            
             <section title="TCP-Option-Value AVP">
            <t>The TCP-Option-Value AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type OctetString and contains the
            option value that must be matched.</t>
            </section>            
            <section title="TCP-Flags AVP">
            <t>The TCP-Flags AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Grouped and specifies a set of TCP
            control flags that must be matched.</t>
              <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
TCP-Flags ::= < AVP Header: XXX >
            * [ TCP-Flag-Type ]
              [ Negated ]
            * [ AVP ]
                     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
              </t>
            <t>If the Negated AVP is not present, the TCP-Flag-Type AVPs specifies which 
            flags MUST be set. If the Negated AVP is present, the TCP-Flag-Type AVPs 
            specifies which flags MUST be cleared. </t>
            </section>
            <section title="TCP-Flag-Type AVP">
            <t>The TCP-Flag-Type AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Enumerated and specifies a
            TCP control flag type that must be matched.</t>
            <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
  Value | Name and Semantic
  ------+------------------------------------------------------------
    0   | RESERVED
    1   | CWR - Congestion Window Reduced.
    2   | ECE - ECN-Echo. TCP peer is ECN capable.
    3   | URG - URGent pointer field is significant.
    4   | ACK - ACKnowledgment field is significant.
    5   | PSH - Push function.
    6   | RST - Reset the connection.
    7   | SYN - Synchronize sequence numbers.
    8   | FIN - No more data from sender.
     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
            </t>
            </section>
            <section title="ICMP-Type">
            <t>The ICMP-Type AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Grouped and specifies a ICMP  
            message type that must be matched.</t>
              <t>
               <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
ICMP-Type ::= < AVP Header: XXX >
              { ICMP-Type-Number }
            * [ ICMP-Code ]
            * [ AVP ]
                     ]]></artwork>
               </figure>
              </t>
            <t>If the ICMP-Code AVP is present, the value MUST match that in the ICMP 
            header. If the ICMP-Code AVP is absent, the ICMP type MUST be present in the 
            ICMP header but the code is wildcarded. </t>
            </section>
            <section title="ICMP-Type-Number AVP">
            <t>The ICMP-Type-Number AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Enumerated and the values are
            managed by IANA under the ICMP Type Numbers registry <xref target="ICMPTYPE"/>.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="ICMP-Code AVP">
            <t>The ICMP-Code AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Enumerated and the values are
            managed by IANA under the ICMP Type Numbers registry <xref target="ICMPTYPE"/>.</t>
            </section>
          </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References"> 
          &rfc2119;  
        <reference anchor="DSCP">
            <front>
                <title>Differentiated Services Field Codepoints</title>
                <author>
                    <organization abbrev="IANA">IANA,</organization>
                </author>
                <date month="" year="" />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name=""
            value="http://www.iana.org/assignments/dscp-registry" />
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="PROTOCOL">
            <front>
                <title>Protocol Types</title>
                <author>
                    <organization abbrev="IANA">IANA,</organization>
                </author>
                <date month="" year="" />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name=""
            value="http://www.iana.org/assignments/protocol-numbers" />
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IPOPTIONS">
            <front>
                <title>IP Option Numbers</title>
                <author>
                    <organization abbrev="IANA">IANA,</organization>
                </author>
                <date month="" year="" />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name=""
            value="http://www.iana.org/assignments/ip-parameters" />
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TCPOPTIONS">
            <front>
                <title>TCP Option Numbers</title>
                <author>
                    <organization abbrev="IANA">IANA,</organization>
                </author>
                <date month="" year="" />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name=""
            value="http://www.iana.org/assignments/tcp-parameters" />
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ICMPTYPE">
            <front>
                <title>ICMP Type Numbers</title>
                <author>
                    <organization abbrev="IANA">IANA,</organization>
                </author>
                <date month="" year="" />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name=""
            value="http://www.iana.org/assignments/icmp-parameters" />
        </reference>
        </references>
        <references title="Informative References"> 
          &rfc3588; 
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
