<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?rfc linefile="1:draft-iab-rfc-editor-model.xml"?>
<!-- automatically generated by xml2rfc v1.33 on 2008-10-02T15:57:55Z -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>

<rfc ipr="full3978" 
     category="info" 
     docName="draft-iab-rfc-editor-model-00"
     >



  <front>
    <title>RFC Editor Model</title>
    
    <author initials="O." surname="Kolkman (Ed.)" fullname="Olaf M. Kolkman">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
	<email>olaf@nlnetlabs.nl</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author  surname="IAB" fullname="Internet Architecture Board">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>

    
    <date month="October" year="2008" />
 
    <keyword>RFC</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
	The RFC Editor performs a number of functions that may be
	performed by various persons or entities. The RFC Editor model
	presented in this document divides the responsibilities for
	the RFC Series into four functions: The RFC Editor, the
	Independent Submission Editor, the RFC Production, and
	the RFC Publisher. The model intends to increase flexibility
	and operational support options, provide for the orderly
	succession of the RFC Editor, and ensure the continuity of the
	RFC series, while maintaining RFC quality, maintaining timely
	processing, ensuring document accessibility, reducing costs,
	and increasing cost transparency.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  
  <!-- +++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++  -->  
  <middle>
    
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
	The IAB, on behalf of the Internet technical community, is
	concerned with ensuring the continuity of the RFC Series,
	orderly RFC Editor succession, maintaining RFC quality, and
	RFC document accessibility. The IAB is also sensitive to the
	concerns of the IAOC about providing the necessary services in
	a cost effective and efficient manner.
      </t>
      <t>
	The definition of the RFC series is described in RFC 4844
	<xref target="RFC4844"/>.  Section 3.1 defines "RFC Editor":
      </t>
      <t>
	<artwork>
| 3.1. RFC Editor
|
|  Originally, there was a single person acting as editor of the RFC
|  Series (the RFC Editor).  The task has grown, and the work now
|  requires the organized activity of several experts, so there are RFC
|  Editors, or an RFC Editor organization.  In time, there may be
|  multiple organizations working together to undertake the work
|  required by the RFC Series.  For simplicity's sake, and without
|  attempting to predict how the role might be subdivided among them,
|  this document refers to this collection of experts and organizations
|  as the "RFC Editor".
|
|  The RFC Editor is an expert technical editor and series editor,
|  acting to support the mission of the RFC Series.  As such, the RFC
|  Editor is the implementer handling the editorial management of the
|  RFC Series, in accordance with the defined processes.  In addition,
|  the RFC Editor is expected to be the expert and prime mover in
|  discussions about policies for editing, publishing, and archiving
|  RFCs.
	</artwork>
      </t>

      <t>
	RFC 4844 makes no attempt to explore the internal organization
	of the RFC Editor. However, RFC 4844 envisions changes in the RFC
	Editor organizational structure.  In discussion with the
	Internet community, the IAB considered changes that
	increase flexibility and operational support options,
	provide for the orderly succession of the RFC Editor, and
	ensure the continuity of the RFC series, while maintaining RFC
	quality, maintaining timely processing, ensuring document
	accessibility, reducing costs, and increasing cost
	transparency. The model set forth below is the result of
	those discussions. The model examines the internal
	organization of the RFC Editor, yet it remains consistent
	with RFC 4884.
      </t>
      <t>
        The IAB approved the RFC Editor model described in this document
        on October 1, 2008.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IAOC Implementation">
      <t>
	The model is constructed in such a way that it allows for all
	these functions to be implemented jointly or under separate
	contractual arrangements. In fact, a bidder could put together
	a proposal that includes one or more subcontractors. Since the
	reporting structure would depend on the manner that the contracts
	are awarded, and they are subject to change over time. As a
	result, the model describes only responsibilities, procedures,
	and process. The exact implementation is a responsibility of
	the IAOC.
      </t>

      <section title="Expenses for the RFC Editor">
	<t>
	  The expenses discussed in this document are not new expenses.
	  They are part of the IASA budget. Today, these expenses are
	  part of the RFC Editor contract with ISI.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="RFC Editor Model">
      <t>
	The RFC Editor model divides the responsibilities for
	the RFC Series into the following:
      </t>
      <t>
	<list style="symbols">
	  <t>RFC Editor</t>
	  <t>Independent Submission Editor</t>
	  <t>RFC Production</t>
	  <t>RFC Publisher</t>
	</list>
      </t>
      <t>
	The RFC Series Production and Process under this structure is
	schematically represented by the figure below.
      </t>
      <t>
	<figure>
	  <artwork>




      [TO BE DONE] For now see:
      http://www.iab.org/documents/resources/RFCEditorProd.png




	  </artwork>
	  <postample>RFC production and process</postample>
	</figure>
      </t>

      <section title="RFC Editor">
	<t>
	  The RFC Editor is a single person, and this person is responsible for:
	</t>
	<t>
	  <list style="numbers">
	    <t>Identifying appropriate steps for RFC Series
	    continuity</t>
	    <t>Participate in IAOC reviews of the RFC Publisher and
	    RFC Publication functions to ensure the above mentioned
	    continuity</t>
	    <t>RFC Style Manual publication for use by authors,
	    editors, and the RFC publisher</t>
	    <t>RFC errata process management</t>
	    <t>Liaison with the IAB</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  There are many potential issues with respect to RFC Series
	  continuity. To name a few: Look and feel of the series,
	  indexing methodologies, accessibility of the publications,
	  IPR and copyright issues, and formatting issues.
	  After identifying the appropriate steps to address such issues,
	  the implementation of those steps resides mostly with the RFC
	  production and publishing functions. Since the IAOC maintains
	  oversight of the implementation, RFC Editor participation in
	  reviews of that implementation is expected.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The RFC Editor is a senior managerial position with a strong
	  understanding of the IETF process and seasoned management
	  skills. The RFC editor may seek support from an advisory
	  board (see <xref target="editorial_board"/>).
	</t>
	<t>
	  The IAOC has two alternative selection methods for selecting the
	  individual to serve as the RFC Editor.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The first alternative involves a Request for Proposal (RFP)
	  process run by the IAOC. The IAOC would seek a person with the
	  listed qualifications in a broadly distributed RFP. The winner
	  would be selected by the IAOC in consultation with the IAB,
	  and then, the IAOC would contract for the services. Contract
	  terms, including length of contract, extensions and renewals,
	  shall be as defined in an RFP. The opportunity to bid shall be
	  broadly available. Expenses to support the administrative
	  operation of the RFC Editor would be part of the awarded
	  contract and be part of the IASA budget.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The second alternative involves a nomination and confirmation
	  process. Candidates are nominated, and then an individual with
	  the listed qualifications is selected by the Internet community
	  and confirmed by the IAB. An approach similar to the one used
	  by the IAB to select an IAOC member every other year as described
	  in RFC 4333 could be used. A stipend (if provided) and expenses
	  to support the administrative operation of the RFC Editor selected
	  in this manner would be part of the IASA budget.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Independent Submission Editor">
	<t>
	  The Independent Submission Editor is a single person, and
	  this person is responsible for:
	</t>
	<t>
	  <list style="numbers">
	    <t>Independent Submissions approval and processing</t>
	    <t>Forwarding RFCs in the independent stream to RFC Production</t>
	    <t>Independent Submissions RFC errata review and approval</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  The Independent Submission Editor is a senior position for
	  which the following qualifications are desired:
	</t>
	<t>
	  <list style="numbers">
	    <t>Technical competence</t>
	    <t>Deep familiarity with the RFC series</t>
	    <t>An ability to assess the technical competence of
	    potential Editorial Board members</t>
	    <t>Good standing in the technical community in and beyond the IETF</t>
	  </list>

	  The Independent Submission Editor may seek support from an
	  advisory board (see <xref target="editorial_board"/>).
	</t>
	<t>
	  The individual with the listed qualifications will be
	  selected by the community and confirmed by the IAB. An
	  approach similar to the one used by the IAB to select an
	  IAOC member every other year as described in RFC 4333 could
	  be used. A stipend (if provided) and expenses to support the
	  administrative operation of the Independent Submission Editor
	  selected in this manner would be part of the IASA budget.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="RFC Production">
	<t>
	  RFC Production is performed by a paid contractor, and the contractor
	  responsibilities include:
	</t>
	<t>
	<list style="numbers">
	  <t>Editing inputs from all RFC streams to comply with the
	  RFC Style Manual</t>
	  <t>Creating records of edits performed on documents</t>
	  <t>Engaging in dialogue with authors when clarification is
	  needed</t>
	  <t>Creating records of dialogue with documents authors</t>
	  <t>Requesting advice from the RFC Editor as needed</t>
	  <t>Provide suggestions to the RFC Editor as needed</t>
	  <t>Coordinating with IANA to obtain registry information</t>
	  <t>RFC number assignment</t>
	  <t>Forwarding ready-to-publish documents to the RFC
	  Publisher</t>
	  <t>Forwarding records of edits and author dialogue to RFC
	  Publisher</t>
	  <t>Liaison with IESG and IAB</t>
	</list>
      </t>
      <t>
      The RFC Production contractor is to be selected by the IAOC
      through an RFP process, possibly as part of the same contract as
      the RFC Editor. The IAOC would seek a bidder who, among other
      things, is able to provide a timely and cost effective service
      against the established style and production guidelines. Contract
      terms, including length of contract, extensions and renewals,
      shall be as defined in an RFP. The opportunity to bid shall be
      broadly available.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="RFC Publisher">
      <t>
	The RFC Publisher responsibilities include:
      </t>
    <list style="numbers">
      <t>Announce and provide online access to RFCs</t>
      <t>Provide online system to submit RFC Errata</t>
      <t>Provide online access to approved RFC Errata</t>
      <t>Provide backups</t>
      <t>Provide storage and preservation of records</t>
      <t>Authenticate RFCs for legal proceedings</t>
    </list>

    <t>
      Implementation of the RFC publisher function can be pursued in
      two different ways.
    </t>
    <t>
      The first alternative is to extend the IETF Secretariat contract
      to include these services. Expenses to support these services
      would be part of the revised contract.
    </t>
    <t>
      The second alternative is a separate vendor selected by the IAOC
      through an RFP process, possibly as part of the same contract as
      the RFC Editor. Expenses to support service would be part of the
      awarded contract.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section title="RFC Editorial Board" anchor="editorial_board">
      <t>
	Today the RFC Editor is supported by an Editorial Board. This
	board is expected to evolve into one or two advisory boards
	that support the review work of Independent Submissions Editor
	and provide input and guidance to the RFC Editor. The board
	or boards exist at the pleasure of their advisee, and the
	members serve at the pleasure of their advisee. The existence
	the board or boards is simply noted within this model.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="IANA considerations">
    <t>
      This document defines several functions within the overall
      RFC Editor structure, and it places the responsibility for 
      coordination of registry value assignments with the RFC
      Production function. The IAOC will facilitate the establishment
      of the relationship between the RFC Production function and IANA.
    </t>
    <t>
      This document does not create a new registry nor does it
      register any values in existing registries.
    </t>

  </section>
  <section title="Security considerations">
    <t>
      The same security considerations as those in RFC 4844 apply: The
      processes for the publication of documents must prevent the
      introduction of unapproved changes. Since the RFC Editor
      maintains the index of publications, sufficient security must be
      in place to prevent these published documents from being changed
      by external parties. The archive of RFC documents, any source
      documents needed to recreate the RFC documents, and any
      associated original documents (such as lists of errata, tools,
      and, for some early items, non-machine readable originals) need
      to be secured against failure of the storage medium and other
      similar disasters.
    </t>
    <t>
     The IAOC ought to take these security considerations into
     account during the implementation of this RFC Editor model.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Acknowledgements Section">
    <t>
      The RFC Editor model was conceived and discussed in hallways and
      on mail lists. The first itteraton of the text on which this
      document is based was first drafted by Leslie Daigle, Russ
      Housley, and Ray Pelletier.  In addition to the members of the
      IAOC and IAB, major and minor contributions were made by (in
      alphabetical order): Bob Braden, Brian Carpenter, Paul Hoffman,
      John Klensin, Subramanian Moonesamy, and Jim Schaad.
    </t>
    <t>
      The IAOC members at the time the RFC Editor model was approved
      were (in alphabetical order):
        Fred Baker,
        Bob Hinden,
        Russ Housley,
        Ole Jacobsen,
        Ed Juskevicius,
        Olaf Kolkman,
        Ray Pelletier (non-voting),
        Lynn St.Amour, and
        Jonne Soininen.
      In addition, Marshall Eubanks was serving as the IAOC Scribe.
    </t>
    <t>
      The IAB members at the time the RFC Editor model was approved
      were (in alphabetical order):
        Loa Andersson,
        Gonzalo Camarillo,
        Stuart Cheshire,
        Russ Housley,
        Olaf Kolkman,
        Gregory Lebovitz,
        Barry Leiba,
        Kurtis Lindqvist,
        Andrew Malis,
        Danny McPherson,
        David Oran,
        Dave Thaler, and
        Lixia Zhang.
      In addition, the IAB included two ex-officio members: Dow Street, who
      was serving as the IAB Executive Director, and Aaron Falk, who was
      serving as the IRTF Chair.
    </t>
  </section>

</middle>

<back>

    <references title='Normative References'>
      <?rfc?><?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4844.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC4844'>

<front>
<title>The RFC Series and RFC Editor</title>
<author initials='L.' surname='Daigle' fullname='L. Daigle'>
<organization /></author>
<author>
<organization>Internet Architecture Board</organization></author>
<date year='2007' month='July' />
<abstract>
<t>This document describes the framework for an RFC Series and an RFC Editor function that incorporate the principles of organized community involvement and accountability that has become necessary as the Internet technical community has grown, thereby enabling the RFC Series to continue to fulfill its mandate.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4844' />
<format type='TXT' octets='38752' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4844.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="436:draft-iab-rfc-editor-model.xml"?>
    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>
      <?rfc?><?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4333.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC4333'>

<front>
<title>The IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) Member Selection Guidelines and Process</title>
<author initials='G.' surname='Huston' fullname='G. Huston'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Wijnen' fullname='B. Wijnen'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='December' />
<abstract>
<t>This memo outlines the guidelines for selection of members of the IETF Administrative Oversight Committee, and describes the selection process used by the IAB and the IESG.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='113' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4333' />
<format type='TXT' octets='15396' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4333.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="440:draft-iab-rfc-editor-model.xml"?>
    </references>

  <section title="Internet Draft editing details">
      <t>[This appendix is to be removed at publication]</t>
      <t>$Id: draft-iab-rfc-editor-model.xml 2 2008-10-02 15:48:52Z olaf $</t>
  </section>

</back>

</rfc>

