<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?rfc linefile="1:draft-iab-rfc-editor-model.xml"?>
<!-- automatically generated by xml2rfc v1.33 on 2008-11-03T11:10:27Z -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>

<rfc ipr="full3978"
     category="info"
     docName="draft-iab-rfc-editor-model-02"
     >



  <front>
    <title>RFC Editor Model</title>

    <author initials="O." surname="Kolkman (Ed.)" fullname="Olaf M. Kolkman">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
	<email>olaf@nlnetlabs.nl</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author  surname="IAB" fullname="Internet Architecture Board">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
	<email>iab@iab.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date month="November" day="3" year="2008" />

    <keyword>RFC</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
	The RFC Editor performs a number of functions that may be
	carried out by various persons or entities. The RFC Editor
	model presented in this document divides the responsibilities
	for the RFC Series into four functions: The RFC Series Editor,
	the Independent Submission Editor, RFC Production Center, and the RFC
	Publisher. The model outlined here is intended to increase
	flexibility and operational support options, provide for the
	orderly succession of the RFC Editor, and ensure the
	continuity of the RFC series, while maintaining RFC quality,
	maintaining timely processing, ensuring document
	accessibility, reducing costs, and increasing cost
	transparency.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <!-- +++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++  -->
  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
	The IAB, on behalf of the Internet technical community, is
	concerned with ensuring the continuity of the RFC Series,
	orderly RFC Editor succession, maintaining RFC quality, and
	RFC document accessibility. The IAB is also sensitive to the
	concerns of the IAOC about providing the necessary services in
	a cost effective and efficient manner.
      </t>
      <t>
	The definition of the RFC series is described in RFC 4844
	<xref target="RFC4844"/>.  Section 3.1 defines "RFC Editor":
      </t>
      <t>
	<artwork>
| 3.1. RFC Editor
|
|  Originally, there was a single person acting as editor of the RFC
|  Series (the RFC Editor).  The task has grown, and the work now
|  requires the organized activity of several experts, so there are RFC
|  Editors, or an RFC Editor organization.  In time, there may be
|  multiple organizations working together to undertake the work
|  required by the RFC Series.  For simplicity's sake, and without
|  attempting to predict how the role might be subdivided among them,
|  this document refers to this collection of experts and organizations
|  as the "RFC Editor".
|
|  The RFC Editor is an expert technical editor and series editor,
|  acting to support the mission of the RFC Series.  As such, the RFC
|  Editor is the implementer handling the editorial management of the
|  RFC Series, in accordance with the defined processes.  In addition,
|  the RFC Editor is expected to be the expert and prime mover in
|  discussions about policies for editing, publishing, and archiving
|  RFCs.
	</artwork>
      </t>

      <t>
	RFC 4844 makes no attempt to explore the internal organization
	of the RFC Editor. However, RFC 4844 envisions changes in the
	RFC Editor organizational structure.  In discussion with the
	Internet community, the IAB considered changes that increase
	flexibility and operational support options, provides for the
	orderly succession of the RFC Editor, and ensures the
	continuity of the RFC series, while maintaining RFC quality,
	maintaining timely processing, ensuring document
	accessibility, reducing costs, and increasing cost
	transparency. The model set forth below is the result of those
	discussions, and examines the internal organization of
	the RFC Editor, while remaining consistent with RFC 4884.
      </t>
      <t>
	Note that RFC 4844 uses the term "RFC Editor function" or "RFC
	Editor" as the collective set of responsibilities for which
	this memo provides a model for internal organization. This
	memo introduces the term "RFC Series Editor" or "Series
	Editor" for one of the organizational components.
      </t>
      <t>
        The IAB approved the RFC Editor model on October 1, 2008,
        based on a draft version of this this document which has
        received clarifications since. It should be noted that the
        publication of the document as an RFC does not cast the model
        in stone, as the primary purpose of this document, throughout
        the publication procession, is to encourgage normal community
        review in order to ascertain consensus to work to this model
        as a first step. The document, and the resulting structures,
        will be modified as needed through normal procedures. The IAB
        will continue to monitor discussions within the community
        about potential adjustments to the RFC Editor model and
        recognizes that the process described in this document, may
        need to be adjusted to align with any changes that result from
        such discussions.

      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IAOC Implementation">
      <t>
	The model is constructed in such a way that it allows for all
	these functions to be implemented jointly or under separate
	contractual arrangements. In fact, a bidder could put together
	a proposal that includes one or more subcontractors. The
	reporting structure will depend on the manner that the
	contracts are awarded, and they are subject to change over
	time. As a result, the model describes only responsibilities,
	procedures, and process. The exact implementation is a
	responsibility of the IAOC.
      </t>

      <section title="Expenses for the RFC Editor">
	<t>
	  The expenses discussed in this document are not new expenses.
	  They are part of the IASA budget. Today, these expenses are
	  part of the RFC Editor contract with ISI.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="RFC Editor Model">
      <t>
	The RFC Editor model divides the responsibilities for
	the RFC Series into the following components:
      </t>
      <t>
	<list style="symbols">
	  <t>RFC Series Editor</t>
	  <t>Independent Submission Editor</t>
	  <t>RFC Production Center</t>
	  <t>RFC Publisher</t>
	</list>
      </t>
      <t>
	The RFC Series Production and Process under this structure is
	schematically represented by the figure below.
      </t>
      <t>
	<?rfc?><?rfc linefile="1:rfc-model-figure.xml"?><figure>
<artwork>
            ------     -----     ------     --------- 
 Stream    |      |   |     |   |      |   |Community|
 Pro-      | IETF |   | IAB |   | IRTF |   |   at    |
 ducers    |      |   |     |   |      |   |  Large  |
            --^---     --^--     ---^--     ----^---- 
	      |          |          |           |
              |          |          |           |              -------
              |          |          |           |             |	 RFC  |
            --v---    ---v---    ---v--     ----v------       | Edi-  |
 Stream    |      |   |     |   |      |   |Independent|      | torial|
 Appro-    | IESG |   | IAB |   | IRSG |   |  Stream   |..... |	      |
 vers      |      |   |     |   |      |   |  Editor   |      | .and .|
            ----^-    ---^---   ----^---    ----^------       |       |
                |        |          |           |             | Advi- |
                |        |          |           |             | ory   |
                |        |          |           |             | Board |
  ------      --v--------v----------v-----------v-----        |       |
 |      |    |                                        |        -------
 | IANA | &lt;-&gt;|        RFC Production Center           &lt;---.     .
 |      |    |                                        |   |     .
  ------      -----------------^----------------------    |     .
                               |                          |     .
                               |                    ------v-------
			 ------v--------- 	   |              |
                        |                |         |  RFC Series  |
                        |    Publisher   |&lt;-------&gt;|    Editor    |
                        |                |         |              |
                         ----------------           --------------
</artwork>
<postample>RFC production and process</postample>
</figure>
<?rfc linefile="177:draft-iab-rfc-editor-model.xml"?>
	      </t>

      <section title="RFC Series Editor">
	<t>
	  The RFC Series Editor, or Series Editor for short, is an
	  individual who may have assistants and who is responsible for:
	</t>
	<t>
	  <list style="numbers">
	    <t>Identifying appropriate steps for RFC Series
	    continuity</t>
	    <t>Participation in IAOC reviews of the RFC Publisher and
	    RFC Publication functions to ensure the above mentioned
	    continuity</t>
	    <t>Developing, maintaining, and publishing the RFC Style
	    Manual publication for use by authors, editors, and the
	    RFC publisher</t>
	    <t>Managing the RFC errata process</t>
	    <t>Liaising with the IAB</t>
	    <t> Overseeing consistency of RFCs with the RFC Series and RFC Style Manual</t>

	  </list>
	</t>

	<t>
	  There are many potential issues with respect to RFC Series
	  continuity. To name a few: Look and feel of the series,
	  indexing methodologies, accessibility of the publications,
	  IPR and copyright issues, and formatting issues.  After
	  identifying the appropriate steps to address such issues,
	  the implementation of those steps resides mostly with the
	  RFC production and publishing functions. Since the IAOC
	  maintains oversight of the implementation, the Series Editor
	  is expected to be invited and participate in reviews of that
	  implementation.
	</t>

	<t>
	  The RFC Series Editor is a senior technology professional
	  with the following qualifications:
	  <list style="numbers">
	    <t>Strong understanding of the IETF process</t>
	    <t>Good understanding of the English language and technical
	    terminology related to the Internet</t>
	    <t>Good communication skills</t>
	    <t>Experience with editorial processes</t>
	    <t>Independent worker</t>
	    <t>Experience as an RFC author desired</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  The Series Editor may seek support from an advisory board
	  (see <xref target="editorial_board"/>).
	</t>
	<t>
	  The IAOC has two alternative selection methods for selecting
	  the individual to serve as the RFC Series Editor. The choice
	  between these alternatives will be based on an RFI issued by the
	  IAOC in December 2009.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The first alternative involves a Request for Proposal (RFP)
	  process run by the IAOC. The IAOC would seek a person with
	  the listed qualifications in a broadly distributed RFP. The
	  winner would be selected by the IAOC in consultation with
	  the IAB, and then, the IAOC would contract for the
	  services. Contract terms, including length of contract,
	  extensions and renewals, shall be as provided in the
	  RFP. The opportunity to bid shall be broadly available. Fees
	  and expenses to support the administrative operation of the
	  RFC Series Editor would be part of the awarded contract and
	  be part of the IASA budget.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The second alternative involves a nomination and
	  confirmation process. Candidates are nominated, and then an
	  individual with the listed qualifications is selected by the
	  Internet community and confirmed by the IAB. An approach
	  similar to the one used by the IAB to select an IAOC member
	  every other year as described in <xref target="selection"/>
	  will be used. A stipend and expenses to support the
	  administrative operation of the RFC Series Editor selected
	  in this manner would be part of the IASA budget.
	</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Independent Submission Editor">
	<t>
	  The Independent Submission Editor is an individual who may
	  have assistants and who is responsible for:
	</t>
	<t>
	  <list style="numbers">
	    <t>Independent Submissions approval and processing</t>
	    <t>Forwarding RFCs in the Independent Stream to the RFC Production Center</t>
	    <t>Independent Submissions RFC errata review and approval</t>
	  </list>
	</t>

	<t>
	  The Independent Submission Editor is a senior position for
	  which the following qualifications are desired:
	</t>
	<t>
	  <list style="numbers">
	    <t>Technical competence, i.e. broad technical experience
	    and perspective across the whole range of Internet
	    technologies and applications, and specifically, the
	    ability to work effectively with portions of that spectrum
	    in which no personal expertise exists.</t>
	    <t>Thorough familiarity with the RFC series</t>
	    <t>An ability to assess the technical competence of
	    potential Editorial Board members</t>
	    <t>Good standing in the technical community, in and beyond
	    the IETF</t>
	  </list>

	  The Independent Submission Editor may seek support from an
	  advisory board (see <xref target="editorial_board"/>) and may
	  form a team to perform the activities needed to fulfill their
	  responsibilities..
	</t>
	<t>
	  The individual with the listed qualifications will be
	  selected by the community and confirmed by the IAB. An
	  approach similar to the one used by the IAB to select an
	  IAOC member every other year as described in <xref
	  target="selection"/> should be used. A stipend (if provided)
	  and expenses to support the administrative operation of the
	  Independent Submission Editor selected in this manner would
	  be not be part of the IASA budget, but could be part of a
	  3rd party's budget.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="production" title="RFC Production Center">
	<t>
	  RFC Production is performed by a paid contractor, and the
	  contractor responsibilities include:
	</t>
	<t>
	<list style="numbers">
	  <t>Editing inputs from all RFC streams to comply with the
	  RFC Style Manual</t>
	  <t>Creating records of edits performed on documents</t>

	  <t>Identifying where editorial changes might have technical
	  impact and seek necessary clarification.</t>

	  <t>Engaging in dialogue with authors, document shepherds,
	  IANA, and/or stream dependent contacts when clarification is
	  needed.
	  </t>
	  <t>Creating records of dialogue with documents authors</t>
	  <t>Requesting advice from the RFC Series Editor as needed</t>
	  <t>Providing suggestions to the RFC Series Editor as needed</t>
	  <t>Coordinating with IANA to perform protocol paramater
	  registry actions</t>
	  <t>Assigning of RFC number</t>
	  <t> Establishing publication readiness of each document
	  through communication with the authors, document shepherds,
	  IANA and/or stream dependent contacts, and if needed with
	  the RFC Series Editor.  </t>
	  <t>Forwarding ready-to-publish documents to the RFC
	  Publisher</t>
	  <t>Forwarding records of edits and author dialogue to RFC
	  Publisher so these can be preserved</t>
	  <t>Liaising with IESG and IAB</t>
	</list>
      </t>
      <t>
      The RFC Production Center contractor is to be selected by the
      IAOC through an RFP process, possibly as part of the same
      contract as the RFC Series Editor. The IAOC would seek a bidder
      who, among other things, is able to provide a professional,
      quality, timely, and cost effective service against the
      established style and production guidelines. Contract terms,
      including length of contract, extensions and renewals, shall be
      as defined in an RFP. The opportunity to bid shall be broadly
      available.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="RFC Publisher">
      <t>
	The RFC Publisher responsibilities include:
      </t>
    <list style="numbers">
      <t>Announce and provide on-line access to RFCs</t>
      <t>Provide on-line system to submit RFC Errata</t>
      <t>Provide on-line access to approved RFC Errata</t>
      <t>Provide backups</t>
      <t>Provide storage and preservation of records</t>
      <t>Authenticate RFCs for legal proceedings</t>
    </list>

    <t>
      Implementation of the RFC Publisher function can be pursued in
      two different ways. The choice between these alternatives will
      be based on an RFI issued by the IAOC in December 2009.
    </t>
    <t>
      The first alternative is to modify the IETF Secretariat contract
      to include these services. Expenses to support these services
      would be part of the revised contract.
    </t>
    <t>
      The second alternative is a separate vendor selected by the IAOC
      through an RFP process, possibly as part of the same contract as
      the RFC Series Editor. Expenses to support service would be part of the
      awarded contract.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section title="RFC Editorial Board" anchor="editorial_board">
      <t>
	Today the RFC Editor is supported by an Editorial Board. This
	board is expected to evolve into one or two advisory boards
	that support the review work of the Independent Submissions
	Editor and provide input and guidance to the Series
	Editor. The board(s) will exist at the pleasure of their
	advisee, and the members serve at the pleasure of their
	advisee. The existence of the board or boards is simply noted
	within this model, and additional discussion of such considered
	out of scope of this document.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>


  <section title="IANA considerations">
    <t>
      This document defines several functions within the overall
      RFC  Editor structure, and it places the responsibility for
      coordination of registry value assignments with the RFC
      Production Center. The IAOC will facilitate the establishment
      of the relationship between the RFC Production Center and IANA.
    </t>
    <t>
      This document does not create a new registry nor does it
      register any values in existing registries, and no IANA action
      is required.
    </t>

  </section>
  <section title="Security considerations">
    <t>
      The same security considerations as those in RFC 4844 apply: The
      processes for the publication of documents must prevent the
      introduction of unapproved changes. Since the RFC Editor
      maintains the index of publications, sufficient security must be
      in place to prevent these published documents from being changed
      by external parties. The archive of RFC documents, any source
      documents needed to recreate the RFC documents, and any
      associated original documents (such as lists of errata, tools,
      and, for some early items, non-machine readable originals) need
      to be secured against failure of the storage medium and other
      similar disasters.
    </t>
    <t>
     The IAOC should take these security considerations into
     account during the implementation of this RFC Editor model.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Acknowledgements Section">
    <t>
      The RFC Editor model was conceived and discussed in hallways and
      on mail lists. The first iteration of the text on which this
      document is based was first drafted by Leslie Daigle, Russ
      Housley, and Ray Pelletier.  In addition to the members of the
      IAOC and IAB, major and minor contributions were made by (in
      alphabetical order): Bob Braden, Brian Carpenter, Sandy Ginoza,
      Alice Hagens, Paul Hoffman, John Klensin, Subramanian Moonesamy,
      and Jim Schaad.
    </t>
    <t>
      The IAOC members at the time the RFC Editor model was approved
      were (in alphabetical order):
        Fred Baker,
        Bob Hinden,
        Russ Housley,
        Ole Jacobsen,
        Ed Juskevicius,
        Olaf Kolkman,
        Ray Pelletier (non-voting),
        Lynn St.Amour, and
        Jonne Soininen.
      In addition, Marshall Eubanks was serving as the IAOC Scribe.
    </t>
    <t>
      The IAB members at the time the RFC Editor model was approved
      were (in alphabetical order):
        Loa Andersson,
        Gonzalo Camarillo,
        Stuart Cheshire,
        Russ Housley,
        Olaf Kolkman,
        Gregory Lebovitz,
        Barry Leiba,
        Kurtis Lindqvist,
        Andrew Malis,
        Danny McPherson,
        David Oran,
        Dave Thaler, and
        Lixia Zhang.
      In addition, the IAB included two ex-officio members: Dow Street, who
      was serving as the IAB Executive Director, and Aaron Falk, who was
      serving as the IRTF Chair.
    </t>
  </section>



</middle>

<back>

    <references title='Normative References'>
      <?rfc?><?rfc linefile="1:bibxml/reference.RFC.4844.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC4844'>

<front>
<title>The RFC Series and RFC Editor</title>
<author initials='L.' surname='Daigle' fullname='L. Daigle'>
<organization /></author>
<author>
<organization>Internet Architecture Board</organization></author>
<date year='2007' month='July' />
<abstract>
<t>This document describes the framework for an RFC Series and an RFC Editor function that incorporate the principles of organized community involvement and accountability that has become necessary as the Internet technical community has grown, thereby enabling the RFC Series to continue to fulfill its mandate.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4844' />
<format type='TXT' octets='38752' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4844.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="498:draft-iab-rfc-editor-model.xml"?>
    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>
      <?rfc?><?rfc linefile="1:bibxml/reference.RFC.4333.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC4333'>

<front>
<title>The IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) Member Selection Guidelines and Process</title>
<author initials='G.' surname='Huston' fullname='G. Huston'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Wijnen' fullname='B. Wijnen'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='December' />
<abstract>
<t>This memo outlines the guidelines for selection of members of the IETF Administrative Oversight Committee, and describes the selection process used by the IAB and the IESG.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='113' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4333' />
<format type='TXT' octets='15396' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4333.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="502:draft-iab-rfc-editor-model.xml"?>
    </references>


  <section anchor="selection" title="IAB selection">

    <t>
      This process is used by the IAB for the selection of the RFC
      Series Editor (if that position is not covered by the RFC
      Production Center contract) and for the selection of the
      Independent Submission Editor. The IAOC selects the RFC
      Production Center and RFC Publisher from vendors that choose to submit
      a proposal.  The IAOC procurement process is not described in
      this document.
    </t>


    <t>The selection process herein is taken from <xref
    target="RFC4333"/> but modified to allow for subject matter
    experts to advise the IAB, to take into account that the
    community with interest in the RFC series extends beyond the IETF
    community, and to prefer the incumbent.
    </t>


    <section title="Ad-hoc advisory committee">
      <t>
	It is expected that the IAB and IAOC will establish an ad-hoc
	advisory committee to assist them in the selection of the
	various functions.  The names of the members of this
	committee, who do not need to be IAB members or IETF
	participants, will be made public through the IAB and IAOC
	minutes or otherwise.
      </t>
      <t>
	The committee is expected to have an understanding of the RFC
	series and related processes, and of procedures and interests of the
	various streams.
      </t>
      <t>
	Members of the subcommittee will be privy to confidential
	material and are expected to honour confidentiality.
      </t>
      <t>
	The IAB and IAOC bear the responsibility for the selections of
	the candidates for defined functions, the committee provides
	advice only.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="The IAB Selection Process of an RFC Series Editor and/or an Independent Stream Editor">


      <section title="Nominations and Eligibility">
	<t>
	  The IAB will be making a broad public call for nominations.
	  The public call will specify the manner by which nominations
	  will be accepted and the means by which the list of nominees
	  will be published. Self-nominations are permitted. Along
	  with the name and contact information for each candidate,
	  details about the candidate's background and qualifications
	  for the position should be attached to the nomination.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Members of the ad-hoc advisory committee mentioned above are
	  not eligible, but besides those there are no limitations
	  with respect to the eligibility for nomination: Nominees do
	  not have to be actively contributing to the IETF and active
	  participation as being a working group chair, an IETF
	  Nominating Committee member, or an IAB or IESG member is not
	  a limitation.
	</t>
	<t>
	  IAB members who accept a nomination for an IAB-selected
	  position will recuse themselves from IAB selection
	  discussions.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Selection">
	<t>
	  The IAB will publish the list of nominated persons prior to
	  making a decision, allowing time for the community to pass
	  any relevant comments to that body. When established the
	  advisory committee will be asked to provide a motivated
	  shortlist. The IAB will review the nomination material, any
	  submitted comments, the shortlist from the advisory
	  committee, and make its selection.
	</t>
	<t>
	  It is noted that the community mentioned above is the
	  community with an interest in RFCs and the RFC Editor's
	  functioning, the IETF community is only a part of that
	  community.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The main intent is to select the incumbent or a superior
	  candidate.
	</t>


      </section>
      <section title="Care of Personal Information">
	<t>

	  The following procedures will be used by the IAB in managing
	  candidates' personal information:

	  <list style="symbols">

	    <t>The candidate's name will be published, with all other
	    candidate names, at the close of the nominations
	    period.</t>

	    <t> Except as noted above, all information provided to the
	    IAB during this process will be kept as confidential to
	    the IAB and, when established, the advisory committee.</t>

	  </list>
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Term of Office and Selection Time Frame">
	<t>
	  The IAB will seat their selected member at the first IETF
	  meeting of every second year, for a two-year term of office.
	  Basic time frame requirements for the selection process are
	  as follows:
	  <list style="symbols">
	    <t>3-4 weeks for solicitation of nominations.</t>
	    <t>3-4 weeks for review of nominees, deliberation, and selection.</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  About 3-4 weeks prior to the process, the IAB will
	  announce the specific dates for the selection process for
	  that year, following the guidelines above.
	</t>

      </section>
    </section>
  </section>


  <section title="Internet Draft editing details">
      <t>[This appendix is to be removed at publication]</t>
      <t>$Id: draft-iab-rfc-editor-model.xml 23 2008-11-03 11:10:22Z olaf $</t>
      <section title="Section 00->01">
	<t>Added Sandy and Alice to the acknowledgement section, they were accidentally omitted</t>

	<t>
	  Added <xref target="selection"/> so that the selection
	  mechanism is explicitly documented. The selection mechanism
	  documents the use of an advisory committee and is explicit
	  about the fact that the community expands beyond the IETF
	  community.

	</t>
	<t>
	  Modified the RFC Editor Function name to "RFC Series Editor"
	  in order to minimize confusion between the collective of
	  functions (RFC Editor) and the function (Series Editor).
	</t>
	<t>
	  Added wording for specifying the technical competence needed
	  by the indep.subm.editor as suggested by JCK
	</t>
	<t>
	  Clarified the responsibilities of the production function in
	  <xref target="production"/>
	</t>
	<t>Enumerated qualifications of the RFC Editor</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Section 01->02">
	<t>Various nits corrected</t>
	<t>Inconsictency in the use of RFC Production house and RFC
	Production fixed: RFC Production Center used as term</t>


	<t>
	  Oversight over RFC consistency with the style manual has been made explicit.</t>
	  <t>
	   Clarified that the Independent Stream Editors budget is
	   independent from the IETF/IASA.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Improved the language that clarified that the RFC Series
	  editors and Independent Stream editor do not necessarilly
	  need to work  without assistants, while they bear the responsibility.
	</t>
      </section>
  </section>




</back>

</rfc>

