<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- 00b circulated to rfc ed board list
     00c developed from Aaron's comments, circulated to Jim Schaad
	 00d Jim's corrections, plus corrections made after Bob Braden's
	 notes on 20080725
	 00e Corrected external reference text
	 00f Added Acknowledgements
    01  Braden hacked at it
   -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2223 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2223.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3743 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3743.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3778 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3778.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4748 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4748.xml'>]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>


<!-- Expand crefs and put them inline -->
<?rfc comments='yes' ?>
<?rfc inline='yes' ?>  

<rfc docName="draft-rfc-image-files-00.txt" ipr="full3978"
	  updates="2223">   <!--  category="info" ?, but note 2119 stuff -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Images in RFCs">
      Images in RFCs </title>
<author initials="R." surname="Braden" fullname="Robert Braden">
  <organization>USC/ISI</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
      <city>Marina del Rey</city> <region>CA</region> <code>90292</code>
      <country>USA</country> </postal>
    <phone>+1 310 448 9173 </phone>
    <email>braden@isi.edu</email>
  </address>
  </author>
<author initials="J.C." surname="Klensin" fullname="John C Klensin">
  <organization/>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>1770 Massachusetts Ave, #322</street>
      <city>Cambridge</city> <region>MA</region> <code>02140</code>
      <country>USA</country> </postal>
    <phone>+1 617 491 5735 </phone>
    <email>john-ietf@jck.com</email>
  </address>
  </author>

  <date month="August" year="2008" day="22"/>
    <keyword>RFC</keyword>
    <keyword>Images</keyword>
    <keyword>Pictures</keyword>

	<abstract>
      <t> Documents in the RFC series normally use only
		plain-text ASCII characters and a fixed-width font.
		However, there is sometimes a need to supplement the
		ASCII text with graphics or picture images.  The
		historic solution to this requirement, allowing
		secondary PDF and Postscript files, is seldom used
		because it is awkward for authors and
		publisher.  This memo sugests a more
		convenient scheme for
		 attaching authoritative diagrams, llustrations, or
		 other graphics to RFCs.
       </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
<section title="Introduction">
      <t> Published documents in the RFC series normally use
		only plain-text ASCII
                characters and a fixed-width font
		<xref target="RFC2223"/>. 
		This simple convention has the
		advantage of a stable encoding for which a wide variety
		of tools are readily available for viewing, searching,
		editing, etc..</t>

      <t> Inclusion of diagrams, state machines,
		and other graphics in RFC text has generally relied
		on the imaginative use of ASCII characters ("ASCII artwork".)
		However, in a few cases over the years, ASCII artwork has
		been inadequate for images needed or desired in RFCs.
		The old solution to this dilemma has been to allow
		three versions of an RFC: a primary ASCII version
		and secondary versions that are
		encoded using PDF and Postcript.  The PDF and
		Postscript versions are "complete",
		containing a copy of the text as well as the full images
		<xref target="RFC2223"/>. The textual content and
		layout of the PDF/PS version is required to match the base
		version as closely as possible.  However, the ASCII text
		version is considered the official expression of the RFC,
		and it is always normative for standards track documents.
		We will refer to this
		old approach as ".txt+.pdf+.ps" encoding. </t>

 	<t> The three versions of an RFC using .txt+.pdf+.ps encoding are
		in separate files in the primary RFC repository
		(http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/"), with suffixes
		".txt", ".pdf", and ".ps".  The RFC Editor
		search engine returns links to all three versions
		when they are present in the repository.</t>
		
	<t>	Unfortunately, the .txt+.pdf+.ps scheme has been awkward
		for both editor and author, and it is error-prone, so it
		has seldom been used (roughly 50 out of 5000+ RFCs).
		The problem is that, in general, only the author has the
		tools to prepare the PDF and Postscript versions.  The RFC
		Editor edits (only) the primary text version, and then
		the author must incorporate all the resulting
		changes into the PDF/PS version while maintaining the "look" of
		the RFC to the extent possible.  There is no practical way
		for the RFC Editor to verify that this is done correctly,
		perhaps leading to editorial errors and usually lengthening
		publication time for these documents.
		 </t>
	<t>
  	       This memo suggests a much better
		scheme for including figures, illustrations, and
		graphics to an RFC. We hope that the method proposed
		here will solve the image problem for RFC publication,
		although the .txt+.pdf+.ps approach would still be
		 possible (and in any case, RFCs using the historic
		 scheme will continue to exist in the RFC repository
		forever).</t>

   </section>

   <section title="A New Scheme for Images">

	  <t>Under our scheme, an RFC may be either a single ASCII
		file as commonly used today, or a composite of two files:
		an ASCII-only "base file" containing the text of the
		RFC, and an "image file".  When present, the image file
		would be a PDF file that contained only images, captions, and
		title information.  Neither file of the composite
		would be complete without the
		other, and a reference to the RFC would be considered
		a reference to both files. An RFC would then be
		a logical entity whose complete representation could require
		two files, base and image.</t>

	<t>The base file would be formatted exactly like current
		ASCII RFCs, with three minor exceptions described below.
	</t>

	<t>The intellectual property 
		boilerplate in the base file
		("Rights in Contributions <xref target="RFC4748">BCP
		78, RFC 4748</xref> ) would apply equally to the
		image file.

		An image file would contain one or more items that will
		be known collectively as "figures", whether they are
		actually diagrams, pictures, tables, artwork, or other
		non-textual constructions.</t>

	<t>  This scheme was inspired by the tradition in
		book publishing, where pictures, figures, or "plates"
		may be grouped together following the text ("end
		figures"), or even bound separately from the main body
		of the text.
	<!-- 
		If the approach of this document is adopted, terms like
		"the RFC" will refer to the combination of the base RFC
		file and an image file if the latter is supplied.  Note
		that just as with the .txt+.pdf+.ps encoding, an RFC is
		a logical entity whose complete representation requires
		multiple files.
	-->
</t>

	<t>In principle, we could allow an image file to be encoded
		using both PDF and Postscript, since mechanical translation is
		possible in both directions. However, in the 20 years since
		the adoption of the .txt+.pdf+.ps scheme, the PDF format
		has become a defacto standard for electronic documents,
		and readers for it are universally available.  Furthermore,
		PDF is being standardized as a format for document
		archiving, as discussed further in the next
		section.  Therefore, we propose to allow only PDF for
		image files, simplifying the new approach by not
		including a Postscript file option.</t>

	<t>An ASCII RFC traditionally uses a file name in the form of
		 "rfcN.txt", where N is integer RFC number without
		 leading zeros. The
		 image file that is associated with RFC number N could
		 be named "rfcN.img.pdf".  As noted earlier, the
		repository contains RFCs with file names
		"rfcN.ps" and "rfcN.pdf", using the historic
		.txt+.pdf+.ps scheme.</t>

	  </section>

	  <section title="Construction of the Image File">
					
		 <t>An image file would be a single PDF file, consistent
			with the description in <xref target="RFC3778"/> and
			defined in <xref target="ISO32000-1"/>.  The
			particular PDF form must be version-stable and must
			not contain any external references in scripts
			or otherwise.  Those requirements are satisfied
			by the <xref target="ISO19005-1"> PDF/A </xref>
			profile.  The RFC Editor may authorize other
			variants of PDF in the future.</t>

		<t>There is an issue of whether particular generators of
			PDF that claim to satisfy PDF/A actually do so.
			Future experience may require published guidelines
			on PDF-generating software that claims to satisfy
			PDF/A but does not.</t>

		 <t>Except as otherwise specified in this document, an
			image file should contain only figures,
			supporting labels and captions, headers, and
			footers.  It should not contain
			explanatory text or other materials that could
			reasonably be expressed in plain-text form in
			the base file</t>

		 <t>Pages of the image file would be consecutively
			numbered.   The first
			page number of the image file would follow the
			last page number of the base RFC, exclusive of
			the  number of the end-of-RFC boilerplate page.
			The page number of the end-of-RFC boilerplate
			(in the base RFC file) would be the first page
			number after those in the image file.
			Each page of the image file would contain the
			same headers and footers as the base file, except
			for one change in the footer, suggested below.</t>
			
		 <t>Figures included in the image file would have to be
			labeled in a fashion that facilitated
			referencing from the base RFC.  They should
			normally be numeric and monotonic.
			Simple consecutive integer will usually be the
			best choice, but in some cases it might be
			desirable to use a hierarchical scheme like:
			&lt;section #&gt;.&lt;fig #&gt;.  An author who
			believes that another labeling scheme would
			increase clarity should check with the RFC
			Editor. </t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="Requirements for the Base File">

	<section title="Overview">
	<t>A base file would be unchanged by the presence of an image file,
	except for the following.</t>
	<t> 
	<list  style="symbols">
		<t>The page number of the end-of-RFC boilerplate page
		 would be changed to be logically one page after the
		last image file page.</t>
		<t>A new unnumbered "Figures" section would be required.
		This is described below.
		</t>
		<t>For a composite RFC, a minor modification to the
		first-page header of the base file and to the footers
		of both base and image files could tie the two files
		together.  This is described below.
		</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Figures Section">


  <t>An RFC that used this scheme (and had any figures) would need to include a
		Figures section in the ASCII base file.
		The Figures section should immediately following the
		Table of Contents, if any, and precede the
		body of the document.  The Figures section
		should list all figures in tabular form,
		indicating for each one the figure
		identification, title, and page number(s).</t>

	<t>The style for the Figures section has not yet been
		fully specified.   Here is a suggested example.</t>

<t>
	<artwork>
___________________________________________________________________________
Table of Contents

  1. Introduction .................................................... 1
  2. Philosophy ...................................................... 7
      2.1 Elements of the Internetwork System ........................ 7
      2.2 Model of Operation ......................................... 8
      2.3 The Host Environment ....................................... 8 
(etc)

Figures

  Figure 1: Protocol Layering . .....................................  2
  Figure 2: Protocol Relationships ..................................  9
  Figure 3: TCP Header Format .................................. 15, *86
  Figure 4: Send Sequence Space ..................................... 20
  Figure 5: Receive Sequence Space .................................. 20
  Figure 6: TCP Connection State Diagram ....................... 23, *87
  Figure 7: Basic 3-Way Handshake for Connection Synchronization 31, *88
(etc)

*Page in Image file

(Page 1 follows)
___________________________________________________________________________
</artwork>
</t>

	<t>An RFC that includes a base file may include
		 ASCII artwork that is
		suggestive of a figure in the image file, but there is no
		requirement to do so.  When such an approximate figure appears
		as ASCII artwork in the base file, its figure identification
		and caption must match those of the corresponding figure
		in the image file, and the entry in the Figures table should
		specify the page numbers in both the base and image file,
		In the example shown above, image file page
		numbers are marked with an asterisk.  Note that very
		simple ASCII artwork need not appear in the image file.</t>		
	</section>
	<section title="Formatting Changes">
	<t>It would be necessary to tie the base and image files
	together, to make clear they are part of one RFC.  Here is an
	initial suggestion for formatting, which needs further
	consideration before it is adopted.</t>


	<t><list>
	<t>The header line "Request for Comments: nnnn" in the base file
		could be changed to "Request for Comments: nnnn/Base".
		For consistency, the lefthand footer could become
		"RFC nnnn/Base".
	The lefthand footer in the image file could then be:
	"RFC nnnn/Image.
	</t><t>
	The following sentence could be placed in the "Status of this Memo"
	section: "This RFC is a composite of this base file and a PDF
	image file."
	</t></list>
	</t>
		 </section>
	</section>


	 <section title="Submission and Processing of the Image File">
		<t>If an image file is needed, it should be submitted
		   as an .img.pdf file along with the ASCII text file.

		The image file should be submitted
	 	without headers or footers.  The RFC Editor will
		overlay the image file with the appropriate headers and
		footers, with correct pagination.  The RFC Editor will
		not normally do any editing of the image file beyond
		this.  If editing the base file reveals problems with
		figures in the image file, the authors will be asked to
		create a new image file.

		</t>
</section>

<section title="Implementation Issues">


<t>This acheme has a number of implications.
	
	<list style="numbers">

	<t>
 	The Internet Draft repository must allow submission and
	retrieval of both base and (when present) image files.</t>

	<t>Internet Draft file names could be draft-...-vv.txt and
	(optionally)  draft-...-vv.img.pdf, where "vv" is the normal
	version number.  Updating either file of the composite RFC
	should increase the version numbers "vv" in both files.  We DO
	NOT want two separate version numbers for one I-D</t>

	<t>The RFC Editor would need to be able to overlay headers, footers,
	and page numbers on a given image file.  It is claimed that
	at least Adobe Acrobat Professional includes this capability, and that it
	also has limited editing capability.</t>

	<t>The RFC Editor would also need a tool to verify that a given
	image file satisfies the constraints of PDF/A.</t>

	<t>Some RFC Editor scripts and tools would need small extensions.
	</t>

	<t>Some small extensions to xml2rfc to include image files would
	be useful.  It should generate the boilerplate with a
	non-sequential page number.  For example, an attribute on
	&lt;back&gt;, might specify the number of pages of image file.
	One could presumably add a mechanism to generate the Figures
	section.</t>
	</list>
</t>
	
	 </section>

<section title="RFC Repository File Formats">

	<t>A frequent reaction to the suggestion given in this memo is some
		confusion over the different file formats that appear in the
		RFC repository.  Here is a brief summary.</t>
	
	<t>If a PDF image file exists along with a base ASCII RFC,
		then RFCs in any other format (e.g., complete PDF files,
		   HTML, or Postscript) remain supplemental, with the reader
		   taking responsibility for assuring that they are equivalent
		   to the base RFC and image file.  That arrangement is
		   identical to the relationship between traditional all-ASCII
		   RFCs and supplemental forms: the RFC Editor has never taken
		   responsibility for guaranteeing that the two are identical
		   in content.</t>

	<t>The existing .txt.pdf files are not affected by
	this proposal.  The .txt.pdf files are facsimiles of .txt (base
	files) in PDF, introduced to help Windows users read RFCs
	online.  However, Microsoft has more recently provided
        an elementary ASCII editor, which probably makes the
	.txt.pdf files unnecessary in any case.</t>

	<t>In summary:</t>

	<t>
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>.txt: ASCII-only file. In old scheme, complete normative file.
		In new scheme, text part of composite RFC, or stand-alone
		text file.</t>

	<t>.ps: Old scheme -- a Postscript file that includes
		figures and whose text is intended to be the same as
		the normative .txt file.</t>

	<t>.pdf: Old scheme -- a PDF file that includes
		figures and whose text is intended to be the same as
		the normative
		.txt file.</t>

	<t>.img.pdf: New scheme: image file part of a composite with .txt file.</t>

	<t>.txt.pdf: Old scheme: Facsimile of corresponding .txt file.</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	<t>
	We note that it would be possible to combine the base and
	image files into a single PDF file, which would have to
	follow a naming convention to distinguish it from the
	.pdf case listed above.  However, we regard this an
	an undesirable step away from the principle of universal
	ASCII encoding of the text of the document.</t>
</section>

    <section title="Internationalization Considerations">

	<t>Our scheme of image files does not, and is not
		intended to, support character set internationalization
		for RFCs.  It does not allow an author to omit the
		ASCII text from the base file and instead include
		the entire RFC text as
		one (very large) image file.</t>

	<t>
	However, we should note two special cases.

	<list style="numbers">
		<t> RFC 3743 <xref target="RFC3743"/> on internationalized
		domain names for Chinese, Japanese,, and Korean
		contains a number of examples that may be
	hard to follow because they can represent those characters only
	in "U+nnnn" form.  An image file could be used that would show
	the alternative Chinese characters for the examples.  This
	would not diminish either the ability to search the base text
	or index the document or its readability for those of us for
	whom reading Chinese characters is difficult, but it should
	help those who can read them.</t>
	
	<t> Suppose that a proposed RFC contained a section
	derived from Japanese text.  The author might put an English
	translation into that section of the base document, note that
	the original was really in Japanese, and attach the Japanese as
	an appendix in an image file.  This should raise no
	difficulties for informative documents.  For normative
	documents, however, the existence of the Japanese original
	would raise some issues about what was actually authoritative,
	which is very undesirable.</t>

	</list>
	</t>
	</section>
		

    <section title="Security Considerations">
    <t>This specifications addresses documentation standards and
	   adding additional flexibility to them.  It does not, in
	   general, raise any security issues.  However, unless the
	   specifications of this document are carefully followed, the
	   image format recommended, PDF, may potentially contain
	   external references or scripts that could introduce security
	   problems.  The RFC Editor and other publishers should
	   exercise due care to ensure that no such references or
	   scripts appear in the archives. </t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="IANA Considerations">
	   <t> This document requires no actions by the IANA.</t>
	   </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments" anchor="Acknowledgments">
    <t> The impetus for this specification arose during a discussion during
	   an RFC Editorial Board meeting in the aftermath of one of the
	   IETF's seeming-interminable discussions about allowing RFC's in
	   "modern" formats.  Aaron Falk made several specific suggestions
	   that have been reflected in the document.  The RFC Editor staff
	   and other Editorial Board members contributed suggestions
	   without which this version would not have been possible.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
<references title="Normative References">
<!--   &rfc2119;	<!-- conformance terms -->
   &rfc0020;	<!-- US_ASCII definition -->
   &rfc2223;	<!-- RFC Guidelines -->
   &rfc3778;	<!-- PDF media type -->
   &rfc4748;	<!-- IPR -->
</references>

<references title="Informative References">

   &rfc3743;    <!-- internationalized names -->

   <reference anchor="ISO32000-1">
	  <front>
		 <title>Document management -- Portable document format --
			Part 1: PDF 1.7</title>
		 <author>
			<organization>International Organization for
			   Standardization (ISO)</organization>
	     </author>
		 <date year="2008"/>
	  </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="32000-1:2008"/>
	  <!-- ISO TC171/SC2,
	  http://www.iso.org/iso/iso_catalogue/catalogue_tc/catalogue_detail.htm?csnumber=51502
	  -->
   </reference>

   <reference anchor="ISO19005-1">
	  <front>
		 <title>Document management -- Electronic document file
			format for long-term preservation -- Part 1: Use of PDF
			1.4 (PDF/A-1)</title>
		 <author>
			<organization>International Organization for
			   Standardization (ISO)</organization>
	     </author>
		 <date year="2005"/>
	  </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="19005-1:2005"/>
	  <!-- ISO TC171/SC2,
	  http://www.iso.org/iso/iso_catalogue/catalogue_tc/catalogue_detail.htm?csnumber=38920
	  -->
   </reference>
   
</references>
</back>
</rfc>

