<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<rfc category="info" ipr="full3978"
     docName="draft-josefsson-openpgp-mailnews-header-05">

  <front>

    <title>
      The OpenPGP mail and news header field
    </title>

    <author initials="A." surname="Smasher" fullname="Atom Smasher">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
	<email>atom@smasher.org
	  (762A3B98A3C396C9C6B7582AB88D52E4D9F57808)</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author initials="S." surname="Josefsson" fullname="Simon Josefsson">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
	<email>simon@josefsson.org
	  (0424D4EE81A0E3D119C6F835EDA21E94B565716F)</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <date month="April" year="2008"/>

    <abstract>

      <t>This document describes the OpenPGP mail and news header
	field.  The field provide information about the sender's
	OpenPGP key.</t>

      <t>See &lt;http://josefsson.org/openpgp-header/&gt; for more
	information.</t>

    </abstract>

  </front>
  
  <middle>

    <section title="Preface">

      <t>This document is intended to define the "OpenPGP" message
	header field.  This field should be considered "informational"
	(and "optional"), and be suitable for both
	<xref target="RFC2822">mail</xref>
	and <xref target="RFC1036">netnews</xref> messages.  This
	field should be used to provide information about the
	sender's <xref target="RFC4880">OpenPGP</xref> key.  This
	field MAY be used in any message.</t>

      <t>This document should be interpreted within the context of RFC
	2822. In the event of a discrepancy, refer to that
	document.</t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
	NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
	"OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
	in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Background and Motivation">

      <t>There are quite a few PGP and GnuPG users who add header
	fields with information about the sender's OpenPGP key.
	Fields in current use include "X-PGP:", "X-PGP-Key:",
	"X-Request-PGP:", "X-PGP-KeyID:", and "X-PGP-Fingerprint:".
	The fields are not standardized, so they cannot be reliably
	parsed automatically by applications, only parsed by
	humans.</t>

      <t>Since both PGP and GnuPG rely on the OpenPGP protocol, it
	appear preferable to use the term "OpenPGP" rather than "PGP",
	or "GPG", in the field name.  The latter forms appear as
	underhanded attempts to advocate specific applications, rather
	than the open standard they both share.  The field specified
	here is named "OpenPGP".</t>

      <t>The OpenPGP field is not a required part of successful use of
	OpenPGP in e-mail or other messages.  It is intended as a
	convenience, in those situations where the user experience may
	be enhanced by using the information in the field.
	Consequently, the information in the field should not disrupt
	the normal OpenPGP key retrieval and web of trust mechanism.
	Neither the integrity nor the authenticity of the information
	in the field should be assumed to be correct or
	trust-worthy.</t>

      <t>No specific scenario when the field should be used, nor how
	it should be used in that scenario, are suggested by this
	document.  It is acknowledged that the dominant use of the
	information in the field may be by humans and not
	applications.</t>

      <t>To promote good use of the field, care should be taken so
	that applications do not trigger error messages that may annoy
	the user, when an error condition arise during handling of the
	OpenPGP field.  It is generally recommended that an
	implementation ignore the presence of the OpenPGP fields if it
	would cause an error condition.  Since the field is optional,
	this approach should not be difficult to implement.  The
	philosophy here is to enable an enhanced user experience.
	Error messages rarely contribute to that goal.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="OpenPGP Header Field">

      <t>The OpenPGP header field is intended to present
	characteristics of the sender's OpenPGP key.  The field
	typically contains the Key ID and the URL where the key can be
	retrieved.</t>
      
      <t>Because the mail header is typically not integrity protected,
	the information conveyed in the OpenPGP header field MUST NOT
	be trusted without additional verification.  Some of the
	information given in this field may also be given in the
	OpenPGP key itself.  When these two sources conflict, users
	SHOULD favor the information from the OpenPGP key, as that
	information can be cryptographically protected.</t>

      <t>The field is of a "structured" type (see section 2.2.2 of RFC
	2822).  In general, the structure consist of one or more
	parameters, each consisting of one attribute and one value.
	The terminology and format of the field was inspired
	by <xref target="RFC2045">MIME</xref>.  The various provisions
	of RFC 2045 apply.  In particular, the value part of
	parameters may be quoted; whitespace, folding and comments may
	occur in the middle of parameters; except as noted below.  The
	provisions of <xref target="RFC2231">MIME</xref> also apply;
	in particular it deals with handling parameters of excessive
	length.</t>

      <t>The OpenPGP header field is defined as below in
	the <xref target="RFC5234">Augmented BNF</xref> notation.  By
	itself, however, this grammar is incomplete.  It refers by
	name to syntax rules that are defined in
	<xref target="RFC2822" /> and <xref target="RFC3986" />.
	Rather than reproduce those definitions here, and risk
	unintentional differences between the two, this document refer
	the reader to the other documents for the definition of
	non-terminals.</t>

      <t>Implementations MUST understand the "id", "url", and
	"preference" attributes.  Parameter with unrecognized
	attributes MUST be ignored.  The grammar permit unknown
	parameters to allow for future extensions.  Each parameter
	attribute (e.g., "url") MUST NOT occur more than once in any
	single instance of the OpenPGP field.  The OpenPGP field
	itself MAY occur more than once in a single email (for example
	if the sender has multiple keys).</t>

      <figure>
	<artwork type="abnf"><?rfc include="openpgp.abnf"?></artwork>
      </figure>

      <section title="Primary Key ID field: id">

	<t>The "id" parameter, if present, MUST hold the Key ID or key
	  fingerprint for the primary key.  The value uses
	  the <xref target="RFC4648">hex</xref> notation.  The
	  parameter value is case-insensitive.</t>

	<t>The length of the field determine whether it denotes a Key
	  ID (8 hex symbols), a long Key ID (16 hex symbols), a v3 key
	  fingerprint (32 hex symbols), or a v4 key fingerprint (40
	  hex symbols).</t>

	<t>Note that each of the following examples includes a
	  comment, which is optional.</t>

	<figure>
	  <artwork>
    id=12345678 (short key ID)
    id=1234567890ABCDEF (long key ID)
    id=1234567890abcdef0123456789ABCDEF01234567 (v4 fingerprint)
    id=1234567890ABCDEF0123456789ABCDEF (v3 fingerprint, deprecated)
	  </artwork>
	</figure>

      </section>

      <section title="Key URL field: url">

	<t>The "url" parameter, if present, MUST specify a URL where
	  the public key can be found.  It is RECOMMENDED to use a
	  common URL family, such as <xref target="RFC2616">
	  HTTP</xref> or <xref target="RFC0959">FTP</xref>.  The URL
	  MUST be fully qualified, MUST explicitly specify a protocol
	  and SHOULD be accessible on the public Internet.</t>

	<t>The content of where the URL points SHOULD be either an
	  ASCII armored or binary OpenPGP packet containing the key.
	  A valid reason for storing something else may be if the key
	  has been revoked.</t>

	<t>For example:</t>

	<figure>
	  <artwork>
    url=http://example.org/pgp.txt
    url="http://example.org/funny;name.txt"
	  </artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>If the URL contains the character ';' the entire URL MUST
	  be quoted, as illustrated in the example.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Protection Preference Field: preference">

	<t>The "preference" parameter, if present, specify the quality
	  of protection preferred by the sender.  The parameter value
	  is case-insensitive.</t>

	<t>The available values are as follows.  A "unprotected" token
	  means that the sender prefer not to receive OpenPGP
	  protected e-mails.  A "sign" token means that the sender
	  prefer to receive digitally signed e-mails.  A "encrypt"
	  token means that the sender prefer to receive encrypted
	  e-mails.  A "signencrypt" token means that the sender prefer
	  to receive encrypted and signed e-mails.</t>

	<t>Note that there is no normative requirement on the receiver
	  to follow the stated preference.</t>

	<t>For example:</t>

	<figure>
	  <artwork>
    preference=sign
    preference=unprotected
    preference=ENCRYPT
	  </artwork>
	</figure>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Comments">

      <t>As discussed in section 3.2.3 of RFC 2822, comments may
	appear in header field bodies.  Comments are not intended to
	be interpreted by any application, but to provide additional
	information for humans.</t>

      <t>The following are examples of OpenPGP fields with
	comments:</t>

      <figure>
	<artwork>
  id=B565716F (key stored on non-networked laptop)
  id=12345678 (1024 bit RSA Key for Encrypt or Sign)
  id=ABCD0123 (created Sun Jan  2 02:25:15 CET 2005)
	</artwork>
      </figure>

    </section>

    <section title="Examples">

      <t>These are valid examples of how the field may be used.  This
	list is not meant to be exhaustive, but to reflect expected
	typical usages.</t>

      <figure>
	<artwork>
  OpenPGP: id=12345678
  OpenPGP: url=http://example.com/key.txt
  OpenPGP: preference=unprotected
  OpenPGP: url=http://example.com/key.txt; id=12345678
  OpenPGP: id=12345678; url=http://example.com/key.txt;
           preference=signencrypt
  OpenPGP: url=http://example.com/key.txt (down 2-3pm UTC);
           id=12345678 (this key is only used at the office);
           preference=sign (unsigned emails are filtered away)
  OpenPGP: id=12345678; url="http://example.com/openpgp;key.txt"
	</artwork>
      </figure>

    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">

      <t>The content of this document builds on discussions with (in
	alphabetical order) Christian Biere, Patrick Brunschwig, Jon
	Callas, Dave Evans, Peter J. Holzer, Ingo Klocker, Werner
	Koch, Jochen Kupper, William Leibzon, Charles Lindsey,
	Aleksandar Milivojevic, Xavier Maillard, Greg Sabino Mullane,
	Tim Polk, Thomas Roessler, Moritz Schulte, Olav Seyfarth,
	David Shaw, Thomas Sjogren, Paul Walker, and Steve Youngs.  No
	doubt the list is incomplete.  We apologize to anyone we left
	out.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">

      <t>The OpenPGP header field is intended to be a convenience in
	locating public keys.  The OpenPGP header is neither secure
	nor intended to be.  Since the message header is easy to
	spoof, information contained in the header should not be
	trusted.  The information must be verified.</t>

      <t>Applications that interpret the field MUST NOT assume that
	the content is correct, and MUST NOT present the data to the
	user in any way that would cause the user to assume that it is
	correct.  Applications that interpret the data within the
	field SHOULD alert the user that this information is not a
	substitute for personally verifying keys and being a part of
	the web of trust.</t>

      <t>If an application receives a signed message and uses the
	information in the field to automatically retrieve a key, the
	application MAY ignore the retrieved key if it is not the same
	key used to sign the message.  This SHOULD be done before the
	newly retrieved key is imported into the user's keyring.</t>

      <t>The use of <xref target="RFC2818">HTTPS</xref>,
	<xref target="RFC4033">DNSSEC</xref>,
	<xref target="RFC3207">SMTP
	STARTTLS</xref>, <xref target="RFC2595">IMAP/POP3
	STARTTLS</xref> and other secure protocols, may enhance the
	security of information conveyed through this field, but does
	not guarantee any level of security or authenticity.
	Developers and users must remain aware of this.</t>

      <t>Version 3 OpenPGP keys can be created with a chosen key id
	(aka "the 0xDEADBEEF attack").  Verifying the Key ID of a
	retrieved key against the one provided in the field is thus
	not sufficient to protect against a man-in-the-middle attack.
	Instead, the web-of-trust mechanism should be used.</t>

      <t>If an attacker wants to check the validity of email
	addresses, he might email arbitrary addresses with a unique
	OpenPGP header field URL (presumably an URL under the
	attacker's control).  The attacker can verify the liveness of
	each email address by checking if the URL for each particular
	recipient has been retrieved.  To protect against this,
	implementations MUST inform the user of that potential privacy
	issue when retrieving keys from an URL provided by the field
	of an inbound email message: either when the feature is
	enabled or to be used for the first time or every time the MUA
	detects an unknown key.</t>

      <t>Given the flexibility of the syntax of the field, slightly
	varying the content between messages can be used as a covert
	channel.  This is already possible using other header fields
	in email, and thus the OpenPGP field do not introduce a new
	vulnerability here.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>The IANA is asked to register the OpenPGP header field, using
	the template as follows, in accordance
	with <xref target="RFC3864">RFC 3864</xref>.</t>

      <t>Header field name: OpenPGP</t>

      <t>Applicable protocol: mail, netnews</t>

      <t>Status: informational</t>

      <t>Author/Change controller: IETF</t>

      <t>Specification document(s): This document.</t>

      <t>Related information: None</t>

      <t><vspace blankLines="10000" /></t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2045.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2231.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2822.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3986.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4880.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234.xml"?>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0959.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1036.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2595.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2616.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2818.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3207.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3864.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4033.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4648.xml"?>

    </references>

    <section title="Copying conditions">

      <t>Regarding this entire document or any portion of it, the
	authors makes no guarantees and is not responsible for any
	damage resulting from its use.  The authors grants irrevocable
	permission to anyone to use, modify, and distribute it in any
	way that does not diminish the rights of anyone else to use,
	modify, and distribute it, provided that redistributed
	derivative works do not contain misleading author or version
	information.  Derivative works need not be licensed under
	similar terms.</t>

    </section>

  </back>

</rfc>
