<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc3484 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3484.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3041 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3041.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4291 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4192 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4192.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4193 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4193.xml'>
	<!ENTITY NAP PUBLIC 'NAP'
	  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-v6ops-nap.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc autobreaks="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>

<rfc category="info" ipr="full3978" docName="draft-ietf-v6ops-addr-select-ps-03.txt">
<front>
    <title abbrev='Address Selection PS'>
Problem Statement of Default Address Selection in Multi-prefix Environment: Operational Issues of RFC3484 Default Rules
    </title>
    <author initials='A.M.' surname="Matsumoto" fullname='Arifumi Matsumoto'>
        <organization abbrev='NTT'>NTT PF Lab</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
		<street>Midori-Cho 3-9-11</street>
                <city>Musashino-shi</city>
                <region>Tokyo</region>
                <code>180-8585</code>
                <country>Japan</country>
            </postal>
            <phone>+81 422 59 3334</phone>
            <email>arifumi@nttv6.net</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    <author initials='T.F.' surname="Fujisaki" fullname='Tomohiro Fujisaki'>
        <organization abbrev='NTT'>NTT PF Lab</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
		<street>Midori-Cho 3-9-11</street>
                <city>Musashino-shi</city>
                <region>Tokyo</region>
                <code>180-8585</code>
                <country>Japan</country>
            </postal>
            <phone>+81 422 59 7351</phone>
            <email>fujisaki@nttv6.net</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    <author initials='R.H.' surname="Hiromi" fullname='Ruri Hiromi'>
        <organization abbrev='Intec Netcore'>Intec Netcore, Inc.</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
		<street>Shinsuna 1-3-3</street>
                <city>Koto-ku</city>
                <region>Tokyo</region>
                <code>136-0075</code>
                <country>Japan</country>
            </postal>
            <phone>+81 3 5665 5069</phone>
            <email>hiromi@inetcore.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    <author initials='K.K.' surname="Kanayama" fullname='Ken-ichi Kanayama'>
        <organization abbrev='Intec Netcore'>Intec Netcore, Inc.</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
		<street>Shinsuna 1-3-3</street>
                <city>Koto-ku</city>
                <region>Tokyo</region>
                <code>136-0075</code>
                <country>Japan</country>
            </postal>
            <phone>+81 3 5665 5069</phone>
            <email>kanayama@inetcore.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>

    <date month="January" year="2008"/>
    <area>Operations and Management</area>
    <workgroup>IPv6 Operations Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

	<abstract>
   <t>One physical network can carry multiple logical networks. Moreover,
   we can use multiple physical networks at the same time in a host.
   In that environment, end hosts might have multiple IP addresses and
   be required to use them selectively.  Without an appropriate
source/destination
   address selection mechanism, the host will experience some trouble in
   communication.
   RFC 3484 defines both the source and destination address selection
algorithms,
   but the multi-prefix environment considered here needs additional rules
   beyond those of the default operation.
   This document describes the possible problems that end hosts could
encounter
   in an environment with multiple logical networks.</t>
   </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
	<section title="Introduction">
	<t>One physical network can carry multiple logical networks.  In that case,
   an end-host has multiple IP addresses. In the IPv4-IPv6 dual stack
   environment or in a site connected to both a <xref target="RFC4193">ULA</xref> and Global scope networks, an end-host has multiple IP addresses.
   These are examples of networks that we focus on in this document.
	In such an environment, an end-host will encounter some communication
	trouble.</t>

	<t>
   Inappropriate source address selection at the end-host causes unexpected
   asymmetric routing, filtering by a router or discarding of packets
   bacause there is no route to the host.
	</t>

	<t>
   Considering a multi-prefix environment, destination address
   selection is also important for correct or better communication establishment.
   <!--   The key to developing the appropriate process will come from the way to
   configure the source address and destination address to the interfaces at
   the end-hosts by the network policy of the site. -->
	</t>

	<t>
   <xref target="RFC3484">RFC 3484</xref> defines both source and destination address selection algorithms.
   In most cases, the host will be able to communicate with the targeted
host using the
   algorithms.  However, there are still problematic cases such as when
   multiple default routes are supplied.
   This document describes such possibilities of incorrect address selection,
   which leads to dropping packets and communication failure.
	</t>

	<t>
   In addition, the provision of an address policy table is an important
   matter. RFC 3484 describes all the algorithms for setting the address
   policy table but address policy provisions are not mentioned.
   RFC 3484 only defines how to configure the address policy table
   manually.
	</t>

		<section title="Scope of this document"> <!-- 1.2 -->

	<t>
   There has been a lot of discussion about "multiple
addresses/prefixes" but
   the multi-homing techniques for achieving redundancy are out of our scope.
   Cooperation with a mechanism like shim6 is rather desirable.
   We focus on an end-site network environment.
   The scope of this document is to sort out problematic cases of false
   dropping of the address selection within a multi-prefix environment.
	</t>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section title="Problem Statement"> <!-- 2 -->
		<section title="Source Address Selection"> <!-- 2.1 -->
			<section title="Multiple Routers on Single Interface">
				<!-- 2.1.1 -->
				<figure>
					<artwork>
                       ==================
                       |    Internet    |
                       ==================
                          |          |
       2001:db8:1000::/36 |          | 2001:db8:8000::/36
                     +----+-+      +-+----+
                     | ISP1 |      | ISP2 |
                     +----+-+      +-+----+
                          |          |
      2001:db8:1000:::/48 |          | 2001:db8:8000::/48
                   +------+---+ +----+-----+
                   | Gateway1 | | Gateway2 |
                   +--------+-+ +-+--------+
                            |     |
       2001:db8:1000:1::/64 |     | 2001:db8:8000:1::/64
                            |     |
                     -----+-+-----+------
                          |
                        +-+----+ 2001:db8:1000:1::EUI64
                        | Host | 2001:db8:8000:1::EUI64
                        +------+

                             [Fig. 1]
					</artwork>
				</figure>

				<t>
  Generally speaking, there is no interaction between next-hop determination
  and address selection. In this example, when a Host sends a packet via
  Gateway1, the Host does not necessarily choose address 2001:db8:1000:1::EUI64
  given by Gateway1 as the source address. This causes the same problem
  as described in the next section 'Ingress Filtering Problem'.
				</t>


			</section>

			<section title="Ingress Filtering Problem"> <!-- 2.1.2 -->
				<figure>
					<artwork>
                     ==================
                     |    Internet    |
                     ==================
                          |       |
       2001:db8:1000::/36 |       | 2001:db8:8000::/36
                     +----+-+   +-+----+
                     | ISP1 |   | ISP2 |
                     +----+-+   +-+----+
                          |       |
      2001:db8:1000:::/48 |       | 2001:db8:8000::/48
                         ++-------++
                         | Gateway |
                         +----+----+
                              |  2001:db8:1000:1::/64
                              |  2001:db8:8000:1::/64
                    ------+---+----------
                          |
                        +-+----+ 2001:db8:1000:1::EUI64
                        | Host | 2001:db8:8000:1::EUI64
                        +------+

                             [Fig. 2]
					</artwork>
				</figure>

				<t>
   When a relatively small site, which we call a "customer network", is
   attached to two upstream ISPs, each ISP delegates a network address
   block, which is usually /48, and a host has multiple IPv6 addresses.
   				</t>

   				<t>
   When the source address of an outgoing packet is not the one that is
   delegated by an upstream ISP, there is a possibility that the packet
   will be dropped at the ISP by its Ingress Filter.
   Ingress filtering(uRPF: unicast Reverse Path Forwarding)
   is becoming more popular among ISPs to mitigate
   the damage of DoS attacks.
   				</t>

   				<t>
   In this example, when the Gateway chooses the default route to ISP2
   and the Host chooses 2001:db8:1000:1::EUI64 as the source address for
   packets sent to a host (2001:db8:2000::1) somewhere on the Internet,
   the packets may be dropped at ISP2 because of Ingress Filtering.
   				</t>


			</section>

			<section title="Half-Closed Network Problem"> <!-- 2.1.3 --> 
   				<t>
   You can see a second typical source address selection problem in a
   multihome site with global-closed mixed connectivity like in the figure
   below.  In this case, Host-A is in a multihomed network and has two
   IPv6 addresses, one delegated from each of the upstream ISPs.
   Note that ISP2
   is a closed network and does not have connectivity to the Internet.
   				</t>

				<figure>
					<artwork>
                        +--------+
                        | Host-C | 2001:db8:a000::1
                        +-----+--+
                              |
                     ==============  +--------+
                     |  Internet  |  | Host-B | 2001:db8:8000::1
                     ==============  +--------+
                          |           |
        2001:db8:1000:/36 |           | 2001:db8:8000::/36
                     +----+-+   +-+---++
                     | ISP1 |   | ISP2 | (Closed Network/VPN tunnel)
                     +----+-+   +-+----+
                          |       |
        2001:db8:1000:/48 |       | 2001:db8:8000::/48
                         ++-------++
                         | Gateway |
                         +----+----+
                              |  2001:db8:1000:1::/64
                              |  2001:db8:8000:1::/64
                    ------+---+----------
                          |
                       +--+-----+ 2001:db8:1000:1::EUI64
                       | Host-A | 2001:db8:8000:1::EUI64
                       +--------+

                             [Fig. 3]
					</artwork>
				</figure>

				<t>
	You do not need two physical network connections here.
	The connection from the Gateway to ISP2 can be a logical link over ISP1
	and the Internet.
				</t>
 
				<t>
   When Host-A starts the connection to Host-B in ISP2, the source address
   of a packet that has been sent will be the one delegated from ISP2, that is
   2001:db8:8000:1::EUI64, because of rule 8 (longest matching prefix) in
   RFC 3484.
				</t>

				<t>
   Host-C is located somewhere on the Internet and has IPv6 address
   2001:db8:a000::1.  When Host-A sends a packet to Host-C, the longest
   matching algorithm chooses 2001:db8:8000:1::EUI64 for the source
   address.  In this case, the packet goes through ISP1 and may be
   filtered by ISP1's ingress filter.  Even if the packet is 
   not filtered by ISP1, a return packet from Host-C cannot possibly be
   delivered to Host-A because the return packet is destined for
   2001:db8:8000:1::EUI64, which is closed from the Internet.
				</t>

				<t>
   The important point is
   that each host chooses a correct source address for a given
   destination address as long as NAT does not exist in the IPv6 world.
				</t>
			</section>

			<section title="Combined Use of Global and ULA"> <!--2.1.4 -->
				<figure>
					<artwork>
                     ============
                     | Internet |
                     ============
                           |
                           |
                      +----+----+
                      |   ISP   |
                      +----+----+
                           |
           2001:db8:a::/48 |
                      +----+----+
                      | Gateway |
                      +-+-----+-+
                        |     | 2001:db8:a:100::/64
       fd01:2:3:200:/64 |     | fd01:2:3:100:/64
                -----+--+-   -+--+----
                     |           |
 fd01:2:3:200::EUI64 |           |      2001:db8:a:100::EUI64
                +----+----+    +-+----+ fd01:2:3:100::EUI64
                | Printer |    | Host |
                +---------+    +------+

                             [Fig. 4]
					</artwork>
				</figure>

				<t>
	As <xref target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-nap">NAP</xref> describes,
	using a ULA may be beneficial in some scenarios.
	If the ULA is used for internal communication,
	packets with ULA need to be filtered at the Gateway.
				</t>

				<t>
   There is no serious problem related to address selection in this case,
   because of the dissimilarity between the ULA and the Global Unicast Address.
   The longest matching rule of RFC 3484 chooses the correct address for both
   intra-site and extra-site communication.
				</t>

				<t>
   In a few years, however, the longest matching rule will not be able to
   choose the correct address anymore. That is the moment when the assignment of
   those Global Unicast Addresses starts, where the first bit is 1.
   In <xref target="RFC4291">RFC 4291</xref>, almost all address spaces of IPv6,
   including those
   whose first bit is 1, are assigned as Global Unicast Addresses.
				</t>
			</section>

			<section title="Site Renumbering"> <!-- 2.1.5 -->
				<t>
   <xref target="RFC4192">RFC 4192</xref> describes a recommended procedure
   for renumbering a
   network from one prefix to another.  An autoconfigured address has a
   lifetime, so by stopping advertisement of the old prefix, the
   autoconfigured address is eventually invalidated.
				</t>

				<t>
	However, invalidating the old prefix takes a long time.
	You cannot stop routing to the old prefix as long as the old prefix
	is not removed from the host. This can be a tough issue for ISP
	network administrators.
				</t>

				<figure>
					<artwork>
                           +-----+---+
                           | Gateway |
                           +----+----+
                                |  2001:db8:b::/64  (new)
                                |  2001:db8:a::/64 (old)
                      ------+---+----------
                            |
                         +--+-----+ 2001:db8:b::EUI64  (new)
                         | Host-A | 2001:db8:a::EUI64 (old)
                         +--------+

                             [Fig. 5]
					</artwork>
				</figure>
			</section>

			<section title="Multicast Source Address Selection"> <!-- 2.1.6 -->
				<t>
   This case is an example of Site-local or Global prioritization.  When
   you send a multicast packet across site-borders, the source address
   of the multicast packet must be a global scope address.  The
   longest matching algorithm, however, selects a ULA if the
   sending host has both a ULA and a global address.
				</t>
			</section>

			<section title="Temporary Address Selection"> <!-- 2.1.7 -->
				<t>
   <xref target="RFC3041">RFC 3041</xref> defines a Temporary Address.
   The usage of a Temporary Address has both pros and cons.
   That is good for viewing web pages or communicating with the
   general public, but that is bad for a service that uses address-based
   authentication and for logging purposes.
				</t>

				<t>
	If you could turn the temporary address on and off, that would be
	better.
	If you could switch its usage per service(destination address),
	that would also be better.
   The same situation can be found when using HA and CoA in a MobileIP network.
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section title="Destination Address Selection"> <!-- 2.2 -->
			<section title="IPv4 or IPv6 prioritization"> <!-- 2.2.1 -->
				<t>
   The default policy table gives IPv6 addresses higher
   precedence than IPv4 addresses. There seem to be many cases,
   however, where network administrators want to control the
   address selection policy of end-hosts the other way around.
				</t>
				<figure>
					<artwork>
                         +---------+
                         | Tunnel  |
                         | Service |
                         +--+---++-+
                            |   ||
                            |   ||
                     ===========||==
                     | Internet || |
                     ===========||==
                          |     ||
             192.0.2.0/24 |     ||
                     +----+-+   ||
                     | ISP  |   ||
                     +----+-+   ||
                          |     ||
            IPv4 (Native) |     || IPv6 (Tunnel)
             192.0.2.0/26 |     ||
                         ++-----++-+
                         | Gateway |
                         +----+----+
                              |  2001:db8:a:1::/64
                              |  192.0.2.0/28
                              |
                    ------+---+----------
                          |
                        +-+----+ 2001:db8:a:1:EUI64
                        | Host | 192.0.2.2
                        +------+

                             [Fig. 6]
					</artwork>
				</figure>

				<t>
   In the figure above, a site has native IPv4 and tunneled-IPv6
   connectivity.  Therefore, the administrator may want to set
   a higher priority for using IPv4 than using IPv6 because the quality
   of the tunnel network seems to be worse than that of the native
	transport.
				</t>
			</section>

			<section title="ULA and IPv4 dual-stack environment"> <!--2.2.2-->
				<t>
   This is a special form of IPv4 and IPv6 prioritization.
   When an enterprise has IPv4 Internet connectivity but does not yet have IPv6
   Internet connectivity, and the enterprise wants to provide site-local
   IPv6 connectivity, a ULA is the best choice for
   site-local IPv6 connectivity. Each employee host will have both
   an IPv4 global or private address and a ULA. Here, when this
   host tries to connect to Host-C that has registered both A and AAAA
   records in the DNS, the host will choose AAAA as the destination
   address and the ULA for the source address. This will clearly result
   in a connection failure.
				</t>

				<figure>
					<artwork>
                        +--------+
                        | Host-C | AAAA = 2001:db8::80
                        +-----+--+ A    = 192.0.2.1
                              |
                     ============
                     | Internet |
                     ============
                          |  no IPv6 connectivity
                     +----+----+
                     | Gateway |
                     +----+----+
                          |
                          | fd01:2:3::/48 (ULA)
                          | 192.0.2.128/25
                         ++--------+
                         | Router  |
                         +----+----+
                              |  fd01:2:3:4::/64 (ULA)
                              |  192.0.2.240/28
                    ------+---+----------
                          |
                        +-+----+ fd01:2:3:4::100 (ULA)
                        | Host | 192.0.2.245
                        +------+

                             [Fig. 7]
					</artwork>
				</figure>
			</section>

			<section title="ULA or Global Prioritization"> <!--2.2.3-->
				<t>
	Differentiating services by the client's source address is very common.
	IP-address-based authentication is
   an typical example of this. Another typical example
   is a web service that has pages for the public and internal
   pages for employees or involved parties. Yet another example
   is DNS zone splitting.
				</t>

				<t>
   However, a ULA and IPv6 global address both have global scope,
   and RFC3484 default rules do not specify which address should be
   given priority. This point makes IPv6 implementation of
   address-based service differentiation a bit harder.
				</t>

				<figure>
					<artwork>
                         +------+
                         | Host |
                         +-+--|-+
                           |  |
                   ===========|==
                   | Internet | |
                   ===========|==
                         |    |
                         |    |
                    +----+-+  +-->+------+
                    | ISP  +------+  DNS | 2001:db8:a::80
                    +----+-+  +-->+------+ fc12:3456:789a::80
                         |    |
         2001:db8:a::/48 |    |
     fc12:3456:789a::/48 |    |
                    +----+----|+
                    | Gateway ||
                    +---+-----|+
                        |     |    2001:db8:a:100::/64
                        |     |    fc12:3456:789a:100::/64
                      --+-+---|-----
                          |   |
                        +-+---|+ 2001:db8:a:100::EUI64
                        | Host | fc12:3456:789a:100::EUI64
                        +------+

                             [Fig. 7]
					</artwork>
				</figure>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>


	<section title="Conclusion"> <!-- 4 -->
		<t>
We have covered problems related to destination or source
address selection. These problems have their roots in the situation
where end-hosts have multiple IP addresses. In this situation,
every end-host must choose an appropriate
destination and source address, which cannot be achieved only by
routers.
		</t>

		<t>
It should be noted that end-hosts must be informed about
routing policies of their upstream networks for appropriate
address selection. A site administrator must consider every
possible address false-selection problem and take countermeasures
beforehand.
		</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Security Considerations"> <!-- 4 -->
		<t>
When an intermediate router performs policy routing (e.g. source address based routing), inappropriate address selection causes unexpected routing.
  For example, in the network described in 2.1.3, when Host-A uses a default
  address selection policy and chooses an inappropriate address,
  a packet sent to VPN
  can be delivered to a location via the Internet. This issue can lead to
  packet eavesdropping or session hijack.
		</t>
		<t>
  As documented in the security consideration section in RFC 3484,
  address selection algorithms expose a potential
  privacy concern. When a malicious host can make a target host perform address
  selection, the malicious host can know multiple addresses attached to the
  target host. In a case like 2.1.4, if an attacker can make Host to send a
  multicast packet and the Host performs the default address selection algorithm,
  the attacker may be able to determine the ULAs attached to the Host.
		</t>
		<t>
  These security risks have roots in inappropriate address selection. Therefore,
  if a countermeasure is taken, and hosts always select an appropriate address that
  is suitable to a site's network structure and routing, these risks can be avoided.
		</t>
  	</section>

	<section title="IANA Considerations">
		<t>
			This document has no actions for IANA.
		</t>
	</section>
</middle>

<back>
	<references title="Normative References">
		&rfc3484;
		&rfc4193;
	</references>
	<references title="Informative References">
		&NAP;
		&POLDIST;
		&DHCPOPT;
		&rfc4291;
		&rfc4192;
		&rfc3041;
	</references>
	<section title="Appendix. Revision History">
		<t>01:
		<list style="hanging">
                        <t>IP addresse notations changed to docmentation address.</t>
			<t>Descriptoin of solutions deleted.</t>
		</list>
		02:
		<list style="hanging">
			<t>Security considerations section rewritten according to comments from SECDIR.</t>
		</list>
		03:
		<list style="hanging">
			<t>Intended status changed to Informational.</t>
		</list>
		</t>
	</section>

</back>
</rfc>
		
<!--
[RFC3484] Default Address Selection for Internet Protocol
          version 6 (IPv6)

[RFC3041] Privacy Extensions for Stateless Address
          Autoconfiguration in IPv6

[RFC4192] Procedures for Renumbering an IPv6 Network without
          a Flag Day

[RFC4291]IP Version 6 Addressing Architecture

[NAP]     IPv6 Network Architecture Protection
          draft-ietf-v6ops-nap-02.txt
-->

